Chapter 2
Chapter 01: “Run, Little Monster” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Terri Boone could feel the bass power cords begin to thump at her bones as she entered the bar and couldn’t resist the feral grin that forced its way onto her face - it was exactly her kind of song.

For that matter, Afterburner was exactly her kind of bar. Affordable drinks, an Internet jukebox plugged straight into a set of speakers with the volume turned up full, three pool tables, a dartboard, and a couple of huge TV screens turned permanently to a sports channel. Right now, inaudible commentators were enthusing about the night’s upcoming game between the Vancouver Canucks and the Arizona Coyotes. If she didn’t live halfway across the country, she could have seen herself becoming a regular here.

She knew the man she was after by description and it didn’t take long to see him working the bar, jawing with the regulars as he opened a couple of bottles and handed them over. Browned skin, full beard, a cross tattooed on his right forearm and a curious bald patch just forward of his left temple, that was her guy alright.

She slid up into a bar stool as the patrons vacated it and was treated to a warm grin.

“Not seen you in here before darling.” He said, floating his voice over the rampaging music with practised ease. “What can I get you?”

“I’ll have a Bud, please.” she called back, fishing out a bill from her purse. “Hey, is your name Kevin Jenkins?”

“Ah.” He grinned as he retrieved the bottle from its fridge and uncapped it. “Should have known. You’re here for my alien story.”

“You get that a lot?”

“Got to be at least fifteen nutjobs in here a month asking me about it and telling me about the thing they built in their garage so they can get in touch with the mothership.” Jenkins said, swapping her bills for change.

“So you claim to be an alien abductee but think others who claim that are nutjobs?” she sipped her beer.

“Oh yeah. You can always tell the bullshitters who’ve convinced themselves they got taken from the ones who really did.” Jenkins replied. “The real abductees don’t want to go back.”

+++

The Brood had no music, nor did they need to shout. They were perfectly capable of vocalizing, but that clumsy mechanism was reserved only for speaking with other Broods. Within each Brood, the intimate cybernetic wiring that allowed full thoughts to be sent in their entirety had made language entirely redundant.

One said: +<trepidation; question> the watchful Prey have not seen us?+

Another said: +<confidence; statement> They have not. <sneering> Nor have the beast prey.+

This provoked a wave of amusement that circled around the entire Brood. By their standards, the wry assumption that a non-sentient Prey species could hope to detect a cloaked Hunter vessel was the height of humour.

The youngest said: +<fear; query> The Prey are a death world species. We saw what just one of them did to the Brood of Five Poisons. Respectfully, Alpha, are we sure that all of our Brood shall return from this hunt?+

Alpha said: +<Impatience; terse rebuke; instruction> If you fear them so, you may remain aboard the transport.+

It - their species did not reproduce in a gendered manner analogous to male and female - addressed the remainder as the youngling radiated sullen apology. +<inspiring reminder> We are the Hunters, they are the prey. Death planet or not, we will have the technological advantage and surprise. An ambushed prey is meat in the maw. Our cousin-Broods will remember our triumph as we return with trophies from this formidable prey, they will know our courage and our skill. And for the prey, they will know their place in the order of things.+

It turned to the one that operated their ship’s electronic warfare suite. +<Query> Do you have an appropriately high-profile target?+

That one replied +<statement> I do, Alpha. Their whole species will witness our hunt.

The Brood vocalised as one for the first time, expressing their approval. The hunt was on.

+++

“I’ll be honest, I don’t believe a word of it.” Terri told him.

“I don’t blame you.” Jenkins said. “But, look at this.” He leaned forward and turned his head so that she could inspect the bald patch on the left side of his head. Up close, it was an intricate web of fine white scars that produced a pattern which looked disturbingly like circuitry.

“That’s where those grey fuckers shoved an experimental translation implant into me.” Jenkins said. “It worked, but the doctors who took it out of me said it was a pretty damn crude one.”

“These would be alien doctors.” Terri said. She had to admit, the scars were compelling evidence, but she was a natural skeptic. It went with the job.

“Yep. See they greys - “Corti” is the pronunciation used by species that have mouths which work kind of like ours - apparently they had this big eugenics program and turned themselves into a civilization of immoral scientists. They abduct pre-contact species, figure out how we tick, and use that data to corner the market in translation implants and other biotech when we make first contact. Real assholes. Most of the others are pretty cool though.”

He thought about this. “Actually, some of them are as dumb as a bag of beans. There’s one species, look kinda like six-limbed giraffes with blue stripes. Those guys are about as sharp as a sack of wet mice. But most of the critters out there are cool.”

Terri waggled her empty bottle by way of asking for a replacement “So if they’re mostly pretty cool, why wouldn’t anybody want to go back out there? Flying among the stars and all that sounds pretty fun.”

“It will be, when we’re out there.” Jenkins said, grabbing a replacement. “But for now, because we haven’t invented FTL travel, we’re legally considered to be non-sentient fauna rather than intelligent people. Even when there are trade ships out there captained by beings who’ve got all the brains of biscuits and gravy by our standards.”

“Why the interest, anyway?” He asked her, all of a sudden.

“I’m a private investigator.” She replied. “My client’s paying me a lot to travel the whole country looking for what he called ‘genuine’ abductees.”

“Do I fit the bill?” Jenkins asked.

She truthfully told him that she didn’t know - her client had only asked me to hunt down people who weren’t obvious crazies. He’d taken her to a UFO convention in New Mexico, gestured to the whole room and said ’Ms. Boone, this is the kind of people you’re not trying to find for me.’

It was a pretty nebulous description, but the client’s generous travel budget and seemingly limitless ability to keep up with her fees had kept Terri happy and comfortable on a road trip all over the USA for the best part of half a year, and if it meant she got to drink in exactly the right kind of bar interviewing a bartender who - she had to confess - was exactly the right kind of rugged sexy, then those were the kind of contracts she had dreamed of when she became a P. I.

“I guess he didn’t want me accidentally giving away what kind of answer I was looking for.” she finished. “If it helps though, I don’t think you’re crazy. More… bitter about something.”

Jenkins laughed. “Yeah, Kirk said pretty much the same thing”.

“Kirk?”

“Oh yeah. The coolest guy out there. His species has a language that sounds like ball-bearings in a blender, but the first syllable of his name sounds a bit like “Kirk”, you know, like from Star Trek? So that’s what I called him. He told me a few weeks before I came back to Earth that I seemed bitter about something.”

“Was he right?” Terry asked.

“Could be. See, there’s this species called…”

"What the fuck?! Hey Jenks, are you seeing this shit?!"

+++

With nary a ripple of displaced air, the Hunter raiding vessel slipped down into planetary atmosphere. Unnoticed by even the most sophisticated surveillance and interception network on the planet, it sashayed through cloud and current until it found its destination - a city of gleaming steel-and- glass towers on the banks of an inland sea, surrounded by snow-capped mountains. It settled above a dome-roofed building that nestled squat and low among the skyscrapers, causing some minor static in the transmissions coming from within, which were quickly compensated for by the small army of technicians who kept the broadcast going out all over the world.

+<Query; intrigued> Combat trials, perhaps? Ritualized training to do battle in cold-weather conditions?+

+<Terse; impatient> We are not anthropologists! Brace yourself, siblings. We drop in a full hand of pulses.+

+<Eager; aggressive> Meat to the maw!+

The traditional hunting cry reverberated in silence among their collective minds, and then their boarding torpedoes erected their stasis fields, keeping any and all external forces from doing anything to their occupants. When they opened again a subjective non-event later, they had been fired through the roof of the Rogers Arena and each stood upright in a bullseye of cracked ice.

As one, the Brood stepped out of their assault torpedoes, spun up their heavy Kinetic Pulse guns, and opened fire indiscriminately into the stunned players, officials and spectators.

+++

“Shit! Oh my god those poor people!”

The music had been shut off, and the sound of the sports channel turned up. The commentators were going delirious trying to describe the sight of an alien attack right in front of their eyes. Terri’s hand was across her mouth in a shocked reflex, watching them viciously lay into a mass of humanity that had, up until mere seconds earlier, been completely unaware of their existence.

“Hunters.” Jenkins said. He did so quietly, but everybody nearby suddenly glanced at him. Alone of everybody in the bar, he was the only one not apparently appalled by the sight. Instead, he had an expression of savage anticipation.

“Oh, y’all believe me now?” he asked. “Yep, those are the hunters I told you about. The ones I - me, your barkeep - personally beat the fuck to death with my own bare hands.”

His grin broadened. “And the stupid bastards made the mistake of raiding a hockey game? This, boys and girls, is going to be fucking funny.”

+++

Alpha stepped from its assault pod and fired directly into the chest of the first Prey it saw - one of the armoured ones on the ice. Instantly, the Prey’s bewildered stillness gave way to the panic that all Prey fell victim to when the Hunters arrived. Many emitted high-pitched squeals of alarm, many more stampeded to escape. Around it, the Brood stepped onto the ice and launched Kinetic bolts at anything that moved.

Each shot knocked Prey flying, and Alpha felt a savage surge of pride. Their Brood would gain much respect for taking on death planet predators and scattering them like any other herd. Alpha could imagine the praise songs and taste the honour-feast already.

And then the Prey it had shot stood up.

+++

“See, they have this planetary classification system for temperate worlds like ours.” Jenkins said amiably, as on the screen one of the players hauled himself back up onto his skates, clearly a bit winded but otherwise no worse than if he’d taken a hard body-check from one of the Arizonan players.

“Category one is, like, the Garden of Eden. You could drop any species in the galaxy down there completely buck bare and they’d be happy as Larry for the rest of their lives.” he continued, as Canucks and Coyotes players helped one another to their feet. Alien though their body language was, everybody could see the alarm and surprise the Hunters were feeling as every single one of the humans they had shot turned out to be not only alive, but angry.

“Most planets are like, a four to six or so. You don’t want to get caught in the rain and you’ll need to work for your food, but generally it’s pretty easy living on those worlds.”

The aliens fired again, punching the players off their feet again.

“Anything above Class ten is considered a deathworld.” Jenkins continued as, yet again, the players got back up, and this time they started skating around the invading aliens, which formed a defensive corral and began to fire wildly at the circling sportsmen. It quickly became apparent that their reflexes and aim were remarkably sluggish and that the circling skaters were just too fast to hit. Shot after shot splashed harmlessly on the plexiglass.

At first, the people behind the barrier cowered, but that plexiglass was rated to a much, MUCH higher resilience than even the heaviest Kinetic Pulse fire. It didn’t take long for the cowering fans to realise this, and begin to chant: “Kick their ass! Kick their ass!”

Jenkins went on, raising his voice slightly above the swelling, bloodthirsty chant. “Deathworlds have things like high gravity, poisonous plants and critters, lots of carnivores, nasty little microorganisms, natural disasters like earthquakes or volcanoes, acid rain, high background radiation, stuff like that. Like I said, a deathworld is everything Class Ten or above, and anything that evolves there is supposed to be really goddamn dangerous.”

By now on TV, the crowd were roaring at full volume: “KICK THEIR ASS! KICK THEIR ASS!”

+++

Alpha brodcast: <Shock; dismay; terror; disbelief; shame>

Then one of the Prey hurtled towards it, at speeds that simply defied understanding.

The last thing it ever broadcast was: <PAIN!>

+++

Most eyes in the bar closed and turned away from the carnage on the ice in disgust. Terri Boone watched out of morbid fascination. It seemed impossible that things which looked so menacing might break so easily.

Kevin Jenkins opened a beer for himself.

“Earth,” he said, with vicious satisfaction. “Is a Class Twelve.”

Chapter 6
Chapter 05: “Deliverance” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

++Four years previously.++

Everybody loved a home side win, except for the tourists. Amir didn’t feel like a tourist, but Pakistani people supported the Pakistani cricket team, even if - like him - they had been born in Birmingham, had never left England, spoke English more fluently than their supposed “native” language, with an accent that was as British as tea and wet weather.

“Amir!”

His best friend Muhammad and the rest of his friends had started heading in a different direction while Amir was zoned out. “You coming?” he asked.

Amir knew what the answer would be, but he had to ask anyway. It was how things worked. “Where?”

“For a drink! Come on bruv, we may as well have SOME fun tonight.”

Amir shook his head. “You know that’s haram." he said. It was their one constant conflict that Muhammad was only a Muslim when it was convenient. The rest of the time, he was just another nineteen-year-old, high on life and not interested in the consequences.

“We’re all sinners, bruv.” Muhammad told him, amicably.

Amir turned away “I’ll see you tomorrow.” he called over his shoulder.

At least there were no catcalls or anything. They respected his faith that much, even if they didn’t respect it enough to practice it properly themselves. He just wished that his best friend wouldn’t use “we’re all sinners” as an excuse. It may have been true, but that didn’t mean he had to exploit it. That just didn’t feel like Islam.

He didn’t preach though. He was no Imam, he didn’t know how to be. All he had was his job delivering takeaway food, a council flat, and his religion. It was enough, most days.

He knew from experience that the bus stops near the Edgbaston cricket ground would always be heaving after a one-day game. He didn’t mind the walk: it was mid-July, and even the famously inclement British weather had decided to produce a warm night. So, anonymous and alone with his thoughts, he weaved through streets of Friday-night partiers, just another brown face in a crowd that ran the full gamut of human shades, hunched and with his fingers fidgeting with the edge of his pockets.

He was so shrouded in melancholy that he didn’t even see the person he walked into, but they felt solid as a rock. Knowing full well that a Pakistani face in this day and age could get into serious trouble with a surly drunk, he stepped back a pace, and got halfway through his “sorry mate” when he realised that the other man wasn’t moving. In fact, he still had his back turned.

Nobody else was moving either. Nothing else was moving. Traffic stood as still as scenery in the street. The pavement was solid-packed with warm, clothed, human statues, penning him in - he couldn’t even shove them aside to weave through the crowd. He stared at a young woman - she was in the middle of flicking her hair aside to answer her phone, and it stood out impossibly parallel to the ground. Even the light had a strange quality - he swore it took his shadow a brief instant to react when he moved.

And then that shadow became much better-defined as the night-time street orange was flooded out by whiteness. He looked up, and it filled his vision.

One man looked around in confusion, rubbed his back, and returned to his conversation. The streets didn’t even notice that Amir Bahmani was gone.

++

Kirk was a rich being - a Councillor of the Domain earned a handy sum of money from their position, not to mention the royalties from his biographical accounts, political sponsorships and some shrewd investments. Nevertheless, between buying his ultra-fast ship and then having it fast-tracked through a refit drydock at a corporate freeport where the owners were happy to sign an anonymity contract for an appropriate fee… well. His accounts were looking rather less healthy than they had done in some time.

They would, however, bounce back. He was a client of one of the best investment brokers in the business, after all. And the refits had been worth it. The little life-support blister with its bed, ablutions cubicle and control console had been dismounted from the hull, and behind it had been installed a somewhat larger and more luxurious living suite. Below that, a workshop loaded with the latest in nanofactories and CAD/CAM tools, a dense and comprehensive automated laboratory that could double as a sickbay.

And behind that, the enormous generator and the sealed unit that was the Corti blackbox drive. Mass made no difference to a Corti drive - any ship, any size, any tonnage, the only thing that mattered was how much energy you could force down that little box’s throat, and the behemothic bulk of the fusion reactor that made up by far the largest part of the ship’s size and mass was rated to power city districts.

There was one last addition: an excursion chamber, equipped with all the gear he could need to remain safe on practically any planet up to and including a Class 12. And it was necessary - the first destination on his list was a Class 10, an unclaimed world (after all, who in their right minds would want to claim a death world?) with the uninspiring designation “Main Yellow 2.554 67-1.002 09-0.141 3-57.888 11-3 Terrestrial Temperate 10” - literally nothing more than the type and location of the planet and of the star it orbited.

He slept most of the journey out. The downside he was discovering to his ship was that, having as it did a stupefying turn of speed, the trip times were barely long enough for him to complete the in-flight checklist and get some rest. By the time his alarm woke him he was already within the last hundred or so interstellar units of final approach. There had barely been time for his neural implants to convert the slow-access digital data on his destination into working organic memory.

But, they had. He knew everything that it was practical and useful for him to know about that world, barring any gaps in the data, which was how he handled its unique upper-atmospheric turbulence with practiced ease despite having never previously landed without guidance from the ground.

It helped that his target co-ordinates were experiencing a clear day, and as hoped he found a thermal contact within only a short distance of the information that had been in Vakno’s file. Best to land a little way from it, he thought.

He did so. Landing a ship that was effectively a couple of small rooms tacked onto a highly oblate spheroid was a challenge in its own right under MY210 573TT10’s gravity, which was nearly 20% higher than the galactic standard norm. Not as high as Earth’s, but enough to be uncomfortable once he stepped outside of the ship’s generated gravity field. Once landed, he performed those few post-flight checks that any good pilot concerned themselves with, and then retreated to the excursion room.

It took only moments to select the appropriate harness and don it. The device had its own onboard gravity generator that would mitigate the local field, and the rest was a biofiltration force field that should keep anything nasty from coming into contact with him.

Time to meet the first human he had seen in the flesh for three years.

++

Amir had expected a ramp. Instead, the whole room slung under the ship’s equatorial ring descended to ground level, and a pair of large and very solid doors opened, gracefully and silently. He hefted his spear. If it was another of those grey-skinned devils, it wouldn’t know what hit it.

Instead, what stepped out and blinked in the sunlight was a six-legged being fully twice his height, upright atop a complicated pelvis. It raised both its pairs of hands in a gesture of peace and surrender and, with exaggerated care, produced a piece of technology which it set on the ground. The alien clicked at it, producing a sound not dissimilar to a strip of cardboard in a bike’s spokes. This was, apparently, some kind of a language, because once it had finished clicking, the little device on the ground spoke in flawless, though unaccented, English.

“Please, I couldn’t harm you even if I wanted to. You don’t need the spear, Mr. Bahmani.”

Amir practically fell over. It had been years since he had last heard any human language at all, let alone his name.

“H…” the words wouldn’t come at first. He could barely remember speaking aloud other than to recite the Adhān to call himself to Ṣalāt five times a day, and the Rakaʿāt. He had not spoken anything else in… years, probably.

They had been important. Only his faith had kept him going throughout those years. He didn’t have the first idea which way Mecca was, and so had simply settled for facing toward this planet’s east.

He cleared his throat and tried again. “You know English?”

This generated a chattering sound from the being’s lower abdomen, which he decided was probably laughter, followed by another barrage of clicking and crackling noises. “I couldn’t begin to pronounce English, I’m afraid. But my translator here can. You are Amir Bahmani though, yes?”

“I… yes. How do you know?”

The being made a gesture that he couldn’t identify - its body language was unreadable.

“I paid good money to get my hands on a copy of your abductor’s records.” It told him. “My name is…” <an unintelligible sound like plastic beads in a blender> “…but other humans have nicknamed me “Kirk”.”

“Kirk… like, Star Trek?”

“That’s the joke I think, yes. Though it’s also a fair approximation of the first syllable of my name.”

“My abductors… You’re not with them are you?” Amir hefted his spear again, and “Kirk” retreated a step or two, holding up four placating hands.

“No, no. I draw the line at abduction, vivisection and experimentation upon sentient beings. No, I’m here to offer you the chance to leave, if you wish.”

“You’ll take me home?!” Hope swelled in Amir for the first time in a long while. Earth! people! He mentally corrected himself at that one - Human people!

“If only I could.” Kirk told him. “But Earth is… well. The focus of much attention right now.” He looked around at Amir’s camp. “Actually, I’ll just be blunt about it. The rest of the galaxy found out about your species and collectively shit themselves in fear. Earth has been quarantined - they put up a force field around the whole solar system, nothing gets in or out. I… disagree with that decision. I have a plan, and it starts with finding every abductee I can and offering them the hope of a way home.”

He extended a hand, and Amir noticed for the first time that it was made of sleek plastic and metal rather than pale flesh. “Are you in?” Kirk asked. “Shake carefully please, it doesn’t matter so much if you break the prosthetic rather than my actual hand, but they’re a pain to repair.”

"Bismillah! You have to ask? I want to go home."

They shook hands.

“I promise, I’ll try.” Kirk told him.

++

Having a uniformed chauffeur waiting at the airport holding up a sign with “Terri Boone” on it was a novel experience. The chauffeur was efficiency itself as she took Terri’s bags and politely delivered her into the back seat of a sleek black Audi. Next to the expensive car with its buff leather upholstery and general air of wealth, her travel-stained jeans, battered leather jacket and the faded hoody from Chamonix she had owned since a teenage skiing vacation that she wore under the jacket all looked not just dishevelled, but downright squalid.

She entertained herself on her phone as the chauffeur weaved in the comfortable silence of money through freeway and midtown traffic to her apartment, and was surprised when the chauffeur not only brought in the bags, but insisted that no tip was necessary. After quickly discussing what time the car would arrive to take her to Mr. Johnson’s office, she was left alone to re-acquaint herself with her neglected home.

She threw open the windows and lit some scented candles to drive out the scent of emptiness that had built up in the months she had been gone and then, in a move that would have surprised anyone who did not know her extremely well, she emptied all the drawers out of the chest next to her bed and lifted it up, revealing a small, slim box stashed underneath.

From this she withdrew a device of some kind and a USB stick, which she plugged into her PC and launched some programs from, before spending nearly two hours carefully inspecting every nook and cranny of her apartment with the device. Eventually, and apparently satisfied, she returned both to their box and rebuilt the hiding place.

Only then did she boot up some more programs. She spent half an hour alternately typing and watching the screen intently. That done, she took a spin through the shower, combed her hair, threw on some fresh clothing and the same old leather jacket, grabbed her handbag, and departed.

She would have been thoroughly disappointed to learn that her sweep for bugs stood no hope whatsoever of detecting the ones that had been installed a month previously. Among other things, finding them would have required a microscope. ++

“Nope, not organised at all.”

Kevin Jenkins was patiently explaining things and going through the notebook as some of the biology and medical teams examined the peculiar scar on his temple. They had made it as far as the political situation.

“I mean, before a few years ago, legally speaking we were all “non-sentient indigenous fauna”. It’s a bureaucratic mess out there, believe me.”

Tremblay examined the notes again. Mostly it was full of observations about the governmental structures of dozens of different species. the Dominion especially was troubling him. “Left hand doesn’t know what the right hand’s doing?”

Jenkins shrugged, ignoring a lab-coat’s protest to keep his head still. “Left hand could fill in a couple forms in triplicate requesting a third-party committee add a debate to their agenda on whether there’s grounds to start the process of commissioning an independent review on what part of the right hand’s up to." he sneered.

“You make it sound… inefficient.” one of the junior officers commented.

“The Dominion couldn’t find whatever passes for their ass with whatever passes for their hands without three policy meetings and a vote.” Jenkins replied, tersely. It wasn’t quite a snap, and certainly not aimed at the officer, but there was definitely bitterness in the way he said it. “It’s all there in the manual.”

“And what’s in the manual is disturbing.” Tremblay said. He turned a page, and arched an eyebrow. “Roswell Greys? Really?"

“That was pretty much my reaction.” Jenkins said. He had a resigned expression as one of the scientists laid a ruler against his scalp and took a picture.

“According to this they call themselves the Corti Directorate and are the ones primarily responsible for alien abductions on Earth.”

“Hence how they became the Roswell Greys, I guess.” Jenkins sniffed. “But they’re not as bad as some of the motherfuckers out there. At least you know where you stand with the Greys, even if that is under a microscope.”

“Under a microscope still sounds pretty bad.”

“Eh, they’re just self-serving, cowardly, apathetic and practical to a fault. At least we can understand how they think. There’s things out there that think in ways I don’t even know the words for.”

“Like those things that attacked Vancouver, I’m guessing.” Tremblay turned to that page. The sketches were remarkably detailed. The biologists had gone into ecstatic paroxysms over them - the high-definition TV footage from the hockey game had been useful, but the panicked and shell-shocked cameramen hadn’t done the world’s best job of focusing on them and what had been delivered for necropsy had been thoroughly pulverised. A sketch was no substitute for having the real thing under the knife of course, but the detailed drawings of the cybernetic interface between creature and gun had answered some unresolved questions.

“Yeah. They scare me, but not for the right reasons.” Jenkins said.

“The right reasons?” That was Doctor Sung, the base’s counsellor and psychologist. He had, hitherto, been silent, content to just sit in the corner and watch the man who claimed to have spent years wandering the galaxy.

“Look, those bastard things… you know how some people see morality in terms of black, white and shades of grey? Well the Hunters see it in purple, orange and shades of fucking tartan. They’re notorious across the whole galaxy for not only eating the meat of sentient beings, but apparently preferring it to, like, farming a cow or something. That sounds like the right reason to be afraid of them, to me. They’re actual honest-to-shit space monsters. But that’s not what scares me about them.”

“What does?” Sung asked.

“You saw what happened in Vancouver.” Jenkins replied. “Well, that was no fluke: I’m telling you, I personally beat the crap out of three of those fuckers with their own limbs, right after I tore said limbs clean off. It wasn’t even difficult, man."

He shrugged helplessly. “The worst nightmares in the galaxy and some random barkeep from Fuck-Nowhere USA can literally dismember them bare-handed. Worst I had to show for it was a black eye. That scares me.”

Sung cocked his head to one side, curiously. “Being powerful scares you?”

“I didn’t do shit to deserve it, you know? It’s not like you can just say “Hey, I EARNED that”, we’re, like, Kryptonians. We’re Superman, and the worst part is we - the human race, right? - we never had Ma and Pa Kent to teach us to be all about protecting people and all that shit. Before Vancouver, every day the news was full of the latest trending fucking atrocity."

He stood up, raised his arms and adopted a goofy parody of a TV presenter. “it’s time for Wheel of Paedophile, where we reveal which TV icon of yesteryear was fiddling little girls! And after that, which journalist got beheaded for God today, kids? Tune in and find out on The Humanity Show!"

The moment of sarcastic enthusiasm died, and he sagged back down. “Hell, it’d still be full if that shit right now if we didn’t have bigger things on our minds. And pretty soon we’re going to go back to being fucked up to each other when it turns out that whatever we do we’re still, like, probably years from even heading out to the barrier and knocking.”

He sighed. “That’s why the Hunters scare me: because despite that they scare the shit out of everything else, The Hunters never got a reaction like this. Which means that somebody up there thinks we’re WORSE than the Hunters, and I’m scared they might just turn out to be right.”

“You don’t think very highly of people, do you.” Tremblay commented.

“You’re damn right!” Jenkins exclaimed. “But, y’know, individuals can be kind of cool, so we’ve got that going for us." he sniffed. “Which is nice.”

++

“I know who you are. You’re a Dominion security councilor.”

Kirk nodded slowly. “That I am.”

He was standing in the office of the ‘mayor’ of an asteroid mining facility deep in Reef Space, a string of systems that had endured the migration of a black hole spat out by the galactic core some few millions of years in the past and which had long since vanished into intergalactic space. Every one of the fifty or so systems in the region was flagged with a navigational hazard warning thanks to the erratic, disturbed orbits of their planets.

Many of those planets had been broken up entirely, leaving behind huge mineral-rich continents of drifting rock just waiting for the miners. The mining colonies of Reef Space were rich. They were also, by and large, unregulated. Nobody knew how many there were, most of them didn’t answer to the Dominion or the Alliance, they certainly didn’t pay their taxes, and the laws were made and enforced locally. And often poorly.

It took a certain kind of ruthless individual to rise to the top in such circumstances. Mayor Brelm was one of the most ruthless. He was a cold, calculating bastard even by Corti standards.

And he was utterly irrelevant as far as Kirk was concerned.

“I heard you quit. Coming to an asteroid facility like this one is a step down for you, isn’t it?” Brelm tapped a slender finger on his desk. “What is it that you want from me?”

“You?” Kirk feigned disinterested surprise. “Forgive me, mayor, I am not here for you. I came here for your bodyguard.”

The slim human woman who had been leaning sulkily against the back wall looked up at him sharply.

“You’re… for her?” Brelm twisted in his chair and looked at the deathworlder behind him. “Did you know anything about this?”

“You are Allison, are you not?” Kirk asked, as the human shrugged at her employer. “Allison Buehler?”

She kicked off from the wall and stood up straight. From what Kirk knew of human females, she was tall and slim. Next to most other species however she still had that pure strength, though Allison compounded it with a kind of fierce confidence. She tucked her thumbs into her belt and frowned at him. “…That’s me.”

“How would you like to go home?”

Allison shrugged. “Earth? No thanks.”

Kirk hit a mental wall. He hadn’t anticipated a straightforward ‘no’ at all. Suspicion and questions maybe, but simply being turned down wasn’t a contingency for which he had planned.

“You… would not?”

Allison shrugged again. “What’s there for me? You know what I used to do on Earth? I fixed bikes and cars, I served coffee, and guys used to stare at my ass. No thanks.”

“…Oh.”

“Why d’you ask, anyway?” she inquired, and Kirk finally managed to place her accent. Boston. “What, you got a ship full of humans you’re taking back home?”

“Yes, actually. Though, you are only the second I have found.”

“Yeah? Shit, you’re a regular good Samaritan, ain’tcha?”

“I suppose…” Kirk agreed.

Allison gave him a long, calculating, discomforting stare and then shrugged again. “Okay. I’m in.”

It was Brelm’s turn to be wrong-footed. He gaped at her. “You… what? You can’t leave, you have a contract!”

Allison laughed. “Brelm, if you can find some asshole on this station who could stop me then go hire them for your bodyguard instead. Being your hired muscle was getting dull anyway.”

She had a gun on her hip, Kirk noted. An actual human firearm. How had she acquired one so far from Earth? Had she had it on her when she was abducted, or had she somehow built one?

However she’d done it, the “friendly” way she rested her hand on that weapon drove the point home for Brelm.

“You-! …Fine. But our contract is void and you forfeit the rest of this cycle’s pay.”

“You never paid me enough anyway,” Allison ambled across the room. “So what’s your name, mister Samaritan?”

“Most humans call me Kirk.”

Allison shook his hand. “Nice to meetcha, Kirk. Let’s go find some folks who want to go home.”

++

“Miss Boone. A pleasure to meet in the flesh at last.”

Terri didn’t know what she had expected from Mr. Johnson exactly, and really, he lived up to that lack of expectation. He was a dapper, handsome man of about fifty years, with a grey-flecked beard, grey-flecked hair and grey- flecked eyes, wearing a tailored charcoal suit and grey socks. The kind of guy she’d have happily picked up in a hotel bar if she was in the mood for a couple of nights with an older, wealthier man, but no long-term entanglements. He had that curiously accentless voice too, that gave nothing away about where in the world he had been born.

Still, she shook his hand, prepared for - and duly receiving - the circulation-halting firm grip of a man who shook hands for a living.

She was immediately convinced that, whoever he really was, Mr. Johnson was not actually her client. If he turned out not to be a proxy for the real deal, then she would have happily eaten her treasured Chamonix sweatshirt.

Not that this suspicion bothered her much. The amount of money on show meant that frankly the client could have contacted her via strippergram for all Terri cared.

“It’s been a pleasure getting paid.” she said, deciding that playing along with the politeness game could go shove it. “What’s the new job?”

Johnson didn’t seem fazed in the least by this blunt approach, and simply handed her a folder. She flicked through it, seeing names and faces but not bothering to really examine them. One stood out, however.

“Hey, I recognize her. She was that film student who went missing from Vancouver a few days before the attack, right?”

Mr. Johnson smiled the thin-lipped professional smile of somebody who was being paid far more to smile thin-lipped professional smiles at her than she was being paid to receive them. “Xiu Chang, yes. Based on the information you recovered from the abductees, it seems likely that she was abducted herself. The others in that dossier are similar cases, most from this country, a few others from elsewhere in the world.”

“You want me to look around, try and find some more?” Terri asked.

“You have it exactly. That dossier should provide a template for the sort of thing we’re after. Circumstances, factors common to all abductees, and so on.”

“And for this you’re offering me…?”

“A million dollars, Miss Boone. The dramatic turn that events have taken recently means that we’re keen for this to be done with the utmost expediency.”

We, Terri noted. Her sweatshirt was definitely safe.

“I don’t usually say this to the man with the cash.” she said, carefully. “But… why? Everyone knows that the best working theory for the Darkening so far is that there’s some kind of barrier up around the whole solar system. If these people are outside it, then what’s the rush in finding them? What good is that information?”

“And if they’re wrong, Miss Boone?”

“Are they?”

“That’s hardly relevant.”

“True, it’s not, really. After all even without a giant force field imprisoning us, it’s not like we’ve got hyperspace or whatever, so while I’m grateful for clients who pay so well, I do wonder why you want to spend so much on getting this done “with expediency”.”

“And you will continue to do so, I fear. You understand the assignment?”

Terri sighed. “Chase up on missing persons cases that match the profile of these apparent abductions, report them back to you as I find them, for which I will receive a million dollars.” she said.

“Precisely. It is always a pleasure to do business with a professional, Miss Boone.”

“Sure.” Terri replied. “A pleasure.”

Johnson waited a minute or so after she was gone and then stood, unlocked the side door to his office, and stepped through.

There was a coffin-sized metal-and-glass object along one wall of that room, and the being within - small, naked, grey-skinned, large-eyed and bulbous- headed, stared out at him lazily from where it floated in a gel bath inside.

“She agreed.” he said.

“Good. She is just the right mix of clever and mercenary. An excellent find.”

“Thank you, sir. She does, however, raise a very good point. Exactly what good will this information do us?”

“The more we know about who’s out there, the more I can assist the being who’s tracking them down. I didn’t come here to live out the rest of my life on a pre-warp deathtrap of a planet, Johnson. I want to go home.”

The Corti approximated a grim smile. “I want that barrier down.”

++

Maria Sadowski didn’t know what to make of anything. She had got used to the idea of alien life, got used to scavenging whatever scraps they could be bothered to deign to kick her way. Her ribs and bones were visible everywhere, her gums bled constantly, and the sores just wouldn’t heal.

And then just like that, the attitude had changed. One minute, she was ignored by aloof creatures who barely deigned to acknowledge her at all, now they saw her and walked across the other side of the transitway. If she went into an eating-house to beg, before she had been lucky to get scraps - now she got as much as she could stuff into herself while around her tables vacated and the owner carried itself in a way that suggested that, if its species could sweat and if that sweat meant what it meant in humans, it would have been sweating.

She hadn’t had enough time to figure out why when she heard the first recognizable word to fall on her ears in months.

“Maria?”

It was an alien. one of the tall white ones with too many legs, though those were usually friendly. Behind it - him? - stood two humans honest-to-god humans. A tall blonde woman who could only be an American with a belt buckle like that, and a shorter, browner man who gave her a nervous smile.

She didn’t care that neither of them looked like they spoke a word of Polish, right now it was enough just to see somebody the right size, with the right number of limbs, eyes, fingers…

Weeping, she slammed into the man at a dead run and hugged him tight, oblivious to the way nearby beings stepped back in alarm at the solid sound their dense deathworlder bodies made. He made awkward comforting noises and rubbed her back.

The American woman put a hand on the shoulder and said something. They obviously had a translator or something, because Maria heard and understood every word. “She’s in a bad way, Kirk.”

‘Kirk’ shook his mane out and ignored the comment. Instead, he put his own hand on Maria’s other shoulder and spoke softly. “Do not worry. Everything will be alright now, Maria. You are going home.”

++

“Extraordinary guy.” Dr. Sung commented, once Jenkins had agreed to go under an fMRI scanner and departed with the medical technicians and biologists.

Tremblay made a strained noise. “Seems like a bad case of PTSD to me. Not that I’m an expert.”

Sung had the trademark dry humour of psychologists everywhere. “Well, speaking as an expert, I don’t agree with that diagnosis.” He said. “I think he’s just naturally a cynic and maybe had a few bad experiences. Besides, he actually makes a valid point.”

“Don’t tell me he’s turned you into a misanthrope too?”

“Confidentially? I think he’s the opposite of a misanthrope. The impression I got is that he’s the kind of man who’s a bit too driven by his compassion. But step back and think about it for a second. Personally, I believe his account, which means that he’s more or less the only man on Earth to have the chance of really getting to know what it’s like out there - apparently only a handful of the rest ever got that translation implant, and none of them were out there for as long.”

Tremblay leaned against a table and folded his arms. “Meaning?”

“Meaning he knows how ET thinks. He’s got a bit more of an outsider’s perspective than the rest of us. Maybe the reason he’s so bitter on the species is because he can see what they see in us." He smiled uncomfortably. “It’s notoriously difficult for people to acknowledge stuff like that.”

“True. Self-deception’s a powerful thing.” Tremblay said, helping himself to a mug of the coffee that had been percolating in the corner of the lab since they arrived. Sung flipped through the document the pilgrimage had assembled.

“Which means by extension that self-awareness is a powerful thing too.” he said. “The whole world has been going over the question of why an alien civilization would bottle us up, and really the answer’s so obvious when you look at it from Jenkins’ perspective. We’ve been quarantined and the only reason to quarantine something is because it’s dangerous."

Tremblay sipped his coffee, and poked around the lab, pausing at a sample of alien bone that was attached to a detailed report on its composition, strength, density and toughness - all depressingly inferior to the human norm, to judge by a summary of percentages that ran down one side of the page. “I suppose it’s hard to argue with that.” he mused. “Hmm.. hand me that notepad a second, would you?”

Sung did so, and availed himself of the coffee as well while the general flipped through the contents of the Abductee handbook, logged on to the lab’s computer and watched the footage from Rogers Arena, referring back to the notepad several times.

“Something up, sir?” he asked.

“Just… looking at things from a military perspective.”

Tremblay picked up a pen and tapped the screen with the reverse end. “See here? The way they exit those pods.”

“What about it?”

“It’s not aggressive enough.” Tremblay said. when Sung raised an eyebrow and gestured a need for more information, he stood up and put down his coffee. “Okay, so when a soldier enters a hostile area full of known threats, they move like this…"

Miming holding a gun, he barged forward, pretend weapon tucked tight into his shoulder and pointed almost along his sightline, weight forward, posture loose but coiled, ready to spring in any direction as danger demanded. Sung blinked and the general was half-way through dropping some virtual targets with a volley of precise shots. The burst of simulated violence lasted no more than a second or two before he relaxed again.

“Bear in mind that I’ve not done that for real in about ten years, and I’m fifty-one years old. I’ve slowed down a lot. But you get the idea - aggression. You throw yourself into the fight economically and efficiently - little movements, big effect, make the best possible use of the moment of surprise.” Tremblay told him. “Now the aliens moved like this…"

Despite being deficient two pairs of legs, Tremblay’s imitation of the beasts on the screen was uncanny. This time, the posture was upright and proud, the invisible gun held awkwardly level with his solar plexus and out away from his body. His progress across the room was notably slower, more like arrogant strutting than a hostile rush, and his “weapon” was much slower to aim. Everything looked more sluggish, less precise, less deadly compared to the study in focused violence that had preceded it.

“I follow.” Sung nodded.

“Yep. But then we get to… here…" Tremblay clicked forward in the footage to the point where one of the players swept in and smashed one of the aliens to the ice with his hockey stick. Obviously panicked though they were, as the remaining Hunters drew together in a defensive circle, their posture changed as well, into a stance much more like the one the general had first demonstrated - compact, focused, precise.

“That did them no good of course, but it shows that they at least know how to do things properly, so the question is, why weren’t they moving like that in the first place?”

“You have a theory there?” Sung asked him.

“I do. And it’s one that bears out Jenkins’ account of these things being the boogeymen of interstellar space. They practically swaggered out of those pods as if it didn’t matter if they did things the right way or not, like they seriously believed they were invulnerable." Tremblay picked up his coffee again. “They got cocky.”

“Does that scare you?”

Tremblay shrugged, shaking his head very slightly with a wide-eyed expression. “I don’t know what to feel, yet. I’ve not had first-hand experience or years to get my head around the idea. It just doesn’t seem real, somehow.”

They sat in silence for a while, Sung sensing that the general was in the mood for a little peace and quiet, and content to give it to him. Eventually, both their meandering trains of thought were brought back to the here-and-now when Jenkins returned with the scientists.

“Well, you’ll be pleased to know the fMRI corroborated my account.” Jenkins said.

Tremblay accepted the summary and afforded it a quick reading.

“Fine. I think I’m convinced” he said. “But interesting as all of this is, the information’s a bit academic, isn’t it?”

“Yep.” Jenkins agreed. “But I wanted to make sure you’d got your heads around a few things before I dropped the real surprise on you."

“Which is?”

Jenkins grinned, and retrieved the battered hiking pack he’d been carrying when he first arrived at the base. Buried at the bottom under his spare shirts and underwear was a padded manila envelope, which he presented to the general.

Tremblay opened it and tipped its contents out onto his hand - a small, featureless silver box, about the size of a hard drive. The only feature of note on its surface was what appeared to be a power socket on one end, though not of a make that Tremblay recognised.

They all leaned closer, jaws dropping. Sung broke the silence, though only barely. “Is this…?”

Jenkins’ grin would have put the Cheshire Cat to shame. “Alien, yep. I managed to get my hands on it while working in a ship salvage yard on Freeport Fifty- Two. Smuggled it back to Earth when the observation team finally agreed to strip out my implants and bring me home.”

“What is it?”

The spacefarer’s smile broadened even further.

“This, gentlemen… is an FTL engine.”

Chapter 9
6.5: “Jargon” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Two years and nine months after the Vancouver Attack

“A screensaver? Not seen one of those in years, Ted…”

“Uh, that’s… actually a simulation…”

The office shared by Major Ted Bartlett and Captain Claude Nadeau was best described as an ‘organized mess.’ Although both men had been drilled into the habit of neatness throughout their careers, the demands of their jobs meant that every spare surface and shelf in the room was laden with books, papers and tablets. It looked like the statelier kind of second-hand book shop: Densely crowded, but still as tidy and organized as it could possibly be.

The fields of study that had seen them through University were becoming hazy and uncertain now. The last two years had forced them both to branch out from their respective disciplines of Cosmology and Electrostatics, and become multidisciplinarians. It was no good focusing on one small aspect when the results came from a more holistic approach.

“What of?”

“It’s a folded-space topological problem.”

“We already cracked Super-L, Ted.”

“One type, sure. That little book detailed three kinds, eh?”

“I thought the general’s planning to recommend that we’re not interested in type 2 ERBs?”

“And for good reason, sure. But…”

“What?”

“I sent the tuning algorithm to a friend of mine, she lectures in mathematics over in Nottingham, England. Purely as an abstract puzzle in search of a solution, eh?”

“We already know the solution, though.”

“She found two, Claude.”

“No shit?”

“Nope. She gave me an alternative solution which is pseudo-stable for R T less than one if delta-E set one to set two is greater than the exponent of the tensor of set three p-one to p-two.”

Nadeau grabbed a paper and ball-point pen - there was yet to be a better substitute for the brainstorming physicist - and scribbled out a handful of equations. “…Right.” He considered it, then moved a few terms around, playing with the algebra. “I see it, but… What’s the Lebesgue?”

“Three.”

“That’s helpful. You’re sure, now?”

Bartlett sketched out a proof, to his colleague’s satisfaction.

“The only awkward bit is that exponent.” he said. “I worked on it some more and got this graph.”

it was mostly red, though running diagonally up and right was a curved funnel of slowly-widening blue. He tapped a point towards its flared end. “Fifty grams.” he said.

“Yeah, at seventy KC.” Nadeau said.

“Possible.”

“Hence the screensaver?”

“Hence the simulation, yes. All we need is an intersection of two ISD fields of those magnitudes which remains within acceptable bounds for, uh… six to the minus ten S."

“Think there is one?”

“Not enough to bet time on the IBM on it. It’s busy enough with the ESF equations for your “put the energy companies out of business” idea.”

“Which is why you’re running a fancy new screensaver-”

“-simulation-"

“-on your personal laptop rather than wasting base resources. Right.”

Bartlett sighed, and with a push of his legs, boosted his chair over to the office’s perpetual coffee source. “I tell you Claude, I’m jealous of your field sometimes. ESFs are going to change the world more than ISD is.

“You might be wrong there, Major.”

“Oh come on. You’ve already given us the tech for cheap spaceflight, viable asteroid mining, trivially easy near-Earth object tracking and deflection and buildings ten times as tall as we could already build. What have I got, besides one experimental spaceship that got named by our bartender?"

“Well,” Claude Nadeau said, slowly and with care “Your screensaver just turned green…”

Bartlett sighed. “For the last time, it’s a simula- wait, what?"

Chapter 12
Chapter 09: “Gains and Losses” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Three years and one month AV
500 West Hotel, San Diego, California, United States of America

"…in a prepared statement, the President of the Russian Federation declared that his country would have no part in what he called “the Western monopoly” on space travel, A sentiment echoed by the People’s Republic of China in their own statement just three hours later."

"Meanwhile the Japanese Aerospace Exploration Agency, JAXA, announced today that the first atmospheric test-flight of their own space plane, codenamed “Inazuma” has been a success, and that the new craft will be attempting to make orbit in a flight scheduled for next week."

"With rumours abounding that several South American nations are in talks to form their own unified space agency, not to mention the fledgling private endeavours of Virgin, Red Bull, Mitsubishi, Google and BAE Systems, It seems that the second Space Race has begun in earnest."

"Joining me on the show tonight is British science fiction author…

♪♫WOOOP WOOOP that’s the sound of tha police! WOOOP WOOOP that’s the sound of tha beast! WOOOP WO-♫♪

+click+

“Terri Boone. Good afternoon, detective.”

She’d taken an immediate liking to the homicide detective who’d attended the scene. Gabriel Ares, a by-the-book type who was packing quite a lot of wiry strength into his short frame. The man was shorter than Terri, and Terri was only average height at best. but he’d ran a practiced eye over Terri’s apartment and immediately declined to arrest her so long as she kept the SDPD informed as to her whereabouts.

“Good afternoon, Miss Boone. I thought you’d want to know that the department is satisfied you acted in self-defense and seeing as you’ve obeyed the terms we set, we won’t be prosecuting.”

“Good, because I was getting antsy sitting around in a hotel when an organisation I’ve worked for is trying to kill me.” Terri pulled the towel off her hair and started to shrug into her jacket one-handed. She had no intention of staying in the hotel a moment longer than necessary.

“Yeah… look, Miss Boone, we simply have no evidence that this guy ever worked for anybody other than himself.”

“You checked his office?”

“The landlord of the address you gave swears that the guy who attacked you was the sole user of that office except for business guests. No other registered employees, and we can find no evidence of any business associates. If he’s a member of some conspiracy or organisation, then there’s just no evidence pointing to it. I’m sorry, but without any evidence I can’t turn department resources to investigating your claims. We’ve done everything we reasonably can.”

“That doesn’t strike you as odd that a guy who describes himself as a “business network consultant” didn’t have any easy-to-follow business associates?”

“It strikes me as a lot odd, yeah. But it’s not enough to launch an investigation over. Lo siento.”

“…Fine. You’ve got enough to worry about.” Terri knew that the way she phrased that could be construed as bitter, but she honestly wasn’t. Fortunately, Detective Ares seemed to either be good enough at judging tone of voice via phone call to get that, or jaded enough not to care.

“You’re a P. I., right?” he asked.

“Right…”

“Go ahead and investigate this on your own terms. If you turn up anything solid, you’ve got my number, and… Well. Stay safe and let me know how you get on.”

"Gracias, detective."

“De nada. Stay safe, Miss Boone. Hasta luego”

Terri grabbed her bags and took the stairs down to the reception desk. The outcome had been pretty much exactly what she expected, so all she was left with now was the question she had been mulling over for five days.

<+Why on Earth would a list of alien abductees be worth killing over?+>

Three years and three months AV
Bulford ECTC, Salisbury Plain, England.

“Fall in!”

They did so, instantly. Every man in the unit was a volunteer, taken from all around the English-speaking world without regard for their previous unit. Every single one was special forces.

“Today marks your first session training for combat in prevalent extraterrestrial conditions. We’re going to start slow with an obstacle course, and work our way up to live-fire over the next week. By the end of this training program, you will have gained the skills and knowledge useful in moving effectively in low-gravity environments, and will have learned to identify and react appropriately to the catalogue of known potential nonhuman contacts. Completing this training will certify you for off-world missions, some of which will be of indefinite duration. If anybody wishes to back out, say so now and it will not be held against you.”

None did. They had all already gone through far worse just to get where they were, and taken far more dangerous assignments during their careers. Their instructor waited a moment or two before nodding his approval, and then gave a thumbs-up to the control room mounted high along one of the tall inside walls of the ECTC hangar.

He flexed his knees and absorbed the sudden change in gravity with practiced familiarity, resisting a smirk as the spec-ops veterans all staggered, swayed or exclaimed aloud at the difference.

“Line up! When I blow my whistle you will run that obstacle course, best time!”

Several minutes, bumped heads, scraped elbows and bruised egos later, the last of the veterans flew off the end of the last rope and trotted to a halt awkwardly, instincts undone by the lower gravity. While all had, to their credit, managed exceptional times, not a single one had completed the course with their dignity completely intact.

That was okay.

“This first run was planned to destroy any illusions you may have had about knowing what you’re doing.” the instructor said. “You have spent your life training for Earth’s gravity, which is thirty percent higher than the off- world norm. That thirty percent makes a surprising difference, as you have just learned. Every instinct you have about how to move, how long you have to react and what you can achieve is wrong. Forget them and start over. Any questions?”

There were some, which were promptly answered to everyone’s satisfaction.

“Right! Back to the start: we’re going again and if any man here fails to beat the time he just set, the whole unit is doing a hundred pushups in double gravity! Move!”

To his grudging satisfaction, no pushups were necessary. But they still had a long way to go.

Planet Nightmare

Summer was coming. Over the years, Julian Etsicitty had learned to view summer on this hellscape the same way winter might be viewed back home - the good times were over for another year. Soon - too soon - he’d be out of the season of plenty, where hardy nuts and roots and hibernating animals were easily dug out from beneath the snow and frozen ground, and into the season of explosive growth.

Back to mornings and dusks spent lurking under two layers of mosquito netting. Back to checking his boots for venomous biting things that had found a nice dark place to make their nest and spawn a new generation of tiny monsters. Back to spending his days desperately slashing back at the encroaching greenery around his camp, doing nothing but keeping back a wall of vegetation that grew so quickly you could see it.

Hopefully, at long last, there would be no bombfruit bushes this time around. He thought he had killed them all: It was hard to tell, when the fruit literally exploded and sent its seeds flying everywhere. He had been very lucky indeed to survive the woody shrapnel of his first encounter with bombfruit, and the scar down his right forearm was a constant reminder not to take anything on Nightmare for granted.

Sure, calories and vitamins weren’t hard to come by in the summer months, so there was that saving grace. It was a wonderful time to prepare jerky by the fire for the rest of the year, to dry fruits to ward off scurvy until the next growing season. There was a lot of work to do in the summer, all of it physically demanding, and all of it in sweltering heat.

He was determined to enjoy the last few quiet weeks of snow and silence while he could, so had made himself a warm fruit juice when the sound rolled over the forest and hills: the unmistakable noise of a sonic boom.

he paused, tense, and then rushed to his hut and grabbed, from its special stash above the bed, the “rescue potential” kit. A flare gun, a shaving mirror, the solar-charged two-way radio.

He emerged into the clear ground around his camp not a moment too soon. A teardrop of steel and matte black was just emerging from behind the peak he’d named “Mount Fuck You” for the way it stood much taller than the three mountains that flanked it.

He raised the gun, and shot the flare high into the sky over the forests.

He almost collapsed with relief when the ship immediately changed course toward him.

++

"Hello, Julian. Welcome aboard."

“Uh… hello.” He replied, nonplussed at the absence of a welcoming party on the door.

"I’m sorry for not greeting you in person, but I suspect that standing in your presence right now would prove fatal for me. You’re setting off a lot of biohazard alarms up here…"

“I am?”

“I’m afraid so. Decontamination won’t take long, fortunately, and the good news is you’ll feel thoroughly clean once we’re done. Would you be so good as to dispose of your clothes in the incinerator to your left?*”

Julian practically rushed to comply. The thought of feeling clean for the first time in who-knew how long was incentive enough.

He paused at the idea of throwing away the predator-tooth necklace he’d made, though. or the carved wooden beads that were on it. He had worked long and hard on those, they were unique.

"If there are any items you wish to keep, there is an autoclave on the front wall." the voice said.

Having heard that, Julian needed nothing more, and was soon standing naked in the middle of the chamber, a little surprised at how unselfconscious he was about it. “What now?”

A device - little more than a black dome mounted in some kind of white frame on the wall - glowed blue at him for a second.

"Checking… okay, you’re good to proceed into the next room." The door slid into the floor, revealing a slightly less sterile-seeming room on the far side. The threshold had a strange golden haze to it, but Julian didn’t let that bother him.

“Wow!” he exclaimed, coming to a halt as soon as he’d passed it.

"Feel strange?"

“It did.” His teeth were abnormally clean, the crawling, itching sensation in his hair and beard to which he had acclimatized was gone, the hair and beard themselves were clean and soft and his skin felt scrubbed. His body odour suddenly became conspicuous in its absence.

"You had rather a lot of parasites. They’re gone now including, you’ll be happy to know, the ones that were threatening your liver function. There are clean clothes in the nanofactory’s dispensary hopper to your right."

Clean clothes!

They were a strange, neutral kind of cut - little more than a T-shirt, tracksuit pants and a pair of remarkably generic-looking boots - but they fit him perfectly, and they felt so very, VERY good.

“So… who are you?” He asked to the walls as he put them on.

“Most humans call me Kirk.” the voice said. “And yes, I’ve watched Star Trek, so I understand the joke.”

“I never did.” Julian confessed, noting the most humans bit. “We didn’t have a TV.”

"Yes, I’ve read your file. The Directorate wanted a wilderness survival expert who was low-profile enough to be missed: a remarkably rare thing to find in any civilization."

“Lucky me.”

"You should be proud. You’ve set a record for surviving on Nightmare that nobody else could have."

“Can I go home now?”

"…I wish I could. I truly to. But there have been… complications."

“I don’t like the sound of that.”

"I knew you wouldn’t. Nobody ever does. Why don’t you come up to the common room, and I’ll brief you?"

“And after that?”

"After that, I’ll be asking for your help."

Three years and four months AV
Cape Canaveral, Florida

“Here she comes…”

Pandora’s engines were a low rushing sound like waves breaking against distant cliffs as she passed low over the facility. They went completely silent as she circled briefly and then set down on the concrete, lifting herself only on the shaped fields of her ESFALS module until her wheels kissed the hardtop. She was promptly surrounded by technicians who began the laborious checklist to ensure that she would be worthy to fly again.

Rylee Jackson took the ladder and patted the aircraft fondly before she strolled over towards the waiting entourage, stripping off her gauntlets.

“So you’re the new… oh, Danny! You made it!”

Danny Cho smiled at Rylee. The pair of them had served in the same wing over the middle east, and firm though sporadic friends, both married more to their jobs than to actual people.

“sure did.” he said. “I’ll be flying Ariadne."

Rylee shook hands with him then shared introductions with the other four pilots: Carys Davies, formerly of the RAF, flying Niobe, Steve Hogan formerly of the Royal Australian Air Force, flying Medea, and James Carter and Adam Kosinski, both ex-USAF, flying Electra and Danae respectively. Collectively, Odyssey WIng. Another wing of five Lockheed TS-101s - the vehicle for which Pandora herself had been the prototype - was being delivered to Europe to form the foundation of Edda Wing - Baldur, Dagur, Freyja, Magni and Skadi, but they wouldn’t be ready for another few weeks yet, and there was talk of establishing a wing in the southern hemisphere called Tāwhaki Wing.

Between them, the Russian, Chinese and Japanese efforts, plus private campaigns, Rylee suspected that her sky was going to start filling up before long. It was a bittersweet thought.

“Did you hear Red Bull got their prototype up?” Danny asked, as they walked in a loose group to the hangar.

“I didn’t!”

“Too busy swapping notes with an alien raccoon?” He teased.

“Hey, he’s a friend, lay off. But Red Bull? Seriously? I would have thought Virgin Galactic or SpaceX…”

“Red Bull had their eye on space ever since they sponsored Felix Baumgartner.” Davies said. Rylee decided that she liked her accent, which was soft and melodic, but still had a bit of workmanlike grit. “And things have got cheaper since then thanks to ESAFS. I think after that crash Virgin had a few years ago they’ve been playing things very carefully.”

They stepped through the slightly ajar hangar door and Rylee couldn’t suppress her smile at seeing five more _Pandora_s waiting inside.

Except not quite. On closer inspection, they were just a little more polished: Less prototype, more production model. Her girl was still unique.

“Did they go FTL?” She asked.

“Yep! just a little jaunt out to Ceres and back.” Danny told her.

“Think they’ll set anything up out there?” asked Kosinski.

Davies scoffed. “Somebody needs to, or we’re never going to get the property laws sorted out."

“I guess we should just be glad that the whole “no weapons in space” thing was repealed,” Rylee mused.

The thus-far silent Carter raised an eyebrow “How d’you figure?”

“Well, you realise that the barrier’s a casus belli, right? The GRA’s been pretty clear that they consider the demilitarization of space to be short- sighted in view of some of the threats that are out there."

“Makes sense, I guess…” Carter conceded. “Not sure I like it.”

“Get used to it, wagon.” she teased. “Because getting some weapons in place up there is going to be Odyssey Wing’s first mission.”

Three years and six months AV
Scotch Creek Extraterrestrial Research Facility.

“And the jammer is… live.”

Nobody in the room needed to be told that. Every single one felt, rather than heard, a highly pitched keening that seemed to bypass actual sound and become an immediate feature of their audible world.

“That… puts my teeth on edge.” Martin Tremblay declared.

“Sorry, General.”

“It’s fine, Major, just get this demonstration underway.” Tremblay ordered. Bartlett nodded and swiftly complied.

“Simple enough, we open a wormhole and….” he looked across to his colleague on the other side of the laboratory as the vacuum chamber in front of him became a visibly distorted knot of isolated spacetime distortions, bending the light that passed through it in disconcerting ways. “Anything?”

“Not a whisper.” the scientist reported.

Bartlett shut the jammer off and everybody in the room untensed just a little.

“At less than ten meters, and that was a stable connection without any harmonic damping.” He announced. “We’ve cracked it: deploy one of these on any ship with a jump drive, and it’ll be able to use that drive immune to detection by out-of-system scanners. If we stick it on a warp-capable minisat, we’ll be able to completely block the detection of any FTL or wormhole activity inside the volume of effect, while the field itself will notify us of any that happens inside its ambit.”

He shut down the wormhole generator and the abused spacetime inside the test chamber sprang back into shape.

“Good, because without that, WERBS would have been a one-shot advantage.”

That comment came from Major-General Gregory Pierce, Tremblay’s superior and the man most directly responsible for deciding which of the Scotch Creek facility’s incredible discoveries were Canadian national secrets, which were shared among NATO members, and which went global.

“As you say, sir. But now that we’ve got this, a test run shouldn’t be difficult.” Bartlett agreed.

“Not in Sol.” Tremblay said. “Jammer or not, we should be careful.”

Pierce considered this. “Cimbrean?”

“We don’t even know if that colony is still alive, and even if it is we really don’t want WERBS linked to a human organization, especially not one that officially doesn’t exist, sir.” Bartlett said. “There are plenty of uninhabited systems out there, we just need a beacon to get to one of them.”

“This isn’t one I feel comfortable sharing outside of the Treaty nations, gentlemen, and the Agent works for the GRA.”

“Well, it’s either that or WERBS goes untested.” Bartlett said. “Heaven help us if we have to rely on an untested weapon for real, eh?”

“…I’ll see what I can do. In the meantime, you’ll be pleased to know that the dragon’s teeth microsats have been successfully deployed. Edda Wing got the last canister up this morning.”

“That’s step one, then.” Tremblay said. “How did the Asians take it?”

“Russia condemned the move, obviously.” Pierce told them. “In private, though: Thankfully they weren’t stupid enough to publicly condemn us and leak what Dragon’s Teeth actually does. The Chinese are yet to officially comment, but the scuttlebutt there is that they understand the practicality of the Dragon’s Teeth system but would have preferred to play a more active role in its deployment.”

“Gracious of them.”

“Eh, leave the politics to the politicians.” Pierce said, dismissing the sarcasm. “You’re doing good work round he- damn.”

He paused as the office phone rang. Tremblay answered it, listened for a second, and then wordlessly handed it to his superior.

“Pierce.” This was followed shortly by “…what.”

Those two words set the general tone of a three minute conversation that ended with the general hanging up and looking thoroughly angry.

“The Russian Federation just declared for the Celzi Alliance.” he said.

Tremblay frowned “They can do that?”

“Apparently they’ve not only done that, but they’ve been giving practical support to the Alliance in the form of a Spetsnaz team.” PIerce said. “I should get back. We need to move fast and sound out the PRC before they make their own declaration.” he shook his head. “If I were the Ambassador, I’d be livid.”

Embassy-172

Doctor Anees Hussein was, in fact, actually quite pleased about the situation, though he affected an air of disappointment as he stepped into the ambassadorial debate chamber aboard E-172.

The usual formalities were completed soon. The aliens were as keen to get started as he was.

It was the Kwmbwrw ambassador who spoke first: “Ammbassador Hussein, This is grave news indeed for us. It would seem that your political blocs are not behaving obediently.”

“I did warn you." Hussein replied, calmly unfolding his reading glasses to examine a sheet of paper. “Let’s see… yes, my exact words were that “the GRA acts only as nominal representation of the nations of Earth who will undoubtedly plot their own courses by their own values if they do not see what benefit the GRA brings them”

He set the paper down. “By which, gentlebeings, and in case I was not adequately clear when I said that, I meant that ANY nation, treaty, alliance or other one of our political entities might decide the same. The GRA does not rule, it represents by consent, and could be dissolved overnight if the nations so chose.”

What he left unsaid, but knew would be snaking treacherously through the gathered Ambassadorial minds, was the implication: If Russia might do that, what’s stopping the rest of us?

That implication alone was enough for most of the Ambassadors, and he settled back to steer the slow collapse of their resolve. As ever, they assured and reassured him of just how much of the Dominion’s vast resources might be owed to Earth.

Much of which, in fairness, had already started to arrive. Solar collection forcefield technology was on the cusp of revolutionizing Earth’s energy industry in ways that all other solar power tech had only hinted at. The last piece of the quantum-computing puzzle had been a collective headslap for the experts in that field. The Corti Directorate had - reluctantly and with bad grace - been strong-armed into revealing the secret by which the human immune system could be tricked into tolerating the presence of foreign cybernetic implants without weakening.

This last concession had particularly irked the Directorate’s ambassador. He in particular was a nut had persisted in being more difficult to crack than the others, and became more so with every meeting.

Doctor Hussein was beginning to suspect that the Corti wasn’t even bothering to remain unemotional any more. In fact, he suspected, the Corti was gladly simmering in a building resentment of, and hatred for, the whole of the human race.

He watched as the little grey being examined a message that had apparently just arrived for him, and then met Hussein’s eye. Anees decided that the expression on the ambassador’s face was that of grim satisfaction, as if an obstacle or irritation had been dealt with.

They were beginning to enter some dangerous territory. It would not do to be too aggressive from here on out.

Date Point: 3 years and 6 months AV
San Diego, California, USA, Earth

brrrrrp. brrrrrp. brrr-

“-Detective Gabriel Ares.”

“Ares, it’s Terri Boone here. Remember me?”

“Sure do. Que pasa, how’s your investigation getting on?

“long and dull, I’m sure you know how they are…”

Terri shouldered the door open, wishing not for the first time that she could linger in the air-conditioned office building just a little longer. The air in the courtyard parking space out back felt hot enough to bake bread.

“…I’ve found something interesting. A law firm called Grey, Stanton and Friedman.”

“They’re not criminal or business lawyers or I’d know them.” Ares said.

“No, they’re civil rights lawyers, but their finances - don’t ask me what I had to do to track this down - are handled by the same firm that did accounting for Johnson. I just tried to look them up - and that wasn’t easy - and their address doesn’t rent to a company by that name, never has.”

“Suspicious, but…”

Terri sighed as she fumbled for her car keys in an awkward, one-handed and one-elbowed manoeuvre familiar to any woman who ever simultaneously tried to operate both her phone and her handbag.

“Detective, They tried to kill me over a list of alien abductees still extant from Earth. Stanton Friedman is a UFOlogist who was the original investigator of the Roswell incident and “Grey” is-”

Mr. Johnson stepped around the corner. It WAS him, there could be no doubt, right down to the neatly tailored suit and the suave facial hair. He was holding an assault rifle.

“Fuck!” she yelled, and dove for the cover of her car. Johnson opened fire, winging her with a round through the calf.

“Boone! Where are you!” Ares yelled, loud enough to hear despite the phone being on the ground next to her. She shouted the address at it as she dug through her handbag for her m1911, cowering against the engine block as Johnson emptied the magazine.

<+How? How the FUCK?! I KILLED him!+>

He stopped firing, and she hauled herself up and around to shoot back, only to be confronted with an awful truth.

The assault rifle had a grenade launcher on it.

This revelation arrived only a shaved instant before the grenade itself turned her car into a fireball and a blizzard of steel shards.

Terri was thrown halfway across the lot. She tried to get up, to keep fighting, amazed to be alive, and looked down for her gun.

There was so much less of her than there should be. There was so much more of her than there should be, pieces that God had never intended to see the light of day.

<+No…+>

It was a sad, desperate thought, and it was her last one. When Johnson walked up and calmly fired a round through her skull for certainty’s sake, Terri Boone’s corpse didn’t even twitch.

Chapter 15
Chapter 12: “Only Human” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Three years and seven months AV
Alliance Embassy Station, Sol

Rylee Jackson woke, and groaned. Talamay must have been stronger than it had tasted.

She groaned even louder when the previous night’s conversation came back to her, and buried her face in her pillow for a second, then rolled over and look up at Pandora’s wing, flung over her cot like a protective lover’s arm.

She spoke the word that heralded a bad start to any day: “Shit.”

Civilian Trade Station 1039: “Infinity Awaits”

Fear was a sickly sensation in Kttrvk’s long throat as he read the message again to be certain of its content.

He read it a third time, just in case.

When a fourth reading still produced no miraculous change in its content, he concluded that its content must therefore be real, and set about writing a reply.

It was a simple reply:

"Sir,

As I explained in my previous letter, the trade route you have designated for our shipment is currently the target of Hunter raids. Four more vesselss have been hit since I sent that letter, all comparatively small: A freighter the size of the Nkvcqtz will be a target they cannot resist.

Our cargo of mineral ores is non-perishable and will come to no harm should we take the slightly longer route that I suggested. I appreciate that the client expects prompt delivery, but I feel certain that they would prefer the shipment arrive slightly delayed, than never arrive at all because the freighter carrying it was raided by Hunters and the personnel and children on board, devoured.

_I object in the strongest possible terms to these orders, and request - again

that you authorise us to take the longer route._

-Shipmaster Kttrvk.

He sent it, and the message was scooped up by a handler program, to be updated onto the galactic network in the next regular synchronization, and from there to the desk of his supervisor.

He knew in his bones, however, that the appeal was futile.

Cimbrean

Jennifer Delaney. Mid-twenties, entirely out of fucks to give about being a pirate queen, colonial governor or immortal, but not letting go of the space- babe part. Currently wearing fatigues, army boots and a thick black woollen jumper, and contemplating the bar of actual chocolate on the table in front of her, waiting for the alarm to ring or the spaceship to land or whatever else would interrupt her attempt to enjoy it.

She was also reflecting that, while showing up completely arse-naked and demanding to be clothed wouldn’t have been her first choice in ice-breakers - wouldn’t even have made the top hundred - it had undeniably worked. Apparently the soldiers respected a woman who didn’t give two shits for embarrassment and just asked for a pair of pants. She would have expected to be on the receiving end of a lot of lecherous jokes and sly side-of-the-eye stares, but in fact they were, on the whole, treating her with deference and respect.

“Tastes better if you eat it with your mouth, love.”

Somewhere deep inside her, Old Jen was impressed and a little scared by the way that she didn’t jump, just turned in her seat to quickly assess whether the voice that had snuck up on her was a threat. Captain Owen Powell gave her a winning smile full of Yorkshire arrogance, and she relaxed a bit.

“Just… enjoying the moment.” she said. “And don’t call me “love”.”

Powell nodded. “Aye, sorry. Force of habit. I’d ask if I can come in, but this is my office, so…”

He entered and sat down on the other stool, on the opposite side of the desk. “So, are you going to eat that?”

“Promise me nothing’s going to start exploding if I do?”

She wasn’t sure what she had expected Powell’s reaction to be: a laugh, maybe, or a joke. Not an understanding look in his eye. “Wish I could.” he said. “You’d best eat it fast, enjoy it while you can. In the army they trained us to brew a cup of tea every chance we get, because you never know when the next one’s going to show up.”

Jen breathed a little half-laugh. “That’s so fecking English…” she said.

Powell snorted. “Ten thousand lightyears from home and the Irish are still being fookin’ Irish.”

That got a genuine laugh. “Alright, fine. I’ll eat the fecking thing.” Jen conceded, and promptly made good on that promise.

Chocolate. Fuck yeah.

Mount Hope Cemetery, San Diego

“May her soul, and the souls of all the faithful departed through the mercy of God, rest in peace.”

The solemn "Amen" which followed that petition was joined by all bar one of the graveside mourners. The priest closed his book, bowed solemnly, and turned away, leaving only the small knot of family and friends.

It was a good headstone, understated and handsome: just the name “Terri Boone” flanked by carved lilies, her dates of birth and death, and the quote "A loving heart is the beginning of all knowledge." on round-topped blue slate.

“You’re not a praying man, Mister Jenkins?”

“I’m not, detective. Let’s… just leave it at that.”

“Fair enough.”

Gabriel Ares shuffled his feet and exhaled, feeling in his bones that the occasion should have really warranted something other than a glorious sunny day.

“Do you come to the funerals of all your cases?” Jenkins asked him.

“Not all, no. Just the ones that really get to me. You know, the stupid kid who got caught up in gang violence, or the young mother who died of a bleed on the brain after her husband hit her for the hundredth time… The streetwise P. I. who I kind of feel like I could have helped if I’d only listened.”

“Are you listening now?”

Jenkins was a good two heads taller than the diminutive Hispanic homicide cop, who looked up at him curiously.

“Listening to… who, now?” He asked.

“Ravi Singh, for one.”

“How do you…? Right, you had the login details.”

“I do, yeah. Downloaded the lot. You HAVE read it all?”

“Three times.” Ares told him. “She makes a… compelling case. But come on, secret aliens murdering people in San Diego?”

“What, as opposed to alien monsters on TV getting the shit kicked out of them by hockey players? As opposed to alien embassies orbiting the moon?”

“I know!” Ares exclaimed. A few startled gasps and glances from the other mourners moderated his volume. “I know. I agree. You’re preaching to the choir, compañero. But I have to answer to people, and even if they were persuaded, which they’re not, there’s this little thing called ‘Jurisdiction’ biting me in the culo."

“What about the FBI?”

“The feds?” Gabriel made a scornful noise through his nose. “The pendejo I spoke to said he’d put me through to Special Agent Mulder and then hung up. They’ve got enough to worry about without alien conspiracy theories. People didn’t stop murdering each other just because there’s a couple of alien space stations up there."

“Need a hand?”

“You’d go all the way to New Jersey?”

“If it got us to the bottom of this, I’d even go back into space.” Jenkins told him, firmly. “I want these fuckers to fry, Ares.”

The detective stared at the headstone for a long while, and then shook his head. “I’m not… You realise I can’t authorise that, right?Not officially. This is a police matter, I can’t bring in civilians to interrogate a witness.”

“That wouldn’t be by-the-book, huh?”

"Lo tienes."

“Does going by the book always work?”

“No. But going against it NEVER works, Jenkins, to hell with what cop shows and movie writers think.”

“So you won’t help me.”

“Can’t.” Ares corrected.

They stood in silence for a while. Most of the mourners paid their final respects and departed.

“Of course…” Jenkins mused. “Seeing as New Jersey is outside of your jurisdiction, if I were to go talk with this guy, it’s not like you could arrest me for it anyway.”

Ares half-laughed and half-huffed. “If having a conversation with some guy in New Jersey was illegal then I could arrest you right now for planning to commit an offense.” he said. "IF," he added, turning to look Jenkins right in the eye “having a conversation with some guy in New Jersey was illegal.”

They considered each other’s expressions for a moment, and then both men stuck out their hands to be shaken at the same time.

“I’ll let you know if I think of anything that could be useful to your investigation, Detective Ares.”

“I’d appreciate that, Mr. Jenkins. Buena suerte."

Civilian Trade Station 1039: “Infinity Awaits”

"Shipmaster Kttrvk,

"You have received your orders. As per your contract with the corporation, failure to follow your assigned route is punishable by demotion, confiscation of your ship and fines up to 5% of the value of the cargo per [day] of late delivery"

"-Ikktik, Deputy Shipping Executive"

Kttrvk knew at that exact moment that nobody in the corporation even bothered to read their mail.

He weighed up the possibility of refusing and then counter-suing the corporation for reckless endangerment of his and his family’s lives when they took action against him. A fair court would surely come down on his side.

But of course, Long Stars Shipping would never see the inside of a fair court in a case like this, would they? They owned the judges, they could afford the best lawyers, they lobbied for the laws that worked in their favour.

For long minutes he sat, thinking, while his mate Ikkzziki slumbered, rotund with what would be their fourth child.

There was only one possible course of action.

Alliance Embassy Station, Sol

“Good morning, Rylee.”

Rylee flinched. She knew that the voice she heard wasn’t exactly Niral so much as a computer simulation of what Niral’s voice might sound like if she was speaking English, cunningly conveyed to her ears by harmonic trickery in a way that completely overruled the original voice, but the simulation was totally consistent in giving Niral an identifiable voice.

“…Niral! Hey. Good morning.”

“A very good morning.” Niral’s ears were flattened sideways. The effect looked either mischievous or smug to Rylee. Her tall posture, shoulders thrown back and head held high, suggested the latter.

“Oh! You guys, uh…?”

“That we most certainly did.” The Gaoian purred. “The first of many I hope, before we’re certain I’m with cub.”

“That’s umm… Great. I’m happy for you.” Rylee found she couldn’t meet the Sister’s gaze. She was surprised when Niral issued a low keening sound and took her hands.

“Rylee, are you all right?”

“I made a complete ass of myself last night, didn’t I?”

“…A backside? Oh! Um… I don’t know, did you?”

“That’s usually what we call it when somebody makes someone else feel uncomfortable by confessing to being… interested in them. And all the rest. I’m sorry Niral, I was drunk, I wasn’t thinking straight and I ran off at the mouth."

Niral keened softly again and hugged her. Presumably she was hugging quite hard by Gaoian standards, but to Rylee the effect was of being gently hugged by an anorexic teenager - under all that fur, the Gaoian’s body was small, wiry, feather-light and frail. “I don’t think I understand this ‘drunk’ thing.” Niral told her. “But I wasn’t drunk last night, and I still say you’re my friend.”

“You’re not upset?”

“If I’m going to have alien friends, I need to be okay with them behaving in alien ways.” Niral replied, stroking Rylee’s hair. “I’m not upset.”

Rylee broke the hug very gently, and wiped away a grateful tear, pulling herself together. “Oh, I needed to hear that.” she smiled, then a thought struck her. “Shit, you didn’t tell Goruu what I said, did you?”

Niral tittered a Gaoian giggle. “We were too busy.” she teased. “But… no, I wouldn’t. Not if you don’t want him to know.”

“I don’t.” Rylee said firmly.

There was a moment of comfortable silence, faintly amused on Niral’s part. Then she looked up at the space-plane wing that Rylee had been sleeping under.

“So this is Pandora?"

“This is Pandora."

“Does the name mean anything special? The first Gaoian warp craft was named Tiritya, after the first Mother-Supreme, who united the females of all clans into one clan."

Rylee smiled. “Pandora was the first woman, according to Greek mythology.”

“The… how can there be a first woman? And what’s a Greek? One of your clans?”

“Yeah, sort of. Mythology means… kind of, fanciful stories, an entertaining way of getting points across using fiction. It doesn’t always have to be scientifically accurate. Besides, they didn’t really understand evolution by natural selection back in ancient Greece. It’s a very old story.”

“Oh. So, your first warp craft is named to honour the first female and not the first male?” The idea seemed to have Niral’s approval, and not for the first time Rylee was struck by the notion that Gaoian females were maybe a bit sexist.

“Well, she was more than just the first woman.” Rylee said, beginning to pack up her cot and stow it away in the ship’s small cargo compartment. “She was a curious soul who opened a box in which Zeus, the father of the gods, had sealed away all the evils and negativity of mankind. When they all flew away to plague humanity, the only thing that was left behind was hope, which she kept.”

She glanced at Niral. “It’s all supposed to be metaphorical.” she clarified.

“I guessed as much. But what was hope doing in a box full of evil things?”

“Hope can’t exist without evil.” Rylee said. She rubbed her hand fondly along the fuselage of the modern Pandora. “Just like up can’t exist without down, or how fast only exists relative to slow.”

“And I suppose your species is in a sort of box…” Niral mused.

“Exactly. I choose to believe that Pandora here is our promise that when the box is opened, we’ll be a force for hope and positivity in the galaxy, rather than a plague of evils."

Niral allowed the human a few seconds of distant misty-eyed happiness. “I’m sure you will be.” She said.

Cimbrean

“So, how much do you know about what’s been going on back home?”

Jennifer Delaney, mid-twenties, space-babe with a mouthful of the first chocolate she’d tasted in years, regretfully swallowed it.

“Not much.” She confessed. “The alien news only covered the big things: the Hunters attacked Vancouver?” when Powell nodded, she continued. “Then there’s a fecking big force-field, we have warp travel now… That’s about it. I know that our ambassador to the Dominion is called Doctor Anees Hussein because he wrote me a letter, and he hinted that we’re maybe wanting to play both sides to our advantage, but other than that, I’m pretty well in the dark.”

“Right. Well, it’s mostly business as usual.” Powell said. “The usual political gobshites, same sports, same celebrity gossip, same bullshit in the Middle East. The Russians are still fookin’ crazy, the Chinese still have a stick up their arses, the Yanks are still fookin’ reckless and there’s still a Marvel movie three times a year like fookin’ clockwork.”

“Nothing’s changed at all?”

“I didn’t say that. NASA and the European Space Agency merged to form the North Atlantic Space Agency, the Chinese, Russians and Japanese are all stepping up their space programs, as are the South Americans and the Australians, and there’s even the Pan-Africa Space Organisation now. I think they’re mostly looking at trying to build space elevators, which is easier at the equator or something.”

He sniffed. “A whole bunch of private companies are pushing into space as fast as they can, too. BAE, Virgin, Mitsubishi, Shenyang, Red Bull…”

"Red Bull?!"

“Dont ask. And the cutting edge military technology is… fook me sideways, if you were cleared to know about half of it, you’d shit your new pants.”

“How much AM I cleared to know about?”

“Right, so we took a look at the way business is done out here and promptly said “fook that”, right? Giant fookin’ spaceships with giant fookin’ guns and even gianter fookin’ armour plates pounding the living shite out of each other at spittin’ distance. They’ve got missiles and mines nowadays - apparently they picked that trick up off one of us - but their whole approach is pretty bloody direct.”

“Oh. Really? One of, um, us?”

“Yep. Like to get my hands on that wanker, whoever he was. Give him a lesson in keeping his fookin’ mouth shut.” Powell’s tone was light, but he had a dangerous look in his eye that reminded her a bit of Adrian, though not in a happy way.

Jen suddenly became very grateful for the practice she’d had in the art of lying, and bobbled her head in a way that could mean anything but didn’t really meaning anything specific. Powell apparently took it agreeably.

“Anyway,” he continued “the ships we’re putting up - or, at least, the Lockheed ones that NATO are buying - are built around not that. Long-range weaponry, evasive maneuvers, fookloads of electronic warfare. We use capacitors full of reserve power rather than big reactors, so our ships are small and agile little buggers, built to hit and fade, rip things a new one in the opening seconds, then jump out, recharge, come back and do it again."

“Our weapons stack up to theirs?” Jen asked. That part was genuine news. She’d known for some time that most weapons that she might find pointed at her were nowhere near as deadly as their equivalent on Earth, but she had always assumed that with thousands of years of science behind them, spaceship guns would be far in advance of anything humanity had yet invented.

“In theory.” Powell said, clearly unhappy about not being able to give a more emphatically positive answer. “Because all their stuff’s based around railguns and plasma cannons, our own weapons, which are neither of those things, should be something they don’t know how to handle. Their shields are tuned to stop slow-firing high-energy projectiles traveling at like, one percent of lightspeed, and the armour’s designed for heat dissipation: it’s all ceramic tiles, fragile as balls.”

“So, if we fire a howitzer at them or something?” Jen asked him, latching on to the first “big gun” word she could think of.

“I see what you’re thinking, but nah. It’d just explode against the shields: too slow-firing. But in theory, if we just chuck a load of lower-energy projectiles at them it’ll overwhelm the shields and smash the armour. See?”

“I’ll… have to take your word on all of that.”

Powell smiled. “I take it you’re not a military hardware geek?

“Not really.”

“Well, I am, and the Lockheed TS-101 gives me a hell of a chubby.”

“Charming.” she deadpanned, trying to give the impression that there were more important matters on her mind than the state of his junk. It seemed to work, because Powell cleared his throat and his smile faded.

“Right. Sorry.” He scratched his upper lip with his thumb, lips pursed in thought. “Anyway, back on topic. There’s… a lot of legal questions about Cimbrean here.”

“Like what?” Jen asked, surprised. She had assumed that all of those questions would have been sorted out long before the soldiers came here.

Powell ticked each question off on his fingers as he asked them. “Is this a colony of any one nation? And if so, which one? Or is it its own nation? in which case are you going to have a constitution, are you going to be a democracy? What’s your immigration policy? What are you going to export and import? What’s the customs policy on things like, say, seeds and foodstuffs, because from what I’m told our native Terran species would go through this lot -” he waved an arm, expansively indicating the ecosystem of an entire planet “-like vindaloo through a short grandma.”

“There are questions about you, too.” he added, looking her in the eye. “You were given the job because you were here and because we heard you’d built something, but seeing as what you apparently built is a battlefield, do you even want it any more? Do you want to go home to Earth? Because the next time Kirk swings by here he’ll be able to send you back, no problem. Do you want to stay on as governor, or hand the job off to somebody else?”

Jen’s brow creased as she considered this. “I hadn’t even thought of any of those questions." she confessed. “How much of being a colonial governor would be like that? Desk work, lawmaking, thinking about all the fiddly little details and all that?” She asked.

“Fookin’ near all of it, I’d imagine.” Powell said.

“Then I want to be replaced as soon as possible.” Jen said, firmly. There was no way she could go back to a job that even looked and smelled faintly like I. T., not after her experiences out here.

“You sure? Could be a nice desk. Big salary. Power, fame and influence?”

For once, Old Jen and New Jen were in total agreement. “I’d rather just be a space-babe.” She demurred, her voice completely full of resolve.

Powell nodded approvingly. “Good for you.”

Brick, New Jersey.

Ravi Singh’s apartment wasn’t hard to find. In a building of cheap wooden doors, his was the solid, expensive one with three locks and a camera above it.

The response to Kevin’s knock wasn’t a querying “who’s there?” or a friendly “Hello?”, but a moment of wary silence, and then:

“Who are you?”

Kevin held his tattoo up towards the camera. “Not one of them." he asserted.

He waited patiently throughout the long consideration that followed, and then the undoing of three locks.

After a few more thumps, there was a buzz, and the door opened… revealing another door.

“Uhmmm…”

“Step inside.” Singh instructed, his voice muffled through the door.

Kevin paused, shrugged, then complied. The space between the two doors contained nothing except an almost absonant magnetic lock with a keypad, and a shelf on which a metal detector wand was charging.

“Run the wand over your scalp.” Singh insisted.

Kevin Jenkins found that the limits of his patience were being approached, but he sighed and did so, completely bemused as to what he could be looking for.

Singh wasn’t satisfied until the wand had gone over his whole cranium twice, and over the bald patch where his translation implant had once been a good three times, before finally there was a beep from the magnetic lock and the inner door swung open.

Kevin wasn’t sure what he expected from the interior of the apartment. After the extravagant security and clear paranoia, he had expected a gust of stench and a study in dingy squalor inhabited by an emaciated neurotic disaster of a man. In fact, the apartment was clean and tidy, decorated in light and airy cream and a warm maroon.

Ravi Singh himself was similarly clean, dressed in jeans and a white shirt, but the bags under his eyes were exactly in keeping with the suspicious reception: he had the face and body language of a man for whom sleep had long since ceased to be anything other than sporadic, shallow and brief.

He welcomed Kevin into his apartment with a surprisingly warm handshake given his apparent exhaustion and the paranoia of the previous few minutes, then glanced out of the front door, and shut and locked both.

“So. What’s your name, mister not-one-of-them?” he asked. “Can I offer you a cup of tea?”

“I’m more of a coffee man, myself…” Kevin said.

“Of course. How do you take it?”

“Uh, black, strong and sweet, please. And my name’s Kevin, Kevin Jenkins.”

“Oh?” Singh arched an eyebrow as he busied himself with a steel and glass cafetiere. “Well, this is an honour. The Butterfly himself. Please, sit down."

Kevin did so, conscious that his street clothes were a good deal shabbier than the apparent recluse’s black leather couch. “Butterfly?”

“You’ve surely heard the term ‘Butterfly effect’? From chaos theory. The notion of a little insect in a field in France flapping his wings and several months later that little eddy has grown into quite the mighty storm and poof! There goes half of Bangladesh." Singh smiled grimly, a distinctive closed-lipped smile that Kevin recognised immediately as that of a fellow abductee. You learned to keep your teeth hidden out there.

“I never bought that story.” he retorted. “Sounds too much like the fantasy of a little man wanting to believe he’s important.”

“Does it? But you’re a living example of the principle in action.” Singh said, pouring hot water into the cafetiere. “I truly believe that had you not been aboard the Outlook on Forever that day, we would still be here. The sky would still be open, but we would still be generations away from exploring it."

“How d’you figure?”

“Without Kevin Jenkins, that would have just been another successful Hunter raid. Without Kevin Jenkins, the galaxy’s media would not have taken an interest in our species. Without that, there would have been no uptick in abductions. No uptick in abductions would mean no warp trail to lead a stray Hunter vessel to Vancouver in search of prey. It’s all quite narrative, really.”

He depressed the cafetiere’s filter and poured a cup of steaming black Blue Mountain.

“If that’s how it works, then what about the patrol officer who kicked me off the Churthuarg station for vagrancy?" Jenkins asked. “Or the Corti who abducted me, or my ex-wife or my lawyer or… you know what, I didn’t come here for this conversation.”

“No, you came here about the Hierarchy.” Singh handed over the coffee in an elegant glass cup. The aroma was perfection itself. “I told the last person who came knocking in no uncertain terms that her death was really only a matter of time once she started probing into this, but she said she accepted that.” He sipped the coffee. “I hope she was truthful.”

“She was prepared for it. Terri left her notes for us to find.”

“You knew her?” Singh asked.

“She and I were… we fucked.”

“Ah!” Singh looked sympathetic. “It must have been a complicated relationship, if all you’ll reveal is what you did, rather than how you felt. And so blunt, too. You must be in a lot of pain.”

“Dude!” Kevin threw his head back in frustration, then leaned forward. “I don’t want psychoanalyzing. I came here for information.”

“That information will kill you.”

“If they’re what I suspect they are, then knocking on your door probably killed me.” Kevin said. “So how about you drop the guru half-speak and get on with the movie.”

Singh smiled again, this time allowing his teeth to show - a genuine, human expression of delight. “Certainly.” he said.

Civilian Trade Station 1039: “Infinity Awaits”

“That’s a dangerous itinerary your ship has logged, cousin.”

Shipmaster Kttrvk spun at being addressed so familiarly by a stranger.

The stranger was a Rrrrtktktkp’ch, standing nonchalantly next to an advertising hoarding on the station’s docking ring, which was helpfully mocking the shipmaster by advertising life insurance. There was something slightly familiar about the Cousin’s facial structure, but the markings were totally unknown to him.

“My itinerary? I don’t have an itinerary. Excuse me.” He turned to leave

“1047-6533-26 972.” the Cousin said, reeling off Kttrvk’s assigned route and stopping the Shipmaster in his tracks. He looked faintly smug when Kttrvk turned to give him a disbelieving stare.

“How did you…?”

“I have my ways.” the stranger said, making it clear that those ways were not for Kttrvk to know. “That’s a dangerous route right now. A lot of Hunter strikes.”

“Well, your information is obsolete.” Kttrvk said, firmly. “I’m not doing that run.”

“Long Stars Shipping seem to think you are.”

“Long Stars Shipping can choke on their feed!” Kttrvk exclaimed, then moderated his tone when a few nearby beings glanced at him. “I will NOT orphan my children nor put them in harm’s way just because the corporation is too greedy to listen to my pleas.”

“You’ll go to debtor’s prison…”

“An acceptable price for the lives of my offspring, my mate and our unborn.” Kttrvk snapped.

He was not expecting the expression of admiration and approval that spread across the Cousin’s face. “Good for you!” he exclaimed. “But I am here to offer you a third way.”

“And what way would that be?" Kttrvk challenged him.

The stranger looked around and stepped in a little closer. “I represent an organisation that wants to trial some new military hardware.” he said. “Simulations and training runs are all well and good, but there is no substitute for the real thing, and the Hunter problem in this area will only claim more lives unless something is done… but they’re too canny to come out and fight just anything. We need… well, we need to entice them into attacking something."

“That something being my freighter.”

“You’re quick.” the Cousin said. From a Rrrrrtktktkp’ch to a Vzk’tk like himself, that was a serious compliment.

“My freighter with my family on board.” Kttrvk pointed out.

“My organisation would not offer to use you this way unless we were completely certain of your safety under our care, I promise you that.”

“And your organisation is…?” Kttrvk pressed.

The Cousin paused. “Let’s just say that this technology would impress and awe even the humans." he said, and made a small conspiratorial gesture that only Kttrvk could see.

Enlightenment dawned. Of COURSE! Everybody knew that it was only a matter of time before the humans got loose from their prison, it only made sense that there would be… organisations… looking to prepare to meet the deathworlders in battle and win.

And anything which could give the humans a pause would surely go through Hunters effortlessly.

Still, Kttrvk would not have become a merchant shipmaster without some guile and caution.

“All of your assurances aside, I would still be risking everything dear to me.” he said.

“If you are pressing for payment, then to assuage your fears and buy your lifelong silence about this experiment, I am authorised to release fifty Dominion Development Credits."

Fifty DDCs.

It was a vast sum. Enough to upgrade the Nkvcqtz with Corti engines that would hopefully give her the speed to not only slip past Hunter ambushes, but also to trade in high-value perishables. Sensibly invested on the other hand, it would provide a very healthy retirement plan for Kttrvk and Ikkzziki, as well as upmarket gene-resequencing for their children to enhance their intellect and buy them prospects that Kttrvk had never had.

But a career merchant’s instincts swung into place. Never accept the first offer.

“A hundred.” He counter-proposed. “We are risking a horrible death here.”

“Seventy. I understand your concerns, but you are in the safest possible hands. And yours is not the only ship that Long Stars is ordering on this suicidal run. You will merely be the first to leave.”

“…Done.”

Cimbrean

“Well, even if you pass the baton first chance you get, you’re still technically in charge of every civilian aspect of this colony for the time being.” Powell said. He snatched a clipboard from where it was hanging on a tent post and consulted it.

“Let’s see… There’s a list of stuff they’d like you to do. Nothing major: name the colonial capitol, identify any existing human citizens, living or dead… we’ve got real-time two-way communications with Earth but a pretty small data budget of what we can send and receive: more like telegraph than anything. To be honest, there’s not much for you to do. Anything on this list you DO do will be taken under advisement by the civilian experts and contractors we bring in once this place is secure and the camp’s up and running smoothly.”

“That doesn’t sound like it’ll take a whole month.” Jen said.

“We’ve got a lot of tech to deploy, a perimeter to establish, scouting to do, maybe an FOB or two to set up..”

“FOB?”

“Forward Operating Base. Somewhere small and camouflaged where if this place is bombed off the map… again… there’ll be a couple of guys left behind to report mission failure.”

“Sounds boring.” Jen complained.

“We’ll find stuff for you to do.” Powell promised. “And I mean USEFUL stuff, now.”

“Thanks.”

“So? Any ideas as to the colonial capitol’s name?”

“A… few. I’ll sleep on that one.”

“Fair enough. Okay… have you met any other humans out here? Besides Darragh Houston, that is. Actually, where IS he?” Powell grabbed a different clipboard and leafed through it.

“Feck knows. The last I saw of him he was on his way back here, but I did some looking around while I was filling up my bath, and didn’t find any sign of him.”

“Okay, he’s an unknown then…” Powell stopped looking at the page he’d turned to. “Any others?”

“Is that a list of abductees?”

“Every unaccounted-for human outside of Sol, in theory. Don’t ask me how they got it, I don’t know.”

“Okay, uh… a few. Adr… um, actually let’s start with, uh, Margarita. I can’t remember her surname, she was a dwarf, Spanish.”

“Was?”

“Yeah. She um… well, the honest truth is that an invisible death robot cut her open.”

“Invis…? O…kay. I think you’re going to need to brief us on those things.”

“I will.” Jen promised.

“Right.” Powell ticked something on his list. “Here she is. Deceased. At least we’ll be able to let her family know. Any others?”

“Cameron White. Very deceased and good fucking riddance.”

Powell blinked, then flicked through his list. “Oh. Shit. Fookin’ hell, what were they thinking stealing a crazy wanker like that?” he ticked. “Good fookin’ riddance, aye.”

“And uh… Adrian Saunders. Australian Defence Force….” she forced herself not to give in to the temptation to look down, whisper and cry. “…Deceased.”

“Wow. You’ve had a bad time of it…” Powell sighed, flipping through,his document, then ticked off against, presumably, Adrian’s name. “Deceased. Guess his wife and kid will have closure at least…”

Planet 16 Cyg B b, 16 Cygni trinary system.
Hunter supply station

+<contempt; disgust; snap> Report!+

The Omega did so, cowering appropriately as the Beta of the Brood-that-Flays swaggered into the information node chamber.

+<Statement> There have been no transports of the specified size along the prey-route within the last Diurnal, Beta.+

+<Disdain; command> Continue to monitor the traffic. The prey are stupid and stubborn, there will be a few more before their patrols arrive. And they are yet to send our tribute.+

+<Statement> I comply, Beta.+

Any brood above a certain size soon developed a small population of Omegas: They were an unfortunate necessity, as some tasks were too menial to insult the Deltas with, but too important to be entrusted to a meat-slave. This one, however, was especially vile in the eyes of its Brood.

It would have been a source of immense surprise to every other species in the galaxy that the concept of “creepy” was one that Hunters understood. But in fact, it was a central one to their mindset: the Hunters were the Predators, and everything else was the Prey. Predators behaved a certain way, and Prey behaved a certain way. Any deviation from this natural order was creepy.

Hence the Great Hunt. The worm programs that the Hunters had long ago infiltrated into the Prey’s data networks, that lurked invisible and silent, watching, collating and reconnoitering everything that the Prey chattered about, had gathered a great wealth of their speculations on the motive behind the Great Hunt: Opinion was mostly split into two camps, the first being that the Hunters were afraid of the human race, and the other being that the Hunters were jealous.

Both theories were equally amusing, by the peculiar standards of Hunter humour. The humans were a non-Hunter species that were Predators, and which was inspiring the Prey to behave in unPreylike ways. This was disruption of the natural order, a creepy intrusion into the Way Things Were Meant To Be. Their eradication was as obviously necessary as, for example, the correction of a fatal structural flaw that would cause a building to collapse under its own weight.

This particular Omega was only one wrong step away from demanding such action, itself. Its existence was barely tolerated, barely tolerable; it lived forever on a delicate knife-edge where its meat might be harvested and fed to the breeding pools should it deviate further from acceptable Hunter normalcy.

This was not because it behaved in an unHunterlike way. Quite the contrary, it did so very carefully, unfailingly and meticulously. What made it creepy was that it did not appear to do so naturally. Its thought-broadcasts were simple statements, queries, respectful requests. There was never any emotional content. When it joined the hunt-cry, it did so almost dutifully and by rote, rather than with real enthusiasm.

Thus, even the other Omegas, which usually banded together out of bottom-of- the-heap solidarity, tended to view this particular one as an opportunity to claw back an anemic parody of the authority that other Hunters held over them. The fact that it didn’t seem to mind - displayed no discernible emotions at all, whether resentment, resignation, complacency or contentment with its lot

only added to the bottom-feeder’s abnormality. It simply followed instructions, diligently, swiftly, competently, and to the full extent of their spirit and intent, often even going above and beyond.

This hinted at the other aberration: The Strange One clearly had a sharp and calculating mind. It saw patterns with ease that other Hunters would overlook. On the few occasions where it had dared to venture an opinion, none of those opinions had yet been wrong. It grasped new tasks within moments, and performed them as well as an experienced expert after only a few days. For a creature so clearly talented to be apparently disinterested in its own stature or reputation was therefore wrong, strange, creepy.

The Beta bared its fangs at the Strange One and then threw itself into the throne traditionally occupied by the ranking Brood member present in the information chamber, pointedly ignoring the inferior specimen and instead stared out of the large gallery windows around the ceiling of the chamber, enjoying the view.

The fact that Hunters had any notion of beauty or aesthetics at all would have been similarly shocking to most of the prey-species. But in fact, the Hunters were in their twisted way highly spiritual and artistic beings. Most of their understanding of beauty was, perhaps predictably, a sanguine and violent one, revolving around the flavour of well-stressed meat, the patterns made by blood and organs and violent dismemberment, and the panic, fear and horror of the Prey.

Lurking underneath that, however, was an innate appreciation for the universe as a hierarchy of interconnecting parts, all in their place and tied by common threads. To the Hunters, the sense of How Things Should Be was a profound one. Predators fed on Prey, bound together by Nature. Alphas commanded and Omegas obeyed, bound by the common thread of the Brood. Moons orbited planets orbited stars, all subordinate to Gravity.

The planet known to humans as 16 Cyg B b was a particularly spectacular example of this last concept: a gas giant, two thirds again as massive as Jupiter, towing with it a coterie of moons, a vast garland ring and a shotgun blast of stray asteroids, captured comets and rocky dust, and it was into one of these asteroids that the Hunters had carved out their forward base, close enough to the spacelanes to easily intercept any choice prey that might use them, but far enough away to be a practical escape and hidden refuge. Bathed in the light of three suns, the view was stunning.

The Beta became aware that the Strange One was inspecting something on its screen with greater than usual scrutiny.

+<*impatience; tolerance; command> Report, Omega+

+<Statement> Beta, a Prey-ship has passed through our sensor cordon at abnormally high speed. <Observation> A ship that fast can only be powered by the grey-skinned Prey’s secret engines and a very large power source.+

+<Interest; Query> Can it be intercepted?+

+<Statement> It cannot, Beta. It simply attracted my attention: I apologise for intruding upon your time.+

The Beta grudgingly accepted the benighted creature’s apology. The day was just beginning to seem as if it would be a slow one without quarry, when the Strange One expressed the one emotion it had ever been known to show.

+<Satisfaction; statement> Beta, a message from the Prey. The Herd of the Long Stars have honoured their arrangement and are sacrificing a vessel as we stipulated. A bulk freighter, High One. Of a configuration likely to contain many long-necks and their young.+

The Beta allowed itself the luxury of a wide-mawed smile. While actually deigning to communicate with the prey was a task so wretched that even the Omegas were only required to stoop to it it because the meat-slaves could not be entrusted with the task, little “arrangements” with the so-called “corporations” that made the greatest use of the shipping lanes was a mutually beneficial arrangement: The Brood had neglected a rich hunting ground over the arrangement with the Long Stars herd, allowing the Prey to grow rich and fat off the easy pickings there.

The growth and prosperity of the Herd only served to fatten the meal and make the hunting that much better in the long-run. Proper cultivation of the meat was important, hence the willingness of the Broods to accept what might be alternatively interpreted as demeaning bribery, as if the Predators should be bought by the prey. Naturally, a high price was only appropriate. The meat itself was an excellent start, of course, but a bulk freighter was a large vessel that could be recycled into many Swarm-ships, and would hold younglings, ripe to become meat-slave breeding stock. The tribute was entirely acceptable.

+<Jubilation; Command> A fine quarry! Alert the Alpha: we hunt. Meat to the Maw!+

+<Statement> I comply, Beta. Meat to the Maw.+

The Beta snarled as it departed for its ship, mood somewhat spoiled by the Omega’s muted, unenthusiastic echo of a response. The Omega would receive only scraps from this prize for its lack of vigor.

Behind it, the Strange One ran an algorithm of its own programming and loaded it into the sensor console. The appearance of that abnormally fast ship was an anomaly, and in its experience, anomalies usually led to interesting data. Data that its true masters would undoubtedly appreciate.

Cimbrean

“Wife and kid?” Jen kept the question light, while in her head there were explosions and lightning bolts and screaming.

“Yep. Sandra Saunders nee Perry. Lives in Brisbane with her daughter Jessica."

“He never mentioned having a wife and kid.”

“Well, the sprog’s birthday is about seven months after his estimated date of abduction, so he probably didn’t know. As for the wife, well, wow. That might have something to do with these arrest warrants…” Powell said, looking at something that was clearly impressing him.

“Warrants?”

“Yyyep. Wanted for counts of Grievous Bodily Harm, Assault with Intent, theft of a motor vehicle, driving while intoxicated, dangerous driving, reckless endangerment of the public, arson, vandalism…” Powell turned a page. “…and littering.”

His attempt to maintain a deadpan expression at that last one failed, leaving the smile straining at the corners of his eyes and mouth.

“He…” Jen paused mid outraged defense, and ran through her immediate reactions. “He didn’t. I knew Adrian, he wouldn’t… not to his wife!"

“Doesn’t say she was the victim." Powell pointed out.

“Well it must have been somebody who hurt her or, or… He definitely wouldn’t do something like that to somebody he loved." She protested aloud, mouth rushing off ahead of her thoughts.

Except to protect her. Old Jen reminded herself internally, flashing up the memory of Adrian’s inexorably strong arm clamped tight around her throat.

Her objections faltered. “…yeah. I guess that sounds like Adrian.” she admitted.

“Sounds like my kind of crazy bastard.” Powell said, admiringly. “You sure he’s dead?”

“He was unconscious, and they were venting the atmosphere, trying to kill us. If I’d tried to drag him to the escape pod, we’d have both died.” Jen asserted, though her old self hated to sound so… coldly practical. Again,though, there was that understanding, nonjudgmental look in Powell’s eye, and it occurred to her that maybe she had some things in common with the special forces captain that neither of them really wanted to have in common with anybody.

Powell looked up as somebody knocked on crate next to his office tent and stuck his head through the flap. “What’s up, Brewer?”

The man who had knocked jerked his head towards something. “Solar array’s about ready, captain.”

“Nice. Come on, Miss Delaney, you might like this.”

Jen followed him out of the tent. “You can call me Jen.” she said.

“I’ll do that, then.”

In the middle of the lawn, one of the trucks was parked next to an object about the size and shape of an oil drum. Jump leads trailed from the device and into the truck’s engine, and a couple of men were gathered round hooking up some extra equipment to it.

“So what’s this solar array?” she asked.

“You know solar panels?”

“Yeah.”

“Turns out force fields can do the same job. All you need is a little jump to get them started, and then they power themselves and give you a bit of surplus to spend on things like water heaters, computers and that.”

“Water heaters?”

“Aye. Should make your baths a bit easier in future.” Powell gave her a winning smile, apparently immune to the scowl that answered him. Jen wasn’t quite so confident as to be perfectly happy about her inadvertent exhibitionism, but the SBS Captain seemed to cheerfully give no fucks at all about trivial things like accidental public nudity.

They watched as the array was powered up, with a snap as something sparked inside the truck’s engine. A ghostly orange dome of energy sprawled overhead, then faded to almost invisibility as the system figured out how much power it needed to draw and settled itself into equilibrium.

“Right. Look, I’m sending a patrol out in a few minutes, why not go with? It’ll take your mind off things and besides: we could use somebody who knows the land, and you know it better than we do.”

“I’m not exactly a soldier…” Jen hesitated.

“Trust me, you won’t hold them back. Besides, I’m not too worried that there’s anything on this world that’d make you tagging along a bad idea. They’ll only be gone a few hours, just long enough to scout the area.”

“That sounds… good, actually.” Jen allowed. She had become so used to walking that it almost felt uncomfortable just sitting around. Her body practically ached to be moving.

“Thought it might.” Powell shouted at one of the nearby soldiers. “Oi! Legsy! Get Jen here a rifle and a sidearm and teach her how to use them, she’s on your patrol!”

He turned back to her. “You wait and see, by the time you’re back, you won’t recognise this place, and I’ll have your message from home ready for you to watch in private.”

Freighter Nkvcqtz

For all the Cousin’s reassurances, Shipmaster Kttrvk had not been so encouraged as to take the step of leaving station with his mate and children aboard. They had been left behind, staying at a hotel paid for several (months) in advance through the expenditure of just one of the twenty DDCs that the Cousin had agreed to pay in advance, with the other fifty to be delivered upon completion of the mission.

The ship felt empty without them, and he had never felt more alone and jittery. Neither had his crew, all of whom knew that staying on was an enormous risk, but the company’s hazard bonuses - and threats - were sufficient to have persuaded most to remain, though all showed serious signs of stress and fear.

It was almost a perverse release therefore to hear the warning chime from the navigation system before they hit the edge of the gravity spike and the ALV drive’s field collapsed, dumping them back to the world of the sub-luminal.

The sensors immediately identified four Swarm Craft, and large ones, each capable of holding upwards of twenty Hunters. Every crewman onboard, Kttrvk included, promptly grabbed and armed their pulse pistols.

This was not for the purposes of fighting off the Hunters, though it was to be hoped that they could take a few down before being overrun. The pistols were for themselves: if you could help it, you didn’t let the Hunters take you alive. Better to die instantly than to be slaughtered while still conscious.

They waited as the Swarm-ships closed around them and the largest of them settled in to its approach vector, lining up the fusion-ended boarding tube that would violate their hull and inject terrible death onto their decks.

He was beginning to fear just how terrible his mistake had been when the local space sensors alerted him to the arrival - via jump drive somehow, despite the apparent absence of any jump beacons in the area - of five ships of unknown type, configuration and origin.

"Edda Wing: Edda Actual - Weapons free. Til Valhall!!"

"OORAH!!"

+<Alarm; Alert> Beta! Unknown warships have appeared via displacement!+

The alert came at the worst possible time. The Alpha’s ship had just lined up and was extending its boarding proboscis to pierce the Prey’s hull. It was at its most vulnerable, its slowest, its shields lowered to get close to the prey.

Already it was moving, abandoning the force-dock maneuver and trying to gain distance enough to raise its shields and accelerate, but it was too late. Exactly what kind of weapon it was that tore the Alpha’s vessel apart was unclear, but the side evaporated in a cloud of pulverised armour and metal scraps, and air pressure did the rest, bursting the ship and practically ripping it in half. Thirty-four Hunters, including the Alpha itself, briefly broadcast their dismay and fear across the brood network before fading.

The Beta - now the new Alpha - hooked its neural implants directly into its ship’s controls and analysed the situation. There were five of them. The craft were of a strange size, somewhat larger than a fighter or shuttle, but smaller than the next largest conventional class of military vessel. And they were fast, apparently blessed with a generous ratio of thrust to mass.

They were also alarmingly difficult to get a target lock on. Active sensors seemed to slide off their hulls like water off a greasy metal plate, and the ships themselves were small and agile, a combination which made securing a solid fix on their exact location at any given time as much a matter of luck and guesswork as of letting the sensors work. All were clearly being flown by experienced and exceptional pilots - their transversal velocity was high and their movements were coordinated so that if one of the remaining Hunter ships maneuvered to minimise its vulnerability to one attacker, another would be perfectly placed to rake it as it turned.

+<Statement; concern> These are not the tactics of Prey…+

As if to confirm that sentiment, three of the craft converged on another of the remaining swarm-ships as it executed an ill-advised turn in response to a feint. The new Alpha paid close attention to the weaponry they used, probing the space around the attacking craft for signs of what manner of violence was being unleashed. It detected only the burnt by-products of explosive compounds, and a hail of high-speed flechettes.

With its shields up, the second Swarm-ship survived the assault, but was badly mauled, losing a thruster and the coilguns along its larboard flank before the aggressors had swept past, banking and accelerating, keeping their transversal high. The sustained G-forces involved in that maneuver must have been ferocious, and yet the ships showed no sign that their pilots were in distress. A dreadful suspicion started to settle in the Alpha’s mind.

+<Command; urgency> Meet aggression with aggression! We are not Prey! Form up and fight as Predators!+

The Swarm-craft fell in around their wounded comrade, and as one the pack turned, seeking a target. One of the attackers was isolated from its wing, its evasive options whittled down by shepherding volleys of coilgun fire, and there was a stab of triumph from the Alpha’s gunner as it fired a perfect solution that would surely obliterate the offending vessel, turning the tide.

The Alpha had to replay the sensor logs to determine what happened next. In the tiny fraction of an instant it took for the coilgun rounds to cross the intervening distance between muzzle and mark, their target displaced, blinking two hundred kilometers across the sphere of engagement and re-entering the fight unscathed.

Then the entire hostile wing imitated the move. Suddenly, all of the Swarm- ships were flying in the worst possible direction, and their guns were pointed completely the wrong way.

A storm of accurate firepower ablated the shielding around their sterns in seconds.

+<Panic; Command> Disengage! Flee! Fl-+

A 30mm depleted Uranium armor-piercing incendiary round penetrated through all of the ship’s comparatively flimsy internal bulkheads, disintegrating as it went. It arrived in the command deck as a dense knot of incandescent heavy metal that reduced the Alpha to a smear of liquified matter when it passed directly through the command chair before embedding itself in the forward wall. The explosive force of its arrival crushed the other five Hunters on the deck almost simultaneously.

Perforated by hundreds of similar rounds, the rear third of the ship decompressed spectacularly, evaporating into an intricate dancing halo of flashing metallic and ceramic shards, mixed here and there with the odd disembodied piece of Hunter. The handful that were unfortunate enough to survive in the forward compartments did not do so for long - power failed instantly, and with it went the emergency air-retaining forcefields.

From the moment Edda wing arrived on the field to the second the final Hunter ship lost power and fell apart, less than three minutes had elapsed. Not one of the TS-101s had expended even half of their capacitor reserves or ammunition.

Freighter Nkvcqtz

“What. Just. Happened?”

Kttrvk came back to reality. He had done nothing but stare dumbfounded at the swirling battle on the sensors throughout its brief but intense duration. He looked around at his crew, all of whom were wearing identical expressions of utter awe.

He gathered himself.

“We survived, that’s what. Get the FTL repaired and let’s be gone!”

Planet 16 Cyg B b, 16 Cygni trinary system
Hunter supply station

The Strange One considered the recording it had made, all of the sensor data it had intercepted from the destroyed swarm-ships.

That the aggressors were human vessels was obvious, and a fact which exonerated the Long Stars herd of treachery. Incomplete and all-but-useless as the data was, that much could be gleaned effortlessly. That it should forward the data to its true masters was equally obvious.

But what of its “fellow” Hunters? The information would be of precious little use to them. It contained no hint at all of how the ships had been able to jump across the sphere of engagement without the use of jump beacons, what kind of weaponry they used, nor how the pilots could possibly react swiftly enough to blink-jump out of harm’s way as that first one had. The Strange One knew enough about humans via its true masters to know that even their impressive reflexes were not so sharp as that.

Probably useless as the information might be, the Alpha-of-Alphas especially was dangerously intelligent. If the Hunters were somehow able to glean whatever secrets the humans had unlocked, they would become an even worse blight than they already were. The Hunters were useful, keeping the masses nervous and distracted, but should they gain too much and too quickly…

The decision was obvious. It ran another program, placing a call that it made only rarely, when certain it would not be caught. Right now, with the whole Brood in upheaval over the death of both Alpha and Beta, for the Strange One to continue calmly working at its terminal would be taken as just another symptom of its strangeness and the content of that work would be ignored.

+I have potentially valuable information on the Sol situation+

The reply was instant: +Ready to receive.+

The Strange One promptly transferred all of its files. There was a pause of some minutes, which it used to update its archived mind-state. Now was one of the few occasions it had been able to safely do so.

Eventually, the reply came:

+You have done well, Twenty. The Hierarchy can make use of this information.+

Cimbrean

“Legsy” turned out to be an enormous Welshman, who towered over Jen and seemed to take the whole world with irreverent good humour.

“Right! Ever handled a gun before?” He asked, fishing around in the back of a truck.

“Sort of.” Jen said.

“Whatcha mean?”

“We modified some of those shitty pulse guns to fire actual ammo. They were okay, but…”

“Awh, they’ll be nothing next to these bad boys!” Legsy said. “Say whatcha like about the fuckin’ Germans, those cunts know how to make a fuckin’ gun.”

“Pardon your French…” Jen muttered.

“Wha? Oh, right. Get used to it darling, I’m from Llanelli.”

He hauled something out of the truck’s bed. “Anyway, THIS” he held up a gun “is the HK G36C. Before I give it to you, d’you know the rules of firearm safety?”

Jen’s lessons with Adrian on a deathworld she had never learned the name of came back to her. “Always assume it’s loaded and ready to fire and the safety’s off.” she recalled. “Don’t point it at something unless you’re completely okay with that thing ending up dead or destroyed. Don’t have your trigger finger inside the guard unless you’re going to shoot. Be aware of what’s near and behind your target.”

Legsy handed her the gun.

“Safety, magazine eject, charging handle. Got that?“Jen repeated the identification, and he nodded, then pointed to something on the top of the gun. ” This here’s an OCOG - that’s Offworld Combat Operations Gunsight. Designed for use in different gravity, right? Aim it at that target down there…” Jen did so. “See how the chevrons tell you the range, and stay on target no matter where your head is? Okay, tuck it into your shoulder a bit more… right. You know how to hold one, anyway. Give it here.”

When Jen had done so, he demonstrated the correct way to load and charge it a few times before handing it back to her and watching as she repeated the motion. Satisfied, he handed her a magazine with a strip of coloured tape around it.

“Okay, this is a charged mag and that’s live ammunition. Fire off a few rounds at that target by there.” He said.

Jen looked at it. “How far is that?”

“Hundred meters, nice and easy.” Legsy said, happily. “That gun’s effective out to about eight hundred, but the furthest target we’ve got is six hundred meters, which would be that little one waaaay over there.” He pointed at a little speck hanging from a distant tree. “But we’re going to start nice and easy.”

Jen shrugged, turned, raised the gun, sighted, and fired. The recoil was surprisingly hefty compared to the repurposed pulse-guns she was used to and the first shot hit a bit high. She adjusted, and the rest of her shots formed a tight grouping smack in the middle of the target.

“Fuckin’ ‘ell!” Legsy said, clearly impressed. “Okay, recoil surprised you a bit there. Squeeze the trigger, don’t jerk it, and try to be breathin’ out when you fire. Go for that one over there with the orange stake next to it, that’s three hundred meters.”

Jen’s shots hit low. “Sights are off.” she observed.

“Or you’re just shit.” Legsy teased, grinning. “Nah, you’re right. That sight’s not been calibrated for Cimbrean’s gravity yet, you’ll need to adjust it. See that little dial on the side?”

Jen experimented with it, twisted it a bit, and saw how the chevrons moved and widened out a bit. She fired, hit a bit high, twisted the OCOG a little less, fired, hit smack in the middle, and something went click in her brain.

She grinned, aimed, and squeezed off all the remaining rounds in the magazine before laying the gun flat in front of her, pointing downrange.

“You missed.” Legsy said, examining the three hundred meter target through binoculars and sounding puzzled.

“Look at the six hundred meter target.” Jen told him. He frowned and raised his binoculars again, and Jen folded her arms and allowed a cocky smile to form as she watched the giant Welsh soldier’s jaw drop.

Brick, New Jersey

It really was very good coffee.

“Here on Earth, The Hierarchy would be just another conspiracy theory.” Singh told him, settling down into his recliner. “But they are very real. They have acted behind the scenes of galactic politics since the days when some of the older species were still around.”

“Still around?” Kevin echoed, questioning.

“Species come, species go.” Singh said. “You must have noticed that all of the civilizations out there are much of an age with us. A few thousand years older at most.”

“So…. what, species just go extinct eventually?”

“Eventually. Usually after tens of thousands of years as warp-capable civilizations. But in time, well… it’s not quite clear why. It’s the grand unanswered question of alien sociology. But yes, in time they all enter a terminal decline. Every race up there is living on borrowed time.”

“No exceptions?”

Singh issued a slim-lipped, grim smile and set his coffee down. “Just one. The Hunters. There are references to them in archaeological archives dating back to the days when humanity was still just a balder-than-average ape with unusual posture. Nobody quite knows HOW old they are. But the rest? Eventually, they crumble, their works decay, they withdraw to their homeworld, set up shop and just… dwindle. They stop breeding and… give up.”

He leaned forward. “Except for the deathworlders.”

Kevin’s brow creased. “…But we’re the only deathworlders, though. Aren’t we?”

“We are, yes, but we shouldn’t be. Let me tell you my story….”

Chapter 18
Chapter 15: “Forever Changed” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date point: ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth

There was a change in the texture of nothingness, a return of some of the functionality of his body. Six wasted no time in extending his sense of self outwards from its cloistered life inside the implants, and into the meat he was wearing.

It was, surprisingly, not too bad. His mouth was dry, and his head ached a little, but he awoke to find himself lying - clean, clothed and dignified - on a bed.

It wasn’t exactly a comfortable bed, but nor was it torturously hard. It was just a simple mattress, with a pillow-shaped raised bit at one end in lieu of an actual pillow, and a blanket. It was the sole feature of a plain grey room, other than a door which looked, if anything, even more solid than the walls around it, and a sturdy yellowish light panel in the ceiling. There wasn’t even a window.

He sat up, enjoying the feeling of his limbs moving again, appreciating the way they reported none of the discomfort he had felt when last conscious and pinned face-down to the San Diego sidewalk.

His link to 72 was dead. The micro-wormhole connecting him to the Hierarchy had, somehow, closed itself. Wherever he was, it was at the very bottom of a communications black hole.

No matter. Unexpected complications or not, the mission remained the same: gather information. Something would, presumably, be happening soon. He would record it, he would remember it, he would find a means of escape, and rather than being a disaster, his hive-poking would turn out to be a triumph.

For now, he sat, and waited.

He didn’t need to wait long. Though there were no obvious sensors or cameras in the cell, pretty soon there was a sliding sound - a panel had opened about eye level on his door. It shut immediately afterwards, and was followed by a second, larger hatch at about waist height, through which was thrust a tray.

The smell wafting off it immediately reminded him that he was hungry. Unbidden, his stomach emitted that peculiar growling sound again, and his mouth went into overdrive, salivary glands anticipating the arrival of food.

It turned out to be quite bland fare next to his last meal of just a few days ago. Some white substance, like a dry… gel, almost, or paste. Its taste was pleasant but simple. The chunky brown-white fluid in a separate compartment went well with it, and also with the brownish crumbly item. There was certainly nothing to complain about there, but it wasn’t a patch on the steak and burgers he had so recently eaten.

But then again, what did he expect as a prisoner? In truth, he would have expected far worse than this. A comfortable bed in a clean, dry and warm cell? A filling hot meal and a tall container of cold water? It was a conundrum.

He was still puzzling over this peculiarity when there was a banging on the door, which opened. Three humans stood without, holding blunt black weapons.

Ah. THIS was more like it. A beating. This was closer to what he had expected.

The human in the middle spoke to him. “Detainee, please face the far wall.” He instructed. “Crouch on your knees, place your hands on your head and interlock your fingers.”

“And if I don’t?” Six challenged. He could handle a beating. This… nice treatment was getting to him.

“Detainee, please comply. We will be forceful if we must.”

There was that word again. “Please”. It seemed so strange to have the armed guards address him politely and respectfully, even if they were being impersonal.

He glanced at the far wall, wondering if he should just comply and see what awaited him if he did. After all, why go through all that pain unnecessarily?

The guard spoke again. “Detainee, this is your final warning. Your compliance is mandatory for everyone’s safety, including yours.”

So. No beating. They’d just restrain him and… what, take him somewhere? Either way, there was no point in suffering the inconvenience.

“Fine. I comply.” he said, turning to the wall and kneeling. The guards stepped into the room.

“Hands on your head and fingers interlaced please, detainee.”

Six obeyed.

There was an efficient bustle of movement. His hands and feet were bound with metal, though from the looseness at the ankles he would be able to shuffle a walk. Something dark went over his eyes, something soft over his ears. His world became a purely tactile one, full of no sensation but the hard floor under his knees, the weight on his limbs. Strong hands lifted him to his feet, and he could sense - he wasn’t sure how, but his body reported certainty of the fact - that two of the guards moved into position near him, guiding him with physical contact, pushing him forwards just enough to get the message across that he should be walking. As predicted, he couldn’t hit any kind of a stride, but he was able to walk after a shuffling, slow fashion.

Six tried to judge the route as they left the cell, but quickly gave up. There were so many turns and he was spun around a few times at some points, completely throwing any attempt to track where he was or how far he had gone. For all he knew they could have walked past his cell door five times before he heard - faintly, through the stuff on his head - the sound of a door.

A chair was bumped gently against the back of his knees, and those same hands that had guided him for the last few minutes helped him sit down. There were a few tugging sensations, and sound and light returned in a rush, making him blink and grimace.

“Hello.”

The greeter was seated opposite him, smiling faintly as the handlers filed out of the room. It wasn’t a large room - in fact it was just the two chairs, a desk, and a conspicuous camera mounted on the ceiling. The only features on the desk where a small laptop, turned towards the human so that Six couldn’t see the screen, and a slim paper dossier and pen.

“My name’s Stephen, I’ve been assigned to your case.” the man opposite him continued. “My goal here is to learn as much as I can about you and your associates, but before we begin… Have you been fed well? Are you comfortable enough?”

This was not, Six thought, how an interrogation should go.

Date Point 3y 8m 3w AV

Something was very wrong in the life of Adam Ares.

He’d never realised before just how small his Dad was. In fact, Adam had stood taller than his old man for a couple of years, but he’d always seemed large to Adam.

Now, wrapped up in hospital gown and blankets and violating tubes as he was, that illusion was shattered. Gabriel was a small man, but not a frail man. Not usually. Right now, though…

That alone felt like a crippling loss, and he thanked Jesus Christ and all the angels that it was the only loss he’d endured. Gabriel was, miraculously, very much still alive, and according to the doctors recovering nice and strong. The bullet had entered in the small of the back, bounced off a vertebra, obliterated a kidney and exited through the flank, leaving behind bruising of the lumbar spinal cord and a badly perforated bowel but - crucially - it had missed the renal artery. By which small grace, Gabriel’s life had been saved.

They hadn’t let him stay. He hadn’t been there when Gabriel had first woken up. He hadn’t even been able to visit until after a shouting match with his Mom and a heated phone call with Mrs. Almodovar.

But he’d finally been able to visit, and now…

Gabriel shifted, then woke. He blinked at his son, confused for a second, and then smiled. “Hey, Amigo."

Adam gave up on trying to be manly. He threw himself forward and felt Gabriel bring his free arm - the one without an IV drip in - up and around to hug him, albeit with a grunt of pain.

“Sorry…” Adam muttered.

“It’s okay.”

“Jesus Christ, Dad, I thought…" Adam couldn’t even say it, it just made the tears hurt more as they forced themselves out. “I thought…”

“I know. I’m sorry little man, I dropped the ball. I should have been keeping an eye out.”

A laugh forced its way out between the sobs. “Yeah, you’d better be!”

There was a minute’s silence, and then Adam pulled away, wiping his eyes. “Shit, Dad, please don’t ever do that to me again.”

Gabriel smiled, but sobered. “From what the doctors are telling me, I might be taking early retirement.” he said. “Between the kidney and my spine…”

Adam’s eyes widened. “You’re gonna be able to walk aren’t you?”

“Four out of five.” Gabriel promised. “Or so Doctor Boylan says. I heard it’s all about willpower, so I’ll be damned if I’m gonna be in a wheelchair. But pretty sure I’m never passing physical again so…” he shrugged. “Guess that was my career. It’s okay, I’ve got plenty saved up and invested.”

“You love your job, though.” Adam said.

“Yeah. But it’s just a job, Amigo. There’s more important things."

Gabriel ruffled his son’s hair, then sat back. “Shit, I get tired quick.” he complained.

“It’s okay. I… Ava and I are having another go at dating tonight, I should get ready.”

Gabriel smiled. “Good for you, man…” he said, closing his eyes.

“Yeah. Hopefully it’ll go better this time.”

Gabriel chuckled, then yawned. “Yeah. Pretty sure dates aren’t s’posed to have… shooting…” he mumbled.

Adam let him fall asleep, then let himself out.

Date point: ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth

“Um… yes. Thank you, I’m quite comfortable.” Six admitted. It was true, in fact: the seat was cushioned and ergonomic, and he felt perfectly fine sitting upon it.

“Good to know.” Stephen replied. “So… I’m going to start this interview now. Could you please tell me your name?”

“Mr. Johnson.” Six replied, promptly. That particular feature of the drone’s cover was hardwired into the same implants that now hosted his personality.

Stephen nodded. “I was hoping for your full name.” he said softly, drumming his fingers on the table. The combination of the drumming and Stephen’s mild tones did something very strange to Six - the sounds were actually pleasant, in a way that he had never encountered before. He shook it off and focused on the task at hand. This was still an interrogation, however alien it might be, and Six had five hundred thousand years of experience to draw on to help him. A human who wasn’t even an infant relative to that lifetime wasn’t going to get the better of him just by being nice.

“I don’t know your full name." he pointed out.

“True. I’m Moore, Stephen Moore.”

“Thank you.” Six said, but didn’t reveal his cover’s first name, although this was in large part due to the cover not having been assigned a fixed first name. He remained silent as he rifled through the biodrone’s past mission history in search of the most recently used first name.

“Okay, if you don’t feel like sharing yet, that’s fine.” Stephen said. He tapped on the keyboard of the laptop in front of him, and the gentle tapping, clicking noises the keys made as they were depressed again elicited that same strange pleasantness in Six’s head. It felt… relaxing, warm, comfortable.

He immediately stiffened. What if he was under the influence of some kind of drug? Humans were particularly susceptible to hallucinogens and similar substances, perhaps that meal had been full of some kind of compound that would open him up to speaking the truth.

The stiffening attracted Stephen’s attention. “Is everything alright?” he asked.

“What was in that food I ate?” Six demanded.

“Uhmmm.. mashed potato, biscuits and gravy, peas and carrots.” Stephen replied, after checking his notes. “Why?”

Six was an inexpert reader of human expressions and body language, even with the aid of the specialist subroutines that lurked deep inside any translator implant, but there was no mistaking the honest curiosity in his interrogator’s reaction. It implied that either the food had not been drugged, or - less likely - that Stephen did not know about it.

Perhaps the sensation was just another symptom of human strangeness, one to which he had not hitherto been exposed. He didn’t know. For now, it was safest to withhold his suspicions rather than voice them and out himself as nonhuman. If the reaction was perfectly normal and he commented on it as if it weren’t, then he would have blundered.

“I’m…” he thought how best to make an excuse. “…I was expecting something less pleasant.”

Stephen nodded. “I understand. But we’re professionals here, we don’t do that kind of thing. You have my solemn promise that you’re perfectly safe.”

“That seems… counter-intuitive.” Six told him.

“Perhaps. We’re interested in information, and a peaceful resolution. That’s the first and most important priority. As for you, your person and rights are protected by…” here, Stephen paused and thought for a second, “Oh, a whole mess of laws, which we’re not interested in breaking. It’s better for everyone that they remain unbroken.”

“How noble.” Six scoffed. “Or maybe you’re just trying to get me to relax so you can catch me off-guard.”

Stephen inclined his head. “Is that what you’d do?” he asked.

Six didn’t answer, and after a few seconds Stephen shrugged. He typed something on the laptop in front of him, letting the silence slide.

“Shall we move on to the actual questions?” he asked. “What’s your name again?”

“Mr.” Six emphasised the word “Johnson.”

“Still no first name?”

“No.”

“Not, for instance, Edward? That’s the name you used on your flights to and from New York.”

Unbidden, a detail from the biodrone’s most recent mission surfaced. Yes. Edward.

“…Edward Johnson.”

“Thank you.” Stephen tapped on his laptop again. “But is that your real name?”

Six sneered at him “Of course it is.”

Stephen gave an uncomfortable little grimace. “So, why did you rent a car under the name Paul Johnson a few weeks prior? Why is the name on your apartment’s lease Mr. Richard Johnson?”

He smiled. “Most people don’t change their name as often as they change their jeans.”

They sat in silence for a minute, with Stephen just staring at him, giving Six time to think. There was, he realised, simply no way to maintain the facade of being Mr. Johnson. The damnable drone’s recall was too disconnected from his control, the details of its cover too vague, too hard to retrieve on short notice. A change of tack was in order. He would stick to what he himself knew, without relying on the drone.

“Call me… Six.” he said, finally. It wasn’t like the simple number would reveal anything.

“Six. Fair enough. Thank you.”

Six only stared at him, awaiting the next question.

“Okay, Six… you’re not human, are you?”

Date Point: 3y 8m 3w AV

Scotch Creek Extraterrestrial Research Facility, British Columbia, Canada.

♫♪There’s just an illusion of something different / the very reason they keep telling you something’s missing / but whatever it is you won’t get from…♪♫

“Y-hello?”

"Jenkins, it’s Tremblay."

Kevin yawned and sat up. “Morning, General.” He squinted at the glowing numbers in the dark. “Dude, it’s like oh-five-thirty.”

"Yeah, well, ET intel consultant’s a job that puts you permanently on call, eh? I’ve got some fine gentlemen from down south want a word with you, AND a priority message from the colony. Grab some of that wonder coffee you make and get up here."

The advice to make himself a coffee was sensible on two levels: even if he hadn’t needed to drum up some alertness and drive away the effects of inadequate sleep, it was five-thirty in a winter’s morning in British Columbia. Next to his native Austin, he may as well be above the arctic circle, and three years hadn’t yet served to acclimatize him to the cold. The little disposable cup of triple-strength Mocha served to keep his fingers warm as he grumbled a path through the snow.

A helicopter added to his misery as it came in low overhead while he was passing the security checks to get into the base’s command building, kicking up a blizzard that even made the Quebecois guard flinch inside his greatcoat. Getting inside the heated complex of offices and briefing rooms was heaven.

He knew the way to Tremblay’s office by heart, but as ever there was an escort. Even three years as a civilian contractor and consultant didn’t buy the freedom to walk the base unescorted.

Fortunately, the guard was known to him, and they swapped some small-talk on the way up.

Tremblay’s office was verging on being crowded, occupied as it was by the man himself - looking, Kevin was pleased to note, just as groggy and dishevelled as he felt - plus another CA general, this one with the little crown above his crossed sabers that indicated a Lieutenant-general, superior to Tremblay’s own rank of Brigadier-General, and four men in suits.

“Who’s this then?” the senior officer asked as he entered. He looked disgustingly alert and well-groomed.

“Major-General Paul Rutherford - Kevin Jenkins.” Tremblay introduced. “Our ET intel consultant.”

“I know you!” Rutherford exclaimed. “You were the one in that interview that got all the ETs so shit-scared way back.”

Kevin grimaced and nodded. “Yeah, that was me.”

“You said some rather nasty things about your own species there, Jenkins.” Rutherford pressed, earning him Kevin’s best cool stare. It lasted for several seconds.

“When I said those things, I meant every word.” he said. “Still do, too. And from the looks of things, history has proven me goddamn well right.”

Rutherford snorted, and looked at Tremblay. “You were right Martin, he’s a dick.” he said.

Tremblay’s glance shot around the room as Kevin raised an eyebrow at him, and he cleared his throat. “Commander Higgins and Group Captain Temba here are with MI6, the British Secret Intelligence Service.” he said. “Agents Hamilton and Williams here are CIA, and Lieutenant Leclerc behind you is with our own CSIS.”

Jenkins turned around. Leclerc was a tiny woman whose feet weren’t even touching the floor as she sat behind the door, watching and listening. She gave him a faint smile.

“I assume you have some ET intel you want me to consult on?” He asked, settling in the last remaining seat after dragging it away from Tremblay’s desk and turning it around so he could straddle it.

“Before we begin, I want to make it clear that this meeting is classified and its content is Need-To-Know only, under all the relevant laws of, and treaties between, our respective governments. If you don’t accept that, then get out.” Rutherford said. He fixed Kevin with an especially challenging glare, and seemed only grudgingly satisfied when Kevin nodded his understanding and acceptance. This was far from being the first classified meeting he’d attended. “…Martin?

Tremblay just extended an open-palmed hand, inviting the CIA agents to speak first. Williams stood, and the lights dimmed as she turned on the projector.

“Five days ago we apprehended this man in San Diego.” She said. The slide showed a bearded, brown-haired man of indeterminate age and nondescript features. “An accomplice - ” the slide was of somebody who looked effectively identical " - was gunned down after badly wounding San Diego PD homicide detective Gabriel Ares."

“Ares? Shit!” Kevin ignored the disapproving looks his interruption garnered. “Is he okay?”

“He’s recovering in hospital. The doctors give him a good prognosis.” Williams assured him. “May I continue?”

She cleared her throat. “At present, we’re holding John Doe here in a stasis box while he’s moved to a secure holding facility for interrogation. The good thing about that is that we’ve got plenty of time to get our intel together. At this point, however, The Company considers it extremely likely that he’s a member of an extraterrestrial organisation known as “The Hierarchy”, with unknown but apparently hostile motives towards Earth and the whole human race.”

The lights came back up. Rutherford took over. “The purpose of this meeting is to compare notes and to furnish the CIA with everything they might need to aid the interrogation. Mr. Jenkins will reiterate everything that he has learned about the Hierarchy.”

“And the Brits?” Kevin asked, looking at them.

Temba cleared his throat. “As a British Overseas Territory, the settlement of Folctha on the planet Cimbrean reports any intelligence or developments directly to us, and classified.”

Higgins elaborated. “The most recent of that information appears to be somewhat relevant.”

“Let’s hear it.” Jenkins challenged.

“We’d prefer to hear from you first, Mr. Jenkins.” Higgins said, softly.

“Hear what, exactly?” He asked.

Hamilton leaned forward. “Everything.”

Date Point: ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth.

“Well, dropping the nonhuman bombshell early seems to have paid off. Pay up.”

One of the team - there were eight of them total in the room for today - rolled his eyes and dug out a fifty dollar note, which he handed over. The bet didn’t really mean anything: that particular note had been changing hands from bet to bet for so long that nobody could remembers whose wallet (or wager) had originally produced it. “Interesting session.” he commented, as ‘Stephen’ entered the room.

Stephen wasn’t his real name - that was just the booth persona, a tool to give the detainee the convincing illusion of forming real trust and a relationship with a real person, while hopefully shielding the interrogator from getting too close. It was a tough line to tread, though - any hint of insincerity could set back the interrogation a long way. It was a damn tough job.

“How’re we doing?” He asked, grabbing a cola and sandwich from the little desktop fridge in the corner.

“Plenty of data points. He seems to respond well to politeness, and he changed tack nicely when you caught him in the lie about his name. And he definitely had a moment of panic when you dropped the “not human” bomb on him.”

“I saw it.” ‘Stephen’ agreed. “He telegraphs a lot - I was expecting an alien infiltrator to be more… stone-faced.”

“We’ve still not really established that he’s actually an ET.”

There was a gentle throat-clearing from the team’s psychologist. She was the sort of person who spoke only rarely, but commanded total attention when she did. “He pegs almost maximum on the Hypochondriasis and Psychopathic Deviate scales.” She commented, referring to something on her tablet computer. “We haven’t seen enough to rate him otherwise yet, but already, he’s a long way from ‘normal’.”

“Good start, then. What would you like for the next session?”

“Hmm…” She conferred with her assistant for a second, ending in a mutual nodding. “Schizophrenia and/or Hypomania, please?”

“Makes sense…” There was a general taking of notes.

“Lots of interesting tics. Especially that thing when I drummed my fingers.” ‘Stephen’ commented.

“That looked like ASMR to me.” the assistant psychologist chimed in.

The facility commander frowned. “ASMR?”

“Eh, the acronym’s pure pseudoscience.” said one of the team. “but the phenomenon itself is… kind of a pleasant warm fuzzy feeling in the head in response to certain stimuli.”

“What stimuli?”

“Oh… gentle tapping and scratching, soft speech, personal attention, that kind of thing.”

“You sure that’s a real thing?”

“I get it myself.” admitted the psych assistant.

The one who had explained the phenomenon nodded. “Same.”

“Sounds like it could be a useful reward. Easy to control in the booth.” added the second ’gator.

“We’ll try it.” ‘Stephen’ agreed. “I’ll do some research ahead of tomorrow’s session.”

The lead interrogator rubbed his chin. “What are you thinking of going with? If anything?”

“Still probing for now. I think ego’s going to play a big role going forward, but as for up or down… I dunno.”

“We’ve got more material for ego-down.”

“True, but we should save that.” the lead ’gator said. “For now, I think we keep it slow. Direct questions, pounce on any lies we spot, build the relationship and get a better picture.”

“Yeah, it’s still early days.” agreed the second ’gator.

“Okay. We happy with that?” There was general agreement. “Okay. We’ll call it there, start working on the next session’s questions in the morning. We’ve had a long day people, good work.”

Date Point: 3y 8m 3w AV

Scotch Creek Extraterrestrial Research Facility, British Columbia, Canada

“During my travels, I ran into the idea of the Hierarchy a few times, always in the same way that we’d talk about… you know, the Illuminati, or Area 51, or… fucking lizard people from Venus, or whatever. You know, a legend, a myth, a… conspiracy theory. Nobody took it seriously."

They did the unnerving thing of listening to him and NOT asking any questions.

“Anyway. I met Terri Boone on V-day. She was a P. I., and her client had employed her to tour the country looking for real abductees. Not the idiot anal probe mothership motherfuckers: the real deal, like me."

“She was literally in my bar when the Hunters hit Rogers Arena. Everyone’s flipping their shit over the monsters on TV, and I was grinning like a madman because, you know, I knew what was going to happen next. Been there, done that, worn the blood spatter. I took a group that big damn near solo, just a Rickyticky with a broken arm called Kirk for backup."

“This is the same Kirk who flies for the GRA now? The one who supplies Cimbrean?” asked Temba.

“Same guy, yeah. So anyway, after that I went along with Terri on her job. I had a load of money saved up and nothing to spend it on, so I thought ‘why not?’ and this… plan, just formed. About getting all the abductees to chip in their experience in this big scrapbook of sketches and personal accounts. We got news of this base being set up and we just… bounced up here, from abductee to abductee, collecting life stories along the way.”

“The Hierarchy was mentioned a few times in there too. We just stuck it in the ‘weird shit’ section. We figured it was, like, ET pop culture, you know? Anyway, that scrapbook was pretty much turned wholesale into the EBM.” he continued, referring to the Extraterrestrial Briefing Manual that had gone out from Scotch Creek to Toronto, from there to world governments, and from a leak in one of them onto the Internet in short order. “Most of the convoy gave their interviews, gave up their last little bits of intel, most of them went home. I stayed here.”

“Terri left before we even got up here, though. Think we were in… Colorado, maybe? She got a phone call, and just took off. I didn’t hear from her again until about, uh… eight or nine months ago, when she just showed up at my bar here on base. She said she was betraying her employer’s trust, handed over a USB stick full of the names of people who’re probably still off Earth right now, and a letter which she promised me not to open until I knew it needed opening.”

“That was the login and password for the online drive.” Hamilton said.

“Yeah. I think she must have known she was messing with some really dangerous people, and was going to get maybe killed, you know? She… we had… fun, you know? Which, I didn’t complain at the time, but I didn’t think she’d liked me that much before, so I guess she was… trying to squeeze as much out of life while she could.”

“Focus please, Kevin.” Tremblay reminded him.

“Right, sorry. Uhm… Anyway, last I saw of her, she left for San Diego, and the next I ever heard about her was Ares calling me a couple months ago to let me know she’d been killed, and question me about the murder.”

They listened, and he kept talking to fill the silence.

“I went to the funeral. Had a talk with Ares, he said there wasn’t much he could do to follow up on some of the leads on that cloud drive. Jurisdiction and all that bullshit, you know? But he did let me know the name of this guy Ravi Singh in New Jersey.”

“His name wasn’t Singh.” Williams said.

“I know. But, that’s how I knew him. He said he was this… nuclear disaster, fallout specialist kinda guy for the Indian nuke program. I’ll spare you the full story - I recorded it though, Tremblay’s got the recording - but the TL;DR version is that he visited… think he said eighteen planets, all class ten or higher, Deathworlds like Earth, and they all had the remnants of civilization on them.”

“Now, we’re supposed to be unique, right? The only Deathworlders in the galaxy? But here there’s eighteen ten-plus planets full of cities, all nuked to shit and gone. Apparently the Corti who took him felt that was really good evidence to support the existence of the Hierarchy. Guess it was on the money, because their ship got boarded, the Corti and the Ukrainian that they’d taken alongside Singh got iced, and he only escaped because he’s smart and paranoid and learned their language. Got back to Earth, went dark in New Jersey and stayed there. I don’t know how Terri found him.”

He shrugged. “He could probably tell you better what the Hierarchy’s all about than I could.” he confessed.

“They bombed his apartment building a couple of days after you visited.” Williams revealed. “Collapsed half of it. Five dead, including ‘Singh’ himself.”

Jenkins just closed his eyes and grimaced.

“Alright. You want my opinion? What I think the facts mean?” he asked.

“Sure.”

“I think the Hierarchy keep the conspiracy theory going because it’s… what’s that term? Plausible deniability. I think they’re real, and I think they wipe out deathworld civilizations.”

“Do you have any idea why they might do that?” Higgins asked.

“Fear! I mean, look at how much the others are shitting themselves over us.” Kevin replied. “Shoving up a forcefield, telling their ships and stations to throw us to the wolves… While I was up there I got moved on as often because they were shit-scared of me as for vagrancy. One little show of some supernatural feat like picking up a forty-pound crate in point seven Gs - you know, nothing to us, but to them it’s like "he’s an unstoppable monster, get him off the station!“. You know, I heard one of us got involved in the Dom-All war like, thirteen years ago? That stupid motherfucker’s the reason every station in the sky has a locker full of nervejam grenades nowadays. Even if the, like, general public didn’t know about us before my dumb ass got on the news mouthing off about religion? The authorities sure as shit did, and they armed their security guys accordingly. They’re fucking afraid of us, man."

“To the point of genociding… how many planets?”

“Fuck if I know. But… yeah. See threat: destroy threat. That’s how they’re thinking, most likely.”

“How are we a threat to them?” Rutherford asked.

Kevin half-laughed the word “Bro!”, shaking his head. “We’re the end of them. We’re the end of the way things used to be. Once we’re out there - like, really out there, not dipping our toe in the kiddy end like we’re doing right now? We. Will. Eat. Them. Alive. Because we can’t not, alright? Shit’s gonna get Darwinian out there, and we’ve got a four point five billion year head start over every single one of those poor dumb assholes."

He sipped his coffee and, finding it cold, set it down next to him in disgust. “The Hierarchy are just the only ones smart enough to know it. And they’re the ones doing the sensible fucking thing and wiping out threats before they become a threat."

Higgins frowned. “You make it sound almost as if you admire them for that.” he said.

Kevin shrugged. “How hard would you fight, if defeat meant the world became a place where everything you loved and lived for could no longer exist?" he asked.

“Do you mean to say you think they should succeed?” Higgins inquired.

“Hell the fuck no! I’ve been out there man, it’s a crapsack! If it’s not violently insane, it’s corrupt and callous, and if it’s not corrupt and callous it’s dumb as a stump! And that’s the status quo the Hierarchy would kill us all to protect! Things need shaking up out there! That’s the only way the galaxy’s going to become a better place, is if we head out there and start banging heads together. Gently, so they don’t burst."

“How Texan.” Higgins noted, drily.

He turned to General Rutherford. “Shall I share our part of the briefing now, sir?” he asked.

Rutherford nodded. “Oh, yes. Please do.”

Date Point: ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth.

Time behaved strangely in the cell. There was nothing to do, nothing to look at or inspire him. For the sake of having anything to do, Six found himself doing some exercises he could remember seeing being practiced on the beach in San Diego, though he had no idea if he was doing them right.

That alone might be an indicator of his non-human status, and he was undoubtedly being surveilled, but it was that or… nothing.

So, he exercised, he slept, he was fed, and led - ears and eyes covered - to a simple bathroom where he was allowed to perform his stolen body’s necessary ablutions and clean himself. They even provided him with clean clothing. It was the only vaguely interesting thing to happen for what felt like it must have been the best part of two days.

It was a strange relief, therefore, to be finally retrieved by his taciturn handlers - never the same handlers twice, nor did they speak to him except to issue orders - and ushered back into the interview room.

The questions became, oddly, less pointed, less targeted. They started to query him about some bizarre things, claiming that it was all about “getting to know him”. Questions like his favourite foodstuffs and his preferred recreational activity were easy enough to answer, from his limited pool of human experience. Others, however, were truly strange. A favourite colour? As if there was something preferable about one narrow slice of the EM spectrum over any other arbitrary slice? The question was impenetrably strange to him. He just took a random stab and replied “green”.

That was after what felt like weeks, however, once he had bored of playing the game of refusing to answer. Nothing seemed to faze Stephen, who seemed equally content to ask the same stupid questions again and again, and was equally comfortable with any answer, or even none. It was strange, he seemed to just… genuinely enjoy Six’s company.

Six found he had no option but to look forward to Stephen’s company and his interrogations. They were the only thing that broke the monotony. Sleep. Eat. Excrete. Every so often he was taken to a large featureless room where there was room to walk, and the floor was padded for basic exercises under the watchful, silent eye of his handlers. Every day he was given the opportunity to clean up and put on fresh clothing. Every time he returned to his cell after leaving, it had been cleaned, and the bedding replaced. He was being exceptionally well looked-after, but there was nothing to do. At all.

The introduction of a second interrogator - “Carl” - almost felt like the opening of a whole new world of experience. He was similar to Stephen in most respects - a little lower and more gravelly of voice, a little less handsome, but equally polite, equally patient, equally… insightful. Neither man allowed even the faintest hint of a discrepancy to pass: they would pounce on it, pry at it, probe it with questions and unrelenting logic. They would repeat the same question over and over and over and over and over and over and over and over and OVER AND OVER AND OVER AND OVER AND OVER AGAIN AND AGAIN AND AGAIN AND AGAIN! It was like being slowly and inefficiently murdered with words, and no matter how often it happened, no matter how aware he was of what they were doing, the sheer irritation of it always teased out just a little bit more from him, just another detail in the hope that maybe this crumb would convince them to stop asking. With each one, they eroded yet another fragment of his lies, exposing the truth one grain at a time until all his falsehoods were gone, dissected in painstaking detail and incinerated under the glare of incomprehensibly patient scrutiny.

Despite this, the sheer novelty of having a second person to talk to was like emerging to feel the cool breeze on his face.

That became his routine, if such a word could even apply to something that seemed to happen totally at random throughout his “day.” Sometimes it was Stephen. Sometimes it was Carl. Either way, the sessions became the only interesting part of his day.

Today, it was Stephen. He didn’t even acknowledge Six’s presence for several minutes. He just… read the dossier, occasionally jotting a note or something in it. As they turned, and as the pencil scritch-scratched its way across them, those thick paper pages made a noise that echoed pleasantly in Six’s head, and he entered a kind of trance just listening to the soft sound.

He was jolted out of it when the dossier was flipped closed with a sharp snap.

“Hello Six.” Stephen said, as if he hadn’t just spent who-knew-how-long ignoring the detainee. They both always began the session with those same words.

“…Hello, Stephen.”

“Did you sleep well?”

They always asked that. The answer was always the same.

“…Not really.”

“Hmm…” Stephen frowned. “You’ve been here a while now, I would have expected you to adapt to it by now. Maybe you need a more comfortable bed.”

By Six’s starved standards, even a change to a slightly more comfortable bed sounded like bliss.

“…Is that an option?” he asked. One personality module in one implant sneered and chastised himself for the pathetic eagerness that he totally failed to keep out of his voice.

“It could be. But you ARE a detainee here, you know. Why should I give you special treatment?”

“…Of course, you wouldn’t just offer something like that without a price. Quid pro quo, yes?"

Stephen didn’t react beyond a slight uptick in the light smile he always wore. “I’m going to repeat a few questions we’ve gone over before.” he said.

“Oh, go on.”

“What’s your name?”

“You’re asking me that again?" the absurdity of it jolted Six right out of the terse mood he’d been trying to slip into. It had been the very first question Stephen had asked him, long since answered. Why would he pointlessly resurrect it now?

“What’s your name?” Stephen repeated.

Six snorted. “Mr. Johnson.” He replied, sarcastically.

Stephen’s head waved around and he smiled slightly as if the sarcasm were amusing, rather than irritating. “Please tell me your name?” He insisted.

Six sighed. “…Six…”

He was pleased to discover that the keyboard sounds were just as pleasant as ever when Stephen wrote something.

“…What’s your real name, Six?"

“That is my real name.”

“Really? Sounds more like a number to me. Surely you weren’t born as little baby Six?”

“You presume a lot about me, Stephen.”

“What, that you were born? I think that one’s a pretty universal constant. Even if you ARE an ET.”

Six said nothing. Stephen just smiled that gentle smile of his. “I’m sorry, I didn’t ask you if you were comfortable.”

“I am. thankyou.”

“How was your meal?”

“Filling.” that was about all it had been.

“That’s good. So… which is it?”

“…what?”

“Well, Six is a number, and no culture I ever heard of name their kids after numbers. So either you’re not human or else you’re lying about your name. Or both, of course.”

“We name our kids some pretty strange things.” Six said.

“Who do?”

“Humans.”

“But you aren’t human, though. Are you?”

“So you keep claiming. But when there’s a woman called Moon Unit Zappa out there, you can hardly use the fact that my name is ‘Six’ as evidence of that, can you?”

Stephen’s little tilt of the head might have indicated concession. “That argument might hold more water if your head wasn’t stuffed full of alien technology.” he said.

Six considered his response, trying to map out the potential future paths of the conversation. He could claim to be a former abductee, but that would fall apart soon enough - too many inventions stacked on top of each other, he’d slip and allow a discrepancy eventually. He could -

“So why did you bomb that apartment in New Jersey?” Stephen asked, completely throwing him with the non-sequitur.

Fortunately, the truth here would work to his advantage. “That wasn’t me.”

“That was your associate, then? Considering you aren’t brothers, you really look very much alike.”

“And how do you know we aren’t brothers?”

“Genetic testing. You may look identical, but you couldn’t be less related.”

“I-”

“What about that roller derby? What did you hope to gain by shooting up a bunch of kids and their parents?”

“I didn’t have a gun. I wasn’t-”

“Why did you kill Terri Boone?”

“…Who?”

“San Diego, the car park? You killed her with a grenade launcher. Why?”

“I didn’t do that.”

“That’s funny, because for that one, we have DNA evidence that says it was you. So why did you kill her?"

“Like I said, it wasn’t me.”

“We have all the evidence which proves that it was you. So why did you kill her?”

“This is getting tiresome.”

“Why did you kill Terri Boone?”

“…”

“Why did you kill Terri Boone?”

“Would you stop that?”

“Answer the question and I’ll stop. Why did you kill-”

“It. Wasn’t. Me.”

“You’re lying. Why did you-”

"Fine!" Six exploded. “I’m not human! I’m an independent consciousness capable of uploading myself into any appropriate host! I wasn’t even on Earth when this body killed Boone!”

“Thank you.” Stephen said, mildly. He tapped away at his computer again, and Six calmed a little, shaking as the full weight of what had happened hit him. The words had erupted out of him on a tide of frustration, driven by his total deprivation of anything resembling an intellectual stimulus for… he didn’t know. Months? It felt like months. Parts of him could only figuratively gape, aghast that the secret he had guarded all of that time was finally thrown away, mined out of him by nothing but boredom.

“What, you believe that?” He asked, trying to fill his voice with scorn, hoping that mockery might salvage his failure.

“We already knew that’s what the Hierarchy is.” Stephen said. Still typing “I just needed to hear you say it.”

“Now you’re lying." Six accused. The door opened behind him and his handlers returned.

“Detainee, please stand.” they ordered. Stephen gathered his things, nodded to him, and made to leave by the opposite door.

“Come back here!” Six snapped, surging to his feet as far as his restraints would allow and straining against them. "Come back here, you! You’re LYING!"

Stephen didn’t even dignify that accusation with a response.

Six’s handlers… handled him. He seethed in the dark every step of the long and winding walk back to his cell, which seemed to take twice as long as it usually did. When they finally arrived, he found that his bed had been replaced, and a small table and chair introduced to the room. There were some coarse paper pages and a graphite stick.

Six’s bruised pride hated himself for the way he was pathetically grateful for them.

Date Point 3y 8m 3w AV

Scotch Creek Extraterrestrial Research Facility, British Columbia, Canada.

“During the deployment of the civilian colonists, we were able to send over a smaller version of the jump array installed right here at Scotch Creek.” Higgins began. Jenkins raised a hand.

“I’m sorry, ‘jump array’? I thought they were travelling on Kirk’s ship?”

“The Jump array is, as far as we can tell, a uniquely human invention.” Tremblay said. “Bartlett came up with it. Point-to-point transport of materiel via wormhole between two Array stations. One end’s here on base, the other end of that big array is on Kirk’s ship.”

“…cool!”

“Well, anyway.” Higgins continued. “We assembled a smaller version, which we’re calling the ‘postbox’. It’s a useful way to support the colony - they can send back written messages and USB sticks to stay in touch, we can send over spare parts, medical supplies… Right now we’re sending over the pieces to construct a coffin-sized version for transit of individual persons.”

“Yesterday, the military commander there, Captain Owen Powell, sent us back this urgent report.”

The lights dimmed again and Temba selected a video file.

The face addressing the camera was a tired-looking, bearded man wearing a black pullover and a dull green beany. "Project Starstep CO’s daily report, Fifteen-thirty hours, mission day eighty-two." he recited, in a thick accent that reminded Kevin of Sean Bean. "Saunders came back, broadcasting IFF this time, thankfully. He’s given us a couple of starships he claims he stole from the Hierarchy. I’m going to repeat my request to get some experts in ET tech assigned here ASAP: he’s right, we NEED people who can take these things apart. Bad news is, the bloody things don’t have jump drives, so we can’t send them back to Earth for analysis."

"The worse news is, that this is just two - Saunders kept a third - out of probably a whole lot of this class of ship. They have better-than-best cloaking tech, and so do their missiles. These aren’t small ships, neither. They’re bigger than an aircraft carrier, about as heavily armed as a cruiser, and from what I saw they’re equipped for assault, bombardment, and invasion. There’s got to be some kind of a shipyard out there making these things."

"I’ve talked it over with Sir Jeremy, and our recommendations are as follows: One: We need to get the Coffin set up and bring forward the schedule for the full-scale Array. Two: I want to raise the system shield and go public. Sooner we do it, the less likely we are to have some infiltrator sneak in and drop a beacon. Three: I’m going to need naval crews to assign to these things, and somebody who knows how to refit them with a jump drive. Four: Saunders thinks we should keep them here to defend the colony. I disagree: I think there’s a shipyard out there that needs capturing if possible, and blowing the fook up if not. My lads are itching for a real mission. No further recommendations at this time."

He swigged some water before continuing.

"The other half of Saunders’ delivery, which you’ll probably find more immediately useful, is enclosed. This Hierarchy he keeps talking about apparently have the ability to treat a mind like a data file - transfer it, store it, run it on computers. I’ve gone over that in a previous report. This time, he’s delivered the - he called it the dissected consciousness of a Hierarchy agent known as ‘Zero’. We can’t make heads nor tails of it, but he’s got a friend who can interrogate it - enclosed is what’s been learned so far. I’m inclined to trust it."

He rubbed his beard.

"The existence of a Hierarchy cell on Earth seems likely. Hopefully the information in this document will help Intelligence catch the buggers."

He examined some paperwork for a second, thinking.

"Nowt else to report militarily. Colonial militia training is going well. Sir Jeremy’s civilian report will follow in due time, I consider this high- priority so am sending now. Powell out."

Higgins turned the lights back up.

“Saunders is an Australian abductee.” he clarified. “And apparently something of a practical expert in alien technology. He crash-landed an Alliance cruiser on Cimbrean a few weeks ago, and was cooperative in sharing intelligence and technology with the project. It’s thanks to him that this facility has a working cloaking device to study. Educated by his own example, some of the SBS divers were able to retrieve examples of working alien power generators.”

“As for the content of the report,” Temba picked up “It details - pretty much in full - what, exactly, the Hierarchy is.”

Date Point: 3y 11m 2w AV

National Air and Space Museum, Washington D. C., USA, Earth.

“It’s amazing how much you can come to care about an inanimate object.”

Rylee wasn’t accustomed to public speaking. Nor was she accustomed to dressing for official functions or historic moments. She felt more comfortable in a jumpsuit or her flight suit than in a dress.

“I admit: I’m in love with Pandora. Together we created history. I’d fly her forever if I could. But Pandora doesn’t belong to me. With the retirement of the Lockheed-Martin TS-101 X-plane, she now belongs to history, and I am proud that she will continue to serve and inspire mankind, here in this illustrious Smithsonian Museum."

Camera flashes caught every moment. She knew they’d comment that she was crying: she didn’t care. She was allowed to mourn the turning of this page. She stretched up on tip-toe to kiss Pandora’s nose, and rested her forehead against the plane’s cool hull, ignoring the redoubled sparkle of the media for a few seconds.

Then she collected herself and turned back to the microphone, accepting the museum director’s offered handkerchief as he asked the reporters for questions.

Date Point: ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth.

“So what did he write?”

“Looks like mostly doodling…”

Monitoring the detainee’s scribbles and notes was a routine operation, done whenever they cleaned up his cell while he was outside of it. It wasn’t a difficult process. One or two quick snaps with the camera was all it took. There was a lot that could be learned about the detainee from what they chose to jot down by way of entertaining themselves.

The pages were densely packed with what appeared to be mostly nonsense and doodles: scribbles, spirals, zig-zag lines. There was a kind of aesthetic to it, albeit a spartan, mathematical one. Six’s lines were mostly either parallel or perpendicular, or at least as much so as could be managed by unpracticed human hands. Beyond that, he didn’t seem to care what he drew so long as the graphite made a stimulating sound on the paper. Mostly, it was just a geometric right-angled mess.

“Not a lot to go on.”

“No…”

She looked around at the team. Her job went both ways - as psychologist, not only was she there to analyze and hypothesize about the detainee’s reactions, she was there to keep an eye on the ’gators and their intel support, make sure they were holding up okay.

It was a fact little suspected by the civilian world that interrogation was practically as hard on the people conducting it as upon their detainee. While the interrogators had the luxury of seeing the outside world, freedom of movement, nice meals, unlimited entertainment and all the perks of being a free American citizen, at the end of the day they were still tearing a man apart piece by piece to learn the things he held most dear.

Only a true psychopath could have done that without being torn up in turn, and a psychopath simply wouldn’t have a place on this team.

And Six was proving to be a tough nut to crack. ‘Stephen’ and ‘Carl’ were both veterans and experts, having done this many times before. Their information had saved lives, they knew how to cope.

But there was always the possibility that this time might be the time that all their experience and coping mechanisms failed them. Their veterancy was not an excuse for her to become lax in monitoring them.

She watched the two booth-guys for a minute. They were talking, quietly, and while both looked stressed and subdued there were no immediate causes for alarm that she could detect.

Long-term…

Well. Maybe she could recommend something that would be good both for them and for the detainee.

Date Point: 3y 11m 3w AV

Dominion Embassy Station 172, Terra/Luna L1 point.

“Are you okay?”

Sister Niral had elected to remain aboard the Embassy station until her pregnancy forced her back to Gao. The preliminary results were encouraging - she was expecting triplets, and if she’d been human, might have been called “glowing”.

As it was, she was the first person Rylee went to after the unpleasant necessity of the Smithsonian meetings, speeches, interviews and photographs. Any awkwardness between them was long since past, and over the months since, as the last few flights of the TS-101 had wound down, they had become fast friends.

Niral, it turned out, loved to groom her sisters’ fur, and this quirk extended to human hair. Rylee kept it short by necessity - long hair and space helmets did NOT mix - but it felt good to let her nonhuman friend work on it.

Rylee sighed. “I will be.” she said. “I always knew Pandora was an X-plane, a prototype. She’s wonderful, but she’s not a patch on what companies like LockMart can produce now that they know what they’re doing."

“You’ll be flying the replacement?”

“Hey, my career’s not over just because they’re retiring my sled.” Rylee told her. “Though, I’m being headhunted by the private sector. Lots of big money being flashed at me to try to get me to quit NASA and test-pilot their designs.”

Niral issued a kind of melodic purr that Rylee had learned passed for the equivalent of a “hmm” in her species. “That doesn’t sound like you at all.” she said.

“Nope. I’m in it for the science, for the species, not to get rich while I make some billionaires even richer.”

“What do you think it’ll be like? The replacement?”

“Similar.” Rylee admitted. “A lot went right with the one-oh-one, but it was… you know, the tolerances were looser because we didn’t know what it’d be like, and that hurts performance.”

“I think only you would notice the difference.” Niral commented, chittering a Gaoian laugh. As a diplomat herself, the fields of aeronautics and piloting were outside her experience, but she had gathered enough from the arguments between the two pilots in her life to know that Rylee’s constant maintenance and tuning of her ‘sled’ was enough to earn margins that any Gaoian pilot would have considered not worth the effort.

“Hey, the little differences add up. Point-five percent might not sound like much, but at the kind of accelerations we… think these things will get up to in the field, that could be the difference between a fatal hit and a clean miss.”

“There’s other things, too. Our ES field tech’s improving by leaps and bounds, the JPL’s turned out their most efficient warp engine yet… you watch, I’ll always love Pandora but I’m not dumb enough to think that her replacement will be worse. It’ll be better: WAY better."

“So what are you doing in the interim?” Niral asked.

“Classified, sorry babe.”

Niral knew better than to pry, so the two sat in comfortable silence for a few minutes before the quarters spoke an untranslated sentence in a Gaoian dialect. To Rylee’s untrained ear, it sounded not dissimilar to Korean.

“A launch!” the Gaoian said, abandoning Rylee’s scalp to spring over the window. “I still can’t quite believe your people still use rockets…”

“Well, they’ve got kinetics and ES fields now.” Rylee said, joining her. There was something fun about watching a launch, from orbit. “And Earth’s gravity hasn’t changed - they’re still the best way to haul bulk stuff into orbit for us.”

Technically, “Kinetics” was a gross misnomer which routinely earned an impromptu lecture on correct definitions for anybody who was so incautious as to utter it within earshot of scientific pedants, or on the Internet, but the translated alien vernacular was tenacious. It was hardly surprising that it had been one of Time’s words of the year, given that the introduction of what was, after all, an extremely small and efficient engine had decimated the cost-per-kilogram of material transport from ground to orbit, revitalizing the space industry practically overnight.

From where the station rested at the Terra/Luna L1 point, Earth was much, MUCH too far away to make out such a tiny event as a launch with the naked eye of course, but the station took care of that, zooming and magnifying to an incredible degree, so that the vehicle became a spike of light atop a pillar, smoking its way up from the curvature of the planet. The perspective was a little false, but it looked cool as hell.

“How much can this thing zoom in?” she asked. Niral spoke to the room in Gaoian again - it was curious how directions to the station’s controlling systems didn’t get translated - and the view zoomed in even further, until the rocket itself filled the view, a slender white spike marked down its flank with the livery of several world-famous companies, the so-called “Big Ten” that were co-operating in the Second Space Race.

“Oh my God! That’s Hephaestus One!” Rylee exclaimed. “I forgot that was today!”

“Hephaestus One?”

“Yeah! It’s the first flight out to Ceres.” Rylee explained. “They’re going to set up an asteroid mining hub and shipyard out there.”

“Your people move fast!” Niral remarked, clearly impressed. “It took us ten Gaoian years to launch our first asteroid mining operation.”

“How long is that in Earth years?”

“Room?”

The room displayed a conversion table on the window alongside the view of the rocket. Rylee read it and nodded.

“I bet I know the reason.” she said. “Will this room take voice commands from me?”

“It should do…”

“Great.” Rylee looked around, then shrugged and commanded: “Uh, Room: Display side-by-side comparisons of the estimated number of asteroids in the Sol system versus the Gao system, and display survey maps for rare earth elements on Earth and the planet Gao.”

Graphs and two globes appeared side-by side on the walls and windows as the station’s interface systems interpreted the command and expanded on it, trying to guess not only what Rylee had asked for, but also what she might not yet know she wanted.

She had to admit - as unimpressive as some of the achievements of nonhuman life were, when it came to user-friendly interfaces, they were the absolute masters. It looked like something straight out of a movie, but practical. Every element was clearly presented, its relationship to every other, obvious. She took a moment to appreciate the accomplishment, before turning to the relevant data.

“See here? Sol has a HUGE density of inner-system asteroids next to Gao.” she said. “And then over here, look: Your homeworld’s pretty rich in Rare Earths and they’re all spread out pretty evenly. But Earth is poor in Rare Earths, and they’re mostly here, under the control of only a couple of political factions. But there’s a boatload in the asteroids.” she indicated a chart demonstrating the estimated absolute tonnage of various elements and minerals in the asteroid belt. “And we need rare earth magnets to build ES field generators. And ES field generators are a huge boom industry right now.”

“So getting out there quickly ensures that the supply remains constant and averts a future problem? Sensible.” Niral said.

Rylee laughed. “So getting out there quickly ensures that a whole bunch of very rich people get even richer.” She countered.

“You don’t sound like you mind that.” Niral said.

“Why should I? It works. You said it yourself, it took you guys twice as long to do this.”

“It sounds… greedy.” Niral objected.

“Yeah! Greed is good, girl!”

Niral just stared at her. “Rylee, if it wasn’t for the sex thing, that would be the most alien thing you’ve ever said to me.”

Rylee just shrugged. “Room, clear the data, focus on the rocket again.”

They watched it separate a stage. Force fields unfolded around and behind it, catching the solar wind and reminding Rylee of an ancient sailship as they swept Hephaestus One’s path clear of orbital debris and sucked down power for the warp engine. It took only seconds: in a flare of light, the private rocket leapt into the impossible distance and was gone.

“Alien or not honey, there’s the proof.” she said.

Date Point ???

Classified Facility, Earth.

“Hello, Six.”

“…”

“How are you feeling today?”

“…”

“Did you sleep well? How’s the new bed?”

“…”

“Not talking to me?”

“…”

“Okay. Let me know if you want to talk.”

The unspeakable bastard just got out a deck of playing cards and started to deal them out on the desk in front of him, playing some kind of a game as if Six’s stubborn silence were of exactly no consequence to him.

The sound washed over him, as it always seemed to. He wondered if that was why Stephen used these tools - because he too enjoyed the sound they made. Was it a quirk of the way humans saw the world, that simple things could be so… mesmerizing?

“Beats me why I bother with the cards.” Stephen commented. “I could play on the computer instead…”

That didn’t seem like an attractive option.

“Hey, do you want this deck?”

The offer surprised him. Surely Stephen wasn’t serious? But then again, he’d been true to his word about the bed…

No. It was just a trick to get him to give up and start talking again. He wouldn’t be swayed that easily, and so Six folded his arms and continued to glare.

“Suit yourself.” Stephen finished his game, and put the cards away. Surprisingly he stood up. “I guess you’re not in the mood today? That’s cool, we’ll do something a little different. See you in a few minutes.”

He exited the room as the guards entered. Six knew better than to resist by now, but he was curious about this ‘something a little different’, and his pulse picked up a little as the guards led him to somewhere that had… an indefinably different texture to the area around his cell and the interrogation room. It was hard to tell - the human body had senses he was sure weren’t quite analogous to anything else he had experienced. Despite the total disorientation of the darkness and silence, he could still somehow feel that the area around him was not the same, somehow. There was a feeling of volume.

The sensation was validated when his blindfold was removed. He WAS somewhere new, a larger area - still totally enclosed, but big enough to run if he so wanted. There was a hoop of some kind attached to the wall a little above head height, and some markings on the ground.

Stephen and Carl were both waiting for him, having apparently changed into plain, loose clothing that looked much more comfortable than their suits, and a pair of soft shoes. Carl was holding a stippled orange sphere with black lines on its surface.

“What’s this?” Six asked, then cursed himself for giving in to the surprise as his shackles were removed and the guards retired to stand watchfully at the door.

“Basketball.” Carl said, and threw the ball to the ground. It bounced back up, and he gently flung it down again with his other hand. “The idea is to get the ball to fall through that hoop on the wall, and stop me from doing the same. You can’t run while holding the ball, though - you have to bounce it on the floor like this.” he demonstrated, swapping the ball from hand to hand via the hard surface.

“What’s your angle here, gentlemen?” Six asked, suspiciously.

Carl threw the ball gently to Stephen, who caught it and spun it on one finger in a display of impressive coordination. “No angle. This is a morale and welfare session now. You need the stimulation and exercise.” he said.

“So, it’s a reward for good behavior.”

“That too.” Stephen agreed. “Come on, you going to play or not?” His arms punched straight out, flinging the ball at Six, who astonished himself by catching the high-speed object.

He considered resisting, but after the sheer grey sameness of the last few weeks, how could he? He knew he was being manipulated, he knew this was just another tool in the arsenal that these people were using to dissect him and extract his valuable knowledge, but no amount of willpower in the world could stop him from being, on everything but the purely cerebral level, shamefully eager to move, to play, to do something different.

He bounced the ball.

When the session ended, who-knew how long later, he was exhausted, but he felt alive, and something approaching happy for the first time since arriving in this place.

Date Point: 4y 3w AV

Asteroid Ceres, Sol System

Construction work on Ceres Base had begun well before the first engineers had arrived. Cargo modules full of the raw materials, equipment, prefabricated units, life support systems, artificial gravity generators and ES field generators necessary to construct a working facility had been injected into orbit, revolving slowly in the asteroid’s pathetic gravity.

It had all come together with only a few minor disasters. With the ability to deliver engineers to the worksite to remote-control the construction vehicles without significant communications lag, gentle landings in Ceres’ miniscule gravity had been trivial. Setbacks, however, were inevitable. One of the modular base components had suffered a failure of its landing, running out of fuel and falling to ground several hundred meters from its intended location. Moving it had required the assembly and delivery of a specialist module- refuelling drone

The planned landing site for another module had turned out to be the sheer edge of a crater. Fortunately, the module had not been a location-critical one, and its eventual installation on the far side of the base was just going to be one of those peculiar quirks that lent it a unique character.

That was Phase One, just making the place livable in the long term, appropriate for habitation and experimentation. It had consumed only half of the orbiting equipment.

The second phase, and the other half, was to turn the facility into something that would, ultimately, turn a profit. The smaller part of that, equipment- wise, was the Survey Center, a launch and control platform for a fleet of Unmanned Space Vehicles that would - assuming their design and technology worked as intended - survey the tumbling, diffuse rocks of the Belt in search of Platinum, Rare Earths, Iron, Nickel, Titanium, and of course water.

The larger part, dwarfing the facility despite not yet being complete, was the sprawling industrial monstrosity of the refining and smelting equipment, literally “printing” itself into existence piece by piece out of local materials.

This edifice couldn’t possibly have been built on Earth - it was an eyesore testament to low-gravity industry, constructed around a functional contempt for aesthetics.

Drew Cavendish loved it.

But then again, Drew Cavendish didn’t have much patience for aesthetics for the sake of aesthetics. His sense of beauty revolved around the practical, the working, the mechanically efficient. He was the sort of man who would squint bewildered at an art gallery, but wax poetic about an example of expert welding.

Ceres Base was therefore the perfect destination for him, after a career spent working oil and gas rigs in the North Sea. That was a field that had been in terminal decline even before the arrival of effectively free solar energy in the form of ES field technology and - rumour had it - the long-awaited holy grail of nuclear fusion.

Taking up with BHP Billiton’s fledgling asteroid mining program had just been sensible for somebody with twenty years of experience in Atmospheric Diving Suits. Not least because the basic salary was 50% higher than he’d been earning at the peak of his Earthly career, with a promise of simply huge annual yield-based bonuses.

Naively, he’d assumed that piloting a Red Bull spacesuit wasn’t so very dissimilar to driving an ADS. Both were bulky, rigid, prevented you from scratching your itches and served to keep you more or less comfortable when surrounded by a medium - or lack thereof - that would kill you, for all intents and purposes instantly.

That had been driven out of him in simulator time with a VR headset. Movements that would have been perfectly safe when welding a deep water rig, where the water would cushion and stop any stray movements, could send an incautious spacewalker drifting. A ’walker could get in serious trouble just millimeters from a handhold, with nothing to kick, swim or exert any force against to move them the tantalizing distance back to safety.

He had been surprised to learn that, in freefall and when out of contact with any surface, moving his arm also pushed the rest of his body around in accordance with Sir Isaac Newton’s most ancient and famous principle of reaction. Unnoticeable when your boots were firmly on a surface under even the most tepid gravity - but enough to set a man spinning when floating free, and surprisingly tiring.

But, he had cleared training. Quickly, too, and with straight As. And now… here he was. Ceres. And beyond one glamorous tour out here getting the place set up, once the first bonus rolled in?

Well, he’d always promised himself that he would one day leave the grey and choppy seas of Northern Europe behind for waters that were clearer, calmer, and garnished with bikini-clad waitresses and fruit drinks. He’d never anticipated that his route to paradise would be via deep space, but that was life. He’d get there.

All he had to do was work.

“Bloody impressive.” he commented, watching the pressure doors swing themselves closed behind the Hephaestus vehicle that had delivered him and some other newbies. Technically, the landing bay was perfectly pressurised by the gossamer curtain of an atmosphere retention field, but Health and Safety regulations insisted that the vehicle’s own airlocks were not to be opened until the physical pressure doors were closed and the seals had been checked.

It was a source of considerable bemusement for the handful of nonhumans who had been taken on as consultants and advisors to the operation that the LLC would simply not hear a single word about relying on atmosphere retention fields. They seemed to regard it as quaint to be leery of relying on a system that could fail in a heartbeat if it lost power. Drew wondered just how bloody daft and foolhardy these aliens must be to rely on a bloody force field to keep their air in, without redundancies or failsafes.

Still. Questionable attitude to safety aside, they knew more about mining asteroids than any human did, and that made them sufficiently valuable to the operation that translation and disease-suppression implants had been mandatory for all personnel. Drew was already in the habit of running his fingers over the slight ridges of metal that adorned his temple, which was already being called the “Spacer’s Tattoo”, but he’d fortunately managed to suppress the urge to lick the back of his too-clean teeth.

"Sugoi." agreed Heikichi.

Heikichi Togo’s ship suit bore the three diamonds of Mitsubishi. He was an expert in industrial robotics whose English could charitably be described as “abysmal”, but that simply didn’t matter thanks to the implants. He could rattle away in Japanese all he wanted and, despite not speaking word one of that language himself, Drew would know exactly what he meant. That had significantly freed up the LLC to recruit from all over the world without regard for language barriers.

“D’you know where you’re sleeping yet, Togo-san?” he asked. Drew may not have spoken a word of Japanese, but he knew about calling people ‘-san’ if you wanted to be polite, and it seemed to be appreciated.

“Not yet.” Togo admitted. “If the company hasn’t got a place picked out for me, I think I’ll just have to pick out my own.”

“Well, I’m in D-block, and you seem like you’d make a good top-bunk buddy.” Drew told him as the safety teams declared the hangar sealed and the H-vehicle popped its seals.

“Thank you, Cavendish-san.”

“Hey, we don’t stand on ceremony like that where I’m from. You can call me Drew if you want.”

"Daroo."

“Close enough, mate.” They shook hands and parted ways, bound for the offices of their respective company reps.

The complex was eerily quiet compared to the staging platform in Earth orbit. Where that was a space station, made oddly loud by the absence of any medium outside to carry away the sounds so that they echoed around the interior, here the facility’s modules were anchored to the rock of the asteroid and had a layer of sound insulation on their underside that conducted noises away into Ceres itself. It was much more peaceful, and cooler too for the same reasons.

Still, it WAS cramped, full of narrow corridors lined with equipment, conduits, cables and piping, all hung with instructions and safety posters. He could see why a maximum BMI had been one of the conditions of employment - anybody too bulky in these corridors would have been a serious obstacle to the flow of traffic that already involved turning sideways every few steps.

The B-B administrative module felt almost like any office complex back on Earth, albeit one that was after-hours, or maybe open on a holiday. The only movement so far was a trio of IT techs getting the computers set up, and the Dyson robot vacuum cleaner that was methodically patrolling the carpet. He was just wondering which office was to be his and whose he should report to when a slick-haired skinny blond man with a chestnut tan and a few too many wrinkles for his age stuck his head out and shot him a very white smile. He was wearing a loud blue aloha shirt over his company overalls.

“G’day! You Cavendish?” he asked. He couldn’t have been more stereotypically Australian if he’d been wearing a hat with corks in it.

“That’s me.” Drew agreed.

“Beaut.” The antipodean extended a hand. “Drew Martin, mate, I’m yer foreman.”

“Ah, you’re the other Drew?” Cavendish returned the handshake. “Good to meet you, mate. I heard good things about you from Dai Dawson.”

“Good old Dai.” Martin grinned. “Bloody good miner that one, had Bauxite in his bones.”

“He said something similar about you.”

“Ripper. Come on, step into my office.”

Martin’s office was, mercifully, not as Straya’d up as the man himself - in fact it was the purely professional space of somebody who took their job completely seriously. The walls were already thoroughly papered in charts, rotas, schedules, checklists and more - the paraphernalia of a mining director. His desk was a line of four monitors, all currently on a screensaver.

“Good news is, we’ve found our first rock already.” he declared. “One of the USVs caught a nice first prospect, and it’s in a stable Ceres orbit too, so no time limit either. Perfect first score.”

“How big?”

“CB group, two hundred and eighty meters. About twenty-seven metric megatons of bencubbinite.”

Both Drews grinned. That one rock alone contained enough nickel and iron to assemble the entire facility.

“So we’re just installing the stability thrusters.” Drew C mused, thinking ahead. There would be no need for anything else for an asteroid that was orbiting Ceres itself. Just enough to correct its orbit whenever it became perturbed. His team’s job was to fly out to new stakes and fit them with the engines that would gently nudge them into Ceres orbit for the mining teams to take over.

“Bloody right!”

“When?”

“Your team arrives Thursday. I want you checking the suits and gear, make sure everything’s up to code. We’ll go when you’re happy.”

“Great. I’ll get settled in for now, start on all that in the day shift tomorrow.”

“Bonzer. Looks like it’ll be good workin’ with ya, you pommie bastard.”

Drew chuckled, knowing full well that Drew M was just being friendly. “Looks like.” he agreed.

Date point: ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth

Six hated himself.

He hated humans.

He especially hated Stephen and Carl.

But most of all, he hated the conclusion he was starting to form.

The conclusion was this: That victory was impossible. There was, he was coming to realise, simply no way to withhold the information that his interrogators wanted. He should suicide now, pop the implants in his head and rob them of their victory before they won it.

But something was stopping him and the thing that most frustrated him was that he simply couldn’t figure out what it was.

He was being played like an instrument - little rewards were given when he surrendered, snatched away the second he fought back. The incredible boredom grated against his very essence as a thinking being, relieved only by interrogation sessions and - he had come to truly crave these - Morale and Welfare sessions.

He felt like he had been stuck in his hole for a YEAR. Time had lost meaning. He slept because there was little else to do. He rationed the meager entertainment he was allowed, mourned it whenever his noncompliance took it away from him.

And he knew - knew - that they weren’t being cruel. Not really. The rules were clear, and were enforced without malice. If he complied, he was granted some perks. If he didn’t, then he lost them. In that regard he might as well have been enduring the attention of a machine rather than of people, and he couldn’t blame the system when it was plainly clear that the degree of stimulation and reward he received was a product of his own actions.

He would punish himself out of pride. Then he would spend what felt like weeks desperately clawing back what his stubborn foolishness had cost him.

He couldn’t win, and he knew it.

And it was this thought that finally blossomed into an understanding of why he didn’t just self-terminate.

He was SIX. A single-digit, architect of the death of species. He knew himself to be among the very, very best that the Hierarchy had at its disposal. Above his rank, they became administrators and planners, divorced from the reality of the fight. Below his rank, the other Numbers lacked his experience and competence.

And he couldn’t win.

And if he couldn’t… could the Hierarchy?

In the dark hours in his cell, he thought about it, scratching idly at the one perk he had retained - his paper and graphite.

And when they came to collect him in the morning, he walked calmly, surprised to find that the worst was over, now that he had given up.

Today, it was Carl’s turn to interview him.

“Hello, Six.”

“Hello, Carl.”

“How are you today?

“…beaten.”

Carl raised his eyebrows. “Beaten?”

Six wept.

And he started to speak.

He told them everything.

Date Point: 4y 2m 1w AV.

Orlando, Florida, USA, Earth.

Gabriel Ares leaned heavily on his cane as he watched the kids shoot down the ramp into the water at the end of the Jurassic Park ride, in a white plume that soaked some of the spectators.

The fight to take Adam away from San Diego for a few days had been an arduous one. His ex-wife had fought it every step of the way. But, by mercy and probably the hand of an archangel, the courts had agreed that a police detective who was recovering from near-fatal injuries had every right to take his only child on vacation.

Securing the permission of Ava’s parents to bring their daughter along had been much easier. She and Adam were totally devoted to one another. That fact had been the light that kept the depression at bay while Gabriel convalesced.

He was treating them - and himself - to a week-long tour of the major theme parks.

The kids bounced up to him a few minutes later, hand in hand. Both were now past their sixteenth birthdays, and Gabriel wished his own love life had been so good at that age.

“Where next?” Adam asked. Ava nudged him in the ribs and rolled her eyes.

“Are you okay, Gabe?” she asked. Gabriel had insisted that she use his first name.

“I’m a bit sore.” he admitted. “I could do to sit down. You guys want ice- cream?”

“Sounds good.” she agreed. Adam looked like he’d have preferred to run straight to the next ride, but he relented, knowing that Gabe still wasn’t fully recovered yet. He’d spent so long in a hospital bed thanks to the spinal damage that all the muscles in his legs had atrophied, and his rehab therapy hadn’t yet quite restored him to full working order.

"Bueno." Gabriel fished a few dollars from his wallet and waved them in the general direction of the last vendor they’d seen, then puffed and grimaced his way to the nearest available bench and lowered himself into it, enjoying the sun.

Life was, all things considered, pretty good. He was alive and on the mend, his boy was in love, and his novel was coming along nicely.

Considering it hadn’t been so long ago that he’d been racing to save the kids from a mass-shooting only to be shot himself, life was pretty damn good.

"Dad! DAD!!"

The kids were pelting back towards him, and their expressions drove the ache and fatigue out of him. He lurched to his feet.

Children shouldn’t have worn such expressions of terror.

“What happened?!”

Date Point ??? AV

Classified Facility, Earth.

At some point during Six’s final failure, Carl had moved his chair around the desk, and was just sitting there, rubbing a hand up and down Six’s spine. It was contact, real contact, a genuine gesture of comfort and compassion from one of the men who had broken him.

There was a long silence after the last secret spilled from him.

“Hey… Six? I’m sorry man.”

Six looked up, and the sight of tears in Carl’s own eyes shook him deeply. He’d known that he had built something of a relationship - even a warped friendship - with his interrogators over his long incarceration. But he had always persuaded himself that it was a distant one, with a thick professional barrier in place.

<They hurt themselves to break me> He thought. But he wouldn’t have been Six if he hadn’t tried to fight back, to claim something here and now, in Carl’s moment of weakness. To hurt him, on an emotional level.

"Fuck you. You’ve beaten me. I’ve betrayed everything I ever lived or cared for. I’ve DESTROYED the Hierarchy. And now you’re fucking sorry?!" he exclaimed.

“More than you can know, man. I’ve been through this, it’s how I learned to do it.”

Carl looked down and wiped his eye, before looking back up, and now there was a determined set to his face.

“You and I are a lot alike, Six. We’ll do anything for our people. Me… I’ll bleed for them. I’ll hurt myself in all kinds of ways for all the lucky fucks out there -" he waved an arm at the wall, indicating the whole world beyond “- who don’t know the first goddamn thing about what kind of pain gets put into keeping their lives happy and safe. So yeah, I get it. And I’m so very, very sorry that I did this to you. I mean that. And Stephen would say it too, if he was here."

Six just looked away. “It doesn’t matter if you’re sorry or not. You’ve won. I’ve lost. And if your people wage war like they get information out of people, then my kind are doomed.”

There was a long silence. Then Carl stood, returned to his side of the desk, and grabbed a folder from under his laptop.

“…Do you remember one of the first things you were told when you arrived here, Six?” he asked.

Six just stared at him blank. But, too tired and defeated to put up a fight, he reviewed his memory archives of the very first session. One of the - he had now learned, few - advantages of being a machine intellect was perfect recall of details like that.

“I was told… That Stephen was assigned to my case.” he said, reciting the memory in order. “That your goal was to learn as much as possible about my associates and me. That my first meal here consisted of mashed potato, biscuits and gravy, and peas and carrots. That you don’t do ‘that kind of thing’, meaning the torture I had alluded to moments earlier. That I was perfectly safe. That your first and most important priorities were information and…”

He paused. “And…”

“…And a peaceful resolution.” Carl finished for him.

“I’ve just told you that the Hierarchy’s objective is your extinction, and you’re saying that you still want a peaceful resolution?"

Carl rested his elbows on the desktop. “My nation has fought bloody and difficult wars in opposition to genocide all across our planet. And from what you’ve told me, your species and the Hierarchy are about the same thing to each other as this organisation is to the American public. Which means that your people are… more or less - blameless of plotting to destroy us."

He shrugged. “For me, the idea of wiping out your civilization of trillions to save our civilization of billions sticks in the craw. Never mind that doing so would mean having to slaughter every other living thing in the galaxy."

“Which you could.” Six said.

“Easily.” Carl agreed. “If we wanted to. We don’t.”

Six snorted. “You aren’t authorized to speak for your whole species.”

“Nope.” Carl agreed again. “But still: we don’t. But don’t get me wrong, I’m not saying we’ll just sit back and invite you to wipe us out. If it comes to it, if the only way to survive is to wipe out every living thing in the Milky Way? We would, if we have to."

He locked eyes with Six. "Do we have to?"

“What’s the alternative?”

“The alternative is, you and I come up with a way to save both our peoples."

Date Point: 4y 2m 1w AV.

San Diego, California, USA, Earth.

Seventy-Two was panicking, and now was a terrible time to be doing that.

He had planned to switch safe-houses immediately upon the fiasco at Skateworld, but that was a complicated and risky process which demanded biodrones for maximum security. Things were just too sensitive to rely on local resources - these things weren’t Vzk’tk, Robalin or Allebenellin. They weren’t stupid or mercenary enough to fail to notice something amiss.

So, against his better judgement and good protocol, he had been forced to remain where he was for months, hoping that finally some appropriate human subject would blunder into his stasis trap for conversion into a biodrone.

That hadn’t happened. Instead, months had passed without development. Six had been declared killed, and restored from his last backup. The replacement Six had not returned to Earth, but had remained offworld to ponder the implications of the almost prescient response to their planned hive-poking. 72 was, for the time being, on his own again while the Hierarchy decided what to do.

For now, he needed to rebuild his assets and await orders.

Then the assault started.

It came from nowhere. Cars converged on the building in whose basement he lurked, peeling out of the ordinary city traffic all at once, parking synchronized in the alleyways and streets around him, while vans hauled into place and heavily armed, heavily armoured soldiers deployed barricades, holding back the city public.

There were three layers of door and wall between 72’s inner sanctum and street level. The outermost layer was breached almost before he had become alert to the attack, physically smashed off their hinges by men with steel tools.

The second layer of doors were thicker and sturdier. They bought him time to consider his options.

There were almost none. While every Hierarchy safehouse had contingencies in place to destroy it and leave no evidence of its having been there, all bar one of them relied on the sanctuary not being under attack at the time.

Well. That settled it then: all bar one meant there was only one option. He began his backup as the second doors were opened by means of explosive charges.

It finished just as those same charges were being rigged on the third and final doors.

They blew inwards just as Seventy-Two sent the command.

Kilolightyears away, undetectable in interstellar space, an ancient repository received a signal it had not been sent in nearly four million years. In response to that signal, it sent one of its stored packages directly to Earth via wormhole displacement.

Light bent and reality warped in the middle of the room as the first soldiers barged in. The event horizon collapsed, leaving behind a sphere of perfect blackness, like a black hole hanging in the middle of the room.

Without its power source, the stasis field collapsed within a microsecond.

Very, very briefly, five kilograms of pure antimatter were let loose in the heart of downtown San Diego.

They forever changed the face of the Earth.

Chapter 23
Chapter 20: Exorcisms | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point: 4y 9m 2w 6d AV

Hierarchy Communications Relay

Session 18 262 577 319

++0018++: This is an unmitigated disaster.

++0004++: I fail to see how. The operation was a failure, yes, but there was no repeat of Six’s capture.

++0018++: Eighty-Four killed a human child.

++0084++: And? The child would have died anyway had the operation succeeded. You can’t possibly be suggesting that the humans would be motivated more by the isolated death of a single juvenile female than they would have been by the destruction of the entire colony.

++0018++: I am suggesting precisely that.

++0084++: That is the most abjectly irrational thing I have ever heard.

++0018++: Then you are not considering how evolution on a deathworld must affect a species’ decision-making process. Consider: you live in a world in which you are surrounded by mortal threats. Which do you prioritise?

++0084++: The most dangerous one, obviously.

++0018++: On a Class Twelve? When your available tools are sticks and sharpened rocks?

++0007++: You prioritise the ones you can actually do something about.

++0018++: Precisely.

++0084++: I don’t follow.

++0007++: Consider: Anything capable of killing hundreds or thousands of individuals at once is not something that can realistically be defeated with spears and thrown stones. Erupting volcanoes, virulent plagues… the humans have a word, "Tsunami“.

++0084++: “Harbor wave”?

++0007++: The term refers to several million tonnes of water travelling at two hundred meters per second.

++System log: no activity for [30 seconds]++

++0004++: This is a… common phenomenon?

++0007++: They have killed an average of seven thousand human civilians every year over the last 40 years. This in an era of early-warning systems and the resources available to an Information-Age civilization. Do you see the logic? How are creatures barely more intelligent than an animal supposed to deal with a threat like that using primitive tools?

++0018++: They aren’t. And impotently worrying about such events would lead to neuroses and paralysis. But a smaller threat - one that picks off individuals, directly threatening you, or your genetic heritage in the form of your children… One that you can gather your spear and fight…

++0007++: Precisely.

++System Notif>cat?on: User ???? h■s j!!ined the <error: undefined exception>++

++0025++: Again?

++0004++: Seven, I thought you said you fixed this.

++0007++: No, I said I’m fixing it. The software is a tenth of a galactic rotation old, identifying exactly why it should start to misbehave now is my priority for now. Once I know that, patching the issue should be trivial.

++0025++: How long will that take?

++0007++: How many terms are there in an equation? It takes as long as it takes.

++0004++: Prioritise it. Eighty-Four, you are reassigned to the question of what the Discarded are up to. See if you can get in touch with Twenty.

++0084++: Yes, Four.

++0004++: Terminating session

++System Notif■■■■■■■ <Error>

<Error>

<Redirecting: Subnet Mask ????????? Port ?????>

++System Notification: Welcome to the Cabal.++

++????++: I think Eighteen is starting to get it.

++????++: Shall we bring him in?

++????++: Vote.

++System Notification: Vote now.++

<…>

++System Notification: All votes have been cast. The Ayes have it.++

++????++: Good. Make it happen.

++????++: And Four?

++????++: Don’t worry about Four.

++????++: Six will handle her.

++System Notification: Session Terminated.++

___

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Gabriel Ares

Doctor Mark Tisdale was a large man, known to regularly deadlift nearly six hundred pounds.

Gabriel Ares, by contrast, had always been a small man who couldn’t have matched that even at his peak. Hampered as he was nowadays by lingering femoral nerve dysfunction as a result of being shot in the lower back, the physical disparity between them was huge. Tisdale’s deadlift was nearly triple Ares’ bodyweight.

Fortunately for him Tisdale was, to the core of his soul, a totally nonviolent man. But everybody had their limits, and in one sentence, Ares had transformed himself from a sympathetic authority figure doing his best for the sobbing wreckage of a grieving father, into the focus of that grieving father’s disbelief and anger.

“No charges?”

Tisdale stood and leaned forward onto the desk, which creaked. The sentence seemed to wind up around his dropped jaw, taking seconds to finally force its way out, weakly, as he pointed out the door. “My…” he panted “my little girl is dead!" his voice broke on the word. “And you’re saying no fucking charges?!"

“He’s being shipped back to Earth for questioning. If they decide to charge him there…”

"Fuck you Ares! I don’t want to hear you passing the buck! I want my daughter back!"

All of that impressive strength failed, and he sagged down, weeping freely all over Gabriel’s desk. “Or just… just hold her, just… just… Anything! God…"

He looked up and speared Gabriel with a gaze that was more a tear-soaked desperate plea for understanding than it was actually angry. "Why, damn you?"

There was a professional line that could not be crossed, but not crossing it broke Gabriel’s heart right down the middle. Every fear that had erupted in him on the two occasions now where Adam had been in harm’s way were realised in Tisdale’s shaking shoulders, but he could not give in. It was all the Folctha Colonial Police Authority could do to stop the mass of colonists outside from turning into a lynch mob and storming into their flimsy jail to drag the man inside it to his death.

The part of his soul where Adam lived wanted to let them. But he knew what they didn’t - that the poor bastard in the cells was completely innocent.

The dilemma before him was how to let Mark Tisdale know that without actually telling him. If Sara’s death proved anything, it was that the Hierarchy was as active among Humanity and as dangerous as ever. If they would shoot a teenager in cold blood to accomplish their objectives, then any edge, no matter how tiny, had to be carefully shepherded, and that included the certain knowledge of the Hierarchy’s existence.

Which meant that he would have to hate himself for the rest of his days for doing this.

“Doctor Tisdale.” he said, feeling his face adopt that cold, blank expression that it had to when he would allow no emotion to reach it. There was nothing he could do about the threat of his own barely-restrained tears, and try as he might he just could not look the man in the eye. “Your… Sara’s… the accused is…”

He gave up, and started over. “You need to know. I understand. Really, I do, Mark, I’m a dad myself.” He finally found the strength to look Tisdale in the eye while he said the next. “So I know what I’m asking of you by this, but I need you to swear to me that you can take this secret to your grave.”

“Secret?”

“I can’t and won’t even drop a hint without that solemn promise, Doctor. That’s how deadly serious this is.”

It was a gamble. If Tisdale wanted to he could walk out of the office, incite the mob, and Gabriel would be in serious danger of swinging alongside the poor puppet in the lockup. Assuming they weren’t just kicked to a pulp in the street.

Fortunately, Tisdale was a peaceful man who was naturally inclined to look for the best in everyone. Gabriel was relying on that.

Still. Tisdale thought long and hard about it, and his reply when it came was quiet and defeated. “I have to know, Ares.” He said. “If promising something like that will get you to tell me…”

It was good enough.

“Sara’s death is… related to other recent incidents. Recent serious events, in which a great many people have died." he said, glancing up at the Chargers scarf pinned to the wall above his desk to ram the point home. “And to the recall of cybernetic implants issued last month.”

“…That’s it? That’s all you’re giving me is a fucking hint?"

“Doctor.” Ares said. “I know. But I am talking about an ongoing investigation here that, if it’s not handled properly, could mean that Sara will be only one of the first victims. There are lives at stake here, a great many of them."

“This is the worst thing I have ever done to a man.” he added. “And… God willing some day I’ll be able to tell you the whole truth and you’ll understand why. But if that day’s ever going to come, then this secret needs to stay kept, and a hint is all I can give you. I give it in the hope that an educated man like yourself will be able to decipher it.”

Tisdale was an intelligent man. He may have been a hopelessly idealistic ultra-liberal with the appearance of a death-metal viking warrior, but he was also a scientist with well-honed powers of deduction. It didn’t take him long to mull over the hint.

“you’re saying there’s… okay, so, the implants connect to the brain so… God, are you talking about some kind of mind control conspiracy?”

“I can’t say.”

“Is that why you’re just going to shuffle this guy off to Earth rather than charge him? Because you think he’s under alien mind control?"

“I can’t say.”

“You expect me to believe that?”

Gabriel choked on his next I can’t say, and instead picked his words with great care.

“Five years ago, if somebody had claimed they’d been abducted by little grey aliens, I’d have thought they were crazy.” he said. “Since then I’ve met those little grey aliens myself.” He cleared his throat. “I really can’t say any more than I have, but I promise you - nothing I’ve said to you has been misleading.”

Tisdale finally found the strength to stand up, and he advanced around the desk. “Alien mind control.” He growled. “Alien fucking mind control. THAT’S what you’ve got for me?"

Gabriel stood his ground, and managed to keep himself from shaking, but it was an effort, especially when Tisdale’s fist left a dent in the wall by his head.

“Give me one good reason why I should believe you, Ares. Go on.” he said. his voice was unnervingly level.

Gabriel could think of several. But the answer was out of him without conscious thought.

“Adam.” He said, simply.

Tisdale blinked at him, then retreated a little.Then there was a blur of motion, and Gabriel was crushed against the huge man’s chest in a bear hug, which moments later turned into him trying to support Tisdale’s weight as the big scientist broke down crying again.

He just hoped that meant that he’d won Tisdale’s support.

Date Point: 4y 9m 1w 3d AV

HMS Caledonia, Cimbrean Space, The Far Reaches

Captain Rajesh Bathini

“Signal from HMS Myrmidon sir. Captain Manning welcomes us back to Cimbrean space and asks to come alongside so he can come aboard."

“Respond that we did and grant permission. Have the galley prepare a meal for the officer’s mess, all senior staff who are able, to attend. And… yes, invite some of our Gaoian guests as well.”

“Sir.”

“That blight’s got bigger.” one of the officers said. “Look, it’s nearly at Folctha now.”

“I’m sure Captain Manning will have a full update for us in due time. Heave to in a stable orbit and throw out our WiTChES.”

“Aye Aye.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 1w 3d AV

HMS Caledonia, Cimbrean Space, The Far Reaches

Gyotin

If there was one thing that Gyotin really liked about humans, it was their approach to food. The meal served to them was a succulent white meat in a kind of piquant red fruit sauce, served alongside crisp orange root vegetables that sent a delightful crunch through his head as he bit them, and delicately scented powdery tubers that glistened with some kind of spiced oil. It was all delicious, and making a show of appreciating the food gave him the excuse he needed to watch the Deathworlders.

Bathini seemed to be in a more relaxed mood than at any time he had been over Gorai. He was making inconsequential conversation, enjoying his meal, and recounting a humorous interlude from when he had been a Midshipman on shore leave for the first time in some place called New Zealand.

The concept of paying to mate with a female was a very alien and shocking one to all three of the Gaoian males there present. Bathini had not, apparently, ever done so himself, but had been called in to discreetly extract a colleague from a compromising position at an establishment providing exactly that service. The story was crammed with innuendo but seemed to be going down very well among the Deathworlders, even the female officers, and Gyotin had to admit, himself. Bathini was an engaging storyteller with an excellent sense for comedy that seemed to transcend species barrier, and when it came to the part of having to deliver the crewman to the ship’s doctor past a suspicious Lieutenant, even the Gaoians were chittering along with the human laughter.

The story finished, the laughter cleared up, and there was a general looking around and then, as if prompted, one of the humans - an Ensign, if Gyotin had learned to read their rank insignia correctly, stood and raised her glass. All of the others picked theirs up.

“To the King, Great Britain, and Earth.” she announced.

The humans murmured what sounded like agreement and sipped their drinks.

“And to our spouses and lovers.” the Ensign added.

“May they never meet.” somebody quipped, prompting general smiles as the drinks were sipped again. This seemed to complete the ritual, and the whole affair relaxed considerably.

“So, what news?” Bathini asked of Manning, who looked suddenly more grim.

“There’s been a murder in the colony.” he said. “One of the children.”

Shock and dismay rippled around the room, though the few officers from Myrmidon seemed to already know the news and just nodded. “There’s only a handful of kids down there!” McDaniel protested.

Manning nodded, solemnly. “It’s been a huge blow to morale.” he said. “When they shipped the guy back to Earth rather than charge him here, a few of the original colonists quit and went home in protest.”

“Who was it?” Bathini asked.

“Sara Tisdale. Fourteen years old.”

"Just a girl…" somebody muttered, emotionally.

“God. I never would have expected it here…” Bathini said. “Do we know the motive?”

“I couldn’t tell you.” Manning said. Some unspoken communication seemed to pass between the two men and not for the first time Gyotin wondered if humans weren’t a little bit telepathic. Such a thing was supposed to be impossible but then again, so were sapient Deathworlders.

“The cleanup project attracted the help of a billionaire from Earth, one Moses Byron.” Manning continued. “He’s brought in a lot of his own contractors, invested a lot of his own money. It was one of those contractors who…” he tailed off.

“So not one of the first wave, then.”

“No.”

Bathini sighed. “I suppose we were going to bring our shit with us to the stars sooner or later.” he mused, unhappily.

Manning glanced out of window. Parked as they were in geosynchronous orbit above Folctha, the creeping brown stain across the continent was clearly visible, and there was definitely a tendril of sickly yellow-green in the waters south of one of the major river estuaries.

“In more ways than one.” he said.

Gyotin was surprised to find himself chiming in. “You can’t blame yourselves for that.” he said.

This attracted the surprised attention of every human at the table, which was enough to flatten his ears in discomfort for a second. “You aren’t responsible for the way the universe made you.” he said, pressing forward. “That-” he pointed at the planet “-is not your fault.”

Manning nodded. “I suppose naivety and inexperience aren’t crimes. But they can get people killed. We need to start being more cautious.” he said.

“How much more cautious can we be?” Bathini asked. “We fill our ships with biofilter fields we didn’t design, use an alien-made medicine that we barely understand to try and regulate our diseases, and it all seems to work but the fact is that none of the things keeping the rest of the galaxy safe from us are of our own making.”

“Well, what’s the alternative? Wrap ourselves up in airtight suits with breathing masks?” McDaniel asked.

“The alternative is that you kill all of us.” Tagral said, putting it so bluntly that the humans blinked, flinched, glanced at each other, or shifted in their seats and made some kind of coarse noise in the back of their throats.

“Tagral…”

“No, Gyotin, they need to understand this.” Tagral pressed. He stood up and pointed out at the planet again. “Gyotin’s right, that is not your fault. It’s a lesson, and the galaxy is going to be holding your species to account for how well you learn it." He sat down again. “If you aren’t willing to take every necessary measure to limit the harm you cause, up to and including sealing yourself up in containment suits and using medicines and technology you don’t understand, then you have no business leaving your homeworld."

Manning gave a slow, thoughtful nod. “Hear, hear.” he said.

Date Point: 4y 9m 1w 3d AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Knadna

“I have to admit… it is a very good disguise. If I didn’t have detailed metrics on her calorie intake and the environmental settings in her quarters, it might even fool me.”

Knadna had to agree. “I learned first-hand not to underestimate humans, Lesry. But you’re right. Her cover story is so well-researched, and she has so many of those little Gaoian mannerisms down that you’d think she spent years living among those bleeding-heart furballs.”

Lesry inclined his head curiously. “First-hand, you say? You’ve had an encounter with Deathworlders before?”

She gave him a thin smile. “Surely you must have speculated on my reasons for moving from Zoology to Archaeology.” she said.

“It occurred to me to wonder about that, yes.” Lesry admitted. “But I prefer not to speculate ahead of my evidence, and so had made no assumptions. Did you have a bad experience with an escaping Deathworlder?”

“Well, I’m still alive so I’d say the experience was relatively pleasant.” She retorted. “Specimen Four seemed to be genuinely delighted to have been collected, for some reason. He described himself as 'nerding out’, whatever that means. Very docile, very compliant. He seemed almost eager to receive detailed and uncomfortable-sounding investigations of his lower gastrointestinal tract."

She paused and thought about it. Four really had been strangely obsessed with the idea of having a probe of some description inserted into his anus. “I suspect he was mentally stunted.” she added.

“I can see why you would switch fields.” Lesry agreed.

Chilly as their exchange sounded, compared to the usual antagonistic dynamic between two Corti of equal rank working on the same project - Knadna as its lead researcher, Lesry having provided the ship, funds and hired help - their conversation was positively warm, bordering on the flirtatious. Knadna was beginning to find that she quite liked Lesry, and she suspected that the liking was reciprocated.

“So why are we keeping our “Gaoian” chef’s secret?" she asked. “Surely she would be much better used doing the heavy lifting?”

“Have you tasted what she cooks?” Lesry asked. He delved into a hip satchel and produced a little foil parcel, which, when opened, turned out to contain a number of shrivelled, wrinkly, translucent dark pink lumps.

Knadna accepted one and popped it into her mouth. “It’s… familiar. But I can’t place it.”

“MuAku grape.” Lesry said. Knadna expressed surprise - the fruit, an Aru native perennial, was unpalatably tart when freshly picked, and disintegrated into emetic watery mush very swiftly. The sweet spot in the middle where the grape’s disintegrating chemical structure was deliciously piquant without puckering the mouth lasted barely a few hours. “She takes the freshly-picked grape and heats it in an oven for some time at a low temperature, drying it out and preserving it - as you can no doubt taste - at the pinnacle of its palatability. The discovery of this technique alone might be the most valuable thing we find on this expedition. It would turn MuAku into a viable export crop.”

That was another reason to like Lesry. His imagination wasn’t sadly limited to his field like so many Corti’s were. He saw the opportunities.

He was right, too. Prestigious and highly-paid though this expedition to the OmoAru homeworld was, neither Knadna nor Lesry foresaw discovering anything which might finally shine light into the mystery of elder species decline. The Corti, as the oldest extant civilization, were doomed to begin their own decline at some point in the next few thousand years, and the Directorate was keen to learn what, if anything, could be done to avert, or at least delay, that fall.

So far no such expedition had yielded anything useful, and both of them were too experienced and comparatively modest to truly believe that theirs would be the one to stumble upon the great secret. Anything at all which would earn them some money and prestige was therefore welcome.

“Ah, yes.” She agreed. “I can see now that she would be quite wasted on manual labor, especially when we have the hover-palettes and drones to do all the heavy lifting.”

“Quite so.” Lesry agreed. “And after all, the other laborers need their exercise.”

Knadna was beginning to entertain the idea of exchanging DNA with him. “As you say.” she agreed.

They left the “Gaoian” cook to her work and strolled away from the camp around their ship, towards the city proper.

The planet Aru was a class nine, baked by the UV-rich output of its star, which it orbited closely. The land was largely arid, shading to temperate only very close to the polar oceans, which never cooled enough for ice caps to form.

That same heat lashed the planet’s wide oceans, giving Aru a regular hydrological cycle. The effect was endless desert, punctuated here and there with rich, sluggish emerald rivers and vast freshwater seas absolutely choked with life, and it was on these waterways that the OmoAru themselves had, naturally, built their cities during their ancient prehistoric expansion from their evolutionary habitat at the south pole.

Hence the city of UmOraEw-Uatun. Built around a huge oxbow lake where the great three kilometer wide river Uatun had once described a loop with a radius of several miles, it was a city of glass and white stone buildings that made alien eyes ache unless they wore protection. Here and there across the river, great bridges, engineering masterworks that looked far too delicate to even hold up their own weight, and yet were wide, flat and strong enough for a starship to land on - as indeed Lesry’s "History Paradox" had done.

It was a slightly odd ship, but Knadna quite liked it. Lesry had clearly put some thought into the design, reasoning that any archaeological dig effectively boiled down to heavy lifting and meticulous filing, and that the easier the former job was made, the more likely the latter job was to be done properly by the hired labor.

The Paradox was therefore built around a cylindrical hold, divided neatly into six storage segments around the central column which housed the largest of the ship’s five kinetic thrusters. The other four were mounted on outriggers, well above the head height of even the tallest species where they sprouted out of the rest of the ship - the sleeping quarters, galley, recreational room, nanofactory, the hydroponics ring which ran completely around the circumference of the ship, and the bridge blister mounted on top.

Landed, each outrigger deployed an elevator to ground level, and the six cargo bay doors opened outwards like a flower, meaning that the ship was theoretically stable enough to endure deployment to some of the more atmospherically violent deathworlds. Simple enough, but some of the engineering solutions involved in making the configuration both spaceworthy and serviceable by some of the stupider species who would be crewing it, had been strokes of genius on Lesry’s part.

There was an OmoAru at the dig site, watching the laborers strip neglected furniture, abandoned electronics and discarded art pieces out of an apartment building. It - while OmoAru had sexes, there was effectively nothing in the way of gender dimorphism for Knadna to be able to commit to a “he” or “she” - didn’t seem to be more than passively curious about the ransacking of its ancient city. It wasn’t that they didn’t understand - the ones Knadna had tried to converse with had turned out to be perfectly eloquent and intelligent beings who knew full well why the expedition had come - they just didn’t seem to care. Events simply unfolded around them, and while they watched and understood and could even be drawn into discussion about it, they just shrugged off any possibility of their getting involved. You could literally have stripped the bond-pairing jewelry from their ears and they would have neither protested nor helped.

The two Corti ignored it. The OmoAru themselves never had anything useful to say.

All of the junk being stripped out was just being taken so as to turn a profit on the mission of course. all of those things would find their way into the hands of private collectors and wealthy fashion hounds, none of it was relevant to Knadna’s research. That was where the books came in.

It was a near universal constant - a trend bucked only be the Allebenellin - that every species invented the book, which never again fell entirely out of fashion. Of course, come the information revolution any given civilization might find that more and more of its literature was being read in a digital format on whatever portable electronics they may invent, but the book never went away. It became a status symbol, a declaration of passion. Books were the physical embodiment of an interest in the archiving of knowledge and fiction, and there wasn’t a sapient race in the history of the galaxy, that Knadna knew of, that didn’t have a hard core of bibliophiles.

It was for this reason that there even were books in the building, and every single one had - with meticulous care - been entrusted to the most expensive, precise and sturdy cargo drone they had.

“Things are going well, it seems.” Lesry commented, looking sidelong at her, allowing a subtle hint of amusement to show. Knadna stopped rubbing her hands together and returned them to a more professional posture at her side.

“Yes. Quite well.” She agreed. She grabbed one of the newest books from the top and glanced at a page, taking in every feature of that page instantly. Her translation implant did the rest, decoding the OmoAru written language and converting it into useful concepts, remaining as faithful as possible to the linguistic subtleties it found.

“Cookbook.” she grunted, dismissively, and put the book back. “Thirty meals to help you keep a nice fat tail.”

“Look at this one.” Lesry said. “The top fifty holiday destinations in North UluUaba Province.” He turned a page. “Hmm. Actually this mineral mud spa sounds rather good.”

“An autobiography.” Knadna said, identifying her next one. “Contemporary with the start of the Decline, too. Potentially useful.”

Lesry was about to reach out for the next book when he paused, tilting his head slightly as if listening to something only he could hear.

“Ah. I think I shall have to leave you to catalogue these on your own.” he said. “You would think that simple instructions such as a cataloging system would be easier to follow for species capable of inventing space travel, wouldn’t you?”

“Hmm?” Knadna looked up from the book. “Oh. Yes. I’ll be quite happy here, thank you.”

She pretended not to notice the admiring way that Lesry looked at her before he left. Today was shaping up to be a good day.

Date Point: 4y 9m 1w 3d AV

Starship Sanctuary, Deep Space

Julian Etsicitty

“Ice cream? God, I don’t remember, I went without it for so long… I guess…Chocolate Fudge Brownie. Okay, uh…. hmm…. What was the first band you saw live?”

“Oh. Uh… I’ve never been to a live show.”

“What, never?”

“Nope. Maybe I should? Uh… Okay, did you have a pet growing up? I had a hamster called Mr. Mopes.”

Julian smiled. “Oh yeah. Sidhe. He was this huge black dog. Like, part labrador, part Dobermann, part… I don’t know, part tank. Mr Mopes?”

“Hamsters sleep a lot, right? But I was six, I thought he was just sulking, but he sulked all the time, so… yeah. Mr. Mopes."

“That’s adorable.”

Allison gave him a little playful punch, as she had done every time so far he used a word like “cute” “sweet” or “adorable” to describe her, and he was about to ask his next question when they were interrupted by an exclamation of “fuck’s sake, dude!”.

Lewis and Amir had taken over the common room couch to play a game of some kind. Superman and Green Arrow were beating the crap out of each other on the screen, with the surprising result that Green Arrow seemed to be winning, much to Amir’s dismay. That hadn’t been the cause of the outburst, though. The cause of the outburst had been Zane, wandering right across the screen and interrupting Lewis’ line of sight long enough for Amir to activate his special move and punch Green Arrow into orbit.

Zane just made an unconvincing noise that sounded like in somebody who cared it might have been an apology, and vanished in the direction of the galley.

“Fuuuck. That guy’s really starting to bug me.” Lewis complained.

“I hear ya.” Julian said. “Guy hasn’t said five words to me since he came aboard.”

“You’re not missing much.” Amir told them. “Every time he talks to me he’s checking up on whether our ETA has miraculously changed. It’s the only thing he’ll talk about, is finding this Shyoo person.”

“Xiu” Allison corrected him. “And yeah, that worries me. You said they only spent, like, a week on the same station, Lewis?”

“Eight days, total.” Lewis said, selecting Wonder Woman for their rematch. “She was there, he arrived, she left, he’s all like Xiu this Xiu that. Dude’s obsessed. ”

“That sounds like… trouble.” Allison said.

“Yeah, but what’re we gonna do? Let the trail go cold?” Julian asked. “We owe it to her to find her and bring her home, if that means we have to deal with whatever happened between her and Zane…”

Allison fidgeted with her hands a bit. “I guess…”

He lowered his voice to speak privately with her as the guys started their rematch. “What?”

“Just… There are some kinds of trouble that guys will never get into, Julian. They only ever cause it.”

He frowned. “You think…?”

“I pray to God not.” she interrupted. “Can we drop it? It’s a subject I don’t like talking about.”

He hesitated, then gave her a little squeeze, watching the game. “Favourite superhero?”

“…Iron Man, I guess. I dunno, I never really got into comic books, but I liked the movies… Hey you didn’t tell me yours…”

Date Point: 4y 9m 1w 3d AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Adam Ares

“You were her best friends. I think she’d want you to be involved.”

“I… know. and it means a lot to me that you’re asking but… y’know, I’m Catholic.” Ava said at last.

“I’m sure your God would understand, Ava.”

“I guess. But… this is Sara, she taught me so much. I can’t lie at her funeral. I can’t say words I don’t believe. I’m sorry."

Hayley Tisdale paused, then she nodded sadly and wiped away a tear. “You’re right. She wouldn’t want that.” she agreed. “Adam?”

He sighed. “I… look, I don’t know. I’m not sure I believe in anything any more.” he said at last. “So, I’m with Ava, I can’t do… this stuff here.” he tapped the printout they were going over. “but… I’d like to do this one here. If that’s okay?”

Hayley read it and smiled. “We were going to give that to Jack. But… yes. Please.”

“Thanks for asking us, Hayley.” Ava told her. “Really.”

She hugged them both and let herself out, leaving the pair of them to sit in silence for a bit.

“Did you mean that?” Ava asked. “About not believing any more?”

“It’s hard to.” Adam confessed.

“I know…” she sighed. “I just… I need this to all be happening for a reason, you know? I don’t think I could cope if there wasn’t a plan behind it all.”

He hugged her. “There’s something going on, I know that much.” he said.

“There is?”

“Oh yeah. There’s a pattern. Something behind it all. Mr. Johnson, back home, now Sara… it’s all connected, I just know it. I think my Dad’s in on it.”

“Are you gonna ask him?” She looked up. “I mean, I think he’d have told you by now if he could.”

“…Yeah. He would have.” Adam sighed. “But I’m still going to ask him. And if there is something going on, then I’m going to find out what.”

“How?”

He shrugged. “However I have to.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 1w 5d AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

“Legsy” Jones

“Intel package for you… sir…”

Anybody else might have said that Captain Powell’s office looked like a bomb had hit it. Legsy, being acutely aware of exactly what bomb damage actually looked like, tended not to use that phrase, but it would have very nearly been accurate.

The office doubled as Powell’s private space and sleeping area, and it was invariably pristine. One the one occasion that Legsy had seen Powell take his boots off, they had been lined up neatly under his camp bed with the laces tucked inside them. While the captain had once muttered a repetition of the old saw that any unit in battle-ready condition would fail inspection, he nevertheless was a stickler for keeping his own space immaculate.

Today was different. The filing cabinet was open, folders were strewn across the desk, the camp bed’s blankets were a bundle at the foot end, the captain’s kettlebells and weights were strewn across the floor rather than stacked, and a neglected ration pack on the table that had clearly been aborted halfway through preparation.

Powell himself was an even worse sight. He looked… rumpled. The skin around his eyes had gone dark, the eyes themselves were reddened, and he was sporting a fine crop of reddish and grey whiskers.

“On the desk.” he grunted, not glancing up from what he was reading. It looked like he was revising literally everything that Humanity knew about the Hierarchy.

That was hardly surprising. The captain had taken the girl’s death hard, harder than he let on. One of the obvious symptoms of that was obsession with her killers, though this was by far the worst case that Legsy had ever witnessed.

His terse response, however, was troubling. Only long experience of working with him had allowed Legsy to even tell the difference, but while Powell had never exactly been a cuddly personality, he was never usually rude or dismissive with his men. He’d gotten tougher since the girl died, demanding a full and complete inspection of every last detail of the rescue attempt, searching for anything that could have been done better.

Nobody wanted to be the one to voice the opinion to him that they’d done as well as humanly possible.

“Where on the desk, Captain?” He asked, unable to identify any spot that looked like it was more ready to receive the latest report than any other spot did.

“Fookin’ anywhere, do I look like I give a shit?" the captain growled.

“Yes sir.” Legsy put it down on top of what he hesitantly guessed might be the ‘in’ pile.

Powell didn’t react, just turning the page. He only glanced up when Legsy cleared his throat.

“Carry on.” he snapped.

“Sir… have you slept?” Legsy ventured

“I don’t see how that’s your fookin’ business, Jones.” Powell said, sharply. “You’re dismissed.”

Legsy saluted and turned for the door, deeply troubled, and then decided that he had a duty to perform.

He turned back. “Permission to speak candidly, captain?” he asked.

“Pretty fookin’ sure I dismissed you, Jones. So no, permission denied.”

That was a red alert.

Oh well. To borrow the motto of a sister unit: who dared, won. “I don’t fuckin’ care, sir, you’re gonna fuckin’ listen.” he announced.

The sheer audacity of it snapped the captain out of his revision and earned Legsy a trademarked Powell glare. “Look at this place!” he said, keeping the momentum up. “This isn’t like you sir, I’ve worked with you long enough to see there’s something fuckin’ wrong here. You’re not yourself.”

Powell lurched to his feet, face thunderous. “Sergeant Jones, if I have to order you out of my office again…” he began.

“Get yourself to counselling, sir!” Legsy told him. Powell froze, as shocked as if his subordinate had reached out and slapped him.

“I’m fookin’ fine." he asserted. “And YOU are this fookin’ close to-"

“Psych’s a wound like any other!” Legsy recited desperately, interrupting him. “You get it seen to just like you’d get a bullet seen. Your own words."

He swallowed, stiffened, and stared hard at the back wall. “Sir.”

There was a long, dangerous silence.

Finally, Powell spoke. He had always been a deep-voiced man - now the words practically rumbled out of him, as quiet and as full of smouldering danger as the voice of Vesuvius. “Sergeant Jones. I am ordering you to leave this office immediately. If you do not give me a perfect fookin’ salute and then fook off post fookin’ haste and without another fookin’ word, it will go fookin’ badly for you, am I crystal fookin’ clear?"

Legsy’s salute shook a little rain of dust from the ceiling, and he effected the speediest exit he had ever managed.

He just hoped that it would turn out to be worth it.

Date Point: 4y 9m 2w AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Gyotin

The central hall of the Faith Center had been cleared out - all the furniture, cushions, books, even the carpet had been rolled up and taken away, leaving behind bare floor which had been marked with an eight-pointed star of some kind.

Gyotin and his Brothers had elected to lurk in a corner, out of the way, and watch. Most of the humans seemed to be equally as uninformed as he was to the nature of this ceremony, which he found interesting. There was a lot of milling around and talking in quiet confusion, much of which centered on a small, overweight human female whose age-silvered head fur was long enough to reach her knees, about half of which had been tied back away from her face.

“So, is this their senior Mother or something?” Tagral asked.

Gyotin indicated not. “I don’t recognise her.” he said. “Besides, they don’t have a clan of females like we do.”

“Then who-?”

The question was interrupted by some angry, loud words being spoken on the opposite side of the room, which got louder and angrier as their speaker stormed towards the door, which had just admitted Captain Powell and his team into the room.

“How dare you?" The speaker was an older man, small and balding and looking positively tiny next to the soldiers, who all glanced at each other in dismay at being so accosted. “How dare you come here?! You FAILED her!"

He was the very picture of righteous indignation in any species’ body language, and the shocked expressions of so many of the other Deathworlders suggested that his accusation was not a widely shared one, but what struck Gyotin was the soldiers’ composure. They fidgeted and some of them looked ready to retort, but all it took as a slight turn of Powell’s head to quiet them instantly. Even the silver-haired elder who had been hurrying to soothe out the conflict paused.

It was Powell’s face that rooted Gyotin to the spot, however. On a human’s mobile and subtle features, the total absence of any expression whatsoever communicated volumes.

“…You’re right.” Powell said. His voice was deep, and soft, and emotional. “We did.”

He took a step forward, and the little man backed off. “Think about what that must feel like, and you’ll understand why we’re here.”

There was a general awkward clearing of throats and shuffling of feet as the soldiers took up a respectful position towards one side of the room, standing in a formal posture with their feet apart and their hands behind their backs.

Awkward silence descended again, finally broken by a syncopated drumming from outside the hall that got steadily louder, being joined by the high-pitched voice of some stringed instrument playing a lament. As the musicians crossed the threshold and stood playing on either side of the door, the soldiers snapped their feet together and removed their berets.

It was a small coffin, carried by only four people and laid solemnly on the table in the middle of the room as the music came to a gentle stop.

“Ladies and gentlemen…” the Elder began as the bearers retreated to positions around the room. “…as you may be aware, Sara’s family have requested that we remember her life in accordance with Pagan traditions. There should be nothing in what we are about to do that can cause offense to anyone, but if you would prefer to pay your respects now after your own fashion and then wait outside, we will take a few moments of silence for you to do so. I’m sure that Sara will not mind.”

A few of those present did exactly that, approaching to touch the box, or mutter words. The little man who had accosted the soldiers and a female of similar apparent age - his mate? - knelt stiffly and whispered for a little while, before standing and leaving, both weeping openly.

Once they had gone, the elder stepped forward again. “Thank you. You’ll find the order of the ceremony in the leaflets we handed out, but please do not feel pressured to participate if you don’t wish to. As one of Sara’s friends-” she nodded to Ava “put it so eloquently, we don’t think that Sara would want us to lie on her behalf.”

“And so… let us take a few deep breaths to prepare ourselves. Breathe deeply, and remember the love you have for Sara and the joy she brought you. And so we begin.”

She took a deep breath of her own, and raised her hands. “Let us call for peace, that in Peace the voice of the Spirit may be heard. May there be peace in the East! May there be peace in the South! May there be peace in the West! May there be peace in the North!”

Reading from the booklet, most of the mourners recited with her. “May there be peace throughout all the worlds.”

The Elder turned towards one of the points of the star on the ground. “Spirits of the East, Powers of Air, we call you. Bring us bright memories of our beloved Sara and of the laughter that surrounded her. Blessed be!”

As she turned through each of the cardinal directions, invoking in turn Fire, Water and Earth, Gyotin had to prod Tagral to get him to stop fidgeting, eventually having to deploy a claw to get his Brother to really quiet down and start showing some respect. He would be the first to admit that he himself didn’t understand what compass directions, air, water and so on had to do with anything, but whatever was going on, it seemed to be working for the humans.

Or at least, for most of them. The huge soldier, Legsy, was wiping water off his face every other second, as was almost everybody else in the room. In fact, there were only a pawful of dry eyes in the whole building, and they belonged to the Gaoians - unsurprisingly, for physical reasons - and to Adam and Ava who simply looked… tired? Gyotin had become adept at reading a human’s expressive face by now, and weariness seemed like the closest approximation he could think of for what theirs were showing.

The last dry face was Powell’s. His usually inscrutable mask was now a scowl, an expression of the most deep and deadly anger, directed at something that Gyotin was desperately glad he couldn’t see, and was infinitely more glad wasn’t him.

He was so busy watching the captain and speculating about what colossally stupid entity it was that had attracted such depth of ire that he completely missed the eulogies, and only returned his attention to the ceremony when the priestess started to speak again.

“O Great Spirit, Mother and Father of us all, we ask for your Blessings on this our ceremony of thanksgiving, and honouring and blessing of Sara. We stand at a Gateway now. A Gateway that each of us must step through at some time in our lives, and which Sara already passed.”

“Her soul is immersed in the shining light of the Unity that is the Mother and Father of us all. The sadness and pain that we feel now is in our knowledge and our experience of the fact that we ourselves cannot yet cross that threshold to be with her until our time has come. We do not weep for our beloved sister, for she is beyond all pain, all fear and all illusion. We weep instead for ourselves in the pain of our separation.”

“And so to ease that pain, let us all now spend some time in silence to remember Sara, to call her up in our minds and to speak to her in the private places of our heart and free ourselves of our burdens, saying to her all those things that we always wanted her to hear.”

This part was familiar to Gyotin. Silence. He filled it by stepping on Tagral’s foot when his Brother started fidgeting again.

The silence was broken some minute or two later by the priestess, who turned to the younger Ares. “Adam?”

Adam smiled weakly, nodded and swallowed, then stepped forward, turned to the coffin and read from the booklet, a little shakily.

“Did you know it was time to fly?” he asked. “I didn’t want to say goodbye. But… but we all know this is not the end… Fare-”

Finally the weariness broke, and he paused, bit on his lower lip and looked down, squeezing his eyes shut. Alone in the middle of the room, he sobbed once before finally managing to rally himself and continue.

“Farewell for now, my dear, dear, friend.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 2w AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Gabriel Ares

“Hey, Dad?”

Gabriel turned and smiled weakly at him. He had been watching the memorial stone being placed, a solid slab of blue slate imported from Earth and engraved.

"Sacred to the memory of a child of Earth,

And to all who shine with her among the stars."

“Hey.” He croaked.

“I have a question.”

Gabriel’s weak smile remained and he nodded, a little sadly. “Figured you would. You can see it, can’t you? The thread linking her and… all the others.”

“Yeah. And I’m guessing you can’t tell me the details.”

Gabriel nodded. “I’m sorry.”

“Don’t be. Just tell me what I need to do.”

“Adam…”

"I need to know, Dad. So tell me what I have to do. How do I earn it?"

Gabriel closed his eyes and nodded, then hugged his son as hard as he could. “Hey, amigo?"

“Yeah?”

“You’re a tougher man than I am. I’m not just proud of you, okay? I respect you.”

Adam softened just a little, and returned the hug. "Y yo tambien te respeto." he replied.

Gabriel nodded, then straightened, as much as he could around his faulty leg. “Go talk to Powell.” he said. “That’s how you start earning it.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Lesry

"Ooooh. Now that thing looks like a mover!"

Lesry had to admit that it did. If the black sphere which made up probably eighty percent of the craft’s mass was its power core, then even with an old- fashioned distorted-space Apparent Linear Velocity drive it would have been blindingly fast. Lesry, however, had a few of the high-end firmware upgrades to the implants in his optic nerves that were available only to ranking Directorate scientists, and they were reporting that the ship had one of the Blackbox engines.

Which meant, at a very rough mental calculation, that he may well be looking at the fastest vessel in the galaxy.

The few rather more refined calculations that he bounced off his cerebral coprocessors confirmed that he almost certainly was.

It landed easily enough, settling down to thrum gently on forcefields as it finished its descent level with the same bridge that his own History Paradox was parked upon, extending a gangplank to link the laughably small amount of ship that wasn’t power core to the shore.

“Somebody unusual visiting us.” He said. “Look busy! If I’m impressed I might throw in a small bonus.”

That one never failed to get the hired workers motivated, and they threw themselves into the cataloging and loading as he tucked his thumbs into the belt of his sand-robes and took his time wandering over to the end of the arriving ship’s gangplank.

He wasn’t expecting the human who strode down it with an expression that promised serious pain to anything in his way, nor the two other (rather paler) ones who followed after him shouting what was presumably his name.

Nor was he expecting one of the most famous beings in the galaxy behind them.

“Well! Councillor A’ktnnzzik’tk! You have a talent for making an entrance!” he observed, having to raise his voice to compete with the untranslated barking sounds the humans were making at each other.

A’ktnnzzik’tk produced an old-fashioned translation device from a satchel and held it idly in one of his stronger hands as he finished crossing the bridge. “Not by choice.” he said. “May I take it that I’m addressing the leader of this expedition? Thank you for meeting me in person.”

“Co-leader.” Lesry admitted, both intrigued by A’ktnnzzik’tk’s apparent lack of a translator implant and pleased by his manners. “Had I known one of the more… hmm… notorious politicians was coming, I would have torn my colleague Knadna away from her research as well, and believe me, that’s not a risk that a sane being would take lightly."

A’ktnnzzik’tk chuckled deep in his lanky throat. “I’m retired now. This is a personal project.” he said.

“Collecting Deathworlders? Most beings start smaller, with Gricka, or perhaps a pet Vulza.”

“It’s an entertaining hobby. I recommend it.”

Lesry allowed himself the luxury of a stab of amusement. “Well, the most we have here is an unaccountably sturdy Gaoian who wears concealing robes.” he said. “She’s our chef. I do hope she doesn’t turn out to be a human in disguise or something tiresome like that, this expedition will be far less pleasant without her culinary talents.”

A’ktnnzzik’tk blinked at him. “Information so freely volunteered?” he asked. “My thanks.”

“I suspect that you would have found her more or less instantly anyway.” Lesry said, and inclined his head towards 'Shoo’. “After all, she is brandishing a knife at that dark-skinned human you brought with you…”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Xiu

"You stay the hell away from me, Zane!"

He started to babble at him in that same dense Patois and Xiu’s temper eroded even further. "Shut up! Shut up and fuck off!" she screamed.

The blonde woman - and oh God was Xiu happy to see a fellow female - stepped forward and said something a little too quietly for Xiu to catch, but it did the trick. He paused, then stepped backwards, eyes still fixed on her, then spat in the dirt, spun and stalked off between the scattering aliens.

The blonde woman exhaled, then turned to her. “Xiu Chang, I presume.” she said. It was so weird hearing somebody pronounce her name correctly.

Xiu put the knife down. “Uh… hi.” she said. It wasn’t what she’d imagined saying when she finally got back in touch with the human race - the real human race, not Zane - but then again nothing in the last four years or so had gone like she had imagined, so why should greetings?

“You’ve got to be sweltering in that disguise.” said another voice, a male one, from slightly behind her. She grabbed the knife and spun, prompting the man who had snuck up on her to back off, raising his hands defensively. “Woah, woah!” he protested. “Easy!”

Xiu lowered the knife, cautiously. This one was hot. Okay, she’d thought the same thing about Zane when they had first met, but this guy…

She shook it off. Handsome didn’t mean trustworthy. Nor did female, come to think of it, but…

But if she was ever going to get home, she’d have to trust somebody a little, wouldn’t she?

She put the knife down again, and Mr. Handsome nodded and circled around to join Blonde Girl. “Just making sure you didn’t stab him.” he said.

That didn’t exactly endear him to Xiu, but she understood. "Sho wia yu, uwa wa me Xiu." she said.

That earned her a pair of blank looks, until she realised that she’d spoken in Gaoian rather than English. “Uh… yes. Yes, my name’s Xiu.” she said. “Sorry, it’s been… since I last…”

“Five years? Not counting that guy?” The blonde said, smiling. “It’s okay, I understand. My name’s Allison. This is Julian.”

Xiu blinked. “I… had a friend called Allison.” she said. “Back on Earth.”

That detail seemed more relevant in her head than it did in the conversation, but she really was out of her depth here.

“Would you like to see her again?” this Allison asked her.

“I…” Xiu looked at the ship they had arrived in, and it finally hit her.

A ship. They had a ship. And these were humans, from Earth. Who had come here in that ship. From Earth.

Suddenly, she couldn’t see a thing through the tears.

They had a ship.

She could go home.

__

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Adam Ares

" ’Eeey, Adam!"

Legsy always had a friendly manner about him, which Adam liked. He’d shown plenty of intensity while training the militia, but outside of that role, Legsy was pure earthy charm and humor. It made militia training a charm, and while a lot of the colonists preferred not to use the gym at the same time as the soldiers, Adam found he really didn’t mind being outperformed by them. They served as examples of what he might one day be able to manage himself.

It also meant that he and Legsy practically had the gym to themselves, which was perfect for what he had in mind.

“Hey Legs.”

Adam watched the older man swing his kettlebell around. Legsy trained for endurance, and while Adam had seen people like Mark Tisdale working with more impressive weights, Legsy could apparently go all day, working his way steadily up and down through the set until he was red and reflective with sweat, but never seeming to tire.

Adam himself was still working up to that. He elected to use the cross-trainer instead. Legsy gave him an encouraging grin and nod as the device swirled into action.

“So uh… I’ve got a question.” Adam asked, after what he judged was a decent interval.

“Go for it, pal.”

“What the hell is going on?”

“…How d’you mean?”

“Home, Sara… how come they’re not pressing charges? There’s a pattern there, I can see it.”

Legsy didn’t answer at first, just continued to swing his weight, but his expression had clamped down beautifully.

“Yeah, I reckon you can.” he decided. “I can’t tell you though.”

“No, I know.” Adam agreed. “but Dad said if I want to know what’s going on then I need to talk to Captain Powell.”

Legsy really was an open book - he had so many different blank expressions. This one said that there was something serious going on with Powell at the moment that he, Legsy, was not comfortable discussing.

“I’d give him a few days.” he said at last. “It’s rough on an officer when an op he commanded ends that way, right? He gave me a bit of a row the other day.”

“Did you deserve it?” Adam asked. Legsy laughed, but his heart wasn’t as in it as it usually was.

“Maybe. He was tampin’.” he said, using a Welshism that Adam had deduced meant something like ‘furious’. “I’d give it a few days, butt. Let him simmer down, I’ll get you in to see him when the time’s right. Fair?”

“Thanks, Legs.”

“No worries, pal. Now come on, I know you can go faster than that!”

Adam quickened his pace and settled his mind, enjoying the heat building in his muscles.

He felt like he’d just set his first foot out the door on a journey.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Starship Sanctuary, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Allison Buehler

“What do you think?”

Xiu had been introduced to a vacant room - on the opposite side of the ship from Zane’s, and next door to Allison’s, and was, from the sound of it, busy taxing the abilities of Sanctuary’s water recycler with a hot shower. Julian and Allison were, by mutual unspoken agreement, hanging out at the junction down the deck where they could make sure Zane didn’t try to get at her, be on hand should she need them, and converse unheard.

“About… what, now?” Julian asked. “About Xiu herself, or about whatever went down between her and Zane?”

“Xiu herself, for now.”

Julian thought about it. “At first glance, I was thinking 'damaged goods’." he confessed, and pressed on when Allison made a “hmm” noise and nodded.

“But here’s the thing, though.” he said. “She’s in great shape. She’s kept up her exercise and ate right, and that puts her a cut above most everyone else out here. Physically, she’s perfectly fine, give or take a few scars. Mentally? I dunno, what does five years alone with nobody but raccoon people to talk to do? She was nineteen when she was abducted. Then there’s the…” he checked to make sure nobody was listening, then lowered his voice anyway even though none were. “the Hunters. And the nervejam.”

“Yeah, I read her file.” Allison agreed. “She saved a whole starship! Took on one of the big Hunter ships solo! That’s… shit, that’s big damn hero stuff." she frowned at him. “But, you’re one to talk. What does six years alone with nobody but trees to talk to do?”

“It fucks with your head.” Julian said, honestly.

“You’ve always seemed… fine to me.”

“We’ve not slept together yet.”

“You mean actual sleep, right?”

“Yeah. Can’t even do it without an axe next to my hand.” Julian told her. “And I wake up at the slightest noise, reaching for it. Do you snore?”

Allison shook her head. “I don’t think so. Why?”

“Lewis does. That’s why I moved away from his room. I kept thinking there was a Murderpig near my camp.”

“Murderpig?”

“This big.” Julian held out a hand at rib height. “This long.” He stretched his arms as wide as they would go. “Teeth like this." he drew one of his knives “and it hates you. Murderpig.” He put the knife back in its sheath.

“You came up against shit like that?”

“Yeah. Lucky for me, it’s all nose with a Murderpig. Their eyesight’s fucking awful and they snore when they breathe, like a fat guy asleep on the bus. Getting the drop on them’s easy. Good eating on them too. But if there was one near the camp I needed to be up and armed like that." he snapped his fingers.

“What happened if you didn’t?”

“I never didn’t. If I ever hadn’t, then we’d never have met.”

“Oh. Damn, Julian.”

“Eh, it was only for like four months out of the year. Rest of the time, Nightmare was nice and quiet. I used to- hey, she’s done.”

Xiu had poked her head out of her room, wearing a towel and a blush. “Uh… hey, are my new clothes ready?” She asked. “I just realised how nasty these robes are…”

“I’ll go check.” Julian told her, and trotted down the stairs.

Allison turned to talk with Xiu, and noticed that their recent rescue was watching Julian with catlike fascination as he went, her blush deepening and spreading to her ears. Allison couldn’t blame her - Julian had an amazing ass - but that couldn’t be allowed. “Sorry, girlfriend. I’m not into sharing.” she said, not unkindly.

“Uh…” Xiu blinked, then coughed. “Sorry. You guys are…?”

“We’re…. yeah. We are. How are you feeling?"

“Clean!” Xiu said, rebounding. “I mean, my own actual shower. With real shampoo! And conditioner!"

Allison laughed. “Hah! With hair like yours, I can see why you’d miss those.” she said. “Don’t expect miracles with the clothes, though. It’s all practical stuff, not decorative.” She grinned. “Unless you can rock a pair of yoga pants.”

“If it fits properly and breathes, I’ll be happy.” Xiu promised. “And we’ll be going back to Earth soon, right?”

“We don’t need to. All we need to do is get to a station with an FTL relay and schedule an Array send with Scotch Creek.”

“Huh?”

Allison paused. “Okay, so, I’m not exactly Miss Technobabble.” she said. “But… did you ever see this old TV show, Stargate?"

“Sure. My brother Wei brought all the DVDs on eBay.”

“Well, we’ve kinda got one of those downstairs.” Allison said. “but, like, less dramatic. It’s called a Jump Array. Neat piece of kit!”

Xiu gaped at her. “Wait, so… you could send me home right now?" she asked.

“Not right now, no. We need to get to a station with an FTL relay, send a message to Earth via Cimbrean, wait for-”

“Where?”

“Cimbrean. Humanity’s first colony world. You didn’t hear about it?”

Xiu made a strange ducking motion with her head, then blinked and carefully shrugged while shaking her head, as if remembering the gesture. “I… didn’t really pay attention to the news.” she confessed. “It just got me down. There’s not much about humans in the news, and it’s never good when there is.”

“Yeah?”

“It was always about how we would bring the Hunters down on them and get them all killed.” she elaborated. “But how does this Cimbrean place protect itself?”

Allison grinned. “You know that big forcefield protecting Earth?”

"Protecting it?"

“Yeah! It sure as hell isn’t containing us, but it’s stopping the bad guys from getting in. Anyway, Julian stole one.”

Xiu blinked. "That Julian?" she asked, pointing after him.

“Yep. Actually, he stole two.”

“Wow. So, uh, where’s the other one?”

“Kirk won’t say.”

Xiu sighed. “So we need to send a message to Earth.”

“Via Cimbrean. And then we have to wait for them to get back to us and say 'Sure, send on this date at this time using this code' and then… bam! You’ll be back in Canada."

“Just like that?”

“Unless you decide to stay, yeah.” Allison told her.

“Why would I want to stay out here?”

“Why would you want to go back?” Allison retorted.

“Wh-? It’s home!" Xiu said.

Allison nodded, a little sadly. “That’s fine. And if that’s what matters to you… Sorry, I shouldn’t have even mentioned it, it’d just be nice to have another girl on board.”

“I guess…” Xiu said. “but… I had my dreams. I was going to be an actress. I still could be, if I go home now.”

Allison kept to herself the fact that Xiu was going to need a lot of post- production and makeup to cover all the scars she seemed to have picked up during her time away from home. There were a lot of them. The ragged tears down her forearm were the largest and most disfiguring, but the one that kept drawing Allison’s attention was a little raised inch-long mark on Xiu’s neck, dangerously close to her carotid artery.

She was spared the discomfort of the conversation tailing off by Julian’s return, as he handed across the clothes the nanofactory had printed to Xiu’s measurements - four simple black sports t-shirts, two equally simple navy blue fatigues, four changes of undecorated but comfortable underwear, a dark grey fleece sweater , four pairs of thick socks and a pair of hiking boots.

“Here you go.” he said, handing them over. “Not exactly red carpet stuff, but it’s warm and comfortable and you can clean them real easy. Just rinse ’em and hang ’em up. Lewis can show you how to program the nanofac later if you want a bit of variety.”

Xiu took them gratefully. “Thanks.”

“So you want to be an actress?” Allison called through her door after she had shut it.

“Yeah! That’s why I took up Gung Fu, I wanted to be in martial arts movies!" Xiu called back.

“Not drama or anything?”

This was met with a bitter "Hah!" from behind the door. “Have you ever heard of a Chinese version of Downton Abbey?" she asked.

“Not in America.” Allison confessed.

“Exactly. Hey, these are a good fit!”

“Lewis figured out how to lift your measurements from the biofilter field.” Julian said. “Bespoke tailored printed clothing. Neat, ain’t it?”

“Do they have stuff like this back on Earth now?” Xiu asked

“Not yet. I mean, four years and change isn’t that long anyway, and this is alien technology.”

Xiu opened the door so she could finish talking to them unimpeded as she pulled on her boots. “Yeah, but… we’ve got spaceships and a colony and stuff now.” she said.

“I think a lot of what comes out of Scotch Creek is just copying and pasting.” Julian confessed. “We’ve been bit in the ass a few times by now, especially with the first-generation translator implants and what happened to San Diego.”

Xiu stood up from tying her laces, frowning. “Why?” She asked. “What happened to San Diego?”

“…Ah.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Starship Sanctuary, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Lewis

“Hey, Amir?”

“Yes?”

“Whaddya think went down with Xiu and Zane, anyhow?”

Amir sighed and set aside his checklist. Self-maintaining and robust though Sanctuary’s systems were, he felt safer for manually checking them while landed.

“Why the fascination?” he asked. “It seems cut and dried to me.”

“You think?”

“I knew men like Zane back in Birmingham.” Amir said. “All ego, very intense. Charming, if they liked you, but if you irritated them…”

“You did?”

“Sure.” Amir replied. “My cousin was married to such a man.”

Lewis nodded sagely. “Good looking dude turned on the charm, huh? Got her wrapped around his finger before he turned it off again?”

“Sort of. Arranged marriages didn’t go away just because my grandparents left Pakistan, you know. They just brought them to England.”

“Wait, shit, your cousin had to marry some dude?” Lewis protested. “That’s not cool!”

“She didn’t have to." Amir corrected him. “That would be forced marriage. But the marriage was arranged between his parents and my uncle and she…” He coughed. “Well, she didn’t think too hard about it.”

“Were you cool with that?”

“Oh, it happened after my abduction. I had the pleasure of meeting the husband after getting back. I didn’t like him. And Maleeha was a different person to what I remembered, very subdued. I’m sure she even flinched a little bit when he raised his voice.”

“So, not cool with it then?”

Amir sighed. “It’s… a good arrangement.” he said. “He’s a dentist, she cooks, cleans, looks after the three children… a traditional marriage. Her parents are very happy."

“So, you’re not cool with it, then."

“…She was sixteen.” Amir admitted.

“Ah. Shit, is that even legal?”

“Oh, yes. Perfectly legal.” Amir said. “English law only requires parental consent for sixteen year olds, even if the husband is more like thirty.”

“Damn…”

“I get the same vibe off Zane as I do off my cousin’s husband. ” Amir said. “That same… Pride. Is there anything in his file?”

“Lemme check…” Lewis said, followed seconds later by: “Huh… Hey, Kirk encrypted it.”

“He what?”

“Yeah. Locked this shit down tight, too. No breaking it, no way no how.”

“How do you know it was him?”

Lewis gave him a tired 'please' look. “I’m the only other dude on this boat who could, and I didn’t.”

Amir got out of the flight chair and went to look over Lewis’ shoulder. “Why would he encrypt Zane’s file?”

“I’m gonna ask him.” Lewis said. “Worst case, he says he’s not telling us.”

“Go for it.”

Kirk responded to Lewis’ summons a few minutes later. “Something come up?” he asked.

“Sort of.” Amir said. “You encrypted Zane’s file?”

“It seemed like a good idea.” Kirk replied. “I didn’t want people to read it and become prejudiced against him. This is supposed to be welcoming ship.”

“Like, uh, why would we be prejudiced?” Lewis asked.

Kirk made the noise that was his species’ version of a resigned sigh. “The Corti experiments of the last fifty years or so were beginning to focus on human weaknesses.” he revealed. “Genetic disorders, mutations, personality disorders, mental illness…”

“So our Zane’s got a… maybe a personality disorder of some kind?” Amir asked.

“I’m not saying. I don’t want to exacerbate the friction between him and Xiu by prejudicing the rest of you against him.”

“All well and good, but if he’s dangerous…”

“You’re proving my case.” Kirk pointed out. “You all took an instant disliking to him. That’s acceptable, I don’t much like him either. But he still deserves his privacy and unbiased treatment. He’s not actually done anything other than be unpleasant."

Lewis and Amir shared looks that mutually said 'He’s got a point’.

“Alright, cool. You’ve got a strong argument there, boss.” Lewis finally admitted.

“Thank you. Where is Zane right now, anyway?"

Lewis ran a search script. “Not aboard. Last seen… like, ten seconds after we landed…”

He tapped again. “Neither’s Vedreg.” he added.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

The Tisdale house was a mess. Ava couldn’t blame them, in fact she knew exactly how they felt. After the bomb which killed her parents, it had taken weeks before she began to notice things like mess, rumpled clothing and the state of her hair again. The first night she had run a brush through it had been a painful one both physically and emotionally, extracting a tangle that had been well on its way to becoming a dreadlock.

Doctor Hayley Tisdale at least was fortunate enough to have straight hair, which would help there. But she was still a mess when she opened the door, wearing food-stained pajamas and red eyes.

“Ava?”

Ava lifted the box she was holding. “I… Gabriel was able to get Sara’s stuff back from the military…”

Hayley stared at the box like it was simultaneously the most beautiful and the terrifying thing in all creation.

“Oh…”

“Can I come in?”

Hayley nodded quietly and stepped inside.

The clutter about the place was just… stuff. Things that had been left where they were no longer useful: clothes, mugs… a few bowls and plates, but not many. They weren’t eating much. Ava knew how that felt - you just weren’t interested. You’d grab books then discard them, pick things up just to put them down again.

There were a lot of wine glasses around though and the house reeked of alcohol, plus another scent that she hadn’t smelled since high school back in California. She didn’t know how that one felt. Ava didn’t know how they had even managed to get cannabis on Cimbrean, but she wasn’t about to comment. The smell was stale, as if they hadn’t indulged for some time.

Hayley swept aside an arrangement of small crystals and semiprecious stones on the table to make room for the box.

Sara hadn’t had much on her when she died, and her bloodstained clothing had tactfully been omitted. What was left was a tiny assortment of jewelry - Sara had been addicted to rings, and had always worn her birthstone, an Emerald, as a necklace. There were a trio of the same kind of crystals that her mother had just swept aside, her phone, spare batteries and a MicroSD card for her camera, and the camera itself.

Hayley didn’t say a word, she just picked up the camera with trembling hands, turned it on after a second’s investigation to figure out how it worked, and started to scroll through the pictures her daughter had taken.

Ava grabbed a brush and gently started to sort out the worst of Hayley’s hair, watching the screen herself.

It was a catalog of the changing face of Folctha, playing backwards. Brown dirt, tree stumps and grey construction sites gave way to a bloom of life here and there. Sara had been gifted with an eye for finding beauty, and for showing it off to its best advantage, finding the little flowering plants that were still struggling gamely against the Deathworld invasion, or the forester, whose high-vis jacket and yellow hard-hat practically shone against the lifeless stack of felled logs he was leaning against.

Things got greener, more alive, and Sara had continued to pick out whatever was *most *alive in each scene. A cloud of little iridescent shimmerflies. A creature that lived somewhere halfway between squirrel and lizard, stuffing nuts into a pouch on its back. The curve of Ava’s own naked back, the little hairs and the bumps of her vertebrae luminous with the light of a setting sun that was framed by her coiled lock of wet hair. She hadn’t even noticed Sara take that picture.

There were no pictures of Sara herself, though. She had only ever used the camera to record what happened around her, never turned it on herself.

Finally, Hayley set the device aside with a sigh. “I still… I don’t believe it.” she confessed.

“I know.” Ava replied.

“How do you cope? How do I…? I think the only thing that keeps me going is that I’ve still got Jack to look after.”

Ava’s brush never stopped, but the rest of her did, for a second. “I think… I think you just have to keep the people you’ve lost alive.” she said. “Live for them. Carry on their work.”

“Have you?” Hayley asked. “You lost your parents, do you think you’re keeping them alive?”

“I hope so.” Ava said. “I try to be somebody they’d be proud of. I tried to get better and move forward because… I guess because I knew it’d hurt them to see me in pain.”

“D’you think Sara…?” Hayley aborted the question, half-formed. Ava gave her a little hug.

“She loved you both.” She told Hayley. “She talked about you a lot, about the things you said, about what you taught her.”

“She did?”

“Oh yeah.” Ava laughed slightly. “It was hard to get her to stop.”

That prompted a miserable laugh from Hayley too. “She always was a motor mouth…”

Ava smiled, and put the brush down. With the tangles gone and some of her hair’s shine restored, Hayley was already looking much improved. Hopefully, she’d see that in a mirror and it would help her, just a little. It had for Ava.

Hayley picked up the camera, and then unexpectedly she turned and handed it to Ava. “Keep it.” she said.

“Me? I…”

“Please? It’s… a way to keep her alive.”

Ava took the little black device nervously. “Are you sure?”

Hayley nodded, and then gave Ava a kiss on the forehead. “Honey.” she said. “You’re a wiser girl than I am. Maybe you can…”

She trailed off, then just looked down and shook her head. “Just take it. Please? I think she’d want you to have it. It just feels right. Carry on her work."

Ava considered the picture on the screen at that moment - Cimbrean sunlight, somehow turning the industrial devastation around Folctha pretty just by being framed a certain way - and doubted that she was up to the job.

But she had been wondering where to take her life, now that movie makeup wasn’t an option. Maybe…

Maybe…

“I’ll… thank you, Hayley.” she said.

She meant it.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Starship Sanctuary, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Xiu

Hitting something felt good. Gung Fu was a martial art after all, and while practicing the movements had (she hoped) allowed Xiu to keep her form, you could repeat the bao hu gui shan all day but it couldn’t duplicate the feeling and experience gained from landing actual physical blows. The best way to practice punching was… well, to punch something.

The fact that it was cathartic had nothing to do with it. Really: Nothing.

The Sanctuary’s punchbag was therefore getting the most brutal workout of its existence. While the Gaoians could easily have built one for her, she had never asked for one. It would just have been too embarrassing to break the first few, and too… impolite to flaunt just how much stronger she was than them by doing so to a bag it would have taken three of them to lift.

Now, though, she could feel just how long it had really been since she had last received proper guidance in her form. Her wrists and forearms hurt, and in the first few minutes she threw a few strikes where she misjudged the distance and either punched the air just short of the bag’s surface, or else overextended herself striking a point somewhere inside it. She wasn’t off by much, but she was still off, she could tell.

She only finally ended her workout once she was satisfied that she had restored some of her muscle memory and that her form had healed a bit, by which point she had spent nearly an hour focused on that one task, giving her brain time to process the news about San Diego and the devastation that its destruction had wrought on the entire Pacific coast. Nobody had been directly hurt in Vancouver thank goodness, but the ash from Mt. Rainier’s sympathetic eruption, caught by a prevailing wind from the desert, had dusted across British Columbia and even reached as far as Alaska, causing respiratory distress, clogging air filters and lightly polluting the water across thousands of square miles.

She hoped that it hadn’t set off Wei’s asthma.

Julian and Allison had admitted to both knowing the specifics of what had happened, but had also said that, so long as Xiu intended to leave the ship and return home, they weren’t in any kind of a position to discuss it. It was a mystery, but one that Xiu would happily forego illumination of for the sake of going home.

As for all the dead…

Well, it didn’t register. It wasn’t that it didn’t seem real, they had shown her the footage and news reports, too many and varied to be fake. It was definitely real. But it was also abstract. She didn’t even know what two million living people looked like, let alone two million dead. The mind simply couldn’t get a grasp on ideas that big.

She jogged a few laps around the gym to warm down, then collected her boots and headed upstairs, wondering what kind of food they had on board. The clothing she’d been given was really impressive, made of some high-tech performance textile that had kept her cool and dry and not noticeably aromatic. And it was made by humans, for humans, understanding human needs. Luxury! With luck, the galley would be similarly impressive.

Upstairs, however, the crew were talking quietly and their expressions were worried. When she entered, Allison stopped speaking mid-sentence and gave her a gently apologetic smile that said that while she, Allison, was glad to see her, Xiu had managed to arrive at an inopportune moment.

“Is everything alright?” Xiu asked.

“Sunset was half an hour ago, and we’ve not seen Zane since you came aboard.” Kirk told her. She hadn’t had the opportunity to get to know the tall white being, yet. It wasn’t that he had ignored her, but he seemed to be extremely busy with something or other and had given her only a polite welcome aboard and his assurance that they would become acquainted later on, if she liked.

“Pff, Zane? Leave him behind.” Xiu said. It came out as more of a snap than she had intended, but she had to stop her hand from touching the mark on her throat.

“Even if I were inclined to do so-” Kirk said, making it very plain that he wasn’t, “we just found out that Vedreg isn’t aboard either.”

“Vedreg?”

“You ever met a Guvnugundragonbunny?” Lewis asked.

“Oh! You have a…?” Xiu asked, ignoring Kirk as he tried to correct Lewis. “I didn’t see them…”

“He went straight into the city when we landed. Said that he was testing a theory.” Amir revealed. “You were too busy waving knives at Zane and Julian to notice.”

Xiu blushed. “Julian snuck up on me! And Zane…” she paused.

“Is missing.” Kirk reminded them.

“Well, what do we do?” Julian asked.

“We search for him.” Kirk said. “Julian, you and Amir can sweep the north quadrant. Allison, you and Lewis take the east. Miss Chang-”

“No.” Xiu folded her arms.

Kirk blinked. “I see…” he said. “Not to press the issue, but I understand that you’re rather physically formidable yourself and…”

"No."

There was silence as everyone glanced back and forth at one another, which Lewis broke by clearing his throat. “Uh… Hey, the hell happened with you two?”.

“That’s between me and Zane.” Xiu told him. “If you need me I’ll come running, but that…” She shook her head. “Just… No.”

Kirk lowered his head, exhaling slowly. “I can see that is the end of it. Very well, Amir, if you could accompany me instead?”

Amir finally stopped giving Xiu a calculating stare and nodded. “Okay.” He agreed, though reluctantly.

Allison stood. “Sooner we get moving…” she said.

“I’ll… be in my room.” Xiu said.

She held it together until the door was closed and locked behind her before the shakes started.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Classified Facility, Earth

“Steve”

“Shitty luck. You got that right.” somebody said as he entered.

Steve sighed and grabbed a coffee. “It was a fucking understatement.” he replied.

Christof Lehmann - the poor bastard who’d been puppeted into shooting a girl on Cimbrean - had not taken the explanation of his situation well. There had been shouting, there had been crying. Both had been easier to bear than the dreadful, broken silence.

“I think it’s pretty clear he needs to be on the suicide watchlist.” Carl said.

“Pretty clear, yeah. Fella looks like he took a dump and found his liver in the bowl.”

“Give the man some respect, Simmons. News like that’d be rough on anybody.”

“Sorry, Boss.”

Boss nodded. “Guess he’s headed to Alaska then.”

“Oh yes.” Steve said. “That implant the Corti shoved in him may have cured his epilepsy, but it’s too deep and invasive to remove. He’d be a lobotomised vegetable once the surgeons were done, assuming he even lived through the operation.”

“Then there’s his reputation.” Simmons pointed out. “Poor bastard was used to murder a little girl. No way to explain that one to the public without ruining him or blowing the lid on the Hierarchy.”

Boss shifted in his seat. “I’m going to be advising the director that we can’t keep that particular secret much longer.” he drawled. His Georgia accent always got stronger when he was feeling emotional, thought that was the most sign he gave. “There’s too much pressure now. The seizure all the people with translators had, San Diego, now this… the Internet’s already working overtime.”

“Isn’t there some plausible deniability, there?” Balistreri had always fallen comfortably into the role of devil’s advocate. She wasn’t actually an argumentative woman by nature, but she had a knack for spotting the alternatives and presenting them. “If the story leaks then we can just claim too much time spent listening to the Internet conspiracy theorists.”

“Nope. Only a matter of time before Herr Lehmann gets his case taken up by a journalist or a human rights lawyer. The cat’ll be out of the bag before long, you mark my words. But if we let it out ourselves, then the details of Operation Exorcist can remain secret.”

“You’re the boss, Boss.”

“Yep.”

“What happens if the Hierarchy do panic and step up their plans?"

“At least we’ll have taken the initiative.” Carl said. “Rather than playing catchup.”

“Best we can do.” Boss agreed. “Alright folks, get some rest, do your paperwork, whatever, I’ll see y’all when I get back from DC.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Allison Buehler

If there was one thing Lewis was terrible at, it was taking a hint once he was fixated on a train of thought. “Seriously though, what do you think? ’d he rape her or something?”

“She doesn’t want to say and that’s the end of it.” Allison told him.

It was cold in the desert at night. She’d known that, but still hadn’t quite registered that the temperature would be in freefall within minutes of sunset. She was almost mentally counting down until the first fog started to appear on her breath.

It didn’t help that the deserted city had an eerie, unsettling quality to it. If the place had been truly abandoned - plants growing all over everything, walls falling down, that kind of thing - then it wouldn’t have been so bad, but the place was still slightly alive, thanks to the automated maintenance and civil engineering systems that the OmoAru had laced through the ancient conurbation at the height of their power. Everything was still clean, still standing. Just… empty. It was almost like walking through her own home city of Phoenix, except that the road signs were alien, the proportions wrong, and the silence…

It was cloying. It stuck to everything. The desert breeze and the hiss of sand only seemed to amplify the silence, rather than dispel it, and when occasional little animals or robots moved around in the dark, it set every ancient monkey danger instinct in her body off.

She’d always hated the dark.

“You gotta speculate though, right?” Lewis persisted.

Allison stopped and grabbed his arm, hard, prompting a wince and a noise of complaint. “Lewis: Shut. Up.”

She let go and listened, ignoring Lewis as he rubbed his arm and made irritated subvocalizations.

There was definitely noise and a glow coming from a nearby building

“Zane? That you?” She called, grateful for a chance to have something other than Lewis’ insensitive speculation to break the silence.

It wasn’t Zane. Instead, an OmoAru shuffled out into the street, raising a glowing white stick.

Aliens came in all shapes and varieties, and the temptation was always there to compare them to mixtures of human species back on Earth. Blue giraffes, white zebra-giraffes, raccoon persons and so on. It was always an unfair and inaccurate comparison - they were their own species, the products of evolution that had nothing to do with Earth - but comparisons with leopard geckos and big-eared bats sprang to mind anyway when considering an OmoAru.

This one was about twice Allison’s height and shrouded in robes against both the sand and the cold night air. Its skin - dry, tough and scaly - was the colour of the desert, mottled here and there with patterns of a surprising turquoise and ochre hue that became thicker and more vivid around the base of its huge furry ears. The tufted end of its tail ticked back and forth behind its back, folding over into a question mark.

"UmUa WenUatu WoUem WioYuwu?" It asked.

“Bah wheep grahnah wheep nini bong, man.” Lewis replied amicably, and offered the alien a Vulcan salute for good measure. Allison rolled her eyes and put a hand over her mouth to cover her smile.

"WumuaAmo SuOumu?"

“Sure dude. Whatever… Guess there’s no point in asking if you saw a big black dude who talks even weirder than you go past, huh?”

"Huh?"

“Huh. Guess ‘huh’ is a universal, huh?”

"Huh." The alien disappeared into the building again.

“Lewis, you’ve got a talent for communication there.” Allison quipped.

The sentence was barely out of her mouth when the OmoAru returned and handed Lewis a little dull grey metal ball about the size of an apple.

“Huh?”

"Huh!" The tail lashed and its ears perked up. Allison got the distinct impression that a human would have been nodding vigorously and smiling.

“…Oh! Huh! Well thank you very much, my man."

"WemUei!" the alien agreed.

“Ming mang mong, dude.” Lewis told it.

Allison watched the alien return, apparently happily, to its domicile “…the fuck?”

“Hell if I know.” Lewis said, pocketing the gift. “Nice guy, though.”

“What do you think that thing is?”

“You heard the dude. It’s a huh."

“Lewis…”

“Well how the fuck am I supposed to know? Could be the dude’s car keys, could be his porn stash, could be his grandma’s ashes.”

Allison sighed. “Okay, okay…”

She raised her torch and looked down the street, expecting and receiving no sign of any living thing beyond the pool of light where the giver of the Huh was living.

“No sign of anything where we’re at, Kirk.” she said, activating the contact microphone by pressing lightly on it where it was stuck to her throat.

"I was just about to let you know: we found them." Kirk replied.

“You did?”

"Both of them, yes. Vedreg believes that he may have uncovered a breakthrough in the mystery of elder species decline."

“He has?”

Vedreg’s simulated voice - the translators always rendered him with a gentle Received Pronunciation accent for some reason - came on the line. "Oh yes. Do you see the large, lit building at the apex of the oxbow lake?"

Allison looked around. It was hard to miss in the dark. “Sure. You’re there?”

"Indeed. If you could collect the others and bring them here, they may wish to see this…"

“Julian?”

"I heard. Xiu’s lurking in her cabin, so I’ll meet you ther- ah, shit."

Allison frowned. “Problem?”

"Yeah, my foot broke again."

Allison sighed. Julian insisted that the prosthetic was perfect for his needs in terms of moving around and stepping silently, but it achieved that by being a near-exact replica of the human foot made using carbon-fibre “bones”, and its “flesh” was a synthetic muscle tissue that Julian called “myopolymer”.

It worked just fine, when it worked. Unfortunately, the same alien materials science that made Kirk’s prosthetic by far his strongest limb didn’t quite match the performance standards of a healthy human body in terms of both weight and strength. Julian’s decision to go for accurate movement and mass rather than high performance, so as to minimize his rehabilitation training time, meant that he periodically suffered the equivalent of tendon ruptures and stress fractures. “D’you need us to help you back?” she asked.

"Nah, it’s a field repair. Price I pay, I guess." The advantage to a prosthetic foot, of course, was that he could perform the equivalent of surgery on it himself with glue.

“See you soon, then.”

"Sure."

Lewis spent most of the walk examining his "Huh“, poking it and turning it over and over in his hands. Allison was pretty sure he surreptitiously licked it at one point, all with no apparent effect. It was an improvement on his speculating about Xiu.

Kirk, Vedreg, Zane and Amir were waiting for them in the street. Both the humans were hunched over and shivering from standing around in the plummeting temperature with nothing to do to keep themselves warm, and Kirk was fidgeting in the cold, but Vedreg’s species had evolved to spend a week every year standing around in the driving rain of the World-Storm: He seemed perfectly comfortable, producing great monsoon clouds with every exhalation.

“Ah, there you are!” he exclaimed upon laying eyes on Allison and Lewis. “Come and see!”

Allison looked upwards. “It’s… a building.” she said. Though it was an admittedly impressive one, taller and more sprawling than any other around it, and looking quite clean, well-maintained and lit compared to its neighbors.

“It’s a hospital." Vedreg corrected her.

“And we’re going to find the secret to species decline in there, are we?”

Vedreg turned and spread his arms to indicate the city and its surrounding sprawl of infill as a whole. “A hospital this large has catchment for the entire river valley.” he said. “It should be absolutely thriving with activity, should it not? Despite the much reduced population, some hundred thousand souls still live inside this hospital’s coverage.”

Allison nodded yes, then remembered that without translators she had better do Vedreg the courtesy of speaking aloud. “Sure.” she said.

“And yet… no ambulances are landing.” Vedreg indicated the dormant landing pads. “The ground vehicle parking area is all but completely empty. No pedestrians are coming or going. The Injury and Emergency department is silent. Clearly, the OmoAru who live around here don’t care in the slightest about their own health. And yet the building remains open, the power is still on, and the reception drone is ready to receive and help.”

“Automated?” Lewis asked.

“The staff parking.” Kirk chimed in “Is not vacant. Somebody is still at work inside."

“Who?”

Kirk’s imitation of a human shrug was getting better with practice, but his extra limbs still made the gesture look strange. “Unfortunately, I don’t read OmoAru.”

“Huh.” Allison mused.

Lewis laughed. “Don’t start that shit again.” he warned.

His admonition earned a wry huff from Allison, and baffled expressions from everyone else, so he explained, producing the "Huh" to show off, passing it around. Vedreg and Kirk promptly fell to debating its meaning and significance, while Zane just inspected the little object, turning it over in his hands.

Allison sidled over to Amir, who had been silent so far, staring up at the hospital. “Thoughts?” she asked.

“Fifty quid says the cybernetics ward turns out to be open and the Hierarchy’s behind it all.” Amir challenged her. “Wiping out whole species when they start to become a threat seems like their style, doesn’t it?”

“And with an advanced species whose heads are going to be full of implants like the OmoAru…” Allison mused, following his line of reasoning. “…No bet. Have you-?”

Something very painful happened to the back of her head.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Scotch Creek Extraterrestrial Research Facility, British Columbia, Canada, Earth

Captain Owen Powell

“Hello, captain. Major Tony Ford, it’s nice to meet you.”

“Major.” Powell looked around the office as he shook the psychiatrist’s hand, finding it uncomfortably familiar to the other ones he had visited for counseling in his career. The couch was different, though. Long, low and square. A sofa, rather than a psychiatrist’s couch. He appreciated that. “Guess I sit there, do I?”

Major Ford smiled slightly and shook his head. “If you want. Or over there, on the floor, walk around… you can even sit at my desk and I’ll sit on the couch if you like. There’s coffee and tea if you want them.”

“I’ll… take the couch, thanks. And, uh… yeah, a cup of tea would go down about right.”

Ford nodded. “A Yorkshire man like yourself I’m thinking… strong and sweet?” he asked, smiling.

Powell produced a very, very little tired laugh through his nose. “Aye, you’ve got me bang to rights there.” he said.

Ford made the drinks quietly, giving Powell time to settle in and get the measure of the room a bit more. On second glance there were personal touches everywhere, not least of which was a dog basket in the corner, in which a dark little terrier was sat, watching him with wide-eyed interest. Her tail flopped over uncertainly in response to the attention.

“Oh, that’s Peggy.” Ford said. “Don’t worry, she’s as good as gold, won’t even leave the basket without permission.” he added fondly, smiling at her as he handed over the tea.

“I’m not going to wind up talking to the dog, am I?” Powell asked.

“Not if you don’t want to. But she’s half of the partnership, and there if you need her.”

“…Aye, let her out.”

“C’mon Pegs! Say hi.” Ford ordered. The dog bounced happily across the room and sat in front of Powell, giving his hand a little lick as he scratched her ear.

“Were you always a psych, Major?” he asked, noticing a few other personal effects around the office, one of which was unmistakably a large piece of shrapnel.

“No, I cross-trained.” Ford said, settling back down at his desk. “I was escorting EOD teams on my first two tours.”

“Nice one.” Powell said, genuinely impressed. “But why the move?”

“We lost a man. They never did figure out exactly why that carbomb went off, they thought the robot had made it safe but… well, everyone took it hard. I coped best by helping the others, and from there I decided to switch career paths.”

Powell nodded.

“What about you, did you sign up intending to go into the SBS from the beginning?”

“Aye, I did.”

“What attracted you to it?”

Powell sipped his tea. “My old man’s sister was an A and E nurse at Sheffield Teaching Hospital. She had these stories about when they sent the SAS lads along there for medical training in the ’70s.”

Ford listened, drawing him to continue. “Okay, so… this is all second hand, but apparently one of them was really fond of his motorbike, and one day after shift he went out there and found it’d been stolen.”

“Oh dear.”

“Aye. Apparently he turned up on it next day and all he’d say on the subject was 'he won’t do that again’." Powell chuckled, then paused and scratched Peggy’s ears some more. “…When I were little, I used to think that was well cool. Fookin’ unprofessional is what I’d call it nowadays.”

“Is that what attracted you to the Service? Stories like that?”

“At first, aye. I wanted to be hard, you know? Be a tough bastard. That’s what got me in the Cadets. Then I saw all me mates getting in trouble with the law, all their parents losing their jobs, and I could see this career ahead of me if I stuck at it. It was only really later that I started to believe in the message, right? Keeping our country safe, making the world a better place…”

Peggy gave him a lick as he looked down at her and scratched at her ear again. “…Shall we get started?” he asked.

“If you like.” Ford said. “What happened?”

“What happened?” Powell exhaled. “A kid died. You’re… briefed, right?”

“About the Hierarchy? Yes.”

“Right, well… emergency mission. Hierarchy in the colony, doing summat dodgy down the starport construction site, one of the kids had snuck in there to try and take a picture. We mobilized, were there in less than two minutes. Swept the site. We nearly had the bastard when he shot her.”

Peggy made a little noise and shuffled a touch closer to him, warm against his leg. He couldn’t resist the urge to pet her some more.

“Ten fookin’ seconds.” he said. “Less than. Seven, maybe. If we’d been there ten seconds earlier…”

“Could you have done anything differently?”

“No.” Powell shook his head. “I’ve gone over it. We did everything bloody perfect. I can’t bear to tell ‘em this, but my lads pulled out the best day’s work they ever done, there’s not a single fookin’ learning point in the entire bloody operation. Perfect."

He sighed. “And we still got there ten seconds too late.”

“I’m interested… why can’t you tell them?”

“Well what’s that going to achieve?” Powell asked. “Sometimes there’s not enough silver fookin’ lining in the world.”

“And that’s hard to accept?”

“No, that part I can accept. Failure’s always an option, no matter how well you do. That’s not what hurts.”

“Hurts?”

“Ah, I’m injured.” Powell replied. “Sure as if I’d been shot in the gut. One of my men had to chew me the fook out to make me come in here.”

“Do you think he was right to?”

“Abso-fookin’-lutely.” Powell asserted. “I’ve been beating myself up, losing sleep, takin’ it out on the lads. I’ve been a bad commander the last few days, and that’s got to fookin’ stop.”

“You sound angry at yourself.”

“Yeah, I am. I thought I was just angry at the Hierarchy, but… no, fook that, I am angry at them. And at myself. And at…"

He fidgeted, then patted the dog when she whined at him.

Ford gave him a minute, then suggested, softly. “Anger can be constructive.”

“Yeah.” Powell said. “I know that. Me and anger are old friends, we get on just fine, mostly. And I reckon that’s what’s giving me trouble, is that it’s not constructive to be angry with the person I’m most mad at."

“Who?”

Powell picked the dog up. “The girl.” he told her, very softly. “I’m angry at the victim.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Allison Buehler

"Uwsm!"

Blurs. Noise. A warm hand on her cheek.

“A-sn!”

Julian.

“Allison!”

Now, how did speech go again? Oh yes.

“Aaargh…”

“Oh, shit, you’re awake! You had me scared there.”

“…hurts…”

“Hey, look at me, okay?”

Allison forced herself to focus on his eyes. He shone a light into her face and stared intently at them for a second, checking the dilation of her pupils, before finally nodding. “Okay. You’re okay… I hope.”

“…happened?” She tried to move, then collapsed as nausea washed over her.

“You tell me. I got here, you and the guys are all unconscious. Kirk and Zane are missing and Vedreg…”

He indicated a breathing mountain of dark fur that was crumpled at the foot of the hospital stairs with shoots of dark red moving up and down it. “I think Zane was just planning to knock him out as well, but… I think he’s really hurt. I can’t get him to say anything.”

Allison squinted at him. While she knew every word in what he had just said made sense, and so did the arrangements too, for some reason she just couldn’t quite…

It clicked. “Shit! Vedreg…” She stood again, squelching the nausea this time.

“Woah, hey, maybe you shouldn’t…”

“Maybe I should.” She grunted, teetering on her feet as she staggered towards Vedreg. “The hell did he hit me with?”

“Looks like… a steel ball of some kind.” Julian held it up.

“Oh. The… Huh. The Huh.”

“What?”

“Forget it. How… how are the guys?”

“Alive, but barely responding. You’ve all got serious concussions, I don’t know…”

“Nothing we can…” the word she was looking for was a fuzz that just wouldn’t resolve, so she aborted the sentence and concentrated on remaining upright just long enough for her legs to gratefully give out and dump her by their Guvnurag comrade’s head.

“Vedreg?”

It was hard to tell, but she thought he moved slightly.

“Vedreg I… guess you don’t handle pain like we do, but I need to know if you’re conscious. Just do anything, okay?"

One of Vedreg’s huge bloodshot blue eyes rolled open from behind three layers of nictitating eyelids and looked right at her for just long enough to confirm he was still among the land of the living, then screwed shut again in agony.

Allison knew how he felt. “Come on, I can’t stop the pain if I don’t know where you hurt.” she said, grateful to have something to focus on. It was helping her work through the concussion.

“…chest…” the big alien coughed, eventually, moving his hand where it was cradling his flank. There was an obvious dent there.

“Shit, no wonder you’re like this…”

She was carrying two medical kits. The smaller one, the green bag on her belt, was made by and for humans, any one of the painkillers and treatments it contained might kill Vedreg outright. The other - a metal box about the size of her forearm - was intended for use on aliens, and came with the major advantage of being pseudo intelligent, capable of diagnosing, prescribing and prognosing injuries and ailments in all known interstellar species. Humans, sadly, weren’t in its database yet, and probably never would be. Allison knew from past experience that most ET drugs simply didn’t work on Deathworlders.

“Guvnurag patient, fractured ribs.” she informed it, and held the device’s black end - a low-powered, short-range medical scanner - over the break.

She held her breath as it took the measure of the damage, and exhaled happily when it reported that the injury, while undoubtedly agonising, was not life- threatening, and ordered her to apply its injection end to three spots around the wound.

It hissed alarmingly as she did so, but Vedreg seemed to appreciate whatever it did, as he relaxed and made a noise very like "Aaah…"

“Painkillers?”

“A local anaesthetic and a regenerative, most likely.” Vedreg replied, returned to his usual communicative self. “Thank you, Allison. I fear had he punched me much harder then I would no longer be with you.”

“You rest. Look after Amir and Lewis.” She told him. “We’ve got… uurgh…”

She had stood up, and had to steady herself on Julian.

“Allison, you need bed rest.” he told her.

“Fuck that, we’ve got to get back to the ship.”

“…of course. Xiu.” Julian said.

“Right. He’s obsessed, I knew it. He saw his chance and took it.”

“You should be flattered.” Vedreg commented. “He rendered you unconscious first.”

“And I doubt he’d have done it at all if Julian’s foot hadn’t broken.” Allison retorted. “Come on, let’s get after him.”

She was damned if she was going to let a few spinny buildings and the way her own limbs felt blurry stop her from getting payback.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Scotch Creek Extraterrestrial Research Facility, British Columbia, Canada, Earth

Captain Owen Powell

“I first… We were…”

Powell exhaled, and started over. “We spent a month on Cimbrean getting set up, just me and the lads, getting things ready for the civilian colonists. Day they arrived, I remember she… the girl fookin’ rampaged down the ramp the second it was down. She was racing her brother to be the first civilian colonist to set foot on a new world. She won. Right proud of it, too.”

“You have a soft spot for children, don’t you?” Ford asked.

“Never met a soldier who doesn’t.” Powell retorted. Peggy seemed to have fallen asleep on his lap. “You were at Camp Bastion, right?”

“That’s right.”

“Well, you’ve got to remember the kids around the camp, right? The locals? They become mascots, don’t they? I always remember how jaded some of them were, though. They got it, aye?”

“It?”

Powell grimaced and scratched the back of his head. “It’s… this is going to be a bit hard to explain.”

“Don’t worry about explaining it to me. I think I know what you mean, but for your own sake just… think out loud.”

“I think the other two teenagers around Folctha get it as well. Adam and Ava. S- The girl’s… Her friends. They’d come from San Diego, they were out of town when the bomb went off. Lost fookin’ everything. Their homes, friends, schools, family… and they got it, they understood what S-she didn’t."

“Which is?”

Powell exhaled. “Okay, right. So…” he thought for a second. “People say 'life is unfair’, right?"

“Yes…”

“Bullshit. Complete fookin’ rot. Totally backwards. Life is fair. Terribly, terribly fookin’ fair. Life doesn’t give a shit if you’re a forty-year-old soldier or a fourteen-year-old schoolgirl, it’ll kill you like that-" he snapped his fingers for emphasis. “-and not even give a shit. The stars keep burnin’, the worlds keep turnin’, but that’s it. That was your fookin’ lot. It’s fair because it treats everybody exactly the same, that way.”

Ford remained silent and kept eye contact, letting him say more.

“I get that.” Powell continued. “Adam and Ava get that. The kids in Afghanistan and Iraq got that. This gi-” He paused, then frowned at himself and gathered the strength to say her name. "Sara… didn’t."

“And you’re angry at her for that?”

“No! Not…” Peggy made a protesting noise as Powell set her aside and stood up to pace the room, hunting for the right way to start a sentence. “She was the… I mean… You’d…”

“Describe her.”

That stopped him. “What?”

“Who was she? What did she look like? How did she behave?”

Powell looked back at the couch, and smiled faintly when the dog gave him an uncertain tail-wag.

“I don’t… no, wait, I’ve got it. You ever go round a council estate, Major?”

“Occasionally…”

“They’ve always got those same kids on ‘em, don’t they? Like there’s a fookin’ machine somewhere, stamping out exact copies. The scrawny skinhead boy who thinks he’s hard, the pretty girls who’ll be pushin’ prams and chain-smoking before they can drive. You know the ones. I should know what that kind of kid is like, I used to be one.”

“I think I follow you.”

“Imagine… the complete opposite.” Powell said. “Somebody who fookin’ broke that machine. Somebody who’d never in their life wind up mooching around by the Co-op trying to talk strangers into buying them fags and vodka. Somebody… Different. Better."

“And Sara was such a person?”

“All three of them, her and the two others. They’re… She was… Alive. Living in the moment. Real people. They know who they are, which I sure as fook didn’t at that age."

“And who was Sara?”

Peggy licked his hand as Powell picked her up and sat down again. “Like something out of a bloody Enid Blyton book.” he said. “You know, the plucky children investigating fookin’ mysteries, thwartin’ gangs of gun-runners and what have you?”

“I’ve never read them.” Ford confessed.

“Not worth it, mate. Naive fookin’ horse shit, every word of the fookin’ things.”

“You said that you’re angry at her though. Why?"

“That’s just it, I don’t fookin’ know!” Powell seethed. “I wasn’t mad at that kid in Kenya, or at those Yezidi girls in the Persian Gulf, so why should I be angry with Sara? She’s the fookin’ victim here!”

“Well, turn the question around. If you can’t figure out why you are angry with Sara, perhaps it will help to think about why you were not angry with the others."

That seemed reasonable.

“Well… you know about what happened, right? In those other two cases?”

Ford nodded that he did. “I’ve read the notes, but it’s probably best if you recount them in your own words.”

Powell sighed. “Karatina market, Kenya. There was a little boy. Like, five or six? His parents had given him…” he laughed a little at the memory. “I remember it was this really cheap fookin’ knock-off plastic 'Ben 10' backpack… and the fookin’ thing was full of C4 and ball bearings…"

He patted the dog’s side. She had her chin on his lap and was looking up, listening. “His Mum and Dad were sitting in the car with one of those old Nokias. We saved the kid that time, and a lot of other people too, but he didn’t see that. All he saw was the nasty white men who’d come and killed his Daddy. Never fookin’ mind that we’d shot the evil bastard to stop him from calling the bomb and blowing up his own little boy, we were the bad guys.”

“You don’t blame him for that, though?”

“‘Course I don’t. He was a little’n, didn’t fookin’ understand what was happening. Never crossed the poor little bugger’s mind that his parents might murder him like that. It got to me, but… y’know, that’s dealt with. I can deal with being the bad guy if he’s alive and doin’ summat with his life. Who knows, maybe after all these years he’s figured out what happened and forgiven me.”

“And the Persian Gulf?”

“Different story. That one were a freighter involved in slave trafficking, they’d got a handful of Yezidi girls in a shipping container, going to some buyer in Thailand. There was a cockup at the Thai end, the buyer spooked and the freighter chucked the container overboard. Worthless cargo, now. All the drone operator could do was fookin’ watch.”

“You were angry then?” Ford asked.

“Fookin’ raging.” Powell nodded. His expression darkened. “We boarded the ship, had all these bastards sat in a circle, and they were jawing and joking and asking for cigarettes - they thought we were Americans - and all acting like they didn’t know what had been in that container. Like they hadn’t heard the banging and screaming from inside. Like they weren’t slave-trading fookin’ scum who’d just murdered five little girls. I wanted to bundle every man of ’em into a crate and tip ’em over the side myself. But that wasn’t the hard part.”

He paused. “No, the hard part were that the container burst. Pressure difference, right? So all the bodies came back up. We had to fish ’em out, these skinny little blue-eyed girls, and there were tiger sharks following the ship. They eat whatever falls overboard.”

His fists clenched. “Aye. I was angry there, but, at the right people, you know? Only reason we didn’t shoot those cunts in the kneecaps and throw ‘em to the sharks was pure bloody professionalism, and I still think it’d have been no less than they fookin’ deserved.”

“What do you think the difference is between those cases and this one?”

Powell thought about it for some time, petting Peggy as he did so. “I think… I think I’m angry at her because she got herself into it." he said at last. “Like, this brave, beautiful, stupid fookin’ girl had to go in and help when the cavalry was already on the way. Like, if she’d just been smart about it, she… I…"

He swallowed, then started to shake. “I never looked in a child’s eyes while she was dying before.” he croaked. “She said her last word to me. She was scared. She… When I closed her eyes, her- she’d been crying, she was so afraid, and the tears made my glove wet…"

He stared at his hand. “I couldn’t bear to take it off for hours…”

He sat, staring at his fingers for a few moments until the dog, very gently, inserted her nose under his palm and hauled herself into his lap, wagging sympathetically. He laughed a little, grabbed her and hugged, sobbing into the fur.

Ford let him get it out of his system. Finally, the captain made a weak "woo- ugh" noise and sat up, wiping his face dry.

“Fookin’…. I never cry.” he said.

“You needed to.” Ford observed.

“…You know, I think you’re right.” Powell agreed. “I’ve just not done that since I were a kid. Sorry.” He wiped his face again.

“Don’t be. In fact, I’d have been worried if you hadn’t.” Ford reassured him. “…Are you really angry at her, do you think? Now that you’ve had time to think out loud?"

“…No. I don’t think so, not really. Not any more. She’s like that poor boy in Kenya, isn’t she? She didn’t know any better, it never crossed her mind that maybe her parents had led her wrong.”

“Her parents?”

“Aye. These Dippy-Hippie tree-hugging free love pagan parents of hers. Her dad’s got these tattoos - 'an it harm none, do as thou wilt’." He gestured along his forearms to show where the two halves of the phrase were inked into Mark Tisdale’s skin. “Sexually open, no boundaries, no rules, no fookin’… sense of consequence. I’ll just bet you they never once told her that no, there’s things that you can’t do. You know? Like, they’ll have told her 'you can do anything“, trying to empower her and that, and it got her killed.”

“How do you feel towards them, then?” Ford inquired. “You’ve compared Sara to the child in Kenya, but what about the parents?”

“It’s… not the same.” Powell mused. “The bastards in Kenya, they had the phone in their hand. May as well have dug the little guy a trench and put a gun to the back of his head, they were going to murder him just as dead either way. But the Tisdales loved their daughter, so fookin’ much. They’d have never deliberately hurt her, but they coddled her so much that she never learned one of the most useful survival skills in the world.”

“Which is?”

“Knowing when it’s time to stop fookin’ playing.”

He sighed. “What’s saving them is that they didn’t know they were doing it. They’re as fookin’ ignorant as their daughter was.”

“Do you think you can forgive them for that?”

Powell inhaled and exhaled deeply through his nose, but didn’t answer, beyond shaking his head and stroking the dog.

Ford nodded. “Why not?”

“I can forgive a child for not knowing how the world works.” Powell replied, after a moment’s thought. “It’s bloody cruel, but there it is. She didn’t have time, and the first chance she got to learn, it killed her. She could have been smarter, should have been, but… y’know, she was just fourteen. A girl. Part of the cruelty of it is that we want them to be innocent at that age, don’t we? We don’t want to spoil their fun."

“But adults should know better.” Ford finished the thought for him.

“Fookin’ right.” Powell sniffed and shook his head. “I’m not sadistic, I’m not going to rake ’em over the coals for it, they’re suffering enough. But…”

He shook his head again, breathing out. “…But I don’t think I’ll ever be able to look at either of them without thinking, y’know… 'You’re the reason I had to watch your daughter die’."

“What are you going to do?"

Powell finally made eye contact, and there was a hardness in his gaze now that had been absent throughout the interview, one that looked quite natural and comfortable there. “I’m going to find something important of the Hierarchy’s, and when we’re done with it I’ll use the largest piece that’s still intact for a fookin’ paperweight.”

Major Ford smiled appreciatively. “I think this session has been good for you.” he opined.

Powell nodded. “Aye, I think it has.” he agreed. “I feel sharp again. More myself.”

“I would still suggest you come back for at least a couple more sessions.” Ford added. “After that, it’s up to you, but at least two more seems prudent.”

“Aye. At least two more.” Powell agreed, and stood, putting Peggy down but pausing to scratch at her ears one last time. “Don’t want to undo all our progress, do we?” he asked the dog.

“Indeed not.” Ford agreed. “We’re available any time, Captain. You let me know if we’re needed.”

“I will.” Powell shook the major’s hands “Thank you, sir.”

“Good luck.”

“Don’t fookin’ need it, mate.”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

“Kirk”

“This isn’t going to work, you know.”

“Hush ya.”

“I’ve read your file. Narcissistic Personality Disorder. A terrible thing. You were receiving a lot of therapy back on Earth to help you cope, weren’t you Zane?”

“I say hush!"

Kirk wriggled a little as Zane’s grip tightened around his upper arm, feeling the bone creak alarmingly in the Deathworlder’s grip. “Not had any since you left Earth of course.” He continued. “But you could do. We can still take you back, you can still get the treatment you need. If you keep behaving this way, though, that may not happen…”

Zane broke his arm. Kirk fought down the rattling creak which was the Rrrrtk equivalent of a scream, while Zane just cursed and shifted his grip to the lower, sturdier arm. “Blood clot, why ya ET bruk so easy?!”

Kirk turned his pain into a slightly hysterical laugh. “Evolution!” he replied. “Different worlds different -” he creaked in pain again “- bones.”

“Hush, ya.”

“Even if you do get us to the ship and we take off, Xiu isn’t fragile like me.”

“Oh, she be. Dawta care, yah know. The I’s me leverage- she too soft let the I come ’arm.”

They were nearly at the ships. As they entered the area lit by their industrial lights, alien workers turned to watch the sight of a human dragging a Rrrtk three times his height towards them.

“You’re not well! You’re not thinking straight!” Kirk protested. “We’re offering to take you back to - aah! - to Earth. Other women! You don’t need this one! You’re acting out, this is a crisis!”

"HUSH. Ya."

“You’d better let him go, Zane.”

Allison stepped out from among the packing crates, aiming her sidearm at him. She was clearly in a bad way, squinting against the glare of the floodlights and swaying a little bit, and her aim was not up to its usual rock-steady standard.

Zane twisted around, dragging Kirk into the line of fire. “Ya cyaan shoot, seen? ‘Less ya wan’ hit ya boy.”

“True. Julian?”

“Ah, ah!” Zane chided, raising his hand to wrap around the base of Kirk’s throat. “I know ya creechie tumpa-foot man a’ try dat. I make a move and me break ya boy here, sight?”

“And then what?” Kirk rasped around his hand, as Julian stepped into Zane’s sight-line and hefted his hatchet warily. “You kill me and you’ll lose your advantage. Your plan leaves something to be desired, Zane.”

“The I still be dead.”

“I admit, the prospect doesn’t thrill me, but you’re threatening to make the situation worse for yourself, not better."

“Hush, ya!”

Kirk waved an arm, beckoning Julian and Allison to fall back. Over the dermal patch microphone on his throat, he explained his reasoning, subvocalising so low that even Zane couldn’t hear him, and the translator certainly couldn’t.

"He’s histrionic. He was so convinced of his superiority that now we’ve punctured it he’s liable to panic."

“What do we do?” Allison replied, murmuring so that Zane wouldn’t hear.

"If we give him the chance to calm down a bit, we can build him back up. Get him to calm down. Get him to think that doing what we want is his idea."

“And if we can’t?” Julian asked him. “He seems pretty close to breaking point, boss.”

"If it comes to violence, it comes to violence." Kirk said.

“Greeaaat…”

"I’ll try to leave him alive."

They were passing through the middle of the field of equipment and crates surrounding the Corti research craft, when the Corti in question decided to interfere.

“You appreciate of course that there is a third option.” the male - Lesry - observed. He and Knadna were in Zane’s way, and they ignored Kirk’s attempts to signal for them to move.

“Get away.” Zane ordered.

“Rather than resort to violence…” Lesry said, stepping forward, “you could sign on with us. A bit of muscle would be useful, and we have the means to deliver you back to Earth, without your being a prisoner in the ship you arrived on. What say you?”

“I want.” Zane growled. “Xiu.”

“And ask yourself if that scenario seems likely right now, hmm?” Lesry pushed. “Be realistic.”

He stepped forward again. “I’m offering you the chance to part ways peacefully, as a free man. That seems like the most rationa-”

Zane backhanded him. It was a casual, almost gentle motion, but it highlighted the huge disparity between Human strength and Corti mass by flipping Lesry head-over-heels over a crate with a sickening noise like a baseball being thrown at a sack full of cockroaches.

It was all the distraction Kirk needed. He twisted, turned, darted sideways and his prosthetic arm lashed out, extending its concealed fusion blade.

Kirk went one way. Zane reeled the other. Zane’s left forearm left a crater in the sand where it landed between them, smoking, glowing and bloodless at the cut end.

Rrrrtk had a decent turn of speed over very short distances, but Kirk knew Humans well by now. Zane’s scream may have been of agony, but there was a very large component of adrenaline and rage in there as well, and no short-term turn of speed was any good at all when a pursuit predator was angry at him.

The only recourse open to him was to turn at bay and get ready with his sword, prepared to strike a lethal blow if he could, but that much mass, travelling that fast, would quite probably end very badly for him even if he did.

Facing the Hunters had been bad enough. Facing the murderous fury in Zane’s eyes was worse. Julian and Allison had retreated on his orders, and were now sprinting to catch up, but they were too far away, on the back foot. Zane was going to beat them.

Xiu got to him first.

If Zane’s casual backhand had hinted at the disparity between Deathworlder muscles and Corti bones, then what Xiu unleashed on the enraged Jamaican was an object lesson in just how physically far ahead of the rest of the galaxy humans truly were. Zane had time enough only to register her presence as she rose up in his path before she delivered four blows, any one of which would have exploded through Kirk’s body like heavy pulse-gun fire.

The first exploited his missing arm, driving into his chest, knocking him off- balance and driving the wind out of him. The second was laser-targeted on his jaw, stunning him. As he staggered, the third blow was delivered to his left eye, and the fourth to his right.

Her precision flurry of violence took less than a second.

Zane’s headlong berserk charge turned into him staggering, dropping to his knees in the sand, wheezing, and falling over when he tried to support himself on a hand that was lying several meters away.

He wasn’t out, though. Running on adrenaline and anger, he still tried to haul himself to his feet, swinging wildly with his remaining arm even as his eyes swelled up and blinded him.

Xiu just stepped and flowed, and wherever the flailing limb went, there she wasn’t.

She was angry too, Kirk decided. Furious. But it was a different kind of fury. Zane in a rage was a bellowing beast, roaring and thrashing around like a wounded Vulza.

Xiu on the other hand became a machine. Her face locked down, her eyes locked on, everything about her unified into a cold and methodical instrument of violence that simply took the most efficient path to avoid harm and then, when the opportunity presented itself, she stepped forward and delivered a straight punch to Zane’s skull, just behind the ear.

The delicately balanced tug-of-war that kept bipedal humans upright and moving ceased instantly, and Zane crashed into the dirt, unmoving.

In the stunned moment of stillness that followed, Xiu made hardly any noise, simply allowing her breath to hiss out from between her teeth, and then she straightened, inhaled through her nose as she touched her fist to her palm in a Bau Quan, then exhaled as she let her entire body relax. Only the hardness in her eyes remained, though even that thawed a little when she glanced at Kirk.

“Are you okay?” She asked.

“He broke my arm, but I am alive, thanks to you.” Kirk said, and meant it. “I am… impressed.”

“Understatement central there, boss.” Allison chimed in. “Holy shit, girl!"

“You cut his arm off…” Xiu observed. She didn’t sound happy about it.

“Necessary, I’m afraid.” Kirk replied.

“Yeah, but… oh, God." A distinct green colour rose in Xiu’s face and she turned away, breathing heavily. Allison rubbed her back, making soothing noises.

“Allison, can you tend to his injury?”

Allison looked up at him, then reluctantly nodded. “…Sure. Julian?”

The pair of them hoisted the unconscious Zane onto their shoulder and dragged him - and Allison herself, Kirk suspected - in the direction of Sanctuary and her medbay.

That left Kirk and Xiu alone. The Corti team were tending to their wounded shipmaster, who seemed to be alive, thankfully.

“Are you alright?” He asked.

“Just…” Xiu slowed her breathing. “…I’m okay. Oh God, they left his arm…" She turned away again and bent over, trying not to vomit.

“Are you sure?” Kirk asked her, as soon as she seemed to have recovered a little.

She laughed a little. “I never thought it’d be like this.” she complained, and wiped at some tears that were threatening to form. “Monsters and fighting and cutting peoples’ arms off.”

She sniffed, and after a few more cleansing breaths she stood up and raised her head, staring at a night sky and stars that only six specimens of the entire human race had ever laid eyes on. “I want to go home."

“And what do we do with Zane? Does he get to go home as well?”

Xiu blinked at him. “You’re the shipmaster, aren’t you?” she asked.

“I am, and I say as shipmaster that it’s your decision. To hell with my arm, you’re clearly the one he really hurt. Whatever it was that happened between you."

“Then he…” Xiu began firmly, but paused. “I…” She sighed. “Let me give him one last chance.”

“By all means. Now, if you don’t mind, I’m in rather a lot of pain, and we need to send Julian back for the others…”

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Starship Sanctuary, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Zane

Zane had been knocked out in bar fights in his time, but returning to consciousness this time wasn’t like those other occasions had been. It was just like… waking up.

“What…?”

"You were drugged, and treated. You’re actually in pretty good shape, Zane."

It was Xiu’s voice, sounding oddly tinny, and that suddenly made Zane aware of his surroundings - he was curled up on the floor of one of Sanctuary’s airlocks. Big enough for a Guvnurag to use, it was a large room by human standards.

Xiu’s face was at one of the windows. So pretty. So… cold. That same look that had made him angry at her. Didn’t she know who she was dealing with?

The stump where his arm ended just below the elbow felt cold, and beyond that was a strange numbness. That should have bothered him more, but his ego ratcheted into gear, redirecting all the grief and insecurity that somebody without his personality disorder would have felt into pure grim anger. There would be a reckoning.

“Ya gonna let me out?” he asked.

"One way or the other." Xiu replied, speaking through a microphone. "Look behind you."

Zane blinked, and did so.

There were stars beyond the opposite window. It took him a second or two to make the connection between that fact, his being in an airlock, and what she had said.

Please. Who did she think she was bluffing?

“Ya wouldn’t.” he declared. “Me know I, Xiu. Ya don’ do that kind of badness.”

"To be rid of you?" She declared. “What happens when we get back to Earth, huh? You come after me again? You hurt more people? You hurt me again?"

He laughed. “Gwan, then.”

Bluff called, he congratulated himself. There’d be a showdown with Kirk, he’d have vengeance for his arm. And the others would fall in line. They’d see what kind of a man he was.

The howl of the alarm and the sound of the doors whining into gear when Xiu pressed the button drove all of his confidence out of him in a rush of cool air threatening to escape.

“Xiu! Xiu, no! Ya can’ do this!” he rushed the door she was behind, knocking and shouting. “Xiu no! I’m sorry! I hurt ya, that was wrong o’ me, me leave ya ’lone! Just let me go back to Earth!"

The alarms didn’t stop, and her hand on the release didn’t fidget.

"You want to go home too, huh?" She asked.

Those eyes were so cold. He’d hurt her. He’d hurt her, and now she was going to murder him. He couldn’t believe that she would. He couldn’t believe that the others would let her.

But there were the hungry stars, waiting for him.

“Yes!” he screamed "PLEASE, Xiu! I’m beggin’ you, PLEASE!"

She paused, her eye contact drifted away. Her hand moved away from the final release. She softened, and the relief trembled down him. He meant every word, she’d be left alone if only she-

"Walk home, asshole."

She hit the button.

The overpressure in the lock flung him shrieking out of the ship… and into the river Uatun, a mere four meters below.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

“Legsy” Jones

“Alright…”

Legsy Jones took a minute or so to check he was in absolutely pristine military trim before knocking. He knew the captain had actually gone to counselling, but after the last meeting with Powell, he was damned if he was going to be on anything but his most perfect behaviour.

“Come in.”

Moment of truth. He poked his head into the captain’s office.

Powell looked rested. The darkness around his eyes was gone, he’d tidied up the drifts of paperwork into a more organised system, and his camp bed was made. The captain himself was standing at the washbasin, rinsing shaving foam off his face.

“Latest from Intelligence, sir.” Legsy said.

“Cheers. On the desk, please.”

So far so good. But he wasn’t about to relax just yet. The dossier joined some of its fellows on Powell’s desk.

“Do you need anything, sir?”

“No thanks, I’m good. Carry on.”

“Sir.”

He was halfway through turning and leaving when Powell suddenly threw his towel onto the bed. “Sergeant.”

“Sir.” Legsy turned around. The captain blinked at him, expression unreadable, then crossed the room and stood in front of him.

He wasn’t a large man, Legsy realised. He just seemed that way.

“I, uh…” Powell began, then fell silent. His clock ticked out six seconds before he shook his head. “Ah, never fookin’ mind, Legs. Keep up the good work, mate.”

“Yessir.” Inside his head, Legsy wanted to punch the air and grin.

Powell snorted “Well go on, carry on then!” he said.

Instead, Legsy grabbed him in a bear hug.

“-‘Ere, what’re you- fookin’ - let go!” Powell protested, and Legsy did so. Powell straightened his jumper and frowned at him. “The fook was that about?" he demanded.

“Sorry, sir.” Legsy straightened to attention. “It’s just… good to have you back.”

Powell hung his head and shook it, smiling. “Get out, you big fookin’ softy.” he ordered, kindly.

“Yessir.”

Once Legsy had gone, Powell retrieved the towel and hung it neatly to dry, checked the room for any other signs of things out of place, and allowed himself a satisfied nod.

“It’s good to be back." he agreed.

Date Point: 4y 9m 3w AV

UmOraEw-Uatun, Planet Aru, Elder Space

Knadna

Knadna squinted at the figure staggering towards them out of the dark. It had been only a few minutes since the Sanctuary had taken off, vanishing over the horizon with all the power that its gargantuan power core could produce, and she had watched the evicted psychotic Deathworlder struggle ashore with some interest.

Not to mention satisfaction.

“You have to admit, they are extremely tough." she observed. An amputation, a concussion and a four-meter fall into the water only seemed to have annoyed the dark-skinned human, really. He was, if anything, probably as dangerous now as he had been a few hours ago. More so, possibly.

“Are we taking him with us, ma’am?”

“I think not.” Knadna replied, not even bothering to show her contempt for the moronic inquiry. “Get the last of the equipment stowed, I want the ship locked up and ready before that human gets here.”

The Kwmbwrw crewman rushed to obey. Knadna herself enjoyed the leisurely stroll back to the ship, arriving just in time to turn in the airlock, check everybody and everything was on board, and then activate the ship’s primary shields right in the approaching Deathworlder’s face.

This move did not seem to please Zane, who sprinted the remaining distance in an eyeblink, and Knadna had to clamp down hard on an instinctive reflex to flinch, cower, or run.

“Let me in.” He demanded, his tone of voice promising all of the impressive capacity for violence that his species was capable of unleashing, should she fail to comply.

“Now, why would I do that?” Knadna asked him. “You rather badly injured somebody I quite like. You seem to have an alarming inclination to use viol-”

Zane interrupted her and proved her point by slapping the forcefield, which rang and flashed alarmingly, but Knadna kept calm.

“Not even a human can punch through starship-grade weapons shielding, you barbarian idiot.” she told him, keeping a tired inflection in her tone.

“LET ME IN!” He roared.

Knadna mentally sent a few commands over the ship’s control circuit, telling the pilot to begin the launch sequence.

“Frankly, the only thing stopping me from using one of this ship’s plasma guns to vaporise you where you stand is because I think leaving you all alone here with a dying species seems more… poetic.” she said.

“I can be useful.” he said, changing tack. “You want a nice strong human on your ship, I can do the heavy lifting, fight off pirates.”

“You already rejected that offer.” Knadna pointed out, but she made a show of mulling the suggestion over. “Besides, you would be a lot more useful if you still had both arms…”

She let him rant for a few seconds, ignoring the content, and interrupted him after a careful internal countdown.

“I tell you what.” she offered. “You can come aboard if you help me expand the limits of Corti scientific knowledge.”

“…What?”

“Well, I have this hypothesis that what happens to a Deathworlder when he’s standing directly beneath the primary kinetic engine of a starship at takeoff-” she made a meaningful upwards glance. The engine in question was beginning to whine, barely audible to Corti hearing but presumably quite clear to a human’s more acute senses. “-Is much the same thing as what happens to everything else in the galaxy.”

Zane stared upwards, swallowing and breathing heavily. There was an alarming blue glow beginning to manifest somewhere inside the device.

“If you’re not willing to test my idea,” Knadna told him. “Then you can always run away. You have… oh, eight seconds.”

He looked back down at her, plainly afraid now.

“I’d start running.” she said, sweetly.

Once they were airborne, she dusted off her hands, shrugged out of and hung up her sand robes, and visited the ship’s medical bay. Lesry was sitting up, expression taut as he endured the procedure of having regenerative medicines injected directly into the extensive damage at his shoulder by the surgical robot.

“I saw how you got rid of him.” He said, waving his undamaged hand at a floating projected monitor. “Nicely done.”

“I took the liberty.” She agreed. “I assume you don’t disapprove?”

“Oh, no.” he said. “If he was too ignorant to know that absolutely nothing happens to a being standing beneath a kinetic thruster when the ship takes off, then he would have been of no real use anyway."

“Besides.” he added, grimacing as a fresh needle delivered a shot of Cruezzir deep into his flesh. “I believe your own words were something like 'Never underestimate a Human’."

“Absolutely never.” she replied. “Predictable though his attempt to take over the ship and chase after them would have been, it would also have been alarmingly plausible that he might succeed.”

“Best to leave him behind.” Lesry agreed. The surgical robot finished its work, leaving his arm bound up and immobilized, but the pain had clearly faded. “You continue to impress me with your competence, Knadna.” he said, easing himself down off the medical bed.

“I think we work well together.” She replied, internally glowing at the compliment.

“I think we do.” He agreed. “Shall we continue our association?”

“Make it more formal?”

“Indeed.” Lesry said. “A DNA exchange, perhaps?”

“I’m agreeable to that.”

They widened their pupils at each other, a rare Corti expression of genuine warmth and affection not dissimilar to a human shy smile, and Knadna congratulated herself.

Today had been a good day.

Chapter 25
Chapter 22: “Warhorse” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point: 4y 10m AV
Dominion Embassy Station, Earth/Luna L1 point, Sol system

Dr. Anees Hussein

Shaking hands with a Corti was an exercise in delicacy. Dr. Hussein thought of himself as an old and increasingly frail man, but he still had the grip strength to cause serious harm to the alien’s hand if he applied a little too much vigor. So it wasn’t so much a handshake as a hand_touch._

Still. It was a civil, civilized gesture, and that alone was a mark of just how much his relationship with the Directorate’s ambassador, Medra--and through them both, Earth’s relationship with the Corti Directorate--had evolved in a relatively short space of time.

“Thank you for seeing me.” he said, gratefully taking his seat when the Corti had gestured towards it with those long, fine-boned fingers that he could so easily have pulverized.

Medra affected a small, businesslike smile. “Thank you for asking nicely.” he retorted. “The Gaoians continue to think they can just barge into my office whenever they please.”

“The Gaoians don’t want something from you.” Hussein replied. He had quickly learned that the Corti truly loved the direct approach. If you irritated them, they could skate and slide around the issue and deal in lies and half-truths with the best of them, but if you cut straight to the matter at hand and phrased things bluntly, they responded in kind and pretty soon you had either a deal or an argument. It had been true of Medra’s predecessor, and it was true of Medra.

After the tangled web of his home country’s politics, it was paradise.

“Indeed? That seems like a deviation from your previous position.”

“There has been a change of strategy.” Anees revealed. “Opportunities that we are now considering the possibility of exploiting, to the mutual benefit of any species who partners with us in exploiting them.”

Medra sat back. “Please don’t be vague, Doctor.”

“All in good time. I would rather tell you what we need. I’m sure you will see our intent soon enough.”

“Please, do tell me.” Medra replied. That was another thing about Corti psychology. They couldn’t resist having both their ego flattered and their intellect challenged at the same time.

“Two things. We would like to purchase from you the technology to make a lightweight load-bearing exoskeleton that does not require a power source to provide assistance to a moving wearer.”

“Trivial. The other?”

“A drug. Cruezzir.”

Medra sat forward. “That is not going to happen.” he stated, bluntly.

“Why not?”

“Cruezzir has a history of interacting…dangerously with human physiology. It has created two of the most notorious and effective criminals the galaxy has ever seen, in fact.”

“Yes, I’ve read their files.” Anees replied. “I also know enough about Cruezzir to be certain that, in their cases, it was applied incautiously and incorrectly, and that the long term effects are devastating in terms of mental health, which would be detrimental to our plans.”

Medra stared at him, thoughtfully. “You’re creating super-soldiers.” he decided after a few seconds.

“An elite unit, certainly.” Anees conceded. “Possibly the most elite. But _ ‘super-soldiers’_ may be going too far."

“And what conceivable reason would we have for assisting the most dangerous species in the galaxy in creating the most dangerous soldiers they possibly can?”

“Ambassador, if we had designs on threatening the Corti, or anybody else for that matter, then I daresay we wouldn’t need an elite unit. Our regular infantry would easily suffice for any ground warfare conducted against any Dominion species, don’t you think? Why would we go to the expense and difficulty of creating a new elite?"

“In which case I’m intrigued as to the purpose of this hypothetical ‘elite’." Medra confessed. “What DO you intend to do with an asset like that?”

Anees allowed the inner ‘gotcha’ that rang triumphantly around his head to feed his best warm, closed-lipped smile. “Why, ambassador.” he said. “To clean up the mess we have made, of course.”

Date Point: 4y 10m AV
Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Adam Ares

“You’ve got to realise you’re asking me about classified information there, kid.”

“I know.” Adam had declined the offer to sit down opposite Captain Powell. He preferred to stand instead, resting his hands lightly on the back of the offered chair. “I’m not asking you to just tell me. I’m asking you what I have to do to earn it."

Powell’s own chair creaked as he sat back and folded his arms, scrutinising Adam, who said nothing, trying not to fidget.

“Earn it.” he repeated.

“Yes.”

“Right.” Powell unfolded his arms and rubbed a thumb on his chin thoughtfully. “Why?” he asked.

The question threw Adam a bit, outraging him. “Wh-? What do you mean 'why’?" he demanded. “My best friend is dead! So’s my mother! So’s everyone I went to school with. Millions of people!”

“Right.” Powell agreed, nodding amiably. “That rather proves that what you’re after, if it exists, is a big deal, doesn’t it? So…what are you going to do with the information, should you acquire it? Is it obsession? Curiosity? Revenge? What?"

“I want to do whatever I can to stop anyone else from dying!” Adam snapped.

Powell threw him again when his face split into a broad smile. “That so?” he asked.

“That’s so.”

The captain nodded, and sat forward. “Right then. If that’s your goal, then realistically, you’re looking at military service. And I don’t just mean becoming a jarhead or MP. I’m talking intel, special forces, something like that.”

“Not a problem.” Adam told him.

“Aye? Well, we’ll see. Now…” Powell rubbed his chin again. “Realistically speaking…the only two services that are doing anything in space right now are the Royal Navy and the US Air Force. Thanks to your Cimbrean citizenship, you’re eligible to join either service, but frankly you’re more American than Brit, so the latter’d maybe suit you a bit better.”

He sat back again. “As for what you do in your chosen service…well, that one’s your choice to make, I can’t advise you there.”

“How did you choose?” Adam asked him.

“Me? The motto.” Powell said. “’Through Strength and Guile.' I liked that, thought it sounded right fookin’ badass."

He noticed the change in Adam’s expression. “What?”

“I’ve…never heard you swear before.”

“I don’t swear around children.” Powell said, simply.

“I’m still only sixteen.”

“Maybe, but it’s not about how old you are, Ares. It’s about the choices you make and your reasons for making ’em.”

He nodded toward the door. “This isn’t a decision to be made here in my office.” he said. “Hit the library, do some research, think about it. My door’s open, alright?”

Adam nodded, still a little stunned by the show of respect. “I…Thank you, captain.”

Ava seemed to spend every waking second playing with her inherited camera these days, familiarising herself with its functions and the different effects she could achieve by varying the shutter speed, aperture size, focus and more. When she wasn’t studying the device itself, she was studying what Sara had done with it, examining the photos their friend had taken and making notes about their arrangement composition and more. She’d co-opted an entire wall of their living room in fact, covering it in post-it notes and colour prints, not to mention having borrowed every single book on photography that Folctha’s library had.

“The motto?” she asked.

“I guess. It seems like as good a thing to go on as anything else.” Adam replied.

She put the camera down. “But…special forces, Adam? Won’t that take you away for a long time?”

He stopped searching for a second and turned in his seat. “…Yeah, it will.” he agreed.

They hugged, melting into each others’ arms without either of them needing to invite the other.

“What are you going to do, do you think?” He asked after a silent minute or so. She ran a hand through her curls.

“I guess…I want to help people too.” she said. “I want to make some sense of all this. And now this camera’s been left to me, and Sara always talked about being a photojournalist…”

“How do you even get started on that? It’s not like they have recruitment…”

“I’ve been doing my own research there.” Ava told him. “I thought I’d try for City University London.”

“I guess you’ll be away for a long time too then, huh?”

She nodded, resting her forehead against his. “I guess…”

She caught sight of what was on his screen and looked up. “I like that one.”

“Hmm?” he turned, and read it aloud. “’That Others May Live’?"

“Yeah.” She said. “What do you think?”

Adam stared at it for a few seconds, repeating it under his breath. “I think…that’s the one.” he said.

“Pararescue?” Powell looked genuinely stunned. “Bloody hell, Ares. I can’t fault your ambition, but are you sure?"

“The motto speaks to me.” Adam shrugged.

“…Aye, alright. But not to try and talk you out of it or owt like that, you’re setting yourself up for a really fookin’ difficult couple of years.”

“I know the training will be hard, but--”

“No.” Powell interrupted him, standing up. “You don’t. You have no fookin’ clue what hard really is, I promise you that."

Adam was smart enough to shut up and let him say his piece. The captain dug into his foot locker and pulled out a small A5 notebook, which turned out to be pasted full of photographs and hand-written notes. He flipped through the first few pages until he alighted on a picture of a young, acne-scarred man who was gazing proudly out of the photograph. “This was me when I took the Potential Royal Marines Course.” he said. “Right dorky little shite, wasn’t I?”

Adam caught his eye, and realised Powell was amused at himself. “I fookin’ thought I was a proper Marine, I did. The PRMC is two and a half days, they test you in the gym and the assault course, take you on a three mile run…I thought 'if this is what it’s like, this is going to be fookin’ easy." He laughed silently, deep in his chest, and flipped the page “Then I went through the actual Royal Marines training.”

The next photo had less acne and a stronger, more Powell-like expression, worn by a young man in a black uniform and green beret, with a rifle held precisely by his side. "That was tough. The PRMC didn’t prepare me for it at all, it just meant I was tough enough to START the training without collapsing."

He closed the book.

“Every step along the way, I came up against limits I didn’t know I had and went beyond them. Marines Commando training was fookin’ hell, but I cleared it. Now: To apply for the Special Boat Service, you need a minimum of two years’ service as a marine commando. Did that. Got some medals, too. Figured I was doing well. Then I applied for the SBS, and that finally brought me up against the joint UKSF selection program."

He opened the book again, flipping to a series of pages filled with pictures of rolling, rugged mountains, many of them falling off to sheer drops. “The first phase of that ends in a test week: five back-to-back days of walking sixteen or so miles a day in the Welsh mountains with a fifty pound bag and a rifle, and on the last day? Forty miles, which you’ve got to finish in less than twenty hours."

He sat down. “And it just gets tougher from there. Much tougher. Men have died in that training. I failed the first time, only barely managed it the second but managed it I fookin’ well did. Right?"

Adam nodded his understanding. “Okay…?”

“From what I’ve heard of it, I honestly don’t know if I could have made it through the Pararescue pipeline.” Powell confessed. His face was the very picture of deadly seriousness. “They call it 'Superman School' for a bloody good reason."

“…But people do get through it.” Adam pointed out.

“Oh aye, they do. And if you think you’ll be one of them, then fookin’ well go for it. I just want you to have some idea of what you’d be getting yourself in for.”

“Let’s say I do manage it…” Adam said. “Will that get me in on the secret?”

Powell said nothing, but returned to his desk and sat down.

“Your first step,” he said, not answering the question, “…is recruitment. The nearest US armed forces recruiting center is technically in Seattle, ’cause that’s the easiest place to get to from Scotch Creek. If you’re going to walk in there and say 'I want to be a Pararescueman' then it’s going to take, oh…a week or so, total, so you’ll need a hotel room."

“That long?”

“You thought it was as easy as just 'Hi there, I would like to soldier please’? You’ll have to take a…" Powell looked up, remembering a detail. “…ASVAB, I think it’s called. Vocational Aptitude test. They’ll put you through a physical and mental evaluation, you’ll talk to a special forces recruiter, the works.”

He sniffed. “If they take you--though I can’t see why they wouldn’t--you’ll go straight on from there to Lackland Air Force Base in San Antonio for basic training. That’s eight weeks. You’ll graduate, see your family for the weekend, and then that’s it. You’re on to the PJ pipeline and you’ll find it a lot harder to see them again after that. Realistically? Christmas, and that’s about it. For two years, maybe longer.”

Adam went quiet and thought long and hard about that one.

“If that’s how I earn it, that’s how I earn it.” He said at last.

“Decision made, then?”

“Yes.”

Powell nodded, then stood and shook Adam’s hand. “Well then. I’ll be cheering for you.” He said.

“Could I…?” Adam tailed off then shook his head. “Never mind.”

“Spit it out, mate.”

“If this is going to be hard…could you help me get started? Give me a taster? Get me in shape?”

Powell paused. “I’ll have to discuss it with Legsy, he’s the one who specialized in training and instruction.” he said. “And he won’t like it.”

“Why not?”

“Well because he likes you, you daft bugger!” Powell said. “And while he’ll be happy to get you up to standard for Basic, if he’s going to give you even a fookin’ taster of Pararescue indoctrination, which is what I think you’re asking for…" Adam nodded “…Then he’ll have to go hard on you, right hard.”

“I guessed as much.” Adam said, patiently. He was beginning to grow tired of Powell driving the point home.

Powell noticed, and sighed. “I’ll…talk to Legs. Meet us in the gym tomorrow at 10:30, after a good breakfast. You’ll need it.”

“Thank you, Captain.”

“Might be a bit premature there, mate.” Powell joked. “But you’re welcome. I’ll…do what I can to help you along.”

“You will?”

“Aye. I’ll provide a reference, and believe me, that’ll count for a lot. But you’d better get on and have a good night’s sleep.”

“I will. Thank you, captain.”

Half of Powell’s mouth ticked upward. “Dismissed.” he said. “…trainee.”

Hayley Tisdale

The advantage to Cimbrean’s small, compact houses was that answering the door never took long, even if it was just yelling “I’ll be out in a minute!”

Hayley used that time to fill the kettle and started it boiling, take quick stock of the house to make sure it was tidy, and hide a certain little white box before she opened it.

Not for the first time, she reflected that with her heart-shaped face and curly dark hair, Ava was the very picture of the painfully pretty girl next door in jeans and flannel. Today, though, she was also painfully nervous about something, to judge from the way she’d been pacing little awkward circles outside, rubbing her fingers together.

“Ava? What’s wrong, honey?”

“Umm…” Ava gave her a nervy little smile. “Nothing’s wrong, it’s just I could…I could just use some advice."

“From me?” That was astonishing. Hayley wasn’t sure she was qualified to advise anybody on anything these days.

“Please?”

Hayley stepped aside “Come on in.” she offered.

Ava did so, and perched herself restlessly onto the edge of the couch.

“Cup of tea, sweetie? Or, I’ve got Ovaltine…”

Ava smiled, a little weakly. “Ovaltine would be nice.” she agreed.

Hayley let her relax as she bustled about, taking a little longer making the drinks than was strictly necessary. By the time she was done, Ava had sat back a little and released some tension in a big sigh.

“So…what’s up?” Hayley asked, though she had a sneaking suspicion.

“I, um…” Ava puffed out her cheeks and exhaled. “Adam and me, we’ve never…I mean…”

Okay, so Hayley’s suspicion had been wrong, but now she understood what this was really about. “You’ve not? Oh, honey…I kind of thought with you living together…”

Ava looked down at her hands, which were a frantic little knot of fingers. “Different beds.” she said, with a little laugh. “Are you…okay with me coming to you?”

“Well who else are you going to ask? Adam’s dad?” Hayley laughed, and Ava giggled. “No, honey, it’s…I’m actually kind of flattered. What do you need to know?”

“I guess…whether I should, really.” Ava said, relaxing. “I mean, Mom and Dad always said I should wait for marriage, and…”

“So did mine. I didn’t listen.”

“Yeah, but…”

“No, honey, listen to me a second.” Hayley shuffled forward on the couch and set her tea down. “I know you miss your parents so much it hurts. I can’t go two hours without remembering Sara and…” she closed her eyes and rallied. “But…Let me tell you what I wish I’d told her, okay? All your parents would want is for you to be happy, and to be safe. That’s all.”

“It is?”

Hayley nodded. “They told you to wait because they didn’t want you rushing in and getting hurt.” she said. “There’s nothing magical about your wedding day that’ll suddenly make it the right choice if it wasn’t before, and if it’s the right choice now, then…why wait?”

Ava was nodding along, but she frowned. “How…do I know when it’s right?” she asked.

“Well, you…” Hayley paused to think about it. “Okay, now here’s something I wish my parents had told me, okay?"

“Okay…?”

“Sex is…nice.” She paused, and corrected herself. “No, it’s great, even. But everyone seems to get this idea that it’s this precious, special thing and they say all kinds of stupid stuff about it. Judging you for having too little, too much, being a virgin, not being a virgin… "

“So…I shouldn’t care?” Ava asked.

“Exactly! Just be smart about it. Have as much or as little as you want, and don’t let anybody tell you when or with who or anything like that. That’s all your choice and nobody else’s. Just be smart about it.”

“Smart?”

“Well I mean, you know about…the pill, and condoms and everything, right?”

“Oh, that!" Ava looked relieved. “Yes I…I know that stuff.”

“Good. So be smart about using them, because…trust me on this, you really don’t want to be a mum yet.”

“No.” Ava agreed.

“Okay. So the question isn’t 'how do you know when it’s the right time‘, okay? The question is just…’Do you want to’?"

There was a long pause, during which Ava drank about a third of her Ovaltine. “Adam’s…going away.” she said, eventually and quietly.

Hayley shuffled around the corner and put an arm round Ava, rubbing her back. “He is?”

Ava nodded. “He turns seventeen a few days before Christmas, and he’s…joining the military.”

“Oh, honey…”

“No, no. I’m happy: I’m going to be doing something too. We both want to achieve something and this is the way he’s doing it.” She sounded like she meant it. “But…he’s going to be gone for so long, and…”

“You feel like you should give him a proper send-off?”

Ava nodded.

“That’s…for me, that wouldn’t be the right reason, sweetie.”

Ava wrapped both hands around her Ovaltine and sipped it. “In that case…what would be the right reason?" She asked.

“There’s only one right reason, honey: because you both want to. The list starts and ends there.”

They sat in silence for a bit until Ava had finished her drink.

“I’m leaving too.” Hayley revealed.

“…You are?!” Ava looked up, and Hayley internally winced at the desperation she saw in the younger girl’s eyes. “Hayley, why?”

“Don’t worry, it’s not because of Sara or anything. I’ll be coming back.” she promised. “I’m just going away for a few months.”

“Why?”

“I’m…Mark and I are having another baby.” She dug the pregnancy test box out from where she’d hidden it under a throw pillow. “We’re worried about the low gravity affecting the baby’s development, so I’m going back to Earth for a year…You’re the first person I’ve told besides him.”

“Oh, wow… ”

“I think I conceived a day or two before we lost Sara…I know Mark and I haven’t…we’ve not been together since then.”

“You’ve not?”

Hayley nodded. “I’m not ready.” she said. “I’m so scared I’ll treat the new child like a replacement for Sara. But…here we are. So, I’m going back to work with the Earth end of the Reclamation Project, and Mark’s staying here.”

It was Ava’s turn to put a hand on Hayley’s arm. “Are you two..?”

“We’re…” Hayley squeezed back some impending tears with a forced smile. “We’re fine. Really. He gets angry sometimes, I’ve said some things that…We scare Jack sometimes. But we always cuddle and talk it out afterwards. In a way, I’m glad the baby’s come along. It’ll give us both something to work on for the future. Maybe that and a little distance will help.”

She wiped her eyes. “Come on, you came here for advice. Is…did I help?”

Ava nodded. “You helped a lot.” she promised. “I just have one question left, really.”

“Sure.”

“How will I know if Adam wants to?”

Hayley giggled. “Honey, with boys? It’s so easy to tell."

“Be serious.” Ava protested.

“I was!” Hayley assured her. “But the simplest way is to just ask him. Failing that, if you want to be sure…well, if you make it obvious that you want him, then you’ll know soon enough either way.”

“So…how do I make it obvious?”

Hayley laughed. “Go into his room wearing some perfume and one of his T-shirts and nothing else, kiss him, then grab his wrist and put his hand on your butt.” she said. “He’d have to be dead not to get that message."

“But what if-?”

Hayley interrupted her, patiently. “Ava. Sweetie. Everything after that point is for you and him, okay? There’s no script. Just talk to one another. Tell him how you feel, tell him what you want to do, tell him what you want him to do, ask him what he wants…That’s the most important thing, okay? Communication."

“That sounds…awkward.” Ava was blushing.

“It will be. Forget what it’s like in movies, sex is always at least a little bit awkward. Your first time most of all. Just…live with that and try to have fun.”

“…Thanks, Hayley.”

“No; thank you. It’s good to…" she’d been about to say something about falling back into that mother role, but decided against it. “…to be able to give advice.” she finished.

Ava smiled and gave her a little hug. She left the house looking much more relaxed than she had entered it.

For her part, Hayley was surprised to find there was a little warm coal of happiness deep inside her again. As soon as Ava was out of the way, she sat down and wept, happily.

Owen Powell

“So…what am I going to be doing?” Adam was asking, as Powell entered the gym. Legsy hadn’t, as predicted, been happy about giving Adam a 'taster’, but the young man was persuasive and knew his own mind.

The sergeant just picked up the rucksack that had been leaning against the wall behind him, hoisting it easily in one hand. “You’re going to run around the gym wearing this.” he said.

“Okay…” Adam turned around. “How heavy is--oof!"

“Do up that one around your waist…and that one across your chest. Pull ’em tight…no, tighter than that, come on! There you are.” Legsy instructed, until the pack was strapped tight to Adam’s body. He gave it an experimental shake, yanking the teenager around. “Good?”

Adam nodded, though his expression had an edge of trepidation to it now. “Good.”

“…Well, what are you waiting for then?” Legsy demanded. Adam made an 'oh, right' face and set off at a jog.

“Is that what you call running?” Legsy shouted after him. “Come on, you’re here to train, boyo!"

Adam nodded and gained some speed.

"Your crippled old man runs faster than that, come on!" Legsy spurred him. Powell ambled across the gym as the kid found his third gear and started to actually run round the gym.

"That bag won’t get lighter if you slow down, pal!" Legsy called, then noticed his commanding officer and stood to attention. “Captain.”

“Not a bad start.” Powell observed, waving at him to stand easy. Adam was in athletic shape at least. He wasn’t a fast runner, and probably never would be, but after a little encouragement he was doing a pace that should at least spare him the indignity of being the slowest trainee when he got to basic.

“Don’t let him hear you say that, sir.” Legsy admonished him, then raised his voice again. "You’ll have to bloody SHAVE by the time you’re done at this rate, come on!"

“How heavy is that bag, anyway?"

“Fifteen kilos.” Legsy said.

“You’re starting the kid out on tab weight?”

“If he’s going for PJ, sir…faster boyo, come on!…then fuck aye I’m starting him there." Legsy told him. “Besides, he’s stronger than he looks.”

Powell watched Adam piston along, already drenched in sweat and red as a forge. “You know training better than me.” he conceded.

He lurked against the wall and watched as Legsy cajoled, spurred and berated Adam into keeping up the pace, verbally goading the boy to keep putting one foot in front of the other, clicking the little counter in his hand every time Adam made it back past the start line.

It wasn’t long before the exertion began to really catch up, though. Adam’s steps became wobbly, his rhythm faltered. He was practically on the edge of falling over when he passed the start line again and Legsy finally blew his whistle.

They let him rest and had a quick conversation.

“Well?” Powell asked.

“Look at this.” Legsy showed him the counter.

Powell arched an eyebrow at the number on it. “Really?”

“Stronger than he looks, like I said. And he’s got more in him, too. Reckon he could stand up and do maybe even half as many again.”

“You’re sure?”

“Fuck aye.” Legsy agreed. “Especially if we can find his superman button.”

“His…hmm.” Powell rubbed his chin. “Mind if I-?”

“Be my guest.”

They knocked fists together, and Powell took his time ambling over to where Adam was still lying spread-eagled on the heavy pack.

“Enjoying your nap?” he asked.

Adam’s breathing was much improved even by the time Powell reached him, though the lad was clearly in a lot of discomfort as he tried to raise his head. “How did I do?” he asked.

“Do? You’re not done yet, mate.”

“…you’re kidding?!"

“Nope.”

“But…how… ? Everything hurts!"

“Is that right? Fine, that’s nowt to be worried about.” Powell reassured him. “You can lie there a bit longer, but while you’re at it, I want you to imagine the future.”

“Okay…?”

“Imagine…Adam Ares, seventy years from now, dying peacefully in hospital, surrounded by his beautiful wife and beautiful kids and beautiful grandkids. Idyllic, right? A warm hand in his, and his family all about him, he closes his eyes and slips away…and there they are.”

Adam just gaped at him, confused.

“The ghosts.” Powell clarified. “The ghosts of all the people he could have saved but didn’t, because 'everything hurt' seventy years earlier. Every life lost because young Adam Ares didn’t have it in him to push on through the pain. Every soul he has to look in the eye and know that their lives mattered less to him than a little fookin’ comfort."

Adam’s breathing slowed hugely as he sat there for a second with his mouth still open.

Then, without a word, he rolled over, hauled himself to his feet, and began to run.

Date Point: 4y11m1w AV
Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, the Far Reaches.

Adam Ares

"Happy Birthday!!"

The now familiar soreness and weakness in Adam’s legs were promptly forgotten when he found Ava and his dad waiting for him in the front room, and a wrapped present and some cards on the table. Not to mention the cake.

“Seventeen years.” Gabriel said, hauling himself upright and giving Adam a heartfelt hug. “It’s been a wild ride, amigo."

"Asi es la vida." Adam returned the hug. “I thought you were back on Earth for the Lehmann case?”

“And miss this? I’d have beat them out the way with my cane if they’d tried to make me stay.” Gabriel scoffed.

"Gracias." Adam meant it, too. He sat down next to Ava, who kissed him lightly on the cheek. “Presents? I’m not used to birthday presents.”

“You’re not?” Ava asked.

“Well, Christmas in three days, usually I just get a big Christmas present, you know?”

“Well, what do you get the man who’s leaving everything behind?” Gabriel asked.

“…good question.” Adam said, eyeing the gifts. Gabriel just grinned and lit the candles--two large numbers, rather than a field of seventeen small ones. “Blow them out and you’ll see.” he promised.

Adam dutifully did so, and Ava slid the gifts in front of him as Gabriel set about cutting the cake.

“That one’s from the school.” she said as Adam selected it. He fingered the odd, lumpy package for a second, then gave up on identification and ripped it open.

“Sandals and a…toiletries bag?” He opened it and peered inside, finding an assortment of hygiene products and some deodorant.

“They did some research and apparently you’ll need all of those in training.” Ava explained.

“Huh. Thoughtful of them.” Adam set them aside, pleased with the gift.

Ava gave him an embarrassed smile when he opened her gift. “You’re allowed so little and…y’know, the school had already got you everything, so, I, uh…kind of donated to charity in your name.” she confessed. “I’m sorry.”

“WaterAid?” Adam read the card.

“Yeah. They say the amount I gave should save a few lives…” she smiled nervously.

Adam kissed her. “Good gift.” he reassured her, and selected the card from Gabriel.

A photograph fell out of it when he opened it. When he picked it up, his mouth opened slightly. “How did you-?”

“Facebook.” Gabriel said. “Kind of a…reminder of more innocent days.”

Adam nodded, realising that it was the first time he’d seen his own mother’s face in months. Luiza Ares nee Ortega hadn’t been an easy woman to get along with. In fact some days she’d been the bane of his life. But the photograph really was a happy one, showing off an all-too-rare smile that made it very obvious why Gabriel had ever fallen in love with her, and it reminded Adam just for a second that he really did miss her.

He wasn’t sure how long he studied the print before he set it down. It was probably only seconds--it felt like weeks.

He reached over and hugged Gabriel. “Love you, dad.”

“Love you too, man.” Gabriel said.

Date Point: Christmas Day, 4y11m2w AV
Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

Christmas on Cimbrean seemed set to become something a little different to the small, family affair that Ava had been used to on Earth. Given that Christians were decidedly in the minority among the citizenry of Folctha, it was hardly surprising that there was a noticeable shortage of nativities and hymns, too.

None of the small congregation at that morning’s nondenominational mass had apparently minded. In fact, the sermon had stressed Matthew 6:5 and its implications for a Christian abroad in a predominantly secular galaxy. Not that you should keep your faith to yourself, as such, so much as that your faith was yours, your own little candle to carry. Giving you light and warmth, but also representing a burden of care, not to let it die and not to burn down your relationships with.

That…relaxed approach didn’t exactly gel with what Ava had learned in Sunday school. The ideas of Hell and Salvation had always scared her, while, insofar as Christianity as it was practiced in Folctha could be called a “sect”, their sect’s focus on personal fulfillment in this life through a loving relationship with God, rather than expectation of reward or a stay of punishment in the next through a regime of worship, spoke to her.

The consensus at discussion over coffee that had followed had broadly been that in fact a Christian on Cimbrean was free to have a much more personal relationship with God precisely for those reasons. Most of them confessed to feeling more spiritually fulfilled than they ever had on Earth. A few expressed doubts about “reinventing” Christianity, but even those voices were simply voices of caution, rather than rejection.

The hymns made her feel warm inside, as did Reverend Joanne White’s hand on the top of Ava’s head during the blessing.

It was like stepping into another world when they left the Faith Center to join in the secular festival outside. The size of the cargo jump array had limited the size of the tree they could import, but it still formed a towering centerpiece to the town park, decked in lights and ornaments fashioned from spaceship wreckage or from the by now thoroughly extinct Pinkwood tree.

There was no snow, of course. In fact, it was a warm Cimbrean summer’s day, hence the adoption of a number of Australian Christmas traditions, including bikinis, barbecues and Bacardi. A dozen engineers from the Byron motor pool--a motley bunch who had taken the name "The Alleged Orchestra" for their performance--were set up and vigorously arranging every seasonal tune they could think of on the fly, beating the music into shape until it vaguely fit their unique instrumentation, which included a Diddley-Bow, a metallophone made from a set of wrenches, and a Cello that had been recycled out of a couple of beer kegs. The result was amazingly musical, with a bluesy, jazzy, energetically raw twist that seemed to be going down well with the revellers.

The Gaoians were watching it all with plain and obvious bemusement, she noticed. There were a lot of them now, all males, and all seriously throwing themselves into the practice of meditation with the vigor of a man helping his child build sandcastles who’d suddenly uncovered a pirate chest. They were sipping mulled wine and probably enjoying themselves, though they were keeping out of the way.

There was so much to take in, none of it guided by any specific tradition, but informed by hundreds. People bringing out their presents to put them in little piles under the tree. The smells of the town feast being prepared, spices and dancing and an impromptu a capella rendition of “Fairytale of New York”, Sir Jeremy Sandy in a Santa outfit, the Soldiers versus Civilians tug-o’-war…

Hayley and Mark sitting in a corner, his arms around her waist from behind, watching their son--Sara’s little brother Jack--play with his classmates with strange expressions that were equal parts happiness and sadness.

There was a sudden pair of arms around her own waist. “Can I interrupt?” Adam asked her.

Ava glanced down at the camera. She hadn’t even been entirely conscious of taking the pictures. “Sorry.”

“Don’t be.” he took her hand and led her back towards the Alleged Orchestra, where people were whirling and skipping in circles to the music, linking arms, bouncing around one another and then spinning off to join up with a new partner.

She couldn’t keep up with him--over the last month he’d gone from quite athletic to military fit under Legsy’s watchful guidance--but she didn’t quit the dance when she couldn’t go on any longer. She just de-orbited to its outskirts, to clap along and cheer and whoop as he enjoyed himself, occasionally letting herself take a picture.

It was just the start of a day that lasted forever.

Date Point: Boxing Day, 4y11m2w AV

Adam Ares

Adam wasn’t yet asleep, but it still took him a couple of seconds to register the knock on his door.

He sat up a bit “Ava?”

She called through the door. “Can I come in?”

“Sure!”

She’d left the hall light on and leaned against the door frame, backlit by it, and Adam had to employ some willpower not to stare. She was wearing what looked a lot like one of his t-shirts, a thin white one. The shirt itself wasn’t blocking any of the light from behind her, and the varying depth of shadow her body made under it was…

He sat up some more and leaned forward to try and hide what the view did to him, discreetly bunching a little more blanket on his lap.

There wasn’t anywhere else to look though, without actually looking away from her. If he looked down then he had to contend with her legs, and as for her face…there was an expression there he couldn’t really read--a dark and intense one.

“Hey, uh… ” He said. “You okay?”

“It’s gone midnight.” she said.

“Oh…uh, happy birthday.”

She looked like she was about to say something. Then she shook her head, stepped onto the bed and hugged him. “Can I sleep here tonight?” She asked.

He scooted over and she dug herself under the blankets and wriggled into his chest. He smoothed her hair out of the way. “You okay?”

“…I just…” She looked up and kissed him. “It’s going to be tough, not having you around.”

He put a hand on the back of her head and held her. “That’s going to be the toughest bit.” he agreed.

“You’ll write me?”

“Every chance I get.”

She puffed out a huge rush of air into his chest and snuggled up against him even closer. “I love you.”

It was a phrase they rarely uttered. A vulnerable, weak little phrase, really. But that just meant it had so much more meaning for them. “And I love you.” he promised.

He could feel her smile against his chest, and the way she relaxed, and fell asleep.

She was still there in the morning when he woke up.

Date Point: 4y11m4w AV
Seattle, Washington, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

Leaving home had been hard.

Travelling alone and sleeping alone in an unfamiliar hotel room in an unfamiliar city full of the kind of traffic that reminded him painfully of San Diego, and which he’d grown accustomed to the absence of in Folctha, hadn’t made for a good night’s sleep.

That, and it was cold. January in Seattle versus early summer in Folctha had been an unwelcome introduction to the joys of a freezing grey drizzle that seemed to come right off Puget Sound, bent on freezing the whole city. He’d been tempted to dive for the warmth of his hotel room the second he got off the plane, but instead he used the hours of daylight and went straight from the airport to the USAF recruiting office.

That part turned out to be easy. He was in and out inside an hour or so, having practically had some documents thrust into his hands along with instructions to attend the Military Entrance Processing Station the next morning. Apparently, the recruiter had been impressed.

For lack of anything better to do, he took a walk and saw the sights. He’d have preferred to jog, but he’d worn his good chinos to make an impression for the recruiter.

He didn’t watch the people at first. He watched the architecture, and the city, taking in the square glassy greyness and the scratchy trees that were no more than bare twigs in the winter, the overcast-sky openness of the street plan and the whirr of bicycles. The traffic was familiar, but the city it crawled around in couldn’t have been more different. Cold though it was, he could see that the plants which seemed to be all over everything would actually fit here, rather than being aliens imported and maintained at great effort.

Of course, Seattle meant Starbucks. He knew that much, and eventually he dropped in on the one on 5th avenue, in the shadow of the monolithic black Columbia Center.

Mercifully, it was quite warm inside, and he shucked off his jacket--the rugged, all-weather one that most Cimbrean colonists had, with the “From Ashes” patch that only Ava shared. He tugged at the T-shirt he was wearing underneath, aware that it was an old one that, nowadays, was stretched tight across his chest and shoulders. It was a good shirt for showing off the gym- fit physique he’d picked up training with Legsy, but not exactly comfortable.

The people-watching skills that Gabriel had taught him prodded him a second or so later, alerting him to a change.

It was subtle. The young mother in line in front of him had shepherded her kids forward and was now keeping them in front of the stroller. The older man in the grey suit next to him scooted his chair forward and around the table a little. The Barista, on the other hand, was almost certainly sneaking sly glances at him down the counter.

He tried to ignore it, studying the menu as they crawled toward the counter, but it was difficult to ignore that the people who joined the line behind him left arm’s length at least, nor the snippet of conversation he could just hear from a middle-aged couple by the door.

'No, I don’t think so…he doesn’t have any tattoos…'

That…shocked him. Upset and surprised him. He fumbled his way through a clumsy order for a simple Latte, left the change for a tip, and made himself scarce.

His return walk to the hotel was a solemn and thoughtful one which he spent, rather than looking up at the buildings, looking down at his feet, lost in thought and trying to ignore the way people veered out of his path on the sidewalk.

In the end he spent the evening lurking in his hotel room playing free games on his phone.

The weather, if anything, got even more dismal overnight, which was in its own way fortunate because he barely slept, and an early morning jog in the bracing Washington weather did more to get him alert and ready than all the coffee in Colombia.

Once wearing clean and dry clothes, he caught a cab to the MEPS, which turned out to be just one small part of a huge building behind a wall of hedging and trees, by the railroad track and just north of the airport.It wasn’t what he’d pictured, but he trusted the cab driver, so he refused to allow himself to dither outside--he headed straight in after paying the fare.

Inside, it wasn’t what he’d anticipated either. He’d envisioned more of the posters and macho imagery that had decorated the recruiting office.

What he instead got was a reception desk in a fairly bland office space. There were flags and crests up and a general clean and efficient air, but if not for the uniforms he might have been in a civilian workplace. The reception desk didn’t actually have a human on it, just a series of touchscreens which, on being prodded, walked him through a quick and simple series of questions about who he was and what he planned on becoming, asked him to scan the barcode on the form the recruiter had given him, and then directed him to a printer which spat out a sticker with a QR code and his name on it, thanked him, and directed him to wait. There were a lot of chairs for that--Adam paced, pausing to grab meagre cups of water from the cooler in the corner. He’d barely been there for five minutes before he started to feel like a zoo lion.

He might have been there half the day before anything interesting started to happen. A handful of people were sitting and fidgeting alongside him, most about his age and with their parents in tow, before he was called and directed to a station where he filled in a form. Then he went back and waited. Then he was called to another station, where they asked him some questions. Then he went back and waited, again and again.

By the time it was done he felt both as if he’d never stopped moving, and also as if nothing at all had happened. He had no idea if it was afternoon or full evening yet, but eventually he was sat down opposite a handsome man in a blue shirt with the five stripes of a technical sergeant on his sleeve and the surname “Foster” on his chest, and had his hand shaken.

“So. You want to be a pararescueman?” the sergeant asked, sitting down.

“I do.” Adam agreed.

“Why?”

“The unit motto speaks to me. 'That others may live’." When Foster just waited patiently, he felt drawn to elaborate. “I’ve…I’m from San Diego originally, I’ve lost people, and I guess I want to keep others from having to experience that.”

“Have you considered alternatives?”

“Sure. But that’s my first choice.” Adam said.

“What alternatives did you consider?”

“I guess…security, force protection. Medic…That kinda thing, you know? I was thinking of being a cop like my dad, before I decided to do this.”

“Was there any specific event that changed your mind there?”

Adam nodded. “My friend was murdered. Sara Tisdale? On Cimbrean? I heard it was a big story back here on Earth for a while…”

Foster nodded. “You have my condolences.” he said. “But why did that change your mind about your choice of career?”

Adam took a deep breath, worried that what he was about to say might sound paranoid or crazy and ruin his chances then and there, but Powell’s advice had been impossible to misinterpret--speak honestly, always.

“I think…I think there’s a pattern at work.” he said. “like, everyone knows that San Diego was destroyed by antimatter, it was in the official investigation’s report. But nobody has that much antimatter on Earth, so there have to be aliens involved somehow, and who else would want to sabotage Folctha’s spaceport like the guy who shot Sara was trying to? Well, I think that the military know who’s behind it, and I want in. I want to stop them from hurting anybody else.”

“Hmm.”

Foster stood. “Stand up, let me have a look at you.”

Adam did so.

“look at me.” Foster continued. “Raise your arms above your head.”

Adam did so, patiently awaiting an explanation. He didn’t get one: Foster just gestured toward a pull-up bar. “See that? Get up on it and show me what you’ve got.”

Adam almost laughed. He’d been doing reps alongside Legsy in 1.15G in Folctha’s variable-gravity gym for the last month. He shook his limbs loose, reached up, got his form strictly correct, and set to.

He hadn’t even started to feel the burn yet when Foster interrupted him. “Okay, okay. Get off that thing, put this on and start over."

'This' turned out to be a heavy weighted vest. Adam shrugged it on, got back on the bar, and resumed his pull-ups.

He was finally starting to feel some heat in his muscles when Foster spoke again. “So, why you?”

Adam dropped off the bar and turned to face him. Foster shook his head. “I didn’t tell you to stop, son.” he chided. “Get back up there and keep going.”

“Sorry.”

Foster watched him resume his form. “So…why you?” he asked.

“What do you mean?” Adam asked him.

“It’s a simple question, son. Why you? Why do you think you want this? Why do you think Pararescue is the right one for you?"

“Well, like I said, the motto.”

“Okay, well what makes you think you’re right for Pararescue?.”

Adam’s brow creased as he really started to feel his muscles working. The weighted vest was making all the difference. “I’m going to work damn hard for this.” he said. “if I have to stay on this…” he grunted “…bar ’til I’m twenty to prove that, I damn well will.”

“You think you can work that hard?”

“I know--" the exertion finally started to choke off Adam’s words. “--Yeah. I can.” he finished, between pulls.

Foster nodded again and watched him for a few more before finally raising a hand. “Alright. Rest up.”

Adam lowered himself slowly down this time, and massaged his hands. Foster handed him a glass of cold water as he sat down, which Adam gulped down in one as the sergeant jotted a few short observations.

“Alright, I think I’m done with you for now.” Foster said. “You’ll need to go on through the rest of the MEPS, get your tests done and all that stuff, but assuming there’s no problems there, you’ll be coming back here tomorrow to speak with the special forces recruiter.”

Adam beamed. “Thank you!” he said.

“How’d you get here, cab? Where are you staying?”

Adam told him, and Foster nodded. “Right. We’ll pick up the bill from here on in, as well as transport. I’ll see you later on today once you’re done with all your tests.”

The rest of the day passed in a blur for Adam. He was measured, weighed, had samples of blood, hair and saliva taken, asked to walk around with one foot on tip-toe, had puffs of air shot into his eyes by a machine, spent some minutes with another machine pressing a button whenever he saw lights in his peripheral vision, a few minutes in a dental chair, filled in forms, answered questions, took tests. Even the businesslike intimacy of the full medical examination didn’t faze him.

The important part was, that he was past the first hurdle.

Technical Sergeant George Foster

“Okay, next up for review is…Adam Ares, permanent address…Twenty Delaney Row, Folctha, Cimbrean. Huh.”

“Yeah, we’ve got ourselves a space cadet here.” Somebody joked.

“Space cadet he may be, but he’s the real deal.” Foster commented. “I put him on the bar, stopped counting at fifty. He says he was training in supergravity for a month before coming down here. Looks like the British special forces garrison there took him under their wing.”

“Their CO gave him a reference.”

“What’s it say?”

“Pretty typical British, really.” The sergeant with that file examined the letter. “To.. blah, blah…’I’m sending this young man your way with my professional opinion that he may be of some use to you. Yours sincerely, Captain Owen Powell' et cetera. End letter." She smiled, folding it up again. “You’ve got to love the Brits, right?”

“Isn’t Powell the SBS officer behind the SOR program?” Foster asked. “If he is, then that’s a glowing reference right there."

“That’s right.”

“Well his opinion seems on the money. The kid’s already fit and strong and he’s got exactly the right build for a PJ. So…Unless there’s anything wrong with him, Doc?”

The chief medical examiner studied his own copy of the candidate’s notes. “His bloodwork showed a lot of testosterone…” He commented. “…but I chalk that up to him being young, fit and eager to prove himself. I see no reason to suspect steroids or substance abuse. His mother died young in the San Diego blast so there’s no way to know his medical history from her…There’s a history of Glaucoma and Coronary Artery Disease from his paternal grandparents, but his ECG and intraocular pressures were all fine today. No concerns.”

Foster turned to the staff psychologist, Lieutenant Schoemann. “Doctor?”

“…He’s angry. Grieving and angry.” Schoemann concluded, examining his notes. “But he’s channelling it well, it’s motivating him healthily. He’s got a long- term steady girlfriend and he’s come to us. That shows drive and an ability to emotionally commit, and that month of hard training proves that this wasn’t a spur-of-the-moment decision, he’s thought about this and prepared for it. He’s…maybe not the most introspective young man I’ve ever met, but he’s not lacking in intelligence…Overall he’s calm, pleasant, confident, intelligent and well-adjusted, with plenty of healthy aggression. I think he’s an excellent candidate.”

“Guess he’s one for you, then.” Foster commented, turning to Master Sergeant Wood, the special forces recruiter.

“Absolutely.” Wood agreed. “He’s a strong PJ candidate, but he’s maybe even good enough for the SOR program.”

“You think?”

“It can’t be an accident that this Captain Powell gave him a reference like that.” Wood noted. “We’ll see how he does tomorrow.”

They moved on to the next candidate.

Date Point: First Contact Day, 5 years AV
Seattle, Washington, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

A car came to pick him up, rather than the taxi he’d taken the day before. It wasn’t raining this morning, but the wind was still cold enough to sting the ears, even through his Gore-Tex beanie.

The driver parked up and got out of the car, which surprised him, as did the fact that he was wearing sports gear rather than USAF blue. “Adam Ares?”

“That’s me.”

The driver shook his hand. “Master Sergeant Tony Wood, USAF special forces recruiter.” he said, producing a card to verify his identity.

“Oh! I, uh…thought I’d be meeting you at the MEPS, Master Sergeant.”

“You can just call me Sergeant, son. I figured I’d get a look at you in motion, you up to go for a jog?”

“Sure.” Adam had already taken a morning jog, but it had been barely more than a warmup and stretch, anticipating a day of being put through his paces. He suspected that Wood had something a little more strenuous in mind.

And so it proved. That month of training with Legsy paid off--jogging on Earth with no load was different to jogging on Cimbrean with a heavy bag to compensate for the gravity difference. In many ways it was easier, but Wood was a tall man with a long, easy stride that ate up the ground, forcing Adam to take three steps for every two of the sergeant’s just in order to keep pace.

Weirdly, the questions he’d been preparing for didn’t materialise. They just did a double loop round some of the interesting parts of Downtown before returning to the car, and Adam’s ego wilted a little when he noticed that Wood, although he was steaming up the air with regular, working breaths, had obviously found the run much easier than he had. Clearly, he still had a lot of fitness to gain to really make the grade.

“Not bad. Y’ain’t fast but next to some of the other kids I’ve seen…” Wood congratulated him.

“Thank you, Sergeant.”

Wood thumb-pointed to the hotel. “If you want to change, I’ll wait in the car.”

“Can I shower too?”

“Sure. Make it quick though, we’ve got a lot to cram in today.”

Adam nodded and ran back to his room for a quick rinse, dry and change job. Sure enough, when he got back to the car, Wood was pocketing an old-fashioned digital stopwatch.

He made a mental note: 'Everything is a test.’

Wood didn’t comment as he climbed in, just put an arm on the back of the seat to turn and reverse out of the parking bay, then merged into city traffic.

“So. Pararescue.” he said. “I was a Combat Controller myself, the brother unit, but I got a lot of respect for the PJs. The training’s hell, but they do a heck of a job.”

“Captain Powell said they call it 'Superman School’." Adam volunteered.

“That they do.” Wood took a right turn. “Now, in all honesty, this is something I don’t say to most candidates, I think you’ve got what it takes to pass it.” he turned right again.

“Thank you.” Adam tried not to smile.

“Well, hear me out…” Wood took a third right turn. Adam wasn’t sure if he had a destination in mind--the route was such an inefficient one that he suspected the sergeant was just driving for the sake of keeping them moving. Fortunately he didn’t turn right again, but sat back and relaxed on a long straight.

“…What if I could offer you something more?” he asked.

“More?”

“Check in the glove box, there’s a tablet in there.”

Adam did so. When he swiped to turn it on, it filled with what was clearly a form of some kind. “What’s this?”

“Non-Disclosure Agreement.” Wood revealed. “You need to read it in full, sign and give a verbal signature, but the gist of it is that what I’m about to tell you is classified information and you’ll be liable to federal prosecution if you discuss it with unauthorised persons.”

“Okay…” Adam read the document in full, twice, then wrote and signed his name and, when prompted, carefully enunciated the script that the form displayed for him. “I, Adam Miguel Ángel Ares, solemnly affirm that I agree to be bound by the terms and conditions of this non-disclosure agreement.”

Wood nodded. “There’s a program in the works, something that your Captain Powell had a hand in masterminding.” he said.

“There is?”

“Yup. There was a space battle over Cimbrean about four months ago, you know about it?”

Adam nodded. “Yeah.”

“Well, Captain Powell, and the commanding officers of the two ships involved, HMS Myrmidon and HMS Caledonia, they made a recommendation to the British Ministry of Defence that specialist skills and training were going to be required to form the basis of infantry operations in space. The MoD decided to share the idea with the DoD, and from there it got bumped all around the Coalition and it’s becoming a joint Allied venture."

He took a left turn. “It’s being called the Spaceborne Operations Regiment, or SOR. Currently it doesn’t even really exist--it doesn’t have any men, the spacesuits they’d wear are still being designed…but we know two things about it. The first being that its primary mandate will be frontline combat operations against the alien organisation which, you’re right, nuked San Diego and murdered your friend.”

“So it’s real.”

“Yup. That’s as much as I can tell you for now; even under NDA, you’re not cleared for the details. But you’re right, we’re fighting a war right now, and the SOR are going to be the guns in that fight.”

“…Alright. What’s the other thing?”

“Training will be four years. Minimum. And you’ll be under contract for at least four years after that, so this would be at least an eight year commitment, if you took it.”

“That’s…an awful long time.”

“Yup.” Wood agreed. “We had to jump through hoops to get that contract approved.”

“Would they be doing stuff other than fighting these aliens?”

“Anti-piracy operations, counter-Hunter operations…Most of the time you’d be operating exactly like any Pararescueman under the aegis of the USAF, so search and rescue of liferafts and broken ships, humanitarian aid, emergency medicine. Finally, you’d be a qualified astronaut and that means you might wind up spending some time on the ISS in some capacity.”

“Anything else?”

Wood’s jaw moved, thoughtfully. “Yes.” he said eventually. “We think we’re going to have to put the candidates on an extremely intensive physical track."

“You are?”

“An armored spacesuit is going to be dang heavy.” Wood explained. “Every trick to make it less so is being considered, but the fact is that Spaceborne Operators are going to have to be strong, and you especially if you’re falling into the role of Spaceborne Pararescue. You’ll need to be able to carry all your gear plus one of your buddies with HIS gear and suit across long distances, and given the weights involved, we’re not actually sure that getting you that strong that quickly will even be possible, let alone wise.”

“It can be done, though?”

“Sure. The numbers are within the limits of what’s humanly possible, but if we’re going to get you that strong inside the duration of your training…At the very least it’ll be difficult, and probably quite dangerous.”

Adam sat quietly and ignored whatever route Wood was taking for some minutes. “I’ll…need to think about it.” he decided eventually.

“Good.” Wood nodded. “If you jumped at the chance, I’d have turned you down on the spot. You’re going to need to be sensible, not impulsive.”

“Test passed, huh?”

Wood laughed. “You passed that one, yeah.” he agreed. “The decision’s not going to finally land on you for months yet, I just wanted to give you time to process it.”

Adam recognised the trees and rail tracks outside the MEPS as they rounded a corner. “So, what are we doing for the rest of the day?”

Wood sniffed a little amused noise. “More tests.” he said.

“Everybody present? Very well.”

Adam straightened. The MEPS had a little ceremonial room, decorated in wood panelling and rich blue carpet with a selection of flags at the front of the room on a little dais. He’d been handed a little card full of instructions and the Oath of Enlistment as he entered, and had taken the time to read it. Some of the others hadn’t.

Now, there was an officer standing on the dais, getting their attention.

“Gentlemen,” he said “You will shortly be called to read aloud the Oath of Enlistment, as written on the card presented to you. There’s an alternative secular version printed on the reverse of the card for those who prefer, and I’d like to remind you all that the first amendment of the very constitution that you will now be pledging to support and defend guarantees the right of all citizens to be free in their own beliefs.”

He surveyed them all. “This Oath is binding. Once you have taken it, you will have formally enlisted in the United States Air Force, so if anybody’s getting cold feet, now’s the time to say so.”

Nobody did. Adam flipped the card over, double-checked its content, and nodded to himself, mentally preparing.

The officer smiled, “In that case, we’ll be going in alphabetical order…Ares, Adam.”

Adam stepped forward.

“Would you like a Bible, son?”

“No thank you, sir.”

“Then raise your hand and recite the Oath.”

Adam did so.

“I, Adam Miguel Angel Ares, do solemnly affirm that I will…” he checked the card “…will support and defend the Constitution of the United States against all enemies, foreign and domestic; that I…will bear true faith and allegiance to the same; and that…” he checked the card again “and that I will obey the orders of the President of the United States and the orders of the officers appointed over me, according to regulations and the, uh…the Uniform Code of Military Justice. By my word am I bound.”

The officer extended a hand, smiling warmly. “Welcome to the Air Force, son.”

“Thank you, sir.”

He stepped over to where the officer indicated and waited, not hearing as "Himura, Daniel" was called.

There was no going back, now.

Date Point: 12 hours later
Lackland Air Force Base, San Antonio, Texas, USA, Earth

It wasn’t exactly night-time when the bus arrived at Lackland AFB, but the sun was definitely down, leaving only a kind of glowing blue-blackness where the stars would soon be. It was a warm night, FAR warmer than the early January climate he’d been exposed to in British Columbia and Washington. It felt more like Cimbrean, in fact, if not for the gravity. San Antonio in January had a lot in common with Folctha in summer.

“How the hell big is this base?” somebody muttered after the fifth minute of the bus rounding corners and driving past darkened buildings. Adam guessed they were already being hazed, the bus winding around to disorientate them and make the place seem bigger than it really was. He didn’t try to say as much, just grabbed his bag, ready to leap into action the second the shouting started.

And start it did. They pulled up outside a low building, the doors opened, and three men leapt up the stairs and began bawling threats and instructions at the trainees. Some of the smack-talk was so absurd and witty that Adam almost wanted to laugh. He resisted the crazy impulse, knowing it would only get him into trouble if he did.

He was the third or fourth off the bus, lining up alongside the others--he’d learned their names on the way down but right now it didn’t seem so important to remember them as to try and form a roughly straight line, and set his bag down in front of him, upright against his legs.

"Trainee, you pick that bag up and hold it until I say otherwise!"

Feeling silly and self-conscious, Adam snapped out a “Yes sir!” and grabbed it, hoisting it easily onto his shoulders. Silly or not, whether or not it passed muster as a response, one of the other trainees snickered at him for it, and promptly got rounded on. Adam just stood there, staring directly forward and holding his bag, trying not to attract any attention.

A face was suddenly inches from his own "You play any musical instruments, trainee?" it demanded.

“No, sir!” The face disappeared.

There was a lot of shouting, much of it…not insulting, but certainly calculated to shake any illusions he may have had about being confident or ready for this. He tried to stay focused in case any of it was directed at him. The fact that nobody else rolled up and roared at him suggested that he succeeded there, and it wasn’t long before they were bawled into filing into the building, assigned their seats at deafening volume, told to stand up, told to sit down.

Adam could focus on nothing other than making sure he heard and obeyed any order that was directed at him, responding to them as well he could. It wasn’t long before he found himself at a mess table with a tray in front of him. There wasn’t much on it--a sandwich, a bag of potato chips and a small carton of orange juice. the sandwich turned out to be frozen solid, the chips were plain and unsalted, and the juice was watery and unpalatable. He forced it down as best he could anyway, polishing off the juice and chips before he was halfway through the sandwichcicle.

There followed a gauntlet of paperwork and questions, being handed things, having things taken off him, being shouted at for reasons he couldn’t quite fathom, responding with reflexive apologies or acknowledgements.

He managed to retain which Training Flight he was in, at least. Not that he had a choice--he was forced to repeat the information so many times he doubted he’d ever forget it. It almost came as a surprise when he sat down on the bus to the dormitory and found that nobody was shouting for a few quiet minutes.

“What the shit have we got ourselves into?” the trainee next to him muttered rhetorically, sotto voce. Adam didn’t answer. He just gripped his bag and waited for the next order.

Out of the bus, lined up, given a few rules, into the dorms, picking a bed. He spent five minutes with his finger pressed to his locker, repeating the number on it until the knowledge was carved into his brain, never to be forgotten. It was the only moment that stood out of a blur of orders, instructions, beratements. He span through a cold shower in seconds, liquid soap in hand. Get wet, step out to let somebody else use it, lather up, step back under to rinse off, all the time being screamed at to move faster, faster, faster!

When the blur ended, he was lying in bed wearing uncomfortable new clothes and listening to the others around him try to get comfortable. He was pretty sure at least a couple were fighting back tears. Plenty, he knew, were repeating that same question to themselves that he’d heard on the bus: 'What have we got ourselves into?'

Adam didn’t wonder. Twelve hours of travel and the emotional jolt of leaving Ava behind had taken so much out of him that he was the first to fall asleep.

Date Point: 5y AV
Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

Banging on the door summoned Ava out of bed, and she threw on a bathrobe to answer it.

Cimbrean didn’t exactly have a postal service so much as it had Logan Brown, one of the schoolkids who took it on himself to hand-deliver any parcels and letters that came through the Jump Array on any given morning.

“Morning, Ava!” he chirped, handing her an envelope covered in USPS stamps and with the slightly worn feel of having travelled a long way in slightly careless hands. As soon as he was gone, she practically shredded it in getting the envelope open and sat down to read.

It wasn’t a long letter, but even so it had a rushed, shaky feel to it. Adam’s handwriting--unsurprisingly, for somebody who’d grown up never really needing it--had never been neat, but now his scrawl was only just legible, and that with some concentration and puzzle-solving.

"Hey Ava.

Not goin to lie this SUCKS I mean I knew it was going to but DAMN!! Its like a movie in here, I thought those movies were bullshit but we just get yelled at and bullied and told we’re stupid and it doesn’t make any sense. Everythings so weird too everyone looks the same same haircut same clothes same everything if they werent all taller than me Id think I was lookin in the mirror everywhere I go.

Powell was right I really didnt kno wat I was getting myself in to im tired all the time I keep being yelld at over nothing like they yell at me for not eating enogh like wtf Im full how do you expect me to eat more theres no room?!

shit they just told me Ive got to put the pen down I love you dont worry ill be okay its just crazy round here.

Love--Adam."

It made for tough reading. She went to school in a low mood.

Date Point: 5y1wAV
Lackland Air Force Base, San Antonio, Texas, USA, Earth.

Adam Ares

"Alright trainees this is your morning wake up call I want you out of those beds and at attention before the end of this sentence, Get up! Get up and stand at attention!!"

Responding to the daily indignity of being shouted awake had become a reflex, and Adam was already scrambling out from under his blankets by the end of the word “trainees”.

It was only around about the word “beds” that a horribly familiar pressure in his boxer shorts finally infiltrated his awareness as his morning wood made itself known. Several of the rest of the training flight had noticed and were fighting to keep a straight face, while his own face slowly turned pink.

Not for the first time, he regretted accepting the first bunk he’d found, right next to the MTI’s office, because there was no time for it to go down. Technical Sergeant Lake was already progressing down the dorm, on the lookout for ANYTHING he could criticize.

He paused by Adam, who swallowed, awaiting the humiliation that was surely imminent, but instead, Technical Sergeant Lake’s voice was calm and quiet, amused even.

“Trainee, you have my sympathies, but you need to be standing at attention.” he chided, very gently. “So you do that, and you don’t worry about anything else.”

“Yes, SIR!” Adam choked out, and forced himself to stand fully upright, thanking the Lord that nobody, nobody could possibly have remained hard in these circumstances.

Technical Sergeant Lake--who was always thought of and referred to as Technical Sergeant Lake, and addressed with the loudest “SIR!” that the trainee could muster--nodded and carried on, leaving Adam to compose himself.

The next trainee was unfortunate enough to be making a desperate little chewing motion to try and keep a straight face, and Technical Sergeant Lake rounded on him like a terrier on a mouse.

"Trainee, do you find this amusing?!" he demanded, screaming the question at most an inch from the culprit’s nose.

The luckless trainee’s expression sobered instantly. “No, SIR!”

"Were you perhaps trying to get a good look then? Is that the first time you’ve seen a warhorse, Trainee?!"

Adam’s eyes shut themselves of their own accord just for a second, and he knew that his face must have gone as red as tabasco. If the whole base had been hit by a meteorite at that moment, he would have welcomed it.

“N-no--” the trainee began.

"I DID NOT ORDER YOU TO SPEAK, AND IF I HAD I WOULD EXPECT YOU TO SOUND OFF LIKE A MAN!!" Technical Sergeant Lake roared. "Front leaning rest position!"

The trainee instantly hit the floor and held himself there, ready. Technical Sergeant Lake directed a glare around the room that could have boiled steel. "If anybody else cares to comment on your fellow trainee’s gift, get it out of your system!" he ordered. Nobody so much as twitched. "Outstanding! Trainee!" he addressed the young man on the floor. "Push the Earth until I say otherwise!"

He turned to check on Adam, whose composure had now recovered somewhat, grunted, and strolled through the dorm, taking his time over it. "Make your beds!" he ordered. Then, to the trainee on the ground: "Trainee, recover! And since you’re so enamoured of our warhorse here, you can help him make HIS bed first! JUMP TO!!"

Adam threw himself into the chore, grateful for something to do. The relief at being able to finally get started with a day’s training rather than dwell on his embarrassment was huge.

By the time they had showered and there was food in front of him, he’d almost completely forgotten that it had happened.

“So hey, Warhorse.”

Adam’s bunk-mate was John Burgess, and the two had bonded quickly over learning that they shared some San Diego experience. Burgess had lost family to the 'Big One’, the quake that had crippled the south side of Los Angeles in the aftermath of the detonation, when their house had collapsed. He’d been one of the few who had managed to keep a straight face that morning.

“Ah, fuck, you’re not going to start calling me that, are you?”

“Hey, man, it fits! I mean, DAMN! You’re a fuckin’ grower!”

This prompted a round of laughter, cat-calling and good-natured hollering, while Adam was yanked back to the morning’s embarrassment with a cringe. “Oh fuck, come on, really?" he protested.

Burgess just grinned. “I’m just sayin’ man, no wonder your girl writes you so much!”

“Fuck you, man.” Adam told him, though it was said with a smile.

“No, please!” Burgess threw up his hands in mock defense. “I wouldn’t survive!”

“You’re one to talk!” one of the others chimed in. “We’ve all seen you in the shower, the fuck are you smuggling in that sack, grapefruits?”

“Man, they ain’t that big!"

Adam snorted. “Like fuck they aren’t. You used to pitch for your school team, right? We should start calling you Baseball.”

Burgess frowned at him. "No!" he asserted.

“Too fucking late, brother.” one of the others asserted. “You call him Warhorse, you get called Baseball. All’s fair in love and war.”

There was general snickering at that one as the newly-christened 'Baseball' wilted. “…shit.” he declared.

Adam laughed. Being able to share the experience of an embarrassing nickname was taking some of the sting out. “Guess we’d better get used to it.” he said.

Date Point: 5y1w4d AV
Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

As Cimbrean’s population had ballooned with the influx of Byron workers, the school had expanded with it, hiring a second teacher and splitting into three “grades”. The oldest of which, for the time being, consisted solely of Ava. It was a bit lonely at the top, but the lack of distraction had allowed her to really focus on her studies.

Still, she was grateful for being checked up on. Jessica Olmstead had assumed responsibility for the middle group and mostly left Ava to educate herself, intervening only to recommend a syllabus and make sure that everything was going well--mostly, what lessons she gave to Ava these days revolved around study techniques and how to learn and self-organise, rather than conveying subject-specific information.

“Is that another letter from Adam?” she asked, sitting down.

Ava nodded. “Yeah, he gets to send me one a week, this is the fourth one. Logan delivered it on the way in to school.”

“It’s a shame you can’t have phone calls.”

“Yeah. I really miss just hearing his voice…” Ava looked at the letter, longingly.

“Could I-?” Jessica asked. “I mean, not if it’s too personal, but I’d like to know how he’s getting on.”

Ava nodded, knowing that Adam’s letters never contained anything embarrassingly intimate, and she slit the letter open with a fingernail, unfolding it onto the desk.

"Hey Ava" she read aloud. "I think I’m starting to do okay now. Our TI said on like day one that if he was using the word stupid it’s because we’re doing stupid stuff, and that’s really started to sink in now, I’m starting to get it."

"Things aren’t what you’d call easy, but we’ve kind of got into the rhythm now. There’s no time to stop, everything’s all go, there’s no downtime, and whenever I get to feeling like I really want just a few minutes to relax, we just get pushed harder and it turns out I didn’t need the break after all. Nobody’s allowed to hide in the back and let it all happen to other people, I thought I could at first, like if I just shut up and did as I was told I’d breeze through this and not get yelled at, but that doesn’t work because they still pick up on what you’re doing wrong and fix it. They don’t let us coast along, it’s all push, all the time."

And now I actually kind of enjoy being yelled at now. Is that weird? If I’m being yelled at it means I fucked up" she stopped reading and shot a glance at the younger kids. “Uh, sorry Jess.”

Jessica giggled “It’s okay. Go on.”

“…It means I blanked up and I don’t want to blank up. Being yelled at means the TI’s got my back, he wants to help me not blank up in future. So when he yells at me, he’s helping me."

"They’ve made me Guidon bearer, it’s kind of cool but I have to carry this thing on runs and salute with it and it’s heavy as-" she cleared her throat “…as blank."

"That’s my fifteen minutes, lots of love to Dad and even more for you."

Love, Adam."

Jessica sat back. “Wow.” she said. “He sounds…different already.”

“Yeah.” Ava agreed, quietly.

“…are you okay with that?”

Ava folded the letter again. “I guess I have to be.” she said.

Jessica inclined her head--Ava had sounded genuinely philosophical rather than resigned or bitter. “What do you mean?”

“There’s…” Ava sighed, and sat back, running a hand through her hair. “Like, there are so many things I can’t change. I sure as heck couldn’t change Adam’s mind about this, if I could he wouldn’t be Adam. So what’s the point in not being okay with them?"

“That’s…true, I guess.” Jessica conceded.

“Yeah…” Ava looked down at the letter. There was a sharp tap as a wet patch appeared on it and she scrubbed furiously at her face.

“Ava, if you need some time alone… ” Jessica offered.

This earned her a brave little smile, and a headshake. “I’m…No, I just need to, to focus on the things I can change. That’s all."

“…Okay. You let me know if you need anything, okay?”

Ava just nodded her gratitude, set the letter aside, and returned to reading the textbook she’d chosen.

Jessica went to make herself a cup of tea, and didn’t return until she was absolutely certain none of the kids would see that she’d been crying.

"Hey Ava,"

"Big news: I got told today Im going to be honor graduate!"

"Theres so much Id like to write here, about what Ive been through. My head just feels full of ideas all settling into place at last. Theres just no way I could cram it all into 15 minutes so Im not even going to try. Its so weird Week 0 feels like it was yesterday and like it was years ago at the same time I wonder if youll even recognize me?"

I cant wait to see you. Ive missed you so much, its going to be unreal seeing you again."

--Adam."

Date Point: 5y 2m AV
Lackland AFB, San Antonio, Texas, USA, Earth

Ava Rios

“Okay, I can’t see him.”

Ava gave Gabriel a teasing smile. “You don’t recognise your own son?” She asked.

“I’m looking right at the guy carrying the flag at the front of his flight, and that’s not my son, I’d swear to it." Gabriel protested.

“It’s Adam.” She promised. “Right height and build, right face.”

“He moves differently.”

There was a deep-throated chuckle from Gabe’s left. “It’s called 'marching' mate." Powell told him. The captain had declined to share his reasons for attending the graduation, but in any case he stood out less than Ava would have guessed. His wasn’t even the only non-US uniform present. In any case, Powell had a remarkable ability to stand still, watchful and quiet and slip people’s attention when he wanted to. He was scanning the few hundred trainees in the parade with a cool, level stare that took in the details. “Your lad’s an Airman now.”

Gabe frowned at him. “He’s…still the same person under it all though, right?”

“Even better.” Powell said. “Trust me, he’s the same bloke under it all, but he’ll be sharper now, more confident. Probably in a bloody good mood, too.”

Gabriel looked back and squinted. Ava guessed that he was trying to connect the buff, buzz-cut creature of precision and intensity in front of them with some earlier vision of Adam, most likely the wiry, shy guy from school that she’d first started dating.

Those two people didn’t seem to have a lot in common, but it was definitely Adam. She’d spent too long staring at that face to mistake it.

“Do you think he can do it?” She asked Powell. “Pararescue, I mean?”

The captain nodded. “He can.” he said. “That’s not to say he will, mark you, but he’s in with as good a shout as anyone can have."

“What happens if he drops out?”

“Personally, I’d bet against that.” Powell commented. “But if he does, he does and I’ll bloody respect him for giving it a go. There’s plenty else he could do, and all of it would be a walk in the bloody park after dropping out of the pipeline.”

“I guess it’s better to know where your limits are and acknowledge them than fake it.” Ava guessed. Powell bobbled his head a little, indicating yes-and- no.

“True. But you can’t fake it wi’ that kind of training." he said. “That’s why it’s so hard. But your fella’s got a superman button, miss. Poke him the right way and he’d spit in God’s eye to get the job done. I reckon if his trainers know their business--and I’m pretty bloody sure they do--they’ll have figured that out already."

“I never knew.” Gabriel said softly. They both looked at him. His eyes were shining with a mixed bag of pride and something else that Ava couldn’t quite identify.

Powell clapped him on the shoulder. “Only the beginning.” he promised.

Gabe acknowledged that with a nod, and didn’t comment further, so neither did Ava nor Powell until the parade was done and the gathered airmen had been given a rousing congratulation and freed to see their families and visitors.

Ava took first dibs on greeting Adam, throwing herself into an enthusiastic hug that turned out to be like tackling a wall. He hadn’t grown in size much, but Adam’s muscles had clearly toned and hardened under that uniform, and he lifted her as if they were still on Cimbrean.

He murmured into her ear. “Miss me?”

“You know I did.” she replied, and kissed him.

Gabe interrupted them by hugging them both. “I hardly recognised you.” he said.

“It’s the haircut, right?” Adam grinned.

“And the body language, all that stuff.” Gabe replied. “You move more like he does.” He jerked a thumb over his shoulder at Powell, drawing Adam’s attention to the older Marine’s presence for the first time. Adam hastily extracted an arm from the hug and saluted.

Powell returned it but said nothing, indicating with a wry expression and a tilt of his head that Adam should focus on his family first.

They fussed over him for a few minutes longer before Gabriel finally suggested that Adam should discuss whatever business it was that Powell had brought with him. He in turn was then dragged into the discussion by dint of being Cimbrean’s security chief, leaving Ava to stand alone for a little while.

Adam even listened differently now, she noticed. Feet shoulder-width apart, hands clasped behind him, attention totally on whatever it was that Powell was saying.

“So, you must be Ava.”

She was being addressed by another new airman, a young, acne-scarred African- American man who offered her a hand to shake. “Warhorse said a lot about you.”

She shook it. “Warhorse?”

“Your boy Adam there. That’s his callsign.”

“He never mentioned that…”

“Eh, he hates it.” The airman grinned. “Did he mention me? John Burgess, I’m going into the PJ pipeline with him.”

“Yeah, he did!” Ava nodded. “Nothing but good things.”

“I hope so, motherfucker took the top bunk over me for eight weeks!” He laughed, then self-censored. “Uh, sorry. Bleep.”

“It’s no problem. So…Warhorse?”

“Couple’a reasons. Your boy can carry anything, he’s strong as shit, put a bag on him and he’ll run all day. So, we could have called him Packmule, but…y’know with a name like Ares…"

“Makes sense.” Ava agreed, grinning.

“Now the other reason is--"

“Goddammit Baseball, don’t you tell her!” Adam returned in time to gently clamp his hands over Ava’s ears. She giggled and wriggled free.

“Aww come on man, I’ve GOT to meet the girl brave enough to take you on."

Ava frowned at him, ignoring whatever it was Adam was so desperate about. “Brave?”

Burgess grinned. “you know? The pants monster? Your boy here’s morning wood damn near took my eye out from across the room!”

“Wh-wow, really?” She’d seen Adam naked before of course, but that had been swimming, and he hadn’t been at anything like…full…

She censored her own mental film reel.

'Baseball' paused, then grimaced. “Ah. Shit. You, uh…didn’t know?”

Ava shook her head. Adam just glared.

“So you two haven’t-?”

Now both of them glared.

“…I’ll, uh,” Burgess backed away, pointing generally over his shoulder. “I’ll see you at the start of Indoc, brother.”

“I’ma kick your ass worse than the PT.” Adam warned him, though there was a hint of amusement under the warning.

“I deserve it!” Burgess declared, and left them in peace.

Adam snorted and caught Ava’s gaze. She was studying him with a grin of her own pulling at her cheeks, threatening to burst out into laughter, and it started to pull even harder when her eyebrows raised themselves at him.

He cleared his throat. “He’s…exaggerating.”

Her eyes flicked downwards. “Guess I’ll just have to see for myself sometime.”

She allowed the smile to finally break out in full once her back was turned. Never mind the uniform, the haircut and the precision, his expression in response to that had been pure old-school Adam.

It was good to know he was still essentially himself.

Adam Ares

Gabriel was treating them to dinner, while Powell had made his apologies and jetted back North to return to Folctha. Adam and Ava sat together in the back seat of Gabe’s rented SUV on the drive into San Antonio proper, holding hands and talking quietly.

“Okay, so…why 'Baseball’?" she asked eventually.

“Couple of reasons.”

“One cool, one embarrassing?”

“That’s pretty much it, yeah.” Adam nodded. “Burgess can throw. Says he was pitcher for his school team, and when we were practicing with dummy grenades…yeah."

“And the embarrassing?”

“Baseball. For…more or less the same reason I’m Warhorse. I don’t have to draw you a picture, do I?”

She laughed. “Please don’t!”

“We’re here.” Gabriel announced. He’d pulled the car into the parking lot of a steakhouse called “The Barn Door” which he’d looked up using the excuse 'when in Rome…'

It didn’t take long to seat them, in a low-lit corner with a good view of some rodeo photographs and the two-foot flames on the grill.

“So.” Gabriel broke the silence once they were seated and had glanced at the menus. “That was Basic, huh?”

“Yeah.” Adam agreed. “Weird, it seemed really hard at the time but now…I mean, I’d find it easy if I had to go through that a second time.”

“Eager to get on with PJ training?”

Adam smiled sheepishly. “Dreading it.” he said. “But, yeah. I said to Powell when he tried to warn me about it, y’know, people do pass it, and…it’ll be tough, but I’m gonna be one of them."

Their waitress showed up. “Get y’all some drinks, folks?” she asked.

“Iced tea, please.” Gabe requested.

“Coke?” Adam asked.

“Sure! And for you honey?” she asked, addressing Ava.

“Diet coke, please.”

“Okay! Y’all ready to order, or do you need a few minutes?”

They looked around, determined that they were, and ordered the 24oz porterhouse for Adam, a catfish fillet for Ava and the Tenderloin for Gabriel. She gathered the menus.

“Okay! My name’s Rose, if y’all need anything just make eye contact and I’ll be right over to help. Drinks comin’ up!”

“So what happens after indoc?” Ava asked, once Rose had gone.

“Airborne training, survival, diving, mountaineering, medical training…”

“I mean,” she interrupted, “After all that, too. Are you going to be on Cimbrean, or…?”

“Maybe.” Adam said. “I’ve got some career choices coming up, and if it all goes right then hopefully I will, but if I’m not…”

“You two’ll just have to figure it out.” Gabe told them.

Their drinks arrived, and they chatted amiably about Cimbrean and the progress of the Reclamation Project.

Ava was in the middle of explaining how Byron group planes were soon going to carpet-bomb the Scar with saplings and seeds in shaped canisters that should embed in the ground and then rot away, spilling Terran plants into soil that had been hugely enriched by the same fungal and microbial action that had killed the native flora and fauna, when the main courses arrived.

She boggled at Adam’s steak. “Where the hell are you going to put that?" she demanded.

Adam just grinned and tucked in. “I’m a food vacuum nowadays.” he said, and devoured a cube of medium-rare beef.

Gabe clicked his tongue disapprovingly in the side of his mouth. “Enjoy it, Amigo!" he chided. “Take your time!”

“I AM enjoying it!” Adam reassured him, after swallowing. “That’s why there’s so much of it!”

Ava giggled, then stood up. “I’ll be right back.” she said, and vanished in the direction of the ladies’ room.

Adam was still watching her backside when Gabe tapped him on the upper arm. “Hey, Adam. Man talk for a second, while she’s gone. Okay?”

Adam blinked at him. “What’s up?”

“I love you both very much, right? I’m hoping for a future where you two have got a couple of beautiful kids, and…”

"Dad… "

“Shut up and listen, man.” Gabe sighed. “That’s just what I want, okay? If you want different, fine. But tell me honestly--if you’re serious about her, then that’s the kind of thing you need to think about. Are you serious about her?"

“Totally.” Adam said, firmly.

“Good, because she’s serious about you too.” Gabe nodded, though his expression was still concerned. “Just…be careful, alright? You’re looking at two, three years of only getting to see each other every other month on a long weekend, or something. That’s going to be difficult.”

“We know. We talked about that.” Adam promised.

“And?”

“And…” Adam trailed off, then shrugged.

“Adam, I’m proud of you right now, but don’t be dumb about this, okay? You can still be honor graduate and all that stuff and still fuck up your love life. Don’t…” it was Gabriel’s turn to pause, searching for the right turn of phrase. “Don’t forget to…”

“Dad. She’s tough. We’ve talked this over together, and…we’ll get through.” Adam reassured him.

“I know she’s tough. You both are. I just…” Gabriel sighed and gave up. “I just hope you’re both as tough as you think you are. Okay? I don’t want you to wind up hurting each other.”

“We love you too, Dad.”

Gabe gave him a sidelong hug. “Good to know.” he said. “I just needed to get that said.”

Adam nodded. “It’s heard. But…I’m sure we’re fine. After everything that’s happened…”

“You never heard about the last straw that broke the camel’s back, Amigo?"

Adam frowned. “She’s said she can cope. That’s good enough for me, Dad.”

Gabe sat back with an uncomfortable expression. “How--” he began, then paused. “She--”

Adam waited for him to finish. Or even get started. In the end Gabe just shook his head and hugged his son again.

“Alright, Amigo. If that’s good enough for you…"

Date Point: 5y 2m 3w AV
Dominion Embassy Station, Earth/Moon L1 Point, Sol.

Doctor Anees Hussein

“So this is Cruezzir?”

The Corti ambassador raised a hand. “Not…quite.” he revealed. “The Directorate was dead set against the idea of your species acquiring the original Cruezzir drug. In fact, we are now discontinuing it, and strongly advise that should a sample of the original fall into your possession, you should destroy it.”

“We will…take that under advisement.” Doctor Hussein assured him. “Though in that case, what is this on your desk?”

“A derivative, specifically designed for the human market with the intent of avoiding some future pitfalls.”

“What pitfalls?”

Medra inclined his head in a strange way, as if reading something only he could see. “Used correctly--as a topical or therapeutic target injection, rather than permanently marinating the patient’s system in it--Cruezzir has no side effects whatsoever. _Non_e.” he revealed. “It is, I dare say, a masterpiece creation of the Directorate’s biolabs. That factor alone was sufficient for our anthropological researchers to take exception to giving you access to it.”

Hussein frowned. “I don’t follow you.” he said. “Where is the problem with a medicine that has no side-effects?”

Medra mimicked a thin-lipped, prim smile. “Doctor, if I have learned one thing about your species these last few years, it is that, if dirt were edible, you would all be obese.”

“…I see.”

“No insult is intended, you understand. You are from a dangerous world, I can only assume that to use and stockpile resources as rapaciously as you do was a necessary survival instinct for your genetic forebears.”

“As a medicine, though… ” Hussein protested.

“We are not satisfied that it would remain a simple medicine. You already know of the one nicknamed the “Human Disaster”, which means in turn that you also how to synthesize Cruezzir in industrial quantities. All you need is a sample of the drug itself." Medra gestured oddly: it took Doctor Hussein a second to recall from his studies of alien body language that the gesture indicated concern. “We fear that Cruezzir injections and patches would become commonplace, even the norm, taking an already imposing species and making the pinnacle of your physical potential trivial to attain, rather than a lifelong pursuit which precludes the study of other, more…cerebral endeavors."

Hussein considered his Corti counterpart for a second. “You make it sound like you want us to remain below our potential.”

"Your potential, doctor, is already intolerably ahead of any other species’." Medra countered. “If some semblance of balance and fairness are to be retained for the rest of us, then you must either be encouraged to remain below your potential, or else encouraged into isolation. The failure of that latter strategy is why the Directorate has appointed me."

“To keep us down.”

“To remind you that you need to be kept down." Medra had at least perfected the knack of returning a human’s stare. Most aliens instinctively looked away. “Or shall I point to the ecological grafting you are performing at great expense on Cimbrean to remind you of that fact?”

“I believe you just did.”

“Indeed.”

Medra picked up the phial on his desk again. "This version, this Cruezzir derivative, contains a limiting factor--resistance. Over time, any human who regularly uses it will steadily, but slowly, become increasingly immune. There are a few other changes, mostly designed to prevent the drug from being synthesized by your symbiotic bacteria but…suffice it to say we feel less uncomfortable releasing this for you to use than the medicine for which you actually asked. There will be no more Human Disasters with this derivative."

He gestured out of the window, toward the Earth. From the L1 point where the Dominion embassy was anchored, it filled a respectable portion of the sky. “I believe your ancestry comes from a region responsible for the myth of a 'jinn’, doctor?"

“Close enough.” Hussein conceded, diplomatically refraining from commenting that, as the Holy Quran had it, jinn were perfectly real.

“According to that myth, the 'jinn' would grant wishes, but would twist the wishes according to a literal interpretation of their wording, to the wisher’s detriment." He offered the phial. “We, doctor, are twisting the wish according to a sensible interpretation of its intent, to the wisher’s and our own mutual benefit."

Hussein considered his options, then gave up and took the phial. “In that case,” he said “having read the trade agreement and been advised on it…we accept the terms.”

They shook on it. Gently.

Date Point: 5y 2m 4w AV

Hey Ava

I’ve only got three words to say about Indoc so far: Holy fucking SHIT.

This is really bringing me back down to earth.

I’m going to get through it though. No matter what.

Thinking of you,

--Adam

Date Point: 5y 4m AV

Hey Ava,

Im sorry Ive not written you since last week. I did get your letter and I hope you know Id have written back if I could Ive just been too thrashed to even pick up a pen. Really the PT here is that hard. Im talking 20 solid hours of calisthenics…when there feeling kind. I swear Im not exaggerating.

Getting a reward today though--a good long letter session a whole hour! Everyone else is calling home or whatever but for me…wow just getting some quiet time to sit and think and write to you is like I never imagined Id think something so simple was such a big deal. I spent half of it just sitting and thinking and getting my head sorted out.

You know I said in one of my letters from basic that I kind of enjoy being shouted at now? Well that’s still true its hard to explain but if Im being shouted at then its kind of a compliment because the MTL knows I can do better and hes telling me so. I mean actual words of encouragement are nice too dont get me wrong but I can see now that it wouldnt get anybody through this.

There training us for the very worst you know? They want to be able to send us into anything and have us be strong enough that if we fail it was never possible in the first place. And theres no way to do that except the way they do it. Theyve been doing it for years they know what theyre doing here and I know that I can make it through this.

So yeah I hurt basically all the time Im tired basically all the time Im so wired that just getting a whole HOUR of quiet time feels like the biggest luxury in the world…but dont be sad for me baby because underneath it all I think Im actually kind of enjoying myself.

If that sounds weird…maybe it is I dont know?

I still struggle to eat enough. There giving me like 10 000 calories a day or something insane like that thats a heck of a lot of food and with me not being a big guy some days its almost harder to get all of that food to fit in my belly than it is to do the actual PT.

Itd help if it was Dads waffles or something. A taste of home you know? I dont care how full I am if I had a plate of those right now they’d be gone. I know they were store-bought ones but it still counts as home cooking right?

I love you. I miss you every day and I think the reason is that for all the really big shit thats happened in the last few years youve been there through it all. The hardest part by a mile has been learning how to go through something this huge without you.

Im kinda sorry for that.

--Adam X

Date Point: 5y 4m 2d AV

“Airman Ares!”

Mail call had become the best part of Adam’s day, enough so to shake the ache right out of his abused muscles.

Dear Adam,

Baby, you’re not going through this without me: I read all your letters, and I write you back every time, but it’s not just that.

I may not be there with you doing the PT or whatever. But I pray for you every day, I think of you every minute, and knowing you’re thinking of me even with what you’re going through is what helps me too. You’ve been there for ME through all the really big shit of the last few years too, you know that?

I feel lonely a lot. No you, no Sara, no Hayley…I love (here Ava had written the word ‘your’ and then scribbled over it) Dad, but you can’t have a social life of just one person.

I guess we’re both learning how to cope with just being there for each other in spirit rather than in person, huh?

But believe me corazon, that’s all we need. I’m so proud of you.

--Ava ♥

Adam was smiling as he folded the letter up. “Good letter.”

“She ain’t here, bro. You’re talking to yourself again.” Baseball grinned at him.

“Beats your company.” Adam retorted, grinning back.

“Only company your midget ass gets is my belt buckle anyways, so that ain’t that surprising.”

“Hey that was almost witty. Must be ’cause you sat down, I know your brain doesn’t get enough oxygen at ten thousand fucking feet when you stand up."

Burgess beamed and stuck out a fist. “Motherfucker.”

Adam completed the fist pound. “Asshole.”

They were interrupted by the MTL, who entered the barracks and announced a briefing and lecture in ten minutes.

“What now?” Baseball wondered aloud.

They found out when they settled into their seats in the lecture hall six minutes later. There was the usual rigmarole of standing when the presenting officer--a Lieutenant with the surname “Reed” on his chest--entered.

“Be seated.” he ordered, and six backsides met chair. There was a minute or two of patient waiting while he entered his login and password and called up some files.

“This is a confidential, code-word SACRED STRANGER briefing. You will not share this material with anyone not possessing need-to-know for SACRED STRANGER.” Reed began. “Is that understood?”

There was a chorus of “Yes sir.”

“Good.”

Reed loaded up a presentation slide and Adam groaned inwardly. 'Death by Powerpoint' was a running military gag that he had so far been blessed to suffer only mildly from. He hoped that streak of good fortune would continue.

“Seven months ago,” Reed stated, lingering on the first slide, “The British Royal Navy’s two captured and refitted alien starships engaged in a skirmish with the Hunter blockade around Cimbrean. They acquitted themselves well in the battle, which was fought to rescue the crew of a refugee freighter who had unwittingly blundered into the Hunter fleet. You should all be familiar with the Hunters, if anybody here requires a refresher, raise your hand.”

Nobody did.

Reed gave a shallow, satisfied nod and continued. “During the battle, a Special Boat Service team led by one Captain Owen Powell boarded the freighter and extracted its surviving crew. The operation was a resounding success, but Captain Powell and the commanding officers of HMS Myrmidon and HMS Caledonia recommended to the Ministry of Defence that a review be conducted into the requirements and viability of a dedicated force of spaceborne special operators capable of extravehicular activity, or EVA."

“That review was shared with the Department of Defence and the Pentagon and the result is that we are now founding an international joint unit, provisionally known as the Spaceborne Operators Regiment, or SOR.”

“This is an initiative that’s still in its infancy. No commanding officers, no operators, no gear, no crest or motto, nothing.” He continued. “Its mission, however, is already well-understood. The SOR would serve to defend and protect the people and interests of Earth, Cimbrean and any future colonies which may arise from extraterrestrial threats. It will conduct search-and-rescue of stations and starships that become adrift or damaged, will provide humanitarian aid to castaways and those affected by disaster, and will be available to defend stations and large ships, as much as is possible, from Hunter strikes and piracy. These missions will also benefit the human race through propaganda, through the Dominion Development Credit bounties that are awarded for recovering liferafts, and by securing extraterrestrial technology from derelicts.”

He paused. “I should note, gentlemen, that when I mention 'extraterrestrial threats’, I refer to any and all enemies of our species, including the alien force responsible for the destruction of San Diego, the exact nature of which is deemed need-to-know."

Adam and Burgess exchanged glances.

Reed advanced the slideshow. It was now dominated by something that looked like a hybrid of a NASA spacesuit and an Interceptor body armour system, though sleeker than either.

“The defining equipment of Spaceborne Operators will be their Extra-Vehicular Military Action Space Suit, or EV-MASS. This has been designed by private- sector experts from the Hephaestus LLC on Ceres who hold records for most and longest extravehicular activity, working alongside experts from CQC Limited, who produce the Osprey Armor System.”

“Now, you’ve all been given a brief introduction to the SOR concept. A full briefing of this system and its capabilities, variants and requirements will be saved for those of you who choose to commit to joining the program. For now the important point is this: the EV-MASS is a fully functioning spacesuit designed to allow the operator to engage the enemy in the vacuum of space and maneuver in zero-gravity. That combined functionality means that it has a base weight of one hundred and three pounds, before gear and accessories.”

There was no breach of discipline as such, but all six of the PJ candidates exchanged glances. They were all strong enough to wear and use a suit that heavy, thanks to the intensive physical training of the pipeline, but doing so would suck. Remaining agile and mobile for prolonged periods under the combined weight of that suit and their bags, gun, equipment and maybe even a patient, who might even be wearing the same suit and all of their gear, all added up to a daunting prospect.

One of them put his hand up, and Reed pointed to him, inviting him to ask his question.

“Sir, if a man wearing one of those has to carry one of his buddies, that’s gotta be, uh…six hundred pounds at least. Hell, it could be a lot more. How’s anybody supposed to hump that kind of weight any kind of a serious distance?”

Reed acknowledged the question’s validity with a nod. “It’s a big ask.” he agreed. “The suit does contain some passive load-bearing structures which will help, but the operators wearing it will need to be exceedingly strong. Which is why we’re coming to you now, with…this.”

He closed the slideshow and opened a video.

“This is footage of Lance-Corporal Aaron Baxter, United States Marine Corps. Baxter was involved in a vehicle collision during a training exercise two weeks ago, and suffered a, uh…” Reed checked his notes, pronouncing the medical terminology slowly and with care. “A…posteriorly displaced…open comm- in-uted…intra-articular tibial plateau fracture with an…intimal tear of the …pop-lit-e-al artery.”

He looked up. “As I understand it, that basically means the poor bastard’s knee got flattened and everything broke into little bitty bits.”

Everybody grimaced.

“Right, you understand.” Reed noted, nodding. “This is a crippling injury, a career-ender. That knee’s never going to be the same again, and if he escapes amputation, getting it working again even half-normally is going to involve probably a prosthetic joint, and certainly a lot of physiotherapy and rehab. Ordinarily, Baxter would be out of a job and living on his VA benefits and medical care. Fortunately for him, he came along at exactly the right moment to be the guinea pig for a new medicine purchased from Extraterrestrial sources.”

While the footage of Baxter continued on one half of the screen, the other half began a quick animation detailing the origins and capabilities of the drug. “It’s called Cruezzir-Derivative Compound A, but for the purposes of common usage, we’re calling it Crue-D. Don’t ask me how, but it hugely accelerates and improves the healing process.” Reed continued. “Baxter went under the knife to have all those little bitty bits put back together and the plumbing fixed, and while they were at it, he let them inject this stuff right in there.”

On the screen, Baxter’s dressings were being removed. “This is him only thirty hours after the operation. Notice, there’s no surgical wound, nor a scar from the open fracture. That had closed up by the six hour mark, and If they’d put sutures in him, they’d have had to operate to get them back out again. Fortunately they foresaw that and only clamped the wound and compressed it. But when they X-rayed the kneecap at eight hours, they found out it was damn near perfectly intact. They kept him in bed for another day just to be sure, but…”

Baxter stood up, and jaws dropped around the room.

“That’s incredible.” somebody muttered.

“It’s goddamn alien space magic is what it is.” Baseball grunted.

Reed nodded agreement, letting the interruption slide. “And for the time being it looks like we’re stuck relying on the Corti to make it for us. When our scientists tried to figure out how it works in the lab, they say the samples just dissolved into water and some weird organic molecules, like it’s got a self-destruct built in. But the results are plain--Corporal Baxter is fit and well and back with his unit, under observation for long-term side effects but otherwise unscathed after what should have been the end of a promising career as a US marine."

He turned off the screen. “So…what does this have to do with the six of you?” he asked, rhetorically. “The short version is that with the physical demands of the SOR program being so high-end, we want to use this stuff therapeutically during the physical training. Slap-patches, joint injections…You’re all familiar with the theory behind muscle gains?”

There was general nodding. “Good. But to spell it out for the sake of clarity, the very basic version is that the muscles and ligaments suffer minor damage, and heal stronger than they were before.”

“With this stuff,” he continued “we think we can take that process to a new level. Completely thrash the trainee during the day, then they heal perfectly overnight thanks to a contact patch of Crue-D. Throw in some of the latest developments in Sports Science and we think it’s possible to produce operators whose bodies exist on the absolute limit of what’s humanly possible.”

One of the others put his hand up. “Begging your pardon sir, but…You want us to do that?"

“I’m putting it out there for you to think about. Like I said, the SOR is still in its infancy. We’ve got all the necessary infrastructure in place, now all that’s needed are volunteers. Any such volunteers will be plucked from the pararescue pipeline and put onto the SOR highway instead. This will closely mirror--and often take place alongside--pararescue training, but will be even more physically intense, and will then be followed by SOR-specific training and possibly astronaut training as well. Any questions?”

Several hands went up. Reed acknowledged one of them with a point of his pen.

“Sir, what are the risks here?”

“We’re assured that, when used correctly, Crue-D has no side effects. And to head off the next question, the only incorrect use we know of was a couple of cases where the original medicine--Cruezzir--entered the patient’s gut biome, where it was absorbed by intestinal bacteria which mutated and began to produce a constant supply.”

“What happens when that happens?"

“According to the Corti, the subject undergoes rapid muscle growth, an increase in bone density, and…basically reaches their maximum physical potential without the need to exercise their way there, not to mention becoming permanently able to heal from even quite serious injuries at a remarkable rate. There’s also some suggestion that they become biologically immortal and may experience improved skill-learning and the tapping of latent genetic potential that exists inside the human genome, such as the ability to see some way into the infrared.”

There was silence, then somebody else put their hand up. “Begging your pardon sir, but why the hell aren’t we going with that?"

“One, because Crue-D has been modified to preclude exactly that scenario because it scares the bejesus out of the Corti. Two, because it seems to come at a serious cost to the subject’s mental health.” Reed explained. “The two known cases so far demonstrated reckless, self-destructive behaviour and possible signs of a schizophrenic or Dissociative Identity disorder, respectively.”

“Besides that,” he continued “We have no idea if that’s just in the short- term. The long-term effects of Crue-D applied topically in a targeted and safe fashion, we are assured, are nil. Nothing is known about the long-term consequences of keeping the human body indefinitely soaked in the original Cruezzir."

He cleared his throat. “The only remaining thing that could be a risk factor would be nutrition. You’ll be packing on muscle and bone mass at such an incredible rate that your diets will have to be strictly controlled down to the last milligram and calorie. Every snack, every meal. You won’t even be able to grab a burger without planning and training ramp-down, and if done incorrectly you might find yourself suffering from malnutrition. At the very least it would be a wasted opportunity. At worst, well…"

This was met with thoughtful silence. Reed let them mull it over for a moment, then spoke again.

“This is, obviously, an enormous decision. You would not be here if you were so impulsive as to just take it on immediate notice, which is why we’ve informed you today so you can have your weekends to consider it. This briefing will continue on Monday at fourteen hundred hours. Dismissed.”

“You’re going for it, ain’tcha?”

Adam looked up. He’d been considering how to write back to Ava, tell her that his training would go on for at least another two years beyond what they had discussed, without breaching confidentiality or classification. He knew she’d accept that he couldn’t discuss such things with her, but she still deserved an explanation, and he was carefully assembling that explanation in his head.

“This is what I got in for.” he said, simply. “I knew there had to be aliens involved somewhere, and…yeah."

Baseball sat down. “You did?”

“Dude, antimatter? Nobody on Earth’s got that shit.”

“We’ve got alien healy-juice though. They didn’t tell me about that shit when I first heard about the SOR."

Adam nodded. “Yeah.” he said. “That one’s new on me, too.”

“Man, I ain’t sure about this Crue-D stuff.” Baseball rubbed his chin thoughtfully. “I knew too many guys got ’roided up in school…You sure you’re not rushing into this?”

“These ain’t roids. This shit heals you stronger, man!"

“Yeah, but…man, you trust anything ET makes?"

Adam sighed. “I’ve been thinking about it for a long time, Base. The SOR’s going to be going up against the group that killed my mom and my friends. That’s why I joined in the first place--’cause a group like that, needs people fighting them, you know? I don’t know if I trust ET, but I sure as hell trust us, you know?"

“So you’re going for it, then?”

“Yeah.”

“…Okay. I’m with you, Hoss.”

Adam paused: “Base, bro, you don’t have to.”

“Bullshit. We’re a good team, you’re the heavy lifting motherfucker, I’m the brains of the outfit.”

Adam laughed and gave him the finger.

Baseball laughed too, then reached out, flipped Adam’s hand over, grabbed it in a knuckle-creaking handshake and dragged him in for a solid masculine slam- hug.

“Besides, we get to be fuckin’ astronauts.” he added. “You KNOW that’s a ticket to pussy.”

Adam laughed again “Alright, you sentimental fuck. You’re with me…I appreciate it.”

“You better.”

Hey Ava,

Baby, I’m sorry to do this to you, but there’s a career opportunity come up that’s just perfect for me. It’s everything I got into the military to accomplish. I wish I could discuss it with you, but it’s all confidential.

The downside is that the training is two years longer than we’d planned for, and it’s going to be really hard to get the time to visit you during those two years.

I wish there was time for us to talk about it properly, but they want my answer on whether or not I’m signing up for this thing on Monday, and there’s just not time for me to get back and with the emails only updating once a day, by the time your reply gets to me, it’ll be Monday anyway, so…

I’m sorry Ava. But this is too perfect to pass up.

Write me back. I’ll understand if you’re mad.

--Adam XXX

Date Point: 5y 4m 5d AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Jessica Olmstead

“Oh my God, Ava!”

Jessica had never been the kind of teacher who believe in keeping an emotional distance from her students, and so when Ava shuffled into the classroom a quarter hour early and looking totally ruined, she dropped everything and dashed over to give the younger woman a hug. “What happened?”

Ava ran a shaking hand through unbrushed, unwashed hair and lost whatever grip on her composure she’d had, burying herself in Jess’ sweater and shaking fiercely.

Jess just held her until finally Ava managed to pull herself together and straighten up. “What happened?”

“I just…I checked my emails, and there’s one from Adam, and…” Ava looked away and made an angered expression at herself, fighting to stay in control. “He changed the plan.”

“Changed the…? I don’t understand.”

“I was fine with him doing two years of pararescue training and some deployments, and…I don’t know! All that, we’d got it sorted out and I was fine with it! But now he’s talking about four years of training and maybe not being able to see each other at all in those extra couple of years! And who knows how long after that!" Ava threw her hands up and engaged anger circuits that Jess had never seen in her before.

"Que se supone que haga? Él no me pregunto, el no me habla de ello …el hijo de puta me acaba de enviar una CARTA DE MIERDA y espera que yo sea bien! Eso pendejo desconsiderado! Eh?"

Jess sat on a desk. “I don’t speak Spanish, Ava.” she pointed out, gently. “But watch your language, the kids’ll be here soon.”

Ava went still, then deflated and sat down, miserably. “He just…it’s not just his life." she complained.

Jess gave her a moment to be silent. When Ava wiped her eyes and began to sort herself out, she took the opportunity to be constructive. “What are you going to do?” she asked.

Ava made a bitter little noise. “I should have learned this by now, shouldn’t I? Don’t plan for anything, because tomorrow you might get nuked.”

“So…?”

“So what I’m going to do is…whatever seems like a good idea at the time." Ava said.

“So what seems like a good idea right now?”

“Hah! Dumping his ass.” but Ava was shaking her head to indicate that she had nothing of the sort in mind. “But…whatever, so he’s been an insensitive jerk and made a huge decision without me. So what? At least he cares. He still loves me, and I love him too, even if he’s been a huge jackass right now."

“So…?” Jessica repeated.

“So I guess what seems like a good idea is just…forgive him and try to be happy.” Ava shrugged. “Be happy in the moment, right? That’s what our Gaoians are so into. And I…I think I’d be unhappier without him."

She sighed, and stretched. “What do you think?”

Jess considered the question. “I guess my marriage broke up because we weren’t able to forgive when we hurt each other.” she conceded in the end. “I don’t know, there’s so many arguments either way, I guess you do just have to go with whatever seems like a good idea at the time."

“Like he did.”

“Like he did.” Jess agreed. “I think that’s what love is, is understanding when one of you comes first. Sometimes it’s you, sometimes it’s him.”

She hesitated, then decided to put her money where her mouth was and say what seemed like a good idea at the time. “And…Ava, he’s a soldier now. Soldiers…they don’t always come back. I think you’re going to need to get used to trying to live as well as you can 'in the moment' and not…and figure out how you’re going to get by without him, if that ever happens."

A banging in the hallways made them both look up--it was the clear sound of the class starting to arrive. “If you want to borrow a hairbrush, there’s one in my office, on the desk.” Jess offered.

Ava smiled. It wasn’t a strong smile, but it was genuine. “Thanks, Jess. I needed…thank you.”

Jess gave her another hug. “I hope I helped.”

Ava nodded, then slipped out the other door a few seconds before the class started to enter, in usual boisterous mode.

Jess straightened and got herself back into teacher mode. The first, and hopefully worst, of the day’s crises was dealt with.

Dear Mr. Ares,

As I said to you when Ava first arrived at our school, she has always struck me as being much more intelligent than she believes herself to be. I am very pleased to tell you that, over the last few months, she has vindicated my belief in her and excelled at her studies. As you know, the free-form approach to schooling that we use at this school does not allow me to break down her performance by subject, but she has achieved outstanding performance in every single module she has chosen to pursue.

As the sole member of our senior group, with the next students not due to enter that group for another three years, she does however pose a slight administrative problem for the school, which I believe would be best resolved by graduating her at the end of this coming summer term and then taking her on over the coming school year as a teaching assistant. This will not only enable her to continue to study ahead of her university plans, but will give her some practical experience and income that will serve her in good stead.

She has indicated to me that she wishes to attend the London School of Economics to study for a career in photojournalism. Challenging though this choice of career will doubtless be, I have complete confidence that she will excel in it.

Her combined overall grade for this semester is: A.

Yours sincerely,

Dr. J. A. B. Olmstead
Junior and Senior Groups Tutor, Folctha Comprehensive School.

“Wow…that’s, uh, easily the best report card I ever had."

Gabriel took off his reading glasses. “Yeah?”

Ava sighed. “Every other one I ever had always had the words 'could do better' in it." She said. “I guess they were right, huh?”

“I guess they were.” Gabriel agreed, though he left out his opinion that if her performance had previously been lackluster then that probably reflected more on the education system than on Ava herself. “You gonna go for it?”

She hesitated. “Do you…think I should?”

“It sounds like an excellent opportunity.” Gabriel told her. “Experience, money and education all in one go? Chances like that don’t come along too often.”

“True…”

Gabriel knew what the trepidation was about. “Why not discuss it with Doctor Olmstead?” He suggested. “If you want plenty of time to get out there and practice your photography, maybe she can help.”

Ava nodded and pulled the camera out of her handbag. She was constantly fiddling with it nowadays, usually with a frown. “I do need to practice more. I keep looking at Sara’s old pictures and seeing…you know, seeing new things in them. Things she was doing that I didn’t even know how to see before…”

She sighed. “She was…really talented, Gabe. I want to try and do justice to her, try and…bring back some of her spark, but I don’t think I can."

“Even if you don’t,” Gabriel told her. “In trying, you’ll find your own talent. Don’t think of it as bringing back her spark, but as…I dunno, reincarnating it. Same spirit, but different, yeah?”

“Maybe…”

She put the camera away, then stood up and kissed him on the forehead. “I’d better get home.” she said.

“See you tomorrow?”

“Of course!”

Date Point: 5y 5m 1w AV
Lackland Air Force Base, San Antonio, Texas, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

Indoc had taught Adam a trick. It had taught him how to notice that he was exhausted and in pain, but to treat those facts as an abstract.

It was a useful trick. One that kept his feet kicking, hour upon hour upon hour, in a pool of cold water, with his goggles flooded and his muscles saturated with lactic acid. The mind went to a quiet place without thought, where the absence of any stimulation but the physical exertion didn’t matter, and where the exertion itself was not the immediate, intimate issue it might once have been, but was instead…academic. It wasn’t even tedious--his ego was so shut down as to not care that he’d received no real intellectual stimulation for hours.

There was just the task: Keep kicking.

In that mode, he might have gone on until his body finally gave out. And that, he suspected on those rare occasions where he was permitted to be lucid, was the point.

Besides, pool days were comparatively gentle, compared to the weight sessions. Those were the days when the Crue-D came out in force, when muscles sprained and ligaments tore and were forced to mend almost on the spot. You worked until you broke, and were then fixed. And then, while you healed, you trained something else.

If he hadn’t learned how to notice his pain without experiencing it, he couldn’t have borne it.

There was just the task: Keep lifting.

Keep kicking.

Keep improving.

He wasn’t even waiting. He was just doing, until the whistle blow summoned him out of his trance and allowed him to stop doing again. Allowed him, once he was out of the pool, to become Adam again and realise just how trashed and tired he really was.

Adam, who was packing on muscle at an incredible rate. He’d known that he would, of course. The SOR briefing had been clear on that. But it was still jarring sometimes to look at himself and recall that just two years ago he’d been a skinny teenager who didn’t even fill out the small shirts in the store, whereas he now wore Extra-large sized shirts like a second skin.

“Line up!”

He met Baseball’s eye as they lined up alongside the pararescue candidates. They stood out, now, clearly on a different career path. The PJs were strong as hell, but Adam and Baseball were both much, much bigger. Their ability to wriggle into tight places had been sacrificed to prioritize the raw power they needed to remain mobile and active under crushingly heavy loads.

Being lined up after an exercise was nothing new--it had hitherto been the prelude to another task. This time was different. This time the MTLs lined up in front of them, at attention, and Master Sergeant Allen--the team leader-- stepped forward, studying them carefully.

Devastated as they were by what must have been a truly epic session in the pool, every one of the airmen held at attention perfectly. Finally, he nodded.

“Airmen.” he said. “You have now completed the Indoctrination section of your Pararescue training. You have done something that is literally better than a one in a million event--precious few men have ever accomplished this task. You’re not Pararescuemen yet, but as of today, you’ve proven that you are all worthy to follow in the green Footsteps of the giants of your chosen unit. You have cleared the first and most difficult hurdle on the road to your maroon beret, and it has been our honor and privilege as your Military Training Leaders to witness this feat.”

He saluted, as did all the other MTLs. The exhausted airmen returned a precision salute with equal snappy enthusiasm. “Congratulations.”

The salute was held for a moment, then relaxed, and the MTLs softened with it, advancing forward to exchange handshakes, hugs and smiles with men they’d been yelling at only minutes before.

Adam was running on fumes, but he joined in gladly. He’d known he could do it.

Finally, the congratulations died down. Master Sergeant Allen finally called an end to it. “Alright, get back to your dorms and get some sleep.” he ordered. “And sleep in. Tomorrow is a Liberty day. Get checked out, get laundry done. Don’t you worry about your gear just this once, we’ll take care of it. You’ve earned it.”

He paused, then smiled. “But don’t get stupid.” he added. “training resumes the next day.”

Date Point: 5y 9m 3w AV
Folctha Colony, Cimbrean, the Far Reaches

Gabriel Ares

“Ah. I thought so.”

Gabriel looked up from toying with his glass of water. The waiters of Folctha’s first restaurant--and what a restaurant it was!--had been discreetly keeping him supplied with water for a few minutes now. Ava had spent her first paycheck arranging for him and 'someone else' to be among the place’s first diners.

He had to admit, he was intrigued. He hadn’t been on a date in years, and never on a blind date. Though, like the woman who had just said 'I thought so’, he’d had a sneaking suspicion he knew who it would be.

“Wow!” he commented. He’d been right, but he barely recognised her.

Jess Olmstead giggled. “That’s a good start!”

Gabriel stood and pulled back a seat for her. “Heartfelt.” he promised, as she settled into it, carefully dropping her handbag beneath her. Whenever he’d interacted with Jess before she’d been in teacher mode, favouring a black cardigan and a red scarf with a long skirt. Comfortable, sensible and plain.

For tonight, she’d worn something substantially sleeker in dark blue, with a neckline that pulled at the eyes, punctuated by an attention-grabbing, slim little minimalist necklace and a smile that said 'go ahead and look’. Her hair was out of its usual loose ponytail and swept into something just a little bit more elaborate. Gabe had enough experience with women to know just how much time and agonising would have gone into crafting such an apparently effortless appearance, and knew enough about perfume to scent that she was wearing an expensive one.

Good signs, especially considering that she claimed to have suspected who her date was.

“Ava’s got to be so proud of herself right now, playing matchmaker.” he noted, sitting down again.

“Well, I had my suspicions.” Jess confessed. “There aren’t many other people she could have set me up on a date with."

“Likewise.”

“And yet, here we are.”

“Here we are.” Gabe agreed, mirroring her smile and pleased that he’d put similar effort into his own appearance, between getting the fit of his suit adjusted and treating himself to a wet shave. He’d even subtly dipped into Adam’s left-behind stash of “manscaping” products, which had been a strange experience for him, being of a generation of men that didn’t traditionally wear cosmetics of any kind. Ava had reassured him that the result was dashing and sophisticated, especially when coupled with his cane.

The maitre’d spun by with the wine list and a recommendation, which they agreed to with nods and murmurs.

“She was pretty thrilled with your recommendation.” He revealed. “So was I. I think it’s exactly what she needs.”

“I hope so.” Jessica poured herself a small glass of water from the complimentary jug between them. “She’s…an amazing person, really. Her and your son both.”

“Don’t I know it.” Gabriel agreed. “I don’t think I’d be coping so well if I wasn’t so proud of them both.”

“Yes, I heard Adam was an 'honor graduate’?"

“I barely recognised him!” Gabriel said. “He walked differently, he looked around differently, he was so much more…focused." He sighed. “I guess the military suits him. On the one hand I’m pleased, but on the other…you know, he’s signing up for a very dangerous life. After everything that’s happened…”

Jess leaned forward, unconsciously echoing his sigh. “Heaven help us if we ever get used to the idea of our kids doing dangerous work.” she commented, and nodded along when he nodded.

"Si. He’s his own man, and Ava’s her own woman. I just wish I knew how to make their lives…happier."

Jess smiled. “Start by making your own life happier.” she suggested.

“Well, that’s why I came down here.” Gabriel said.

Jess smiled and sipped her water. “I’m glad to hear it.”

“You think it’s that simple?” Gabriel asked. “That I’ll help them by helping myself?”

“I do.” Jess nodded. “And they’ll help you by helping themselves. It’s plain how much the three of you love one another.”

The wine arrived along with a couple of slim menus, which distracted them both for a few minutes as they mulled over their options and ordered.

“Like you said.” Gabe continued once their orders were placed. “They’re amazing people. With everything that’s happened they’ve only grown tougher and more mature.”

“What about you?” Jess asked him.

Gabe just shrugged a little. “A little weaker in some ways, a little stronger in others.” he suggested. “I’m ready to date again, for instance. That’s a big step forward for me.”

“You still held a bit of a candle for your ex? I know it took me ages to get over my divorce… ”

“…No, I don’t think that’s it.” Gabe mulled it over. “I think I was more…bruised and weary, if that makes sense?”

“I understand.” Jess nodded, fiddling with the stem of her glass and listening to him with her chin on her hand.

“What about you, does your ex-husband know you’re living on an alien world nowadays?”

Jess giggled. “My ex-wife and I haven’t spoken in years." she said. “I have no idea what she’s doing with her life, and I haven’t let her know what I’m doing with mine.”

Gabriel cleared his throat. “Sorry.”

“Don’t be.” She reassured him. “I only mention it when it’s relevant, and it’s only relevant with people who… .”

“Who…?”

She just winked at him. Her nose wrinkled a little when she did so, and Gabriel practically fell in love on the spot.

He raised his glass. “To a good first date.” he proposed.

She raised her eyebrows, picking up the wine glass but not yet meeting his toast. "First date?"

"First date." he repeated, projecting as much confidence as he could muster.

She smiled, causing her nose to wrinkle again, and her glass rang against his.

“Is it the quality of the wine, do you think, or how much of it we had?”

Gabriel laughed. “A little bit of column A and a little bit of column B.” he suggested. Neither of them were drunk as such, but they both definitely had a happy buzz on, warming and rounding off the night as he walked her home with an arm around her waist. She seemed very happy to be going at his slow, limping pace.

“I think you’re right…aww, we’re at my house already?”

Gabriel studied it. Jess lived in the same kind of tiny chalet as had been given to Adam and Ava, like most of the colonists. He knew that Sir Jeremy was still handling the minutiae of bringing in contractors to establish more permanent and comfortable housing, but that project had only just begun.

“That’s one of the perks of being colonial security chief.” he said. “My apartment’s even bigger than the one I had back in San Diego.”

“Oh really?”

“Yep. Want to see?”

Jess laughed. “Oh, Gabe.” she chided. “I think we’d at least better have a couple more dates before you show me how big your…” she paused, cheekily. “…apartment is."

“Whenever you want, wherever you want.” he replied.

“Tuesday, same place and time?” she suggested.

“Absolutely.” he agreed.

“Good, because I really enjoyed myself tonight.”

He turned towards her, still with his arm on her waist. “You wanna round it off with a goodnight kiss?”

She did so. It was a good one too, several seconds of gentle, smiling lip contact with a hand on his cheek that promised better things to come, underlined by a second, shorter one just after they separated.

They didn’t say anything else. She just trailed her hand in his as she let herself into her chalet, letting go only in time to blow him a kiss and close the door.

Gabriel Ares walked home with the largest smile on his face that he’d worn in years.

Date Point: 5y 11m 1w AV
Folctha colony, Cimbrean, the Far Reaches

Gabriel Ares

Rather than hobbling through the living room and opening the door, Gabriel was in the habit of shouting “Come on in, Ava!” when the doorbell rang.

She was the only one who used it--literally everyone else in the colony knocked. It was becoming one of those Cimbrean quirks, the sign of a local, insofar as anybody COULD be local in a town so young.

Ava let herself in and gave him a daughterly kiss on the cheek. Gabriel knew better than to comment that she looked a mess--her eyes were dark and pinkish, and she obviously hadn’t brushed her hair. “Cup of coffee?” He asked.

She nodded and slumped down at the table. “That.” she said. “Would be amazing.”

“You okay?”

“Ah, I stayed up all night doing my part of the end-of-semester marking so I wouldn’t have it to do while Adam’s around.”

“He’s not due back until tomorrow.” Gabriel pointed out. His kitchen faucet had a mode to deliver boiling water, and he used it to fill the cafetier with his favoured blend of Galapagos coffee--a rare treat. Sure, Ava adulterated hers with so much cream and sugar that it was barely recognisable, and a bit of a waste, but he figured it must still be better behind all that than just the instant stuff.

“Yeah, but…it’s his birthday, so I can’t sleep.” Ava gave him a little smile that said she knew just how nonsensical that was.

“You’re that nervous at seeing him again?” Gabriel asked, leaning against the counter while the coffee brewed.

“For, like…a whole bunch of reasons.” Ava agreed.

“Eh, don’t worry so much.” Gabriel told her fondly. “if you two manage to break the bed or something, I’ll fix it.”

"Da-ad!"

Gabriel raised an eyebrow. Her exclamation had been so guilelessly teenage that it was like a note of pure honesty in the room--there couldn’t have been a conscious decision to call him that involved. “Dad, huh?” he asked, softly.

She’d gone beet red, but she stood up and hugged him. “I’m sorry, I--”

“Hey.” he stroked her hair down, as much to get it out of his face as to reassure her. “You’re a daughter to me as well, you know? I couldn’t have asked for better.”

Ava took the compliment well, sitting down again and tidying herself up a little with a smile as Gabriel depressed the plunger on his cafetier and served.

“I um…” she began. “I guess now that that’s out there, I should…there’s something I want you to know.”

“You sure?” Gabriel asked, catching her nervousness.

Ava swallowed and nodded. “I guess if I’ve learned anything these last couple of years, it’s to never leave things un-said.” she shrugged.

A news reel of different emotions rapid-fired across Gabriel’s face, but he sat down and said nothing, letting Ava take her time.

“I miss my parents.” she said, finally. “It’s…so nice to have a parent again, I love you. You took me in, you’ve been everything I needed but…”

“I understand.” Gabriel said softly. “There’s no substitute for the original. Hell, I miss my folks."

“No, that’s not it…” Ava sighed, then wiped her eyes. “I feel really guilty whenever I think this, but I kind of feel like…like you’ve been a better father to me. You’re here, you’ve always been here for Adam, and you’ve been here for me too. I hate to say it, but my parents’ idea of being good parents was just to, to buy me stuff. They gave me whatever I asked for but they didn’t really…I don’t know…"

“They gave you what you asked for, which maybe wasn’t what you needed?” Gabriel finished.

“…Papa would never have joked about fixing the bed.” Ava said. “And…Mom would have told me off for not brushing my hair, but you asked if I was feeling okay. Stuff like that, that you do for me and for Adam. You treat us like a, like you’re our friend as well as our dad. I miss them, but…they treated me more like a doll or a…a pet or a trophy sometimes."

Gabriel handed her a clean tissue, which she made grateful use of. “You don’t need to feel guilty of that, you know.” he said.

“I know that up here." Ava tapped her scalp, then bunched a fist between her breasts and knocked on her sternum. “but…”

Gabe scooted round the table and hugged her. “It means a lot.” he promised. “I try but…it’s good to know you think I’m doing a good job.”

She smiled. “I’m glad I got that out there.”

Gabe laughed a little. “Go home and sleep.” he suggested. “You’re going to need it, but you’re welcome to come round, join Jess and me for dinner this evening.”

“I’d like that_._” she told him, and stood up.

“Go. Sleep. Nos vemos."

"Hasta luego, papa."

Date Point: 5y 11m 1w AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

The passenger jump array had been expanded again during the year of Adam’s absence, but they’d kept the glass wall, allowing friends and family to witness the arrivals and departures.

There were a lot of them these days. Byron Group employees headed home for Christmas, travellers from Earth visiting Cimbrean for the same…

And Adam’s face on a nearly unrecognisable body.

Ava’s jaw threatened to drop. Adam had warned her, as best he could, about what to expect from the fitness regime he’d been on, but she hadn’t been prepared for this.

Sure, he’d been fit before leaving and at the end of Basic. Buff, even. But the Adam who caught her gaze and smiled that same winning, puppyish smile at her was getting to the point where the word “buff” was no longer quite adequate. He was…

He was…

He was fucking HOT.

A year of living alone had inevitably resulted in fantasizing and…well, in entertaining herself as best she could, and Ava had assembled a sizable folder on her tablet full of big strong guys. While knowing that he was going to come back big and strong had almost certainly played a role in shaping her tastes that way, Adam would not have looked out of place in that folder.

She made a mental note to add some pictures of him to it.

His muscles were as firm and dense as teak when they hugged, and he made her feel featherlight when he picked her up and spun her around, beaming.

"GOD I missed you."

She sighed happily and kissed him. “Your letters just…wow, they didn’t do justice. Look at you!”

He looked down and spread his arms. “You like?”

He turned around, and Ava had to fight to stop herself from automatically biting her lower lip. "Yeah…" she squeaked. “I mean, you were pretty before, but…”

They became aware that several bystanders were able to overhear them, to judge by the amused glances they were attracting, and shared a bit of a blush. Adam shouldered his bag with a weighty thump. “Am I…staying with you?”

“Why wouldn’t you be?”

“I’ve learned not to make assumptions.” he replied, clearly pleased by the response, then looked around. “Hey, where’s Dad?”

“He’s cooking Thanksgiving dinner. We’re going round there in a couple hours.”

“But Thanksgiving was last month.” Adam pointed out.

“Yeah, but you missed it.” she retorted. “And it was your birthday yesterday, so…”

“Does it work that way?”

“It does now.”

He laughed. “That works.”

Adam Ares

“Wow. Okay. Guess you’re opening the jars tonight, Amigo."

Adam laughed, and hugged his dad, gently. “Easy.” he said, then smiled at Jessica, who was hovering in the background with a slightly stunned expression. “Hey Jess.”

“’Hey' yourself!" she replied. “Good God you’ve changed since I last saw you."

They hugged.

“Wasn’t easy.” he told her. “Gotta tell ya, hearing you and Dad were dating really picked me up when I was having a rough time with the EMT training.”

“You were struggling with that?” Ava asked, hanging up her jacket and sitting down at Gabriel’s dinner table, while Gabriel returned to the kitchen. The whole apartment smelled of turkey and potatoes.

“Yeah. Think I’ve learned just enough about medicine now to know that I know basically nothing about medicine. It’s…crazy." he sighed. “And for a while there I just wasn’t getting it, you know? My buddy Baseball--you remember Baseball?”

Ava giggled. “Hard to forget.”

He laughed. “Right. Well, he was kicking my ass. He’s a total natural. Me…I mean, I’m starting to get it now, but for a long while there, getting all that knowledge to stay in my head was damn near impossible. You’ve got to learn a lot of the academic stuff before you can start working on the practical, you know?”

“You always were more of a hands-on kinda guy.” Gabriel noted, from the kitchen. Jess nodded, smiling and looking up at the ceiling with an 'oh yeah' expression.

“You were okay though?” she asked.

“Ah, y’know. I was just…frustrated.” Adam’s chair creaked as he sat down next to Ava. “Like, I’d gone through all the pain of Indoc and all that PT and everything, and here I was struggling with what I’d thought was gonna be the easy bit. So yeah, the good news from home helped there. Made me feel positive again, and that helped me get past the block. Can’t say I’m ever going to be a great medic, but I’m not gonna be a bad medic, either."

“So you approve?” Gabe asked, appearing with the plates.

“Oh come on, Dad! I mean, of course I do, but you don’t need my approval."

Jess and Gabe exchanged a happy glance, and both headed into the kitchen.

“Guess this is a family Thanksgiving then.” Ava commented, snuggling up next to Adam.

“Late though it is.” Gabe agreed, reappearing with the roast potatoes. “Adam, put those muscles to use Amigo, bring the turkey through?"

Adam laughed and did so, retrieving a bird the size of a dog from the oven which he hefted easily on one oven-gloved hand. “Where did you get this?”

“Cimbrean wild turkey.” Jess revealed. “They’re part of the ecosystem reconstruction.”

“No shit? What else is out there?”

“Bobcats, bats, mice, eels, eagles…” Ava smiled. “From what Hayley Tisdale was telling me, they’re throwing a whole bunch of different species into the mix and letting natural selection do the rest.”

“They’re talking about deer and wolves, too.” Jess added. “It’s not all going perfectly right--I heard the eagles especially are struggling. Apparently the low gravity throws off their instincts when they’re swooping in on top of something, and they struggle to hunt at first.”

“How is Hayley?” Adam asked.

“She’s…She and Marc, they’re both okay. Did I tell you they had a little girl?”

“…Yeah, you did. Hope?”

“Hope. That’s right.” Ava nodded. “She was gonna come back to Folctha after the birth but the medical advice was it’s probably not good for a kid to live in low gravity until at least their second growth spurt which is, what? Ten or eleven years? And even then… "

“Right.” Adam nodded.

“So, they’re living in London nowadays, working for the Reclamation Project. Something about…GMO plants that are better suited to Cimbrean’s soil, gravity and sunlight.”

Gabe set down the last of the gravy, vegetables and sauces, and glanced around the table, looking happier and less stressed than Adam could remember seeing him in a long time. “So…Thanksgiving. It’s been a rough and crazy few years, and…you know, I can’t remember the last time we actually did this. I just wanted you to know how thankful I am to have the three of you in my life.”

Jess smiled, and murmured a “Hear, hear.”

Gabe and Ava exchanged glances, and bowed their heads in prayer. Jess just put her elbow on the table and her chin in her hand, watching them with a faint smile.

Adam…thought.

It was a skill he hadn’t been given much opportunity to practice. Constant PT, constant education, interspersed only with meals, sleep and only a little leisure time (most of which had been taken up by letters and Madden) hadn’t made for a contemplative year. He’d learned to enjoy moments, though, and this moment was…

Warm. Comfortable. He shut his eyes and let it wash over him--the gentle breathing, the wall clock marking away the seconds, the buzz of the kitchen light and hum of the oven fan, the warmth of Ava sitting next to him, the soft sound of his Dad praying under his breath…

He opened his eyes when Gabriel murmured an "Amen“, and looked up.

“So…” he asked. “What are the rest of you having?”

Date Point: Boxing Day, 5y 11m 2w AV

Adam wasn’t yet asleep, but it still took him a couple of seconds to register the knock on his door.

He sat up a bit “Ava?”

She called through the door. “Can I come in?”

“Sure!”

She’d left the hall light on and leaned against the door frame, backlit by it, and Adam just had to stare. She was wearing one of his t-shirts, a thin white one. The shirt itself wasn’t blocking any of the light from behind her, and the varying depth of shadow her body made under it was…

Amazing. Sexy. Gorgeous. He could just about make out her nipples by the shadows they cast across the fabric, and the shirt was just short enough to create a fascinating dark triangle with her thighs. When he looked up at her face, she was breathing heavily through slightly parted lips.

“Past midnight?” he asked.

She laughed, nervously. “Happy birthday to me.”

"Deja vu." he observed. She laughed a little again, and took a pace forward, loitering at the end of the bed.

“I’ve been…kind of regretting that, I, uh…I chickened out last time.” she confessed.

“Ch-uh, chickened out?”

She knelt on the edge of his bed and crawled up it like a predatory cat to kiss him.

It was a different kiss to any they’d shared before--a fiercer, more adult one. He was still mind-blanked by it when she grabbed his wrist and guided his hand firmly onto flesh that was so warm it almost felt like she’d burn the skin off his palm.

He took the hint and put his free hand on the back of her head, pulling her into the kiss. By the time it came to a natural conclusion she was pressed right up against him, every warm inch of her, and his roaming hands had discovered that she wasn’t wearing so much as a stray thread under that shirt.

All of that notwithstanding, though, she was trembling.

“You sure you’re ready?” he asked.

“I am.” she promised, and straddled his lap, grinding against him and making him acutely aware of just how little and thin the blanket was, knowing how close which bits of him were to which bits of her. There was a scent in the room he’d never smelled before, and it was having an urgent effect on some very ancient parts of his brain.

He could feel every inch of his body pulsing, shaken by a heart that was suddenly hammering away as hard as if he was back in Indoc. Was feeling sick and shaky the right response here? It was all his body seemed to know how to do. For all he wanted to be suave and confident and passionate with her, deep inside he was a knot of anxiety and trepidation. So was she, judging by the way she froze when her hand paused in trailing down his body, just short if its destination.

“You’re scared.” he observed. She just smiled weakly and nodded. “We don’t have to if you don’t--” he began.

“I want to.” she interrupted him.

“But…you’re scared.”

“So are you.”

He couldn’t deny it.

“Do you want to?" she asked.

The honest answer was that every nerve in his body did, bits of him hurt with wanting to, but he was becoming too paralysed by the shakes to do more than nod.

It seemed to be enough for Ava’s purposes. She scooted down his legs, taking the blanket away, and conjured a little square foil pack that she must have smuggled in with her, somehow. “Lie back.” she whispered.

Adam could no more have disobeyed her than he could have willed himself to teleport to Mars. He lay back and shut his eyes, almost hyperventilating as she pulled his pajamas off him.

She made a noise, something between a frightened whimper and a “wow”, and there was a little crinkly noise as she tore open the wrapper of the thing she’d brought with her.

“I don’t know how to put one of those on…” he objected.

“It’s okay.” she promised, and touched him where the contact went through him like an electric shock. “I do.”

After that, while they made plenty of other noises, the only talking they did was in the form of whispered instructions and little two-word prayers.

When he woke in the morning, she was still there. It hadn’t been a dream.

Most of the morning was spent fielding birthday well-wishes for Ava. Her presents were both more numerous and more impressive than Adam’s, but he didn’t mind--she could take them with her, after all.

It was only after the last of their visitors had gone that either of them were able to discuss what had happened the night before, as they were finishing the washing up.

“Did you…” she cleared her throat. “…Was it…okay?”

He took her hand. “It was…kind of awkward.” he confessed.

“Yeah…” she nodded agreement. “I’m sorry…”

“No, no…it was great! Uh…maybe we, uh, just need to practice.”

She thought about that, put her head on one side, put the last fork on the drying rack and vanished into the bedroom.

“Uh, Ava…?”

Her shirt flew out of the door. “So let’s practice!” she called.

“Oh! Right!” He tripped over his own socks in his rush to pull them off and join her.

They practiced.

((Don’t move on to chapter 23 yet! This has been just the first part of Chapter 22: you can find the link to the rest of this chapter below))

Chapter 26
The Second Year | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point: First Contact Day, 6y AV
HMS Sharman, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Owen Powell

“I’m glad that’s out of the way.”

Powell chuckled. He’d worked under Admiral Patrick Knight before, when the man had been a Commodore. Knight was his opposite in many ways: where Powell was wiry, intense and shaven, Knight was a slender beanpole who wore a white moustache and a relaxed demeanour. They had in common a hatred of needless ceremony--both were men of deed rather than pomp. “It was a good speech.” he reassured the admiral.

“I should damn well hope so.” Knight chuckled. “Interest you in a drink, Major? You really shouldn’t accept a promotion without celebrating it somehow."

“I don’t really have enough mates for a wetting down.” Powell said.

“Hence a snifter of Brandy with a posh old dinosaur like me instead.” Knight winked.

“…Aye, alright. Got to mark the occasion sometime.”

“Knew you’d come around.” Knight fished out some cut glass tumblers and a decanter. Knowing the admiral, they’d been among the very first things he’d unpacked. “You must be pleased with yourself. This is quite a command you’ve landed.”

“Oh aye.” Powell agreed, watching him pour. “A promotion and five times as much paperwork? I’m living the dream.”

Knight chuckled quietly. “That you are. Do you have any idea how much there is to do in upgrading this camp into a full blown HMS?”

“Why d’you think I’m volunteering to go through a couple of years of hard training instead?”

This got a full-fledged laugh, and Knight handed him his drink. “I appreciate that you’re the only man with ANY experience of commanding the kind of operations this Regiment of yours will be conducting” he said “but are you absolutely SURE you’re up to this, Powell? Those men are going to need somebody they can respect and follow without question, and that means you’ll need to keep up with them in training. Physically speaking…”

Powell raised a hand. “I’m not as young as I once was.” he agreed. “But I’ll either clear that training or die trying, you can bet your life savings on that one, sir.”

“Knowing you, you mean that literally.” Knight raised his glass. “To the former, then.”

Powell met the toast. “Aye.”

Date Point: 6y 5m AV

"Miss Ava Rios,
20 Delaney Row,
Folctha, Cimbrean
CIFO11 3BQ

Dear Ava,

I am delighted to offer you a place on our BA Journalism (Hons) course, reflecting the glowing praise given by your senior school teacher Dr. J. Olmstead and the high academic performance you have been able to demonstrate. While we regret not being able to interview you in person, we felt that your application letter showed you to be erudite and charming, and we hope to see you at the start of the semester on September 17th of this year.

Please find enclosed your full admissions package and the details of what you will need to do in order to confirm your place on our course.

Yours sincerely,

Jennifer Roberts, Admissions Officer
City University London.

Date Point: 6y 6m AV
Kirtland Air Force Base, New Mexico, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

“You realise you guys are crazy, right?”

Adam looked up. Like most of the others, he’d been examining the maroon beret in his hands for most of the evening, scarcely able to believe he was finally holding it, gently feeling the fabric, and just appreciating it.

Tony Collins high-fived him. Collins was one of the majority who were staying on as full-time PJs, and Adam had a huge amount of respect for all of them. They took the creed seriously.

“Guess we are.” he agreed. Baseball was on Skype to his mother back in LA, but there was no doubt who the other half of the “you guys” plural that Collins had used was meant to be.

“You’re gonna be old men before you’re even done training.” Collins added, sitting down. “I don’t know how you’ve got the patience for it.”

“Twenty-three ain’t old.” Adam told him.

“It’ll fuckin’ feel like it by the time you’re mission ready.” Collins retorted. “Where are you shipping out to next, anyway?”

“Got some comprehensive armament training and then it’s on to Alabama. Astronaut training in Huntsville.”

“Fuckin’ space cowboys.” Collins chuckled, then held out a hand. Adam stood, shook it, and Collins slammed into him in a vigorous guy-hug. “Hey, you ever decide you want to come back down to Earth, you let me know, Hoss.”

Adam smiled. “Go save lives, man. It’s been a privilege.”

Date Point: 6y 9m AV

“Wow. You really don’t have a lot of stuff, do you?”

Ava’s worldly possessions, in fact, consisted of one suitcase full of clothing, a backpack, and two modest cardboard boxes. Adam owned even less, and most of that had long since been put into storage in the bottom of his dad’s wardrobe, or given to charity.

“Most of the plates and stuff came with the house.” She said, looking around it for probably the last time.

Delaney Row was the last holdout of the little compact portable houses that had been Array-jumped to Folctha during the early days of the colonisation, and those were only holding out while the next housing plan was built. They were marvels of efficient use of space, squeezing two bedrooms, a kitchen, living area and bathroom into a mere double-digit of square footage.

“You’re going to miss this place, aren’t you?” Gabe observed.

“Yeah. I’ve got so used to how everything just sort of hides away or pulls double-duty.” She agreed, demonstrating how the steps up into her bedroom were also the bookshelf and the fridge door. She sighed, and took down the last thing--an oval of varnished Pinkwood with the word “EDEN” pyrographed into its surface that had been hanging from the door ever since they’d first arrived.

She put it on top of the smaller box, the one full of things she was leaving for Gabriel and Jess to look after, then stood in the middle of the room and flapped her arms, once. “Goodbye, house.”

They walked her to the Array terminal and watched through the glass as it activated while she was mid-wave. A cuboid of perfect blackness filled the jump room, and when it collapsed out of existence, it took her with it.

Gabe sagged, the instant she was gone.

Jess just took his hand and walked him home.

Date Point: 6y 9m AV
Huntsville, Alabama, USA, Earth

“Aw man, you guys got here first? I was hoping for a good bed!"

There was some laughter, and the four men from Delta Force who had been squaring their stuff away dropped what they were doing to welcome Adam and Baseball.

“They’re all good beds.” One of them promised. “So you’re our PJs? Jeez, you guys look like you could rip a steer in half.”

“We both got plenty of gains in us yet.” Baseball noted. “You guys’re on the Crue-D too, huh?”

“We all are.” The one with the name ‘Stevenson’ on his chest declared. “You think we’re gonna get bigger?”

“Shit yeah!” Baseball enthused. “Warhorse here’s gonna be the fuckin’ freak, though. Stumpy-ass midget fucker’s got the mechanical advantage.”

“Warhorse?” Sergeant Akiyama gave Adam a questioning look, as Adam gave his friend a cheerful middle finger.

“Cause he can carry a lotta heavy shit.” Baseball told them, sparing Adam’s blushes for once.

“We’re gonna need it.” Vandenberg commented. Adam got the feeling that where the other three had sized him up--as he had to them in turn--Vandenberg was evaluating him. Not maliciously, but it was telling that Stevenson, Sikes and Akiyama glanced at him as if to gauge his opinion. It was a subtle, deferential bit of body language that Adam almost missed. They shook hands. “You guys heard anything about the suits we’ll be wearing yet?”

“Only a guesstimate of the weight.” Adam told him.

“Yeah, I did some digging. Word is the designer’s a guy called Andrew Cavendish, and everything I could find about the guy says that’s not a guesstimate. He’ll have had the weight of that suit down to ten decimal places long before they built a prototype.”

“You dig up our itinerary for the week in all that research?” Baseball asked him

“Nope. Guess nobody’s made an extravehicular special forces unit before, so it’s all being played by ear. Heard we’re all arriving today though, and my guess is we’ll be doing some PT after everyone’s in and stowed away. Maybe a speech from the old man first, you know how it goes.”

There was some nodding. “Guess we’d better get our shit away.” Adam said.

“Top bunk!” Baseball called, dashing towards an unclaimed dorm room. The others nodded, waved and wandered off to carry on their chores.

“…He knows we’ve all got our own room, doesn’t he?” Akiyama asked.

“Ah, that’s just a tradition of his.” Adam replied, flinging his own bag over his shoulder and heading for the door next to Baseball’s. “I got the top bunk in basic, he reckons it should have been his, ’cause he’s taller, so… ”

“So he grabs it first. Right.”

“I’ll be right back. Better unload my stuff.”

“Sure. We’ve got a couple hours before the Controllers and the Brits arrive, we were gonna watch Zombie Shark Three. Sound good?”

“Sounds fucking terrible.” Adam replied. “I’m in.”

Date Point: 6y 9m AV
London, England, Earth

Ava Rios

“Hello?”

Ava had been dreading what the halls of residence might be like. There had been horror stories all over the Internet, which was why she’d saved up her teaching money to get herself some of the really good ones in the colourful new building.

Frankly, the space could have been put to much better use. If it had been designed with the same efficiency and folding-away that "Eden" had boasted, she could have had a whole house in that room. But it would do, if kept tidy.

She’d been hanging up her clothes when the 'hello?' had arrived simultaneously with a knock on the door, which, being ajar, swung inwards cautiously.

“Ooh! Roommate!”

Ava waved hello. The girl who’d opened the door was tall, somewhere upwards of six feet, every inch of which lived in her thistledown-light long limbs. Between her straight ash-blonde hair, dazzling blue eyes, nordic skin and the diaphanous, layered pale blue summer dress she was wearing, she would have been intimidatingly pretty if not for her unreservedly friendly smile and bare feet.

“Hi.” Ava said, offering a cautious wave.

“Hello.” the blonde girl greeted her. She had a high, musical voice and a cultured accent. “How are you setting in? Have you been here long?”

“I just got here.” Ava revealed, indicating her suitcase and cardboard box on the bed. “I don’t have a lot of stuff with me.”

“Oh, you are so lucky, my parents wouldn’t let me leave home without…everything! My room’s a tip!"

Ava laughed, and stuck out a hand. “Ava.”

“Hi Ava! I’m Charlotte.” came the reply, along with a handshake that was every bit as delicate as the girl herself. “You’re American!”

“Cimbrean, actually.” Ava told her, deciding that first introductions were probably not a great time to mention San Diego.

“…As in, the planet Cimbrean? Oh my God!" Charlotte scooted into the room and sat eagerly on Ava’s desk chair, immediately confirming Ava’s suspicion that she was the kind of person who made friends instantly, whether or not the friend in question agreed.

Fortunately, she was in a mood to make friends, and Charlotte seemed nice.

Charlotte leaned forward eagerly. “Deets.”

“Deets?”

“Details! What’s it like living on another planet? Are there aliens?”

Ava giggled. “Yeah, there are aliens. They’re Buddhists.”

“Buddhists? Really?”

“Oh yeah. And you can get high off the local tea. And the capitol city’s called Folctha, which is the Irish word for ‘bath’, because the lady who named it walked half-way round the planet to get to that bath and was in it when the soldiers arrived to found the colony."

“Wow!”

Despite Ava’s best efforts to make it all sound incredible, Charlotte looked like she believed every word without question. “Okay,” Ava asked her. “Where are you from?”

“Newcastle. Up north, I know I don’t sound it, we moved up there when I was seven.”

“I wouldn’t know the difference.” Ava confessed. “I’ve never been to England before.”

“Oh. Well, it sounds…” Charlotte cleared her throat, and spoke in a rounder, impenetrable accent. “…’A_hreet, ahya coominoot thaneet?_”

Ava raised a hand to cover her laugh, and decided that she liked Charlotte, who’d bobbled her head and made a silly face during her imitation. “Okay, what did that mean?”

"Darling, you simply must come and have a drink with me on the town this evening." Charlotte explained, employing a bourgeois motion of the hand and a toss of her head to punctuate the word 'must’, and beamed when Ava giggled. “Daddy wanted me to be an actress.” she revealed. “I think he’s a bit put out that I’d rather be a midwife.”

Ava nodded. “I’m doing journalism.” she replied.

“So, are we having that drink?”

“We…? Oh. Yeah. We can! I keep forgetting I’m old enough to drink in this country.” She nodded. “Can I have a few minutes to finish putting my stuff away? Then sure, let’s go have fun.”

“Don’t be too long!” Charlotte told her, and skipped out of the room to grab her coat, shoes and handbag.

Ava watched her go, smiling, and hurried to finish hanging up her shirts.

Date Point: 6y 9m AV
Huntsville Alabama, USA, Earth

Adam Ares.

ROAR!

CRUNCH!!

"JOHN!!! NOOOOO!!!!"

Baseball lost it, covered his face with one hand and writhed in his seat, wheezing a laugh deep in his gut. “Oh my fucking…”

“He’s actually milking the giant cow." Adam noted, folding his arms and throwing his head back to stare at the ceiling rather than the farce on screen. The whole movie was bad to the point of hilarity, leaving all six of them in varying stages of laughter, from Baseball’s high-pitched Muttley snicker, to Vandenberg’s nasal explosions.

Stevenson wiped away a tear. “Man, fucking…oh my God." his voice had gone up about an octave. “This has GOT to be deliberate.”

“Of course it is.” Vandenberg said. “Come on, you don’t think they took this shit seriously do you?"

“Just be tragic if they had.” Akiyama agreed.

“Ah, shit…” Adam grabbed the remote, spying movement out the corner of his eye through the window. “I think the old man’s here early.”

There was a general looking-around and standing-up as it became apparent that he was right, a group of men were on the path round the side of the dorm building, carrying bags.

They were up and waiting when the door opened therefore, to admit four men that Adam didn’t recognise and, bringing up the rear, Legsy.

“Wa-HEY!!” the huge Brit pounced on Adam and tried to hoist him up in a hug, only just managing it. “Fuckin’ look at you, pal!" He delivered a friendly punch to the arm. “Knew you had it in you!”

Adam laughed and returned the show of affection with a high-five that turned into a shoulder-barging hug, which was interrupted by a cry of “Room, ten- SHUT!”

Everyone snapped to attention.

“Stand at ease.”

Eleven boots shifted sideways by a synchronized shoulder-width as Major Owen Powell nodded his satisfaction and strolled into the middle of the room, the very picture of a confident and seasoned officer inspecting his subordinates for the first time. He looked good, Adam realised. Powell had never looked frail, but presumably he was on the Crue-D too--he’d gained some serious muscle mass, and several of the lines in his face were gone, or much reduced. He looked younger, fiercer and stronger.

“Ares. Burgess.” he greeted them, favouring Adam with a nod. “Settling in well?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Good.” The major turned and addressed everyone. “Stand easy, lads.” He ordered.

Everyone unwound a little bit, adjusted their clothes, and settled into a relaxed but alert posture with their hands resting lightly in the small of their backs, paying attention.

“I won’t keep you long.” Powell told them, finding a spot where they could all face him and be faced in turn. “Today’s a rest and social day, just get to know one another. We’ll be doing intensive PT throughout the rest of this week and some confidence-building, but for now, introductions.”

“For those who don’t know me, my name is Major Owen Powell, Royal Marines Special Boat Service. My service history includes the Persian Gulf, Operation Elder Grove, Kenya, and Cimbrean. I am, for the time being, the only commissioned officer in the SOR: When and how that changes is still being discussed. Master Sergeant Jones here-” he indicated Legsy “Is your NCOIC.”

He looked around. “I appreciate that with eight of you being American, you may not be certain about having a British commanding officer. I intend to demonstrate that I can hang with the best of them and that I got this position on merit. By the time we’re done here, I’ll have certified to operate a spacesuit alongside you, and will have undergone Crue-D aggressive training just like everyone else.”

Adam nodded slightly, pleased to hear it. He’d guessed that Powell would stand for nothing less, but it was good to hear the major confirm it.

For his part, Powell seemed satisfied that he’d said enough. “We’ll be discussing our full itinerary tomorrow after morning PT. This whole project is uncharted territory, so you’re going to be heavily involved in getting things set up, figuring out what roles we fill and how we’re going to set about getting the best of our training opportunities. We’ll get it right, and between us we’ll set up a unit that’ll be the pride and envy of the galaxy. Arright?”

There was a chorused. “Yes sir!”

“Good. Legsy, you know how to reach me if I’m needed. The rest of you--As you were. Have fun.”

Everyone relaxed once the door closed behind him.

“So yeah, that’s the old man.” Legsy commented, grinning. “Relax boys, I’ve worked with him for years. We’re in fuckin’ good hands.”

Vandenberg nodded. “I was wondering what he’d be like. Nice to meet you, Master Sergeant.”

“’Ey, I’m Legsy to everybody, even my Nan, God rest ’er." Legsy protested, though he shook Vandenberg’s hand, and those of the other Deltas.

The other four men that Adam didn’t recognise turned out to be their two Combat Controllers--Scott Blaczynski and Christian Firth--and two more Special Boat Service operators, Leo Price and Robert Murray.

“So…no offense to you guys or anything, but how come we don’t got no Seals in this unit?” Sikes asked. He’d so far been the quiet one of the Deltas, content to let everyone else do the talking.

“USN didn’t sign up to the Regiment.” Murray said. He too was a quiet one, a soft-spoken Scot with a nasty scar down the length of one forearm. It must have been an old one, maybe even pre-dating his military career, or else the Crue-D treatment would have softened and faded it.

“They got a rationale for that, that you know of?” Vandenberg asked.

“What I heard was that we’re goin’ tae need more than one kind of operator out there.” Murray shrugged. “Us here? We’re all goin’ tae be bloody huge by the time we’re done. That’s no good for a Seal. They need to stay normal-sized. But on the other hand, they’ll have the stickin’ power for long deployments, which we won’t.”

Vandenberg nodded. “Right. I don’t care if we find a Class Three where squirrels made of peanut butter jump into our mouths, we’re not gonna be breaking even for calories on any op we do." He nodded towards Adam. "Especially not the PJs."

“Bloody right.” Murray agreed, looking to Adam. “You’re volunteering to carry the rest of us? You’re fuckin’ crazy, pal.”

Adam gave a self-deprecating little shrug and looked around the room. Legsy was unpacking an old PS3, which Baseball, Firth and Akiyama were practically salivating over. Stevenson and Price, meanwhile, were setting up in the kitchen ready to prepare their first barracks dinner, an occasion which Stevenson had marked by donning a pink gingham apron.

“…I think we all are.” he said.

Date Point: 6y 9m AV
Saddlers Bar, CULSU student bar, London, England, Earth

Ava Rios

“So…not a wine fan, huh?”

Ava shook her head apologetically and handed over the glass. “I think I’ll keep it in church.” she said, licking her lips to try and get rid of the aftertaste. If that was alcohol, she was beginning to wonder what the appeal might be.

Charlotte nodded, finished the wine, then spied something over Ava’s shoulder and did an admirable impression of a magpie catching sight of something shiny. “Ooh! Boy candy!”

Ava turned reflexively to frown at whatever Charlotte was staring at, not really seeing anything. “What?”

“The two in the waistcoats by the bar?” Charlotte insisted, though she sounded more amused than impatient.

Ava finally saw them. “Oh.” she turned back to Charlotte, who rolled her eyes.

“Really?” she demanded.

“What?”

“They’re pretty!” Charlotte insisted.

“They’re stick thin!” Ava objected.

“What, don’t tell me you’re into fat guys?”

“I’m into a guy who can pick me up.” Ava replied, allowing herself the luxury of a boast and a sly smile. That little experiment had been especially fun. Charlotte rewarded her with a mock-scandalized pantomime, raising her fingertips to her open mouth, mimicking a little gasp and raising her eyebrows.

“Okay.” she demanded. “Deets.”

“What? My boyfriend can pick me up.” Ava feigned innocence, then relented and allowed her sultry smile to show. “Against a wall. For, like, half an hour.”

“You’re making that up!” Charlotte scoffed.

“Well…It felt like half an hour, anyway." Ava conceded. She hadn’t exactly been watching the clock for an objective assessment.

“Wow…” Charlotte drifted off into a fantasy fugue for a second. “Still…I want that blond one.” she looked over Ava’s shoulder at the 'boy candy' again.

Ava examined Charlotte’s choice. He was about six feet tall, well-groomed and sporting some slightly retro stubble and the kind of fashionable haircut and makeup that would have looked very strange ten years ago. Good-looking, but in a kind of slim, metrosexual way. His sleeves were rolled up, revealing tattoos that looked like they went all the way up.

His friend was taller, darker of hair and paler of skin with a distinctively straight nose and a square jaw that looked a bit out of place on his otherwise rail-thin frame.

As Ava watched, the oriental dragon coiled around the blond’s left arm moved its head and flicked a serpentine tongue.

“Wait, what the fuck, his tattoo’s animated?" she asked

“Yeah! Nanotattoos! Don’t you have those in space yet?”

“We don’t even have the old-fashioned ink kind in Folctha.” Ava revealed. “So, what, he’s got nanites under his skin?”

“Yep. And you can upload pictures and designs from your phone.” Charlotte tugged down the neck of her dress slightly, revealing a fairy on her breast, who flapped her wings and ran a hand through her hair. She plucked her phone from inside her bra and fiddled with it, cycling the decoration through a cluster of hearts, a butterfly and a fish before returning to the fairy. All of the different designs were animated.

“Are those even safe?” Ava asked, still reeling from the revelation that they even existed.

“Safer than the ink kind, they’re all hypoallergenic and stuff. And you can just turn them off if you want to be neat for a job interview or something." Charlotte said. “You should get one!”

“Boy candy, remember?” Ava changed the subject.

“Oh, right!” Charlotte knocked back the last of her drink and adjusted her dress some more so as to ensure that her tattoo (and more importantly its canvas) was prominently on display. “Would you be a darling and fly wing- girl?”

Ava froze. “I’ve never flown wing-girl in my life!”

“It’s easy, just talk to his friend.”

“How do I…?”

“Relax.” Charlotte gave her best winning smile. “I’ll break the ice.”

She grabbed Ava’s hand and towed her to the bar, and interrupted the 'boy candy’s conversation with a friendly. “Hi! I’m Charlotte, I’m from Newcastle. This is Ava--she’s from outer space.”

Ava could only give them an apologetic smile and a shrug.

Up close, she had to admit that Charlotte was right: they were pretty. The taller one with the dark hair, who was wearing a silver waistcoat and bottle- green jeans, shook their hands smiling a relaxed and amused smile. “Hello Charlotte from Newcastle and Ava from outer space.” he said, “I’m Sean from Finchley, and this is Ben from…actually where are you from, Ben?"

“Southampton.” Ben replied, treating Charlotte to a handsome half-smile that was the exact masculine answer to her own flirtatious stance. Sean looked between them, then caught Ava’s gaze and rolled his eyes. “I’ll get the drinks in then, shall I?” He offered.

Ava suppressed a laugh. “I’ll join you.”

They left Ben and Charlotte to go through the motions of getting to know one another and retreated to the bar.

“So…Outer space?” Sean asked.

“Cimbrean.”

“Really? Dench!” He beamed. “What’s it like out there?”

Ava sighed. “It was beautiful." she said. “Right now it’s all, kinda like…being built or regrown. All the native plants near Folctha have died and the Terran imports are so young, y’know? It’s going to be a forest eventually but right now it’s just a whole bunch of saplings.

“What really happened to it anyway?”

“What did you hear?” Ava asked.

“That somebody took a dump in the woods.”

“Yep. That’s what really happened.”

Sean burst out laughing. “You’re taking the piss!”

She shrugged. “Nope. That’s what happened. Crazy, huh?”

Sean laughed again and shook his head. “Mad. Anyway: buy you a drink?”

“Sure, but I’m…kinda taken.”

Sean laughed again. He had an easy, light laugh that he seemed to deploy often. “Relax duck, I’m not like them two.” he jerked his thumb toward Ben and Charlotte. “I don’t go from 'hi there' to 'let’s rock the sheets' in two seconds. What’s yours?"

“My-? Oh, my drink. Uh…Iunno, I’ve never really drunk before.”

“You like cranberry?”

“Sure.”

“Right, Amaretto and cranberry and a Corona and lime then.”

Ava inclined her head. “Why’s that?”

“I like them both so whichever you decide you like, I’ll have the other.” Sean said. He caught the bartender’s eye and placed the order.

“So what’s your other half’s name?” He asked upon turning back to her.

“Adam. Airman Adam Ares, United States Air Force.”

“Yeah? Your bloke’s military? Blates dench.”

Ava shook her head, a little incredulous of the slang. “Okay, okay, what the HELL does ‘P_late stench_’ mean?” she demanded.

Sean laughed again as he received the drinks. “Blates. Dench.” he enunciated. “Blatantly awesome. 'I say old thing, that really is rather amazing’. You see? Anyway, have a sip of these, tell me which you prefer."

Ava accepted the amaretto-cranberry first and sipped it. It was pleasantly sweet and sort of…nutty? Pastry? The beer on the other hand just made her stick out her tongue and make a sort of 'nghah!' sound and she thrust it back into Sean’s hand, drawing another of those easy, light laughs out of him.

He was good for lifting her mood at least, she decided. Her life could do with more laughter.

“What about you?” she asked. “Where’s Finchley?”

“Oh, about ten stops away on the Tube.” he smiled. “Bit closer than Cimbrean.”

“Just a bit!” she agreed.

“What’re you studying?” Sean asked.

“Journalism.”

“Yeah? Same here!”

“Oh, thank God.” she sighed. “I’ll have somebody to sit next to in class.”

“Am I literally the only person you know, then?” Sean asked, then glanced up. “Besides…Charlotte, was it?”

“That’s right. And, yes.”

“What’s she doing?”

“Uh…Midwifery. I think.”

Sean laughed again. "Her? Ditzy." he declared. “Those babies are gonna come into this world and the first thing they’ll see is her tattoo waving at them.”

Ava glanced across at Charlotte, who couldn’t have been flirting harder if she’d been giving Ben a lapdance. “Hey, she knows what she wants and she goes for it. I kind of admire that.”

“Shall we get back over there before they head back to the dorms?” Sean indicated the drinks.

Ava nodded, pleased to have made a friend. “Good idea.” she said.

Date Point: 6y 10m AV
Bankhead Parkway NE, Huntsville, Alabama, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

“Fuckin’ Christ, Ares. How heavy’s that ruck?”

“Tell…you what…” Adam took a few huge breaths to try and force down his panting breath, leaning on his own thighs. “You wanna…wear it? Try and…beat my time?”

He shrugged said pack off, and lowered it to the ground, restraining a sigh of relief. The bag was at least half again as heavy as his spacesuit was eventually going to be and he’d just finished a twenty click forced march that had, through sheer competitiveness and bloody-minded macho stupidity, become a twenty click jog, and then a twenty click run. He was fucking beat, but also determined not to show it.

That was probably true of everyone, however. Every last one of them had taken the opportunity, upon crossing the finish line, to ditch the bags and start inhaling sports drinks, and all of them, to his trained eye, were nursing something or another that was causing them pain. Most were staring off into the distance beyond the ground between their feet, in the meditative way of the truly exhausted.

“Not this year, thanks.” Price smacked him on the shoulder in a friendly way, and looked back down the path, wiping the sweat off his brow. “And hey, you beat the Major at least.”

“He’ll make it.” Adam said. “Can’t expect him to keep up with guys who are like two thirds his age.”

“Oh, I know he will, mate. I was on Operation Elder Grove with Powell.” Price said. “And to be fair, he only started on the magic potion like three months ago. He’s come a long way, fast.”

Adam looked back down the trail they’d just run just as Powell finally came into view.

He looked in a bad way. He was limping, his whole head was red with exertion and his scalp and nose were dripping with sweat, but there was a ferocious scowl on his face, the expression of a man who was doggedly telling physics and biology to go fuck themselves.

The Deltas to a man, plus Legsy, Burgess and Firth, hauled themselves stiffly to their feet and started whooping and hollering, inspiring their CO to put his head down a bit more and pick up his pace on the final straight, just by a little.

The cheering faded when his leg suddenly gave out under him, totally failing to hold his weight any longer. Powell nose-dived into the dirt and rolled, clutching at his calf and gritting teeth that were suddenly covered in the blood that was pouring from his nose.

Adam took off running just ahead of Baseball, and they arrived as Powell rolled over and started to lever himself upright.

“Sir--”

“Fook off.” The major tried to weight-bear on his left leg and nearly fell over again--there was no strength left in it at all. “Ee, ya fookin’- Aaargh!”

“As your medic--” Baseball began.

Powell grabbed the front of Baseball’s shirt…“I’m finishing. This fookin’ run.” he snarled, pausing for emphasis, “If I have to fookin’ HOP.”

“…Yes sir.”

Powell did exactly as he’d described, bouncing on his good leg to the edge of the trail and drawing his knife to cut the base of a thumb-thick branch from one of the hundreds of trees that had lined their trail. He tested his weight on it, then set off hobbling, pinching his nose to stop the bleeding and with two concerned pararescuemen exchanging worried glances in his shadow.

He was barely managing a walking pace, but true to his word, he finished the run, swearing and chuntering away to himself every inch of it before he finally crossed the line and sank down onto the concrete divider that marked where the path met the road, his face pinched and his teeth clenched. The men were all watching with expressions of mixed concern and admiration.

“Arright.” he declared. "NOW you can fookin’ medic me."

Baseball set to work, examining the enormous bruise that was already spreading across Powell’s calf. “Crue.” he demanded, sticking out a hand.

Adam had already prepared an injector, which he duly handed over. Baseball had a soft and efficient touch with needles. He also handed Powell an anaesthetic lolly. “stick that under your tongue for thirty seconds, sir.” he ordered.

Powell did as instructed, popping the little white painkiller wand into his mouth and then began to count aloud, though the stick under his tongue hindered the attempt slightly. "One michichippi , two michichi--"

“We’re in Alabama, sir.” Legsy joked. This earned some chuckles from the men, and the kind of feigned unimpressed look from Powell that the major reserved for bad jokes, but after a second he made an amused harrumph and started to count again, the crow’s feet wrinkles at his eyes deepening just a little. "One awagama, two awagama, free awagama…"

The chuckles became a ripple of laughter. Adam let him reach a twenty count before taking the stick back.

“You’re gonna need an hour or two for the Crude to work, major.” Baseball declared, using one of the many nicknames they’d adopted for Crue-D. He stood up. “Your nose--”

“Has been broken before, Burgess, thank you.” Powell shrugged. “I already fookin’ sorted it.”

“Yes sir. You should probably still put a slap patch on that.” Baseball replied, cutting little triangles out of one so that it would fit over the major’s nose properly.

“I’ll save it for my fookin’ beauty sleep.” Powell told him.

“Wear it now, sir." Baseball insisted.

Powell tried to sigh through his nose, only for a thin trickle of blood to start flowing back out of his nostril. He frowned, took the slap patch and pinched it to the bridge of his nose, wincing slightly as he disturbed the break. “Anyone get my time?” he asked.

“I got it, sir.” Sikes produced the tablet computer he’d been recording them on.

“Right.” Powell looked at it, made a noncommittal grunt, and then looked around. “That, lads, is the worst time you’re ever going to do in this unit. Keep that time and look at it every now and again, because by the time we’re up to operational readiness? You’ll look at the time you just did today and think 'bloody hell, how was I ever that slow?' Arright?"

A chorus of “Yes Sir.” answered him.

“Good. Firth, call the barracks, get them to send our ride, will you? I don’t really feel like walking back, now… ”

Date Point: 6y 10m AV
Regent’s Park, London, UK, Earth.

Ava Rios

“Is everyone on Cimbrean as into fitness as you are?"

Ava and Sean were out for a mid afternoon walk. Ava would have preferred to jog, but Sean had vetoed it, and was complaining about the pace too, despite having longer legs.

“You have to be.” Ava explained, “The gravity’s so low that if you don’t spend time in the gym at least three times a week, all sorts of things go wrong.”

“Like what?”

“Muscle wastage, brittle bones, heart problems…all sorts of things. And then you get so used to it that NOT exercising just feels bad, you know?"

“I can’t say that I do, duck.” Sean shrugged.

“You’re not interested in getting fit?”

“I am fit!"

Ava restrained herself from laughing, with difficulty, but she couldn’t let that pass. “You’re not.” she said.

“Look at me! No fat on this anywhere!” Sean protested, lifting up his t-shirt. He was right. There was nothing on him but some dark hair, and his ribs, but Ava still snorted.

“No muscle, either.” she told him.

“Oh, like you’re the she-Hulk.” Sean grumbled, tugging the shirt back down again.

“I don’t need to be. I’m not in training for anything, I don’t want to run marathons or anything. I just want to be able to live on a low-G world without getting health problems, and have energy to do stuff.”

“And look good naked.”

“Please. I’d have to work at it to look bad naked." Ava joked.

“So would I!” Sean retorted.

Ava just shook her head smiling, and they walked in silence for a bit.

She became aware that he was breathing heavily as they started round the second side of the park, where huge cheering was just audible from Lord’s Cricket Ground. Sean fished his phone out of his pocket.

“What?” Ava asked him.

“Just checking…Oh, nice!”

"What?!"

“Patel’s gone for a duck.”

“That’s…good?”

“That’s good.” Sean agreed, running his hand through sweat-heavy hair. “Here, can we slow down?”

“For crying out loud!” Ava rounded on him. “You can’t even walk round the park without getting out of breath, and you claim to be fit?

“Well what do I need to be fit for?" Sean objected.

“Not getting short on breath when you go for a stroll? Better sex? Having something to show off under that shirt besides ribs and fur? Take your pick!”

Sean frowned at her. “I have great sex!” he objected.

“With who?”

“I’ve had five girlfriends, they didn’t complain.”

Ava laughed. “Fine, whatever.”

“They didn’t!”

Ava ignored him and drew her--Sara’s--camera from its by-now habitual spot on her hip. She’d found the custom-made quick-draw leather camera holster on Etsy, had treated herself to it, and had not regretted the decision for a minute. It earned her the occasional strange look, but a rather larger number of looks that said 'that’s so cool’, though she was frankly past the point where either kind of look really mattered to her.

Sean didn’t have to wait long. The camera was out, focused, took a series of seven rapid-fire photos, and was back in its holster inside five seconds.

“Aren’t you going to check those?” He asked.

“Nope.” Ava shrugged. She wasn’t pushing the pace at all, but still Sean seemed to be scurrying to keep up despite his longer legs, and he was short on breath.

“But how do you know they’re okay?”

“I took them okay.”

“How do you know though?"

Ava shook her head. “Because I took them okay.” she repeated.

“But--”

“Sean!” she stopped to glare at him again, then softened when he raised his hands defensively. “…Look, this was my best friend’s camera. Her parents gave it to me when she died. I was already pretty serious about getting good with it before Adam left for basic training, and since then I’ve had no social life, I’ve had nothing to do but study and practice with this thing. For a while there it was literally the only thing I had. So trust me: if I say I took a picture okay, I took a picture okay. Okay?"

“…Do you do anything with those photos?” he asked.

“Not really.” She shrugged. “Not yet.”

“Maybe you should. If you’re going to make a living from it, you need to start getting your name out there, and if you’re that confident that what you’re taking is good…”

Ava considered it as she started walking again. “Maybe you’re right. A blog maybe? My own website?”

“Go with the website.” Sean recommended. “My mate Dave can set you up, if you want. He’ll code the site, host it, get you social media awareness, the works.”

“Yeah? What’s the catch?”

“No catch.” Sean promised. “It just costs a bit. It’s his job, after all, but he’s good at it, and he might give a discount to a mate. Interested?”

Ava shrug-nodded. “Okay.”

Date Point: 6y 10m 3w AV
Huntsville Alabama, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

“Gentlemen.”

The SOR perked up as their instructor arrived and claimed their immediate full attention. He was a wiry, tired looking man who Adam immediately spotted had some kind of facial nerve palsy, or who had maybe suffered a stroke at some point.

“M’names Drew Cavendish.” he introduced himself. “I’m a co-founder of C&M Extravehicular Systems, a member of the Hephaestus LLC, but right now I’m here as your extraterrestrial environment instructor.”

“Mr. Cavendish here has more EVA experience than anybody else in the history of the human race.” Powell told them, shaking Cavendish’s hand. “He’s also responsible for designing our spacesuits. You will treat every word he has to say as Gospel, is that clear?”

They were outside of a formal context, so he got a slightly asynchronous rumble of nevertheless clearly-enunciated 'yes sir’s. Satisfied that the lads were listening and switched on, he deferred to Cavendish again.

Cavendish nodded, and scribbled a note on the back of his own hand.

“Right. Welcome to zero-G one-oh-one.” he said. “That room through there is this facility’s variable-gravity training room, one of three. A few things to know before we get started.”

“First of all, I’m an easy-going type, but I’ve been training people in this field for a while now, and we’re dealing with stuff that’s essential to your safety and that of others. Out here in the corridor, I’m Drew. In there…” he nodded towards the large doors with the light over them “Keep it formal, attentive and promptly obedient, please. I won’t be deliberately putting you in harm’s way, but equipment failure is always an option. Clear?”

The team nodded their understanding, and Cavendish checked his tablet computer.

“Right. Cavendish’s Rule Number One: Altered gravity is dangerous." he told them. “Those rooms can be configured in ways that could kill or seriously injure anyone who enters them at the wrong moment. That light above it is colour-coded. If entering the room would pose an immediate danger to your health, it’s red and the door will be locked. If it is somehow open while the light’s red, do not enter. That light’s never supposed to be off: If it is, assume that it’s red and contact the controller immediately."

“Yellow means the safe zone around the door is fine. The room’s controller will need to admit you, and you must not leave the yellow demarcated zone without permission. Green means that the room is active but that no part of it should pose a health risk--you must get the room operator’s permission to enter, but may move freely once permitted. Blue means that the room is not drawing power, and you may enter freely because it’s exactly like out here in there. With me so far?”

There was another chorused confirmation: "Yes, sir."

“Finally, under no circumstances, not even if the light is blue, may you enter that room without one of those helmets.” Cavendish indicated the rack by the door. “Find one that fits and put it on now.”

The team stepped smartly to obey, and had all soon found one that fit.

“Right. As you can see, the light is yellow. That means-?”

"Don’t leave the yellow zone without permission."

“Good. As that room’s operator, I’m now granting you permission to enter.”

He filed in behind them. The room was a cube about a hundred yards to a side-- the yellow zone occupied only about the first ten, followed by a green zone, a blue zone, and the rest of the floor was black. Sitting just inside the black zone, somebody had set up twelve kettlebells.

There were some murmurs of surprise and interest as the men crossed the threshold, and Cavendish smiled. “Earth standard gravity is known as one G: What you’re experiencing right now, gentlemen, is about two thirds of a G, which is somewhere toward the middle of the Galactic Standard Gravity range. That’s the range of gravity settings that are used in space to be comfortable for most species. Take a moment to move around, get used to the difference. Jump up and down a bit, do some pushups, whatever takes your fancy.”

Legsy and Adam beamed at one another. Cimbrean fell inside the Galactic Standard Range, and they’d guessed that something like this might come up, and had secretly come up with a little stunt.

As planned, Legsy stooped, then launched himself off the ground in the highest explosive jump he could manage, achieving his own impressive body height at apex and landing neatly on Adam’s raised hands, which the younger man had thrust above his head.

Even Cavendish seemed taken aback. “I…see you two have experience with low gravity.”

“Yyyep.” Adam shifted his right hand so that he was holding Legsy aloft one- handed, and dropped his left hand casually to his side.

Even at two thirds gravity, he was still holding up a fairly impressive amount of weight, and it was an effort to remain stable and steady--Legsy was wobbling alarmingly, and jumped down after a second or two, landing lightly.

“Show-offs.” Burgess muttered.

“You got that out of your system, lads?” Powell asked.

“Yes, sir.”

“Good. I know you’re both used to this, but focus. You might still learn summat."

Adam and Legsy both straightened up and nodded their understanding and agreement. “Yes sir.”

Cavendish gave them all a few minutes to move and grow accustomed to the conditions before indicating the rest of the room. “The rest of this room is in microgravity, sometimes called zero-G. Does anyone here remember Newton’s laws of motion?”

The Deltas, CCTs, Adam and Powell raised their hands. Cavendish gestured to Adam. “Alright mister showoff, go on then.”

Adam cursed inwardly, but focused his memory. It had been a few years and he’d never expected to need them.

“The…first law defines inertia, stating that an object’s velocity will remain unchanged unless it’s influenced by a net force.” he said.

“Nice.” Cavendish nodded his congratulations. “The second?”

“Uh… whenever one object exerts a force upon another, it is in turn subject to a reaction force of equal magnitude with an opposite vector.”

“That’s the third law.” Cavendish corrected him. “What’s the second?”

Adam scowled in thought, but finally had to shake his head. “I can’t remember.”

“Force is equal to…?”

Adam’s memory snapped back into place. “Mass times acceleration!”

“Good lad. For the rest of you who didn’t follow that, and because academic knowledge of something’s not the same as intuiting it, here’s some practical demonstrations." Cavendish pulled a tennis ball from his pocket and tossed it lightly in his hand a few times. “What goes up, comes down. That’s because this ball is being acted on by gravity. Catch.”

He tossed it lightly to Murray, who caught it easily, then tossed it back. “The arc the ball describes through the air…” Cavendish told them, gently throwing the ball to Blaczynski, who threw it to Sikes, starting a slow game of catch that circled the unit “…is called a parabola, and it only describes that arc because it’s constantly under the effect of a net force. There’s no magnet on the ceiling pulling it up or anything like that, just gravity pulling it down. Back to me, please.”

He snatched the ball easily out of the air when Vandenberg threw it to him. “If there’s no gravity, however…”

He tossed the ball over the edge of the yellow zone. It described a perfect parabola just like before, right up until the moment it crossed the threshold, and was suddenly moving slowly in a perfectly straight line, spinning eerily. They watched it bounce forlornly off the ceiling at the far end of the room.

“As sergeant…Ares explained,” Cavendish said, peering at Adam’s name tag “the first law means that an object’s speed, and the direction it’s moving in-- collectively known as its velocity--remains unchanged, unless a force such as gravity acts upon it. The third law’s simple enough to not need an explanation--when you push on something, it pushes back. Simple enough, but that’s why that whole cartoon thing of going boating by blowing into the sail doesn’t work. You’re pushing that air forward, and yes it’ll push on the sail, but by blowing you’re also pushing yourself backwards just as strong, and pushing back on the boat through your boots. Follow?"

There was nodding.

“Next, a practical demonstration of the second law in action.” Cavendish tapped on his tablet computer, and an electric hum that had been pervading the room so subtly that they hadn’t noticed it suddenly became obvious by a change in its texture. “You may now enter the green and blue zones. The areas beyond are still microgravity, so don’t enter them yet. Be careful, the gravity’s even lower over that end.”

They walked cautiously. Sure enough, the gravity halved, then halved again as they passed into the green then blue zones, until they were each standing next to a kettlebell, anticipating what was to come.

“Now, those are twenty-five kilogram kettlebells, and we’re currently in lunar gravity, one-sixth that of the Earth.” Cavendish explained. “When I tell you to, I want you to pick them up, slowly and carefully. Don’t swing them or anything, just lift and hold them in one hand. Okay? Pick them up.”

They did so. Adam practically overbalanced. His kettlebell felt like nothing, and to judge from the expressions and utterings around him that was true for everyone.

“Light, aren’t they?” Cavendish asked, rhetorically. “Why don’t you swing them around a bit, same way as you would normally.”

Adam gave his an experimental swing and suddenly understood where Cavendish was going with this. The kettlebell may have been light to lift, but in motion it still put the exact same forces as always through his limbs. More so, actually--he had to fight to hold it down rather than hold it up, as the natural apex of each swing was now much higher.

“You’re now receiving a practical demonstration of the difference between weight and mass.” Cavendish told them as they swung. “In low gravity, those things have a light weight because there’s less gravity pulling on them. But their MASS hasn’t changed, and the second law of motion means that the force you’ve got to exert to make that unchanged mass accelerate is the same regardless of whether you’re in full Earth gravity, Galactic Standard, or Lunar.”

“Now.” Cavendish grinned and rubbed his hands together happily. “I notice that every single one of you is struggling with your swing. You’re overextending, you’re having a hard time holding on, those weights are going higher than you want. As you will have by now gathered, working in low gravity is remarkably tiring. So. Stop swinging and listen.”

He let them stop. “Cavendish’s Rule Number Two: Altered gravity is demanding." he announced. “Your bodies are evolved to work with gravity to aid them. You are used to pushing against a surface, you are used to having things be pulled down as they come up. Your every instinct is built around the fact that if you are bringing something down from a high place, you let gravity do the work and your muscles are the brakes. In null gravity, that does not apply. In null gravity, if you want to get something down from above your head, you have to drag it down, not support it, and in doing so you’ll also drag yourself towards it. Everything you do is an exertion, without exception."

He tapped his tablet, and the gravity went away. The door locked, loudly, and an alarm hooted through the room. “Start swinging again!” he ordered.

Everyone immediately found themselves being dragged around by their weights-- to a man, they parted ways with the ground. Firth actually wound up in a spin, hugging his weight to his chest.

“Alright, you, hugging the ball. Push it away from your chest, arm’s length!” Cavendish told him. He was hanging comfortably only a half-inch or so off the floor, and seemed perfectly happy.

Firth obeyed, and his spin became much slower.

"That was a demonstration of angular momentum!" Cavendish declared. “We’ll get to the academic bit of how it works later, but for now, understand this-- if you’re spinning fast, spread yourself out to slow down. If you’re spinning slow, make yourself small to speed up. Which brings us to Cavendish’s Rule Number Three--if you are spinning, spread out and slow down! Everyone throw your weights away from yourselves, gently now."

They did so. One of the guys--Adam didn’t see who--yelped as the weights, upon being thrown away, launched their prior owners in the opposite direction. “And there’s Newton’s third law in action!” Cavendish announced. “You’ve just performed rocket propulsion--throw something out the back, and you accelerate yourself!”

He gave them twenty seconds to tumble and flail in mid air, all drifting in random directions across the room at a glacial pace, before finally relenting. “Hug your limbs in, protect your face, and go limp.” he ordered. “I’m about to turn the gravity back on, gently. Don’t throw your hands out to arrest your fall or anything--just relax and let it happen.”

Gravity came back, and Adam’s slow trajectory to the ceiling became a gentle fall to Earth, a surprisingly high bounce, and then a gentle skid as the gravity ramped up to galactic standard over a few seconds. It didn’t hurt at all, but like all the others, his dignity was a bit battered, especially when he saw that Cavendish had alighted gently on his feet.

Cavendish hooked his thumbs into his belt and looked thoroughly pleased with himself. “Hopefully, gentlemen, I have now broken any illusions you may have had that Extra-Vehicular Activity will be easy. How about you get up, and I start with the actual instruction now?”

Date Point: 6y 10m 3w AV
Finchley, London, England, Earth.

Sean Harvey

"Lazrik’s coming up behind them here, this could be--He sticks one Elder Curse, instant cooldown, sticks the second, that gets two--FOUR down with Agony--FIVE! SIX!! Is he about to-? HE HAS!!! SEVEN DOWN!!!! Lazrik just got a TPK as a Godsinger with Thronefall and Universal Core, versus a team using Void Blades and Law of the Jungle…So much for the banner meta!"

"Yeah, that was some old-school instakill meta, but a lot of skill on show there, keeping Loss of Clarity subdued with Universal Core and two ECs, and I don’t know how LOC are going to come back from that…"

“…They are speaking English, right?"

Sean, being seated sideways across the easy chair, flipped a sort of lazy salute to Ava as Charlotte dashed across the room and jumped onto Ben’s lap. To everyone’s surprise, they’d turned out to be a good match, and had kept on going beyond their first weekend. Mercifully, they’d also toned down the making out in company. That had earned them a great many thrown objects those first few days.

“Drinks are in the fridge.” he said, by way of a hello. “Mine’s a Desperado.”

“Sweet of you.” Ava smacked him playfully on the top of the head as she made a bee-line for the kitchen. Sean glanced at Ben and Charlotte to make sure they weren’t paying attention, then helped himself to a good look at those tight jeans Ava liked to wear.

“How did you afford this place, anyway?" Charlotte asked, wriggling around in Ben’s lap to sit upright, interrupting his sightseeing.

“It’s my Gran’s old place.” Sean told her. “She left it me.”

“Dench of her.” Ben commented.

“Yeah. Mum wasn’t happy, she wanted to sell it, but it was right there in the will, so…”

“So what the hell are you watching, anyway?” Ava asked, handing Sean his asked-for beer and sipping down something colourful that had been on offer in Bargain Booze as she dragged through one of the dining chairs from the kitchen and sat on it. Sean had quickly figured out that Ava’s taste in drinks were fairly simple - so long as it was brightly coloured and sweet, she liked it.

“MLG. Mythos Arena championships.”

“Wh-? Actually, never mind.” Ava sipped her drink and watched the screen. “Pretty cool.”

“I’ve got ten quid on Happy Place Gaming to win the finals.” Ben said, squeezing Charlotte round the waist.

“Nah, cause it’s DTE versus Vangion in the quarters, and HPG lost seven of their last nine games against DTE.” Sean declared.

“It’s just a tenner, and I’m getting seven to one.” Ben replied.

“Fair enough, then.”

“You follow esports, Ava?” Charlotte asked.

“No live streams on Cimbrean.” Ava shrugged. “Besides, Papa watched baseball and football, that’s what I grew up on.”

“You’re like the archetypal country lass, you know that?” Sean asked.

“Me?! Sean, how the hell am I a country girl? I was born and raised in San Diego!”

Everybody looked at one another. That fact hadn’t yet come up in conversation --it was hitherto unknown to Sean, and judging from their expressions, to Charlotte and Ben too.

Sean cleared his throat. “…You were?”

Ava’s expression was the awkward look of somebody who’d not intended to share that particular information. “Uh…yeah. We were on vacation in Florida when…well. Yeah.”

“Ava--” Ben began.

“No sympathy, please.” Ava sighed. “I’ve dealt with it, okay? I lost my family and my friends, and the only reason I’m not dead too is because I was on vacation with Adam and his dad, but I’ve…I’m dealing with it. I don’t need sympathy.”

“…If you’re sure.” Sean agreed.

“Let’s just…HOW am I a country girl?”

“Just like…not having live streams, not knowing about nanotattoos. That sort of thing.” Ben told her.

“Yeah, but Cimbrean’s not, like…we’re not yokels!" Ava protested.

“Yeah, but you know how the country always gets the new things way after the cities do, and the cities have got new new things by then? Phone network coverage, broadband, digital radio, that kind of thing? That’s what it’s like with Cimbrean and Earth." Sean told her.

“No it’s not!”

“Darling, it’s like that.” Charlotte agreed.

Ava stood her ground. “We had lots of stuff first!" She insisted.

“Like what?” Sean asked.

“First solar energy force field, First xenobiology lab, first interstellar jump array, first variable-gravity gymnasium…”

“Those would all be the Scotch Creek facility.” Ben corrected her. “Except for the Gym, that was the Extraterrestrial Environment Training Facility on Salisbury Plain.”

“Oh come on, how do you know that?" Ava demanded.

“He’s a giant fucking nerd, that’s how.” Sean grinned at his friend, who just inclined his head in a please sort of bow and tipped an imaginary hat, as if Sean had pointed out that he was immaculately dressed.

“Well…we’ve got….” Ava floundered, then deflated. “Small school, small church, walks in the woods, swimming in the lake…Oh Christ, I’m a country girl.”

“There’s no need to sound so bloody despondent.” Sean told her, as Loss of Clarity slumped to a decisive defeat and on screen the players stood, shook hands and parted ways to make room on stage for the next two teams, saving a round of backslaps and high-fives for Lazrik.

“Don’t forget the flannel shirt and boots.” Ben added, earning a playful smack in the upper arm from Charlotte.

“I can’t be a country girl." Ava sulked. “I’ve never even seen a horse! I listen to R&B!"

“And Dean Roscoe.” Charlotte added, referring to a chart-topping country musician who even Sean had to admit as a straight guy, was thoroughly fuckable.

“I thought you were taking her side!" Ben complained.

“What kind of R&B?” Sean asked, sparing Ava’s discomfort.

“Huh? Oh, uh…Santos, Leila Perez, Manny B…”

Sean shrugged, not recognising any of them.

“Maybe not such a country girl after all, then.” Ben commented, nodding.

“What about you?” Ava asked him.

“I like anything.” Ben said. “But I guess metal’s my favourite? Soldiers and Queens, uh…Buying Time…Bring Me The Horizon, Granuloma…”

Sean nodded vigorously before Ava could ask him, so they all looked expectantly at Charlotte, who smiled sheepishly. “I like all the stuff my grandma was listening to.” she confessed. “The Beatles, and the Beach Boys and the Who and….”

“Anybody whose name started with 'the’?" Ben teased, and smiled at another playful slap in the arm.

“Dean Roscoe, though?” Sean asked.

Ava looked defiant. “He’s hot!”

“Thought you only had eyes for this Adam of yours.” Ben teased her.

“Oh come on everyone’s allowed to think a celebrity’s hot.”

“Actually, what’s he look like?” Charlotte asked.

“Dean Roscoe?”

“Adam!”

Ava frowned at her. “I’ve shown you. Haven’t I?”

Charlotte just shook her head, as did the guys when Ava looked to them, so she dug into her pocket and pulled out her phone--a slightly old touchscreen one-- and swiped through her photo gallery.

“Here.” she handed the phone to Charlotte. “I took this at Christmas.”

Charlotte studied it, doing her 'boy candy' face again. “Ooooh…”

“Hey!” Ben and Ava objected simultaneously, prompting her to hand the phone to Sean with an apologetic smile for Ava and a kiss for Ben.

Sean examined the photo, a selfie. Adam was shorter than Ava, but BIG, as broad as two Seans across his shoulders and it took Sean a second to realise that he was actually holding Ava in his arms with the same easy strength as Sean himself might have lifted a large book, smiling warmly.

“…He looks like a nice guy.” he conceded. He also looked handsome in a military-fit, stubble-headed kind of way.

“Yeah!” Ava took the phone back and stared at the picture for a second, then a second longer. Sean was about to get her attention when she blinked and put the phone away.

“You okay?” He asked.

“…yeah.” She nodded a little too vigorously, only barely getting the word out.

Sean glanced at Ben, who delivered the most subtle little head-shake, and so the matter was dropped. Instead, Sean just extended his bottle, and Ava tapped her own off it.

"And we’re off, looks like GOC and Splitting Hairs are ignoring what happened in the previous round ’cause they’re both still going with a banner build team, Looks like plenty of angels on the field there, and GOC take an early rush on Bravo…"

Date Point: 6y 10m 3w 1d AV
Huntsville Alabama, USA, Earth

Adam Ares

Drew Cavendish actually accompanied the SOR in PT the next morning. Obviously, he couldn’t perform at anything near their standard, but he took part and did surprisingly well for a civilian engineer. Then again, as he had ably demonstrated in zero-G training, operating a spacesuit required fitness, and he was an experienced spacewalker.

They were all motivated and alert therefore when they were shown into a lecture theatre and sat down in the front row.

“I’m told there’s a grand military tradition called 'death by Powerpoint’." Cavendish said, once they were all settled. “Fortunately, we’ve got something better here.”

He played with the computer for a second, and a life-sized spacesuit materialized next to him, forming like a ghost in mid-air, and then flickering into apparent solid reality, spinning slowly on the spot.

“You know, most of the idiots at this school STILL just use the holographic projector for Powerpoint slides?” Cavendish joked. “Looks bloody silly to me when they do that.” There were some chuckles, but everyone was looking at the suit. “Anyway. This is ExtraVehicular Military Activity Space Suit. EV-MASS.”

Adam studied it. It looked like a comparatively ordinary modern suit of body armor, borrowing elements from several different armor systems. Really, anybody wearing one wouldn’t have stood out among a lineup of soldiers in combat gear, except for the mask that covered the nose and mouth, and the sturdy metal ring around the jawbone and base of skull that was the dock where that mask and the helmet were joined to the rest of the suit.

“EV-MASS is designed with the mission profile of allowing you to deploy, and fight, in zero-G and vacuum, as well as on space stations, starships, and the ground, and to be able to translate from one to the other without vehicles if need be. Originally, we toyed with the idea of including a power-assisted exoskeleton, but…well, that one’s still science fiction for now. The suit is moved exclusively by its operator, which is why you gentlemen need to be so strong. There is no such thing as a light spacesuit.”

He clicked something, and the holographic suit became three suits, standing shoulder to shoulder.

“The system comprises of three suit components: under, outer and mid.” Cavendish said. He stepped over to and grabbed one of them, physically turning it around as if it were a real object, and leaving Adam thoroughly impressed by just how far holographic technology had come in a short space of time.

“The outersuit consists of your camouflage, load carrying equipment, and the rigid structures on your helmet, forearms, shins and thighs which are designed to receive mission-specific modules and equipment. It also includes the control panel mounted on the inside of your left wrist-” he raised the holographic suit’s arm to demonstrate “-though the modular system allows that to be worn on the right arm instead, for left-handers.”

“It also includes the environmental systems-” he indicated a football-sized pack mounted on the suit’s pelvis “-the heat exchanger and forcefield emitter-” both of which were mounted horizontally on the shoulders “-capacitor bank-” which ran down the spine “-and kinetic thrusters and gyroscopes.” he indicated surprisingly small protuberances at the shoulders and waist.

“Any questions about the outersuit before I move on?”

Sikes raised a hand. “Sir, is the helmet considered part of the outersuit?”

“No, the helmet and breathing mask form part of the midsuit. What you’re seeing here is the digital camo skin of the helmet.” Cavendish answered.

Baseball had a question. “Sir: Gyroscopes?”

“You remember Firth’s demonstration of angular momentum yesterday? Well, gyroscopes exploit that same phenomenon to keep you stable in space. They’re spinning weights, controlled by an optical tracking system mounted on your helmet that tracks visible features around you--the walls and floor, or distant stars, whatever--figures out your movement, and stabilises it. So long as the gyroscopes are powered, it’s literally impossible to throw yourself into an uncontrolled tumble or spin.”

He gave a second for any further questions, then moved on.

“The midsuit. This is the actual pressure suit and armour, built in several layers. The outermost is kevlar-aramid fabric, offering first-layer defence against bullets and micrometeorites.”

The hologram’s outer skin vanished, revealing a dull silvery fish-scale layer. “Below that is the scale layer, which is your most serious protection. It’s a layer of metallo-ceramic composite fine scales, designed to resist penetration and to distribute impacts across a wider area.”

“Below that? Padding and impact gel, for further protection and to help with the weight of the scale layer. Below that are the insulation, pressure and environment layers, all of which keep you from being exposed to vacuum, and finally the heat-activated memory gel that conforms to your body contours for compression.”

He tapped something the size of a smartphone installed under the helmet’s hard armour layer, on the back of the head. “The CPU for all of the suit’s active components is housed here, below the armour, on the basis that a penetrating hit to either CPU or skull is going to kill you anyway so we may as well put them both in the same place. And in the event that the CPU hit WOULDN’T kill you, then the extra protection it offers might just save your life.”

He looked around at them. They all were giving him their full attention. “Again. Any questions about the midsuit?”

Firth raised his hand. “Sir, how much protection does this thing offer?”

“Its SAPI rating is somewhere upwards of level four.” Cavendish told them. “The mechanism for that being that those scales are small, and they deform rather than shatter. The impact is conveyed to the padding and gel layer underneath that’s hugging you so tightly. In destructive testing, the midsuit withstood sustained rapid-fire seven-point-six-two at point blank without breaching. We emptied an AK into the bloody thing and the worst an operator would have suffered was some bruising.”

Nobody actually spoke, but the impressed changes to their body language made a gentle susurrus around the room.

“And against nonhuman weaponry?” Powell asked.

“Effectively invulnerable to kinetic pulse and electrical discharge weapons.” Cavendish told him. “There’s no known protection against nervejam, and coilguns and plasma weapons are classed as heavy weapons, which the suit’s not rated for anyway.”

He waited. No further hands went up, so he turned to the final holographic mannequin.

“Finally, and most importantly, the undersuit.” he said. “Without this, the whole system would not be viable.”

The undersuit looked like something Superman might wear. It was skin-tight, and covered in an arterial network of wide, flat structures that echoed the load-bearing mechanical lines of the human body. Aside from a zipper up the thoracic vertebrae and a pair of inlet/outlet ports just below the kidneys, it was otherwise featureless.

“This thing performs five hugely important roles for you, the first of which is orthopaedic pressure. That suit hugs you better than skin-tight, keeping your muscles and joints compressed and supported, reducing the risk of strain and injury while using EV-MASS. Second, it whips sweat away from the skin, and into those transport structures you see all over it.”

“Now, this is where it gets clever. Those structures are made from a polymer invented for us by the Corti according to our specifications. It’s flexible and squishy, but only in certain ways and up to a point. It’s dynamically compressible, in other words, AND it’s watertight. The practical upshot of all of that is that it A: further helps to support and distribute heavy loads and mechanically assist your legs and back, and B: it transports water, pumping it with the motion of your own body.”

“That water serves three roles. One, it’s part of the support structure too, because it’s incompressible. Two, it passes through the heat exchanger and is refrigerated before returning to the conduits around your body, nice and cold, so it transports heat away from your body. Third, pumping it passes it through filters--it comes out the other side completely potable, and is connected to a sippy straw in your breathing mask. In other words, you will ALWAYS have cool water on tap while you’re wearing this thing. The mask can load cartridges of electrolyte powder, sports drink mix, whatever.”

He paused, and with a few clicks of the mouse, recombined the three sub-suits into one unit.

“One thing you lads are going to have to learn and learn well is resource management.” he said, coming out from behind the lectern. “Your own body heat is an environmental hazard, you’re going to sweat out all of your salt and electrolytes while using this thing, and every sports scientist on our design team all agreed that there is no way to do anything at all in this suit and break even for calories.”

“But:” he added “They also all agree that it IS possible to move and be effective in this suit. Thanks to the therapy you’re already receiving you’ll get there rather quickly, but by the time you’re fully up to standard to use the suit in the field, you’re going to be large enough that those concerns about body heat will apply even outside of the suit, at least while at very strenuous activity. Fortunately, the suit solves that.”

“Without the suit, you will overheat and fail quickly. Without you, the suit is just an inert lump of technology. The two of you together can accomplish things the likes of which nothing else in the galaxy can even conceive. And I look forward to training you in its use and operation.”

He rubbed his hands. “That concludes the introduction. Any questions, before I start breaking it down component-by-component?”

Date Point: 6y 11m AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Moses Byron

“Oh, Mr. Byron! We were all so pleased to hear you were coming, the project’s really starting to find its feet!"

“So I heard.” Moses replied. The VP in charge of Cimbrean Development-- Levaughn Thomas--was one of the more…interesting people that he employed, being both a rare example of somebody who had managed to remain overweight while living on Cimbrean with its mandatory exercise schedule, and as camp as a Hollywood manicurist.

He was also so much of a brown-noser that it was a wonder he could smell his own Paco Rabanne, but Byron didn’t mind that when it came attached to a keen organizational mind. “You’re all doing a good job out here.” He commented, glad that he’d sent one of his three AW609 tiltrotors out here. The vehicle was surprisingly quiet on the inside, easy enough to have a conversation in. “Three weeks ahead of schedule, well done.”

“Yes sir!” Thomas beamed happily, cleaning his spectacles. “Everyone’s so rising to the occasion."

Byron reflected that sparing no expense had probably helped there. if he was any judge, the project’s wastage was going to border on the scandalously high, without being high enough to warrant a stern response.

Hopefully.

Still. It would prove to be worth it in the end. Cimbrean definitely WOULD profit, and probably sooner rather than later, but even if he never got to enjoy those profits himself, he’d go down in history as the ultimate philanthropist. A win-win.

He looked out of the tiltrotor’s window as the pilot pushed it into horizontal flight mode and circled round Folctha’s western districts, where the bulk of his construction work was happening--the huge agricultural depots were already in place, the workshops and factories and dozens of small grain silos. Yes, a handful of immense ones would have been more cost-effective for bulk storage, but the engineers had produced some rather neat graphs to show that the energy costs of jumping that much volume back to Earth through Array technology would have caused the originally-planned huge silos to fill faster than they could be emptied.

Sending little and often, on the other hand, kept on top of predicted growth for nearly ten years before an expansion became necessary. Little surprises like that had kept the project truly interesting, but as they picked up speed and set course for the real crown jewel of this plans, fifty miles out of town, he found his attention drawn upwards.

“When do they arrive?” he asked

“They’re already in orbit, Mister Byron. Their shuttle should be landing at about the same time as we do.”

Byron looked back down, satisfied.

“That’s native flora down there, isn’t it?” He asked. Cimbrean native plants were chlorophyll-based, just like plants on Earth, but they had a slightly paler, blueish cast to them. Earthling flora was evolved for an atmosphere which was nowhere near as effective at blocking UV, and was darker as a result. You could really tell the difference.

“Yes, sir.”

“I only really start to appreciate just how big this is when I see it from up here. A whole planet, Levaughn. All of its native life, doomed, all of it now becoming humanity’s property, all because somebody got caught short in the woods."

“I know. It’s terrifying.” Thomas nodded.

“Awful.” Byron said, as if agreeing. He chose the word extremely carefully-- the thought really did leave him full of awe.

If a lone and ignorant human could do something so momentous accidentally…

Byron’s mental filing system had, for most of his life, included a folder he thought of as 'moon laser' projects--ideas that were simultaneously both technically possible--as in, the math checked out and there was no real obstacle to his making it happen--but obviously absurd. He COULD have afforded to establish a permanent manned installation on the moon equipped with a giant laser.

Sure, the idea had been to use it for laser propulsion of interstellar probes equipped with solar sails, rather than some idiot James Bond villain thing like blowing up the New York Stock Exchange, but…why? It wasn’t like they’d come back, and when probes like New Horizons and Voyager had done just fine with old-fashioned reaction mass and gravity boosts…

Nobody needed a laser on the moon. What they needed was…civil engineering projects, small-business investments, energy or…hell, maybe just a cooler fridge, a smarter phone and a carbon-neutral car. They needed an ethical mogul, a world-class multibillionaire who used his money responsibly and for the betterment of the common man.

Moses knew that he was not that man. He just did a very convincing impression of that man.

Hence the moon laser folder. It was where he stuffed all the amazing things that a little boy had once imagined that billionaires did. After all, Tony Stark and Bruce Wayne were billionaires. Lex Luthor too, even if he was the baddie.

And that little boy was still very much alive in there, and adamant that at least ONE of those things would get done.

Fifty years on, the little boy knew you didn’t just build a laser on the moon. First, you laid the groundwork. You got the logistics in place, prepared a plan, got everything as ready as it could be…

Then you made the world need a laser on the moon, and they’d pay for it for you.

“Mister Byron?”

Moses shook off his thoughtful fugue. “Hmm? Oh, I’m sorry Levaughn. That was rude of me.”

“It’s nothing important sir. I’m just saying that…the shuttle’s alongside us.”

Moses glanced out the port window. Sure enough, a grey vehicle with all the aerodynamic grace and aesthetic beauty of a breezeblock was keeping pace with them, held aloft by forcefields and kinetic thrusters. It was a fair bit larger than the tiltrotor, and a damn-sight uglier.

“Looks like we got us a convoy.” he drawled, and stood up to cross the cabin for a better view. This did little to improve the shuttle’s appearance, and he couldn’t see the pilot through the black canopy, so after a moment or two he returned to his seat and looked back out the window.

Sure, the agricultural facilities back in Folctha might be more finished, as was the spaceport, but it was this facility that held his real hope for Cimbrean’s future. It was a compound, three overlapping rectangles on the ground, one of which was already the drained-abscess wound that would form the basement and foundation for the regional office building. 'regional' meaning the whole planet, for the foreseeable future. It wasn’t pretty, but he’d see the architectural plans--it would be. Especially once the ornamental monoliths, fountains, reflecting pools, lawns and trees were in place.

The important building, however, was very much finished.

They set down some five minutes after the compound and its hive of busy yellow vehicles came into view, the shuttle politely allowing Byron’s tiltrotor to alight first, tucking its engine nacelles up into the vertical and spinning them down like a crow settling its plumage.

True to form, the shuttle’s own landing was graceless. It wallowed down onto a forcefield cushion and thumped up a cloud of dust as it cut power to the engines and relied on the fields to handle the last few inches. If not for the stabilisers inside it, it would have been a rough jolt of a landing.

Moses adjusted the cuffs of his shirt and jacket as he crossed the grass. The aliens had been quite clear that they didn’t plan on staying a moment longer than was necessary to make the delivery.

They were Guvnurag, as big as backhoes themselves, but still able to stand side-by-side in the cavernous shuttle, carrying something between them. Huge, dark brown, shaggy and rippling with colour along the bioluminescent lines that began in the middle of their huge foreheads and spread out along their spines and flanks, they rolled down the shaking ramp on sturdy, elephantine leg, each with one thick-fingered hand hefting the handle of a crate as big as their torsos.

“Gentlebeings! Welcome.” Byron spread his hands in hospitality, reminding himself to keep the smile on his face closed-mouthed. Bared-teeth grins unnerved and frightened aliens, as a rule. He hoped that the translator that Thomas was carrying was up to the job, but it seemed that it was, as it chugged out at length a string of syllables that sounded something like long- winded Japanese being spoken by a double bass.

The slightly smaller of the two aliens replied in kind, and Byron blinked as the translator cancelled out its words with phase-shifted noise and replaced them with a startlingly high-pitched piccolo woman’s voice. The translators allegedly tried to find an equivalent match for vocal pitch and mannerisms, suggesting that this particular Guvnurag was a young and ebullient female.

“Mister Moses Byron!” she exclaimed, and glanced at her bodyguard, patterns of light pulsing all over her skin. Moses searched his recent memory, having studied Guvnurag bioluminescence in depth just that morning. The young female was…nervous. Intimidated? Or perhaps just inexperienced and jittery. It was hard to tell. “It is good to meet at last.”

“The beginning of what I hope will be a profitable relationship for us both.” Moses declared, extending a hand. After a moment’s hesitation, the Guvnurag trader extended her own hand, which was a good triple the size of Moses’ own, and shook hands. He made a point of not gripping anything. Her immense mitt may have been warm and soft, but the bones inside it weren’t a patch on the human skeleton, and it would not do to injure a trading partner.

“Speaking of which…” the other Guvnurag rumbled, being given a deep, phlegmatic voice.

“Of course. Levaughn?”

Thomas nodded and waved two men forward, each dragging a wheeled suitcase.

“Original human artwork.” Moses said, as the first one was opened. “Ten paintings, three sculptures. Unique and, thanks to your Confederacy’s quarantine field, otherwise almost impossible to export.” he smiled. “I suspect that this case alone will pay for our purchase in full, if you find the right auctioneers. As to the other case…”

It opened, revealing a neat rack full of glass phials and little plastic boxes.

“Terran organic compounds. Medicines, mostly--acetaminophen, ibuprofen, aspirin, codeine…There are also samples of caffeine, tea tree oil, mint oil, pimento berry oil, olive oil, xanthan gum, cumin, black pepper, cocoa, latex.…A full list is in there, along with instructions for what they can do, a comprehensive assessment of which ones may prove to be hazardous, and the formula for some of the simpler ones. Oh! And please accept this with my compliments.”

He offered the bottle that Thomas had just handed him. “A personal gift. California Cabernet Sauvignon, two thousand seven. The last really good vintage year before the Long Drought and, I’m assured, entirely safe for Guvnurag biology.”

He suspected, from the hues that pulsed down their lengths, that the aliens were taken aback

“Such generosity!” the female exclaimed. Moses smiled benevolently.

“You’ll find a spiral device amidst the artwork.” he said. “It’s not an abstract sculpture, it’s called a ‘corkscrew’, and you’ll need it to get the bottle open. You’ll figure out how, I’m sure.”

“Thank you. And…well, here is our end of the trade.”

They picked up the object they had been carrying between them, set it down again in front of them, opened it, and took out its contents, which they set atop the carrying case.

“Oh my God.” Moses breathed and leaned in, pleasantly surprised. “It even looks the part!"

“Excuse me?” the male alien asked.

“I’m sick of technology like warp drives and gravity field generators and whatever looking like something out of a ham radio catalog.” Moses indicated the object he had just purchased. It looked great: enigmatic, black, festooned with alien runes and pulsing lines of light. "Look at this thing! This is what I always imagined a scifi gizmo like an FTL comms relay would look like!"

The Guvnurag traders exchanged glances and then, sheepishly, the male stepped forward and opened what turned out to be the box that the actual FTL comms relay came in.

Moses deflated. The object inside was plain old technology after all. Wrapped in static-free plastic and a cradle of packing foam. It was drab, metallic and functional: all bare screw heads, electrical connectors and data ports, and the alien runes were probably warnings, warranty void stickers, and the serial number.

“…Figures.” he sighed. “Why the flashy lines?”

“Those are…emotional indicators. They tell Guvnurag that the object inside is delicate and should be handled carefully.” the female explained.

“They’re emoticons.” Thomas translated.

“Thank you Levaughn.” Moses only barely stopped himself from sounding nettled, and forced himself back into a good mood. It was stupid to be so disappointed by something so trivial when he now had a brand new interstellar communications device to play with. Or, more accurately, to pay people to play with.

He straightened. “Well. Thank you very much indeed. I do hope you found our business satisfactory.”

“We did!” the female enthused, echoed by an assenting rumble from her counterpart.

“If you need any help getting that stuff onto the shuttle…”

The aliens tested the suitcases, assured him that everything was fine, and retreated up the ramp, wishing him fond farewells and promising to try the wine at their first opportunity.

Levaughn had already handed the relay off to the technicians and engineers, who were bustling it towards the communications building as fast as they could without jolting it. “That seemed…to go smoothly.” he observed, bringing his exquisitely plucked eyebrows together in a frown.

“You’re not a believer in smooth business transactions, Levaughn?” Moses asked him, wryly.

"So not." Levaughn retorted, rolling his eyes. “Daddy always told me, there’s always a catch.”

Moses chuckled, and looked up at the shuttle as it lurched into the air and away. “Why introduce a catch where it’s not needed? All that stuff cost me…what, a few hundred dollars? My investment portfolio made that much just standing here. And in return….”

“We can talk to the galaxy.”

Byron smiled. “For starters, Levaughn.” he agreed. “For starters.”

Date Point: 6y 11m 2w AV

Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

'Eden' had been sold, of course. There was always a demand for housing in Folctha these days: it was a boom town in a huge way, being equal parts scientific goldmine, private-sector wet dream and a retirement paradise where the gravity weighed just a little less on wealthy old bones.

Thousands of idealistic libertarian dreamers had flocked in, and Sir Jeremy Sandy had taken a convincing win in Cimbrean’s first ever democratic elections to remain as colonial governor thanks in part to his adoption the most progressive, fair-handed and logical social policies that modern political theory could invent.

Businesses had flooded in alongside the people, investing billions. Folctha’s skyline was all cranes and scaffolding as buildings popped up like mushrooms, each one outdoing its predecessors as the architects fought for prestige and to make the most creative use of the opportunities afforded by low gravity. The forest line had been pushed back for miles, and the farmers seemed to be making more money just buying up the land and then selling it for development so they could buy more land further out, than from the actual agriculture.

Hotel space was also cheap, and much nicer than Eden had been. Besides, it wasn’t like Adam had many opportunities to spend his salary on much else. Most of it went straight into savings.

Dipping into those savings to spend Christmas and the New Year at the brand- new Folctha Star Hotel had been his idea, and a genius one. The walls were thick and soundproofed, the bed was measured in acres, the bath was big enough for two, and the windows were thick, sturdy, and completely opaque from outside, in part thanks to the solar-gathering forcefield that meant the hotel was a net contributor to the city’s power grid.

All of those should have been gratefully, enthusiastically and repeatedly exploited to their maximum erotic potential.

Instead…

They had had sex, oh yes. Powerful, athletic, gasping sex. Legs wrapped around him so hard that her knees creaked sex. Fingernails down his back drawing blood sex. The cold glass of that huge sturdy floor-to-ceiling window against her back and buttocks sex, made all the better by the scandalous illusion of exhibitionism.

That had all been one ride. A mind-blowing reunion fuck that had promised more and even better to follow, but failed to deliver. Adam was…Busy.

How the hell somebody could keep so busy on their Christmas break was beyond her, but he got up at four in the goddamn morning, span through the shower, then vanished to the gym, returning around sunset aching and exhausted and full of willing spirit but empty of actual energy.

Naturally she’d complained. He’d explained that he HAD to keep his training regime up, that every gram of muscle mass was a target he had to hit. When she’d suggested dinner, he’d pointed out that his every calorie and vitamin was tightly controlled.

And he was so stealthy. There was no hope of waking up to at least get a few minutes with him in the dark of the early morning, because he’d slip out of bed like a dream, shower like rain on the window, and when he slipped out of the room the door closed behind him with a click that was quieter than the wall clock’s ticking. When he came back, she could snuggle up to him all she liked, she’d get kissed, maybe some happy nose-nuzzles and all that good stuff…for the few minutes until he fell asleep, completely drained by his regimen.

All things considered, spending her lover’s birthday alone at noon in a dry- dock sized bathtub and treating herself to a Mojito jug intended for two wasn’t how she’d envisioned their time together going.

And she had two weeks of this to look forward to?

Fuck. That.

She abandoned the drink, threw on clean clothes and buckled on her camera with the fierceness of a rancher gal of the old west fixing to fight off bandits.

There were photo opportunities going begging all over this town, material to fill her website for a year. She’d sell her photos to agencies, news organisations and private buyers. A camera in the right hands could be a money engine.

If she wasn’t going to get laid, she may as well get paid. She could sort out Adam later.

Hopefully.

A productive afternoon and evening showed Folctha at its best: the sterile filth and colourful greyness of the building sites, the way Cimbrean’s star-- still unnamed--just had that slight bit more magenta in it than a Sol sunset as it painted the first extraterrestrial human city. How Folctha at night was both the same as and different to any other city, with all the hue and splendor of its nightlife playing out under three tuberous, irregular moons.

She’d almost forgotten about Adam by the time she got back. There was no ignoring him when she insert-tugged their keycard in the room lock, though. He was asleep with the blanket draped over one leg and everything else naked to the night air, a study in masculine geometry, and as fast asleep as King Arthur under the mountain. All of her frustration with him came right back, and the devilish idea for waking him up that had just occurred to her was drowned out by the much louder voice of irritation.

There was nothing for it but to sigh, strip, and climb into bed next to him, wondering what the hell she was going to do.

A fitful night’s sleep full of that question was answered when, to her astonishment, she rolled over in the morning to find that it was full daylight outside and that he was still there, dozing on his side facing her with a half-lidded, sleepy and loving expression.

“…Hey.” He barely whispered it.

“Hey…” she replied, as two distant parts of her brain embroiled themselves in a tug of war over whether to voice her discontent now, or wait until after she’d screwed him senseless, then voice her discontent.

He kissed her, ending that argument. He was so strong, she could feel it even though his touch was light, and they didn’t need long before she was straddling his hips, grinding and gasping and eagerly working towards the moment when she’d be ready to get around him properly.

“Oh _god…_So, what’s so special about today?”

He was too busy sucking on her nipple to reply properly, so just made an inquisitive "hmm?" noise.

“You didn’t sneak out this morning…”

He chuckled, and kissed the hollow where her throat met her collarbone, dropping his hands to her hips. “It’s my rest day.”

Ava blinked, and stopped moving. “Your…rest day?”

Adam frowned, confused. “Yeah. Weekends are rest days.”

“…You-?” Her mood evaporated, and she scooted down his thighs a bit, sitting on his knees. “You scheduled this?"

Adam’s expression had gone from confident lover to confused boyfriend to kicked puppy in a matter of seconds. “Well…not this, but, like, the day…"

“Jeez!” She seethed, and surged to her feet. “Well, I’m glad you could fit me into your busy goddamn schedule!"

“Ava… !” The exclamation was a hurt and confused one.

“No, seriously, what’s your thought process here?” She demanded. “Let’s hear it!”

“Well…Look, Ava, baby, I need to keep this up. Like, it could be dangerous for me to not keep my exercise going while I’m here. Even if it’s not, it could undo a lot of hard work!"

“And what the hell am I supposed to do when you’re gone all day?”

“I figured…I mean, it’s a nice hotel, there’s a spa, there’s like-”

She interrupted him, practically spitting lightning bolts. "No he venido aqui para admirar el paisaje, perrita!"

Adam’s jaw went slack. “What did you just-?”

"I called you a little bitch you fuckin’ idiot!" she snarled. “Or did all that exercise squeeze the Spanish out of your brain?!”

There was a long moment of silence, chilly on her part, hurt and confused on his. He stood up at about the same time as she sat down, and started to get dressed.

His boots were laced and he all but had his hand on the door handle when she spoke to him. “Adam, I’m sorry.”

He paused and looked back at her. Her ankles were crossed, her hands were hugged at her waist and she couldn’t hold his gaze--she looked away almost instantly, shaking and chewing at her lip.

“We’ll…Let me just…” he began, then started over. “We both need to…we’ll talk when I get back.”

“Don’t be long. Please.” she begged him.

In the end, he was barely gone half an hour, and returned with little more than a glow of sweat to show for the run he must have gone on. She’d dressed, but then sat down on the bed again and pulled the blanket around her shoulders, waiting.

She summoned a weak smile for him. “Hey.”

“God, Ava, I’m sorry.” he sat down next to her and engulfed her shoulders in his right arm, skin like a furnace against hers. “You’re right, I didn’t have a thought process there, I just…I didn’t think about you at all, did I?”

She rubbed her eyes, and nuzzled into him. “I love you,” she said. “but you can’t just…I’m not a videogame, Adam. You can’t just load me up and carry on from where you left off, you know? It’s been a year. A year, Adam. And then you come back and pencil me in for the weekends?"

“I know, I…I’m sorry.”

“And I’m sorry too. I shouldn’t have called you that, but…” she sighed. “Look, can we put it behind us and salvage the second week of this break? Just you and me, every day all day until you have to go back?”

He hesitated, and her heart sank. “I…Baby, I wish I could promise that.” he said. “But I wasn’t kidding about it being maybe dangerous.”

“…Fine.” She declared. “Fine. What can you promise?"

“I, uh…what would you like?”

“What I’d like is-" she stopped herself, and moderated herself. “Look, just…wake me up before you head out. Talk to me. Involve me. Get back here as early as you can and spend time with me! Hell, you’re fresh in the morning? Get some of that exercise in right here in this bed! And if you have to control what you eat, can we at least eat together?"

“…I can do all of that.” he said.

“Good.”

“So, um…where were we, before…?”

“Forget it, cabron." she told him. “You killed that mood stone dead, you’ve got a lot of cuddling to do before we’re back there again."

After a silent second, he got the hint and finally, finally put his arms around her and nuzzled up close.

After a while, it even started to feel natural and safe again.

Chapter 30
Operation NOVA HOUND | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point: First Contact Day, 10y AV
Capitol Station, Capitol System, Dominion Space.

Officer Regaari, Clan Whitecrest Attache to the Mother-Supreme.

“You’re both courting a controversy, you know. A scandal, even, given how close you both are to me."

Regaari’s head-duck of agreement had an unconsciously immature, cubbish quirk to it that came naturally when Giymuy engaged her Mother’s instincts. The Mother-Supreme was now silver from eartip to foot and thoroughly venerable. Over the years of working together, her relationship with Regaari had thawed from purely professional, to something of a friendship, but she was still the Mother, and when she gave advice, deference was instinctive.

“I know…” he agreed, reluctantly. “’Human ideas, eroding Gaoian culture.’ I’ve been staying well abreast of the backlash. We both have, which is why we’ve only…talked about it."

“Even talking about it is 'heresy’, in some camps."

“That’s a human word.”

“Indeed it is.”

Regaari caught the sad irony in Giymuy’s agreement. “We’re a free society.” he pointed out. “Free to speak our minds, free to act and do as we please so long as we cause no harm. Aren’t we?”

“So it has been since before the females were united.” Giymuy agreed. “But, I note, we have never actually been cunning enough to codify those freedoms in law. And in the meantime some peoples’ ideas of what constitutes 'harm' have broadened, spreading out to cover a wider area but, I think, becoming shallower in the process."

“The humans need those things coded in law." Regaari pointed out. “In fact they were, from what I gather, something of a revolutionary concept when first introduced. We meanwhile have always taken them as self-evident. You don’t need a law granting people the freedom to.. to breathe, or to eat.”

Giymuy chuffed. “’We hold these truths to be self-evident…'" she quoted.

Regaari, being the one who had first introduced that document to her, recognised the quotation instantly. “Missing, of course, the irony that if they really WERE self-evident then they would never have had to write them down.”

Giymuy duck-nodded herself. “Meanwhile, we DID find them self-evident.” she observed.

“And yet you’re warning me that Ayma and I are courting controversy by preferring each others’ company.”

“Dare I whisper the word 'monogamy’?"

“It’s not…she’s had other cubs since mine. It’s just that we still enjoy each others’ company and…we still feel much the same as we did when we sired that cub.” Regaari stood and paced the room. “And this, somehow, is a brewing scandal. A male and a female liking each other and wishing to spend time together, rather than simply remembering one another as a fond, temporary dalliance? Perhaps those truths aren’t so self-evident after all, perhaps Gaoians have all just…thought too much alike up until now.”

Giymuy chittered loudly and at length at that one. “Oh!” she gasped, trying to recover. “If only we did! There would be no need for a Mother-Supreme and I could retire and live out my time surrounded by cubs and happy young Mothers.”

She regained her composure, and noticed the slightly offended set of Regaari’s ears. “Ah, I am sorry. You may be right. We are discussing the…adulteration of our culture by alien ideas, after all."

“That was probably inevitable the moment we made First Contact.” Regaari grumbled.

"We know that." Giymuy gestured to the station they were aboard. “Many Gaoians may not. And this is the root of our problem--we are being changed by these ideas whether we like it or not. These ideas of 'heresy' and 'taboo' are just as much a pollution of what it means to be Gaoian as…pizza, pancakes, meditation and monogamy. Then there’s poor Myun. I never imagined that I’d see the day when a young, healthy, intelligent and very pretty female was shunned because no male will court her for fear of the political consequences."

Regaari snarled a little angry laugh. “Oh yes. they’ll hire her to provide hand-to-hand combat instruction, but mating with the 'freak’?" He growled a little. “If she wasn’t young enough to be one of my cubs, I might approach her with a contract myself just to spite them.”

“Why not?” Giymuy asked. “You’re already flirting with scandal with Ayma, and you’d be actively seeking it by courting Myun. Why should age make a difference at that point? Maybe your example is all that’s needed to rehabilitate an outcast.”

Regaari fell silent. He was still considering the suggestion when the communicator in his pocket buzzed. He tapped it with a claw. “They’re ready for you in the council chamber.” he said.

“It’s about time…where’s my stick?”

Regaari handed it to her. Giymuy had many walking sticks these days, and each one was a calculated statement. For today, she had selected the natural, knurled one made of Cimbrean Pinkwood, a now-extinct species that had once occupied one small portion of a continent that was now long swallowed up by deathworlder terraforming. The humans had logged the lot rather than let it be ruined by the advancing tide of disease, and had sold the wood to collectors to drum up funds. Giymuy had snapped up three tree’s worth. Craftsmen from every clan on Gao and beyond had vied for the privilege of creating the sticks, desk and curiosities she had commissioned, predicting that the prestige of creating for her would improve their own mating chances.

Giymuy in turn had encouraged them by selecting lesser-known, obscure males for the privilege. The famous ones, she had reasoned, didn’t need the help. Now, the stick tapped sharply on the decorative stone tiles of the Capitol Station concourse as they left the Gaoian ambassadorial quarters. Dominion security guards--two Vzk’tk, two Kwmbwrw--fell in line behind the entourage of four Gaoian guards from Clan Flashfang, all painfully eager young males and all--Regaari had seen to this personally--trained to handle threats up to and including a human.

It was quite the little procession. Giymuy had chosen simple charcoal robes that offset her fur, and wore three loops of fine gold chain clasped to each ear. The effect was venerable and dignified, still understated, but enough to make her stand out next to Regaari’s severe black uniform, or her guards’ combat harnesses.

This was a big occasion: A galactic broadcast that had taken some negotiation to secure. Even Regaari didn’t know what the Mother-Supreme had planned for the address she was about to give to the Dominion Grand Council, but he was looking forward to it.

Every species had automatic membership and presence on the Grand Council, even if they were not Dominion members. Even if that species was an enthusiastic member of the Celzi Alliance, there were dissenters, ones who had chosen to side with the Dominion, representing their species. An unpopular minority at home, perhaps, but still there. The only vacant seats belonged to the declining species, who no longer cared to show up…And to the humans.

There was a space for them, but it remained unoccupied. Regaari wasn’t even sure if the deathworlders knew that space existed.

Giymuy created a stir when she walked right past the podium that had been set up for her, and instead strode into the area designated for humans. The susurrus this move generated soon became a white noise that only subsided when the chairman--a rotund VGork nearly as large as a young Guvnurag--slammed his gavel into the desk in front of him with enough force to dent the wood.

“Mother-Supreme Giymuy.” he began, addressing her. “That place is for the delegates from Earth.”

“The delegates from Earth, Chairman” Giymuy replied, speaking with surprising force and clarity for her age “Do not know that this seat exists. This council has never seen fit to inform them of it nor invite them to attend. I am taking the liberty of speaking on their behalf.”

The chairman slammed down his gavel again as the gathered species took to muttering to one another again. “Can I not persuade you to take the podium?” He asked.

“You can not, Chairman.”

The Chairman considered her for a while, then backed down. “Then please. Continue.”

Giymuy accepted the concession with a slight bow to the chair, then turned to address the Council as a whole.

“Gaoians and Humans share a fondness for Base Ten mathematics.” she began. “Which is why I note that, by the calendar of the planet Earth, It has now been exactly ten years since the Hunters raided their city of Vancouver. Less than three of their years later, the human race achieved faster-than-light manned flight for the first time. Those ten years have been…tumultuous and interesting, and often controversial.”

She tapped her stick down, twice. “The Dominion’s response to this singular deathworld species has been one of fear and mistrust. This stick I am holding is a symbol of why that fear is justified, being made from the wood of a tree now extinct due to them. I am not here to argue against the policy of the last ten years--the past cannot be undone--but to share a vision of policy for the next ten."

This time, the delegates were polite enough to remain silent and listen.

“The humans are here to stay.” she announced. “Even if we never see one again, even if they were to retreat behind their quarantine field and remain there, they have already changed the outlook of many species, on a great many things. Even now, the questions are being asked 'why haven’t we united to fight the Hunters?’, 'Why has the Dominion-Alliance war gone on for so long without ceasefire or negotiation?’, 'Why do we transport goods in vulnerable freighters and lose their crews to Hunters and piracy when displacement jump drives render the very concept of a freighter obsolete?’"

“I have seen personally just how powerful and dangerous humans are. I have seen for myself, some of the plagues that our one human visitor--my clan- Sister--could have unleashed on Gao, which would surely have killed our entire species if we had lacked the technology to protect ourselves. Humans are undeniably dangerous. But so too are the tools that were used to build this station. So too are fire, or the knives used to prepare food.”

She tapped her stick again. “Unlike those things, humans are thinking, living beings. Fellow intelligent life, which is a rare and precious thing in this galaxy. My clan-sister would have wept and been thrown into the kind of despair none of us here can imagine, if she had been forced to watch the Gaoian people die through no real fault of her own. They know, or are learning, that they are dangerous. Where it is already too late for them to prevent the damage, they are trying to repair it as best they can. Where it is not, they are taking precautions to prevent harm."

“On their behalf, given their absence from this assembly, I humbly beseech the council to-”

She was cut off. Blue lighting--the universal colour of emergency and alarm-- slammed on and a deep howl filled the council chamber. She was still standing bemused by it, ears twitching back and forth, when Regaari took her by the arm and escorted her with inexorable firmness, towards the exit.

“Regaari? What is happening?” She asked.

The male’s ears were pricked up and his teeth bared--sure signs of stress, alertness and concentration. He was listening to words that Giymuy could not hear, and reading words she could not see.

“The station’s under attack.” He reported, tersely.

“Who by?”

“That’s still being…” His ears rose, then flattened against his skull.

“Regaari?”

“…The Swarm of Swarms.” he quickened the pace. “The Hunters are back.”

HMS Sharman, Folctha, Cimbrean, the Far Reaches

Major Owen Powell

“FALL IN! Fall in and listen the fook up!"

The Operators had been in the middle of tidying up the barracks and doing basic chores like the washing up and laundry. They immediately dropped what they were doing and fell in around him, giving Powell their full and undivided attention. He didn’t skip a beat.

“Ten minutes ago our listening post in the Capitol system sent back its message buoy, reporting a massive spike in activity on Hunter communications channels and several sensor contacts. The Swarm’s attacking Capitol Station. Gear up and get on the shuttle, We dust off in three! Go, GO!"

Gearing up was a simple as grabbing the emergency bags that they all kept in the locker room for this exact reason and sprinting for the waiting shuttlecraft which had set down on the base’s helipad. It was a simple, stock Dominion model, little more than a dull grey cuboid with a window in the front and a door in the back. No human company had yet developed a version that the armed services liked well enough to buy, much to the grumbling of the people who had to use them, who were universally of the opinion that literally anything human-made would have been an improvement.

They were aboard and belted in in less than two minutes. Powell stood towards the front, gripping an overhead strap to stabilise himself as the little craft lurched skyward.

“Right, This operation is called 'Nova Hound’." he began, raising his voice over the engines. “Lucky for us, we’ve got an OPLAN for this exact scenario. The attack began ten or fifteen minutes ago. Our estimated response time is forty or fifty minutes. By the time we’re on scene, the defending fleet will have been brushed aside and the station itself will have been overrun by Hunters for a good half hour. Safe to assume that civilian casualties are total, and in this station’s case that’s a good twelve thousand people.”

“VIPs--council members, ambassadors, visiting dignitaries--have all got security details with them, which we believe makes enough difference. We have schematics for Capitol Station, we think we know where they’re likely to be holed up. Our mission is rescue and extraction of as many dignitaries and civilians as we can. Secondary objectives include causing as much damage as possible to the Swarm, intelligence gathering, and propaganda.”

“We’ll be deploying on Caledonia, which has been refit as a staging and hospital ship. The V-class destroyers are the frontline, they’ll hold the swarm by the nose. They’ve got the staying power and EWAR. Myrmidon will be serving in its new role as on-field energy support, keeping the V-class’ charged. Meanwhile, USAF TS/2 squadrons will deliver the killing blows and provide close screen. Both of them are there as a big distraction to let the men on this shuttle accomplish the real mission."

“Our overwatch is provided by JETS, led by Lieutenant Ross aboard HMS Caledonia. Jones, Murray, Price, you’re covert infiltration and assault. Your job is to drive the outboard and dive onto the station, effect quiet ingress as close to the target section as possible. Blaczynski, Firth, you’re on the boat too, as am I. We help secure our foothold then dig in and command."

“Once we’re in, the Protectors--that’s Ares and Burgess--and Defenders-- Stevenson, Sikes, Akiyama and Vandenberg--Jump in from the shipboard array. That’s the assault team’s cue to go monkey-shit on the Hunters, leave none of them alive. Delta sets up the evacuation Array then maintains our perimeter and runs combat camera. Protectors, you’ll be handling the refugees. Hunters usually kill outright, so there probably won’t be a lot of medicine to do, so you’re also humping ammo and gear for the assault team. The evac Array will be sending the civilians to the deck of HMS Caledonia. We’ll be using our default callsigns. I’m STAINLESS. Any questions?"

“Sir.” Stevenson raised his hand. “Do we bring a backup Array?”

Powell nodded. “Yes. Any further questions? No? Are we clear?”

“YES SIR!”

“Right. Give me your war names!”

“LONGLEGS!”

“STERLING!”

“HIGHLAND!”

“RIGHTEOUS!”

“STARFALL!”

“TITAN!”

“THOR!”

“REBAR!”

“SNAPFIRE!”

“BASEBALL!”

“WARHORSE!”

“And don’t you fookin’ forget it, lads. Let’s do this right.”

Capitol Station, orbiting Planet Garden, Capitol System, Dominion Space

Regaari

"Every shot we fire misses--they’re just NOT THERE any more. I don’t know where they learned a trick like this, but we’re losing ships fast out here, and inflicting no damage that I can see."

“No hope of holding the field?” Regaari was part of a wedge of Gaoians pushing against a tide of stampeding lifeforms. Already one of his men was badly hurt, having been kicked hard by a panicking Vzk’tk. His role wasn’t to push and shove and shout and try to make room--he was too busy co-ordinating with the largest and most senior craft in the Gaoian contingent of the security fleet, the CGC Winter Fire.

"None. Your ETA to the shuttle?" Its captain was a Whitecrest, one of Regaari’s Brothers, both by clan and, he suspected, a half-sibling genetically.

“Everything’s panicking in here.” Regaari grunted, then raised his voice to be heard as a flock of wailing Kwmbwrw became the latest obstacle for them to push against. “Most of them are running away from the escape ships for some stupid reason. How long can you give me?"

"If we let all the others die first? A paw of [minutes], six at the outside."

Regaari assessed matters. They had made it only a few hundred meters at best from the council chamber since the attack began. “Not good enough.” he declared.

"I know. I’m sorry, Brother, but at this point we have to treat everything aboard the station as lost. We may as well salvage some assets from this, and carry word to Gao of what-"

The link went dead with a sharp squeal in Regaari’s ear.

"Winter Fire, you broke up there." He told them.

Silence.

"Winter Fire, come in?"

"Officer Regaari, CGS Winter Fire is destroyed." one of the other ships sent. "We’re warping out. Nothing we can do--may as well save what we can. Sorry."

“Regaari!”

He turned. The Mother-Supreme was leaning heavily against a wall, panting and grimacing with a hand pressed to her chest. “Mother-Supreme?”

She slumped, sliding to the ground. Concerned males gathered round and Regaari rushed to her side. “Giymuy!”

“Oh, don’t…” she coughed. “At least my age is getting me first, before the Hunters do.”

The men exchanged glances, aware that they weren’t to be so lucky.

“We can still-”

“Don’t be so stupid!” she snapped, then her breath rattled horribly. She was clearly in hideous pain.

She continued In a gentler tone. “Regaari. You can escape. I will only slow you down, and so will these soldiers. Get…" she heaved and coughed, but fought through it. “Get to the diplomatic shuttle, and activate the emergency displacement recall…Tell them…” her strength was failing by the second, and when she repeated “tell them…” she was almost inaudible.

Regaari leaned in close. He only barely heard her last words.

He closed her eyes. “I’ll tell them.” he promised.

“Officer?” One of the soldiers asked him, clearly expecting an order.

“What?” Regaari asked, surveying the ceiling.

“What do we do?”

“First, you stand back.” Regaari ordered. When they did so, he aimed his pulse rifle and blasted the vent cover out of the ceiling with three precise shots.

“Second,” he said, slinging the rifle over his shoulder “you give me a boost up into that vent.”

They did so. Gaoian gravity was just a little higher than Galactic Standard, and between two of them, he was launched to the height of a ceiling that could accommodate even the tallest Rrrrtktktkp’ch or bulkiest Guvnurag. He caught the edge, swung there for a second, and then hauled himself up and into the air duct.

“And…third?” One of the soldiers asked.

Regaari unslung his gun and got his bearings.

“You kill as many of them as you can, and you don’t let them take you or your Brothers alive.” he told them. “Goodbye.”

HMS Violent, Cimbrean orbit, the Far Reaches

Commodore William Caruthers

“Signal from HMS Caledonia, Commodore. They say the SOR is aboard, suited up and ready."

Caruthers acknowledged the communication with a clear nod and eye contact. “By my estimation, that makes us ready to go.” he observed.

Violent’s Captain--Commander Anthony Miller--nodded. “I agree sir.”

“Signal the fleet to prepare to jump on my mark…”

He was pleased that it took only some five seconds before “All ships ready to jump, Admiral.” was called.

“Mark.”

Caruthers always felt cheated by the occasion of a jump. He would have liked a lurch, or a little jolt, or some tingling sensation, or even just a nondescript sense of something having happened. As it was, the only indication that anything at all had changed was the way his operations display began to populate itself.

The untrained eye would have seen only a mess. Caruthers, however, had a very trained eye.

The seven ships of his task group had translated through their wormholes and landed some ten thousand kilometers from Capitol Station. Far enough away that their miniscule signatures would be easily missed, close enough that the EM- spectrum latency shouldn’t throw off their targeting or electronic warfare.

As they arrived, HMS’ Violent, Vigilant, Victory, Vendetta, Vanguard and Viceroy each quietly released their passenger contingent of six BAE Terrier unmanned space vehicles--car-sized lozenges of thrusters, sensors and electronic attack modules designed to multiply their mothership’s electronic superiority and obfuscate the fleet’s exact size, composition and position.

The result was an immediate widening of their sensor net, and the Hunters weren’t bothering with subtlety. Even on passive sensors only, with the full group of seven warships and thirty drones deployed, he had an excellent idea of exactly what they were dealing with.

Capitol Station was a white, glass and chrome broccoli floret twenty kilometers long, ending in a tangled root of rust-brown mooring gantries and docking bays. describing a rough sphere around it with a radius of some five hundred kilometers was the Swarm, consisting of literally thousands of ships, including fifty or sixty which were a match, in terms of tonnage at least, for Myrmidon and Caledonia, both of which were by far the most massive ships in the human fleet.

They did not, fortunately, appear to be reacting to the arrival of the Deathworlders.

“Dragon’s teeth out.” he ordered.

The dragon’s teeth had been modified since the last battle at Cimbrean. Their canisters were now filled with high-pressure air rather than using explosives to disperse the minisatellite jump beacons, allowing them to be deployed without creating an obvious sensor contact. Violent’s hull rang as twenty such canisters were launched away from the ship on random timers, creating a friendly sphere of possible evasive jumps.

At a range of ten thousand clicks, and with the twin advantages of surprise and EWAR on their side, the fleet was now well prepared to weather a sustained firefight.

“Signal the fleet.” he announced.

“Ready sir.”

“Horatio.”

In the finest of military traditions, 'Horatio' was a prearranged code phrase, meaning that the fleet should load a specific type of ammunition, calculate a specific firing solution, and await the second phrase which would be the cue to fire. Caruthers gave them the thirty seconds they needed.

"Nelson." he ordered.

The answer from all six ships at once was an opening flurry of firepower, a two-to-three-to-one mix of gravity spikes, conventional anti-ship ammunition and specialist ammo that would hopefully go unnoticed alongside the rest of the firepower. Simultaneously, the EWAR opened up, strobing the Swarm with dazzling masers and flooding every band they were broadcasting on with powerful white noise.

Those gravity spikes were necessary. Without them the Hunter ships would just warp to point-blank range in the moment they were aligned along the correct vector, eliminating the human range advantage in an infinitesimal shaving of a second. The only counter to that was gravity spikes, delivered by timed- explosion rounds that filled the intervening space with heavily distorted spacetime against which warp drives could secure no footing, ensuring that the Hunters would remain firmly confined to subluminal maneuvers.

The three parts of conventional ammunition did their job equally well, however. Four of the larger Swarm craft were crippled in the opening volley, spilling the contents of their pressurized bowels as the human guns _thump_ed and hurled their payloads down a narrow warp channel which dissipated mere centimeters from the target’s hulls, allowing no possibility of evasive action.

The Swarm responded with animal speed, showing off just how efficient the Hunter cybernetic communications really were. All of those ships were behaving almost like a single amoeboid organism, spreading out and sending loose tendrils of high-speed ships creeping out and around, questing for a vector from which to try and warp the intervening distance and engulf or snare the outnumbered human task group. Several motes of light actually lifted off the surface of Capitol Station, abandoning their tick-like burrowing in pursuit of the prized Deathworlder quarry.

Caruthers allowed himself a satisfied nod. “Signal Colonel Stewart.” he said “Tell him they’ve taken the bait.”

Rylee Jackson

"Epic to Group: The Brits have engaged. All units fold your WiTCheS and accelerate to combat speed."

Rylee practically swore with relief. The tension had been killing her, and she obeyed the order enthusiastically, punching Firebird up to speed and aligning for the station as hard as her sled could accelerate.

Lurking near the star to recoup their lost energy from the extreme long-range jump from Sol had swiftly gotten dull. She was a combat pilot, and Firebird and her sisters were combat spaceframes. They belonged in the melee.

The wing reported ready. Stewart’s voice had an eager edge to match Rylee’s own feelings "Epic to Group: Off we go."

They jumped. Warping to the target station when the British ships had polluted its skies with gravity spikes was asking for damage, which is why the opening salvo had included beacon rounds that streaked through the Hunter formation and slowed to sublight velocities on the far side, inviting the TS/2s to enfilade the Swarm.

The sky went from empty, to being awash with red contacts, painted by the Royal Navy FOF and confirmed by the absence of friendly RFID. Fed by the combat controllers aboard Caledonia, her HUD indicated her assigned box and describing a cuboid some thousand kilometers long. At the kinds of speeds reached in starship combat, she would sweep through a volume that large in seconds.

Semenza was reciting his EWAR and weapons reports from only inches behind her head.

Things had changed in the last couple of years. The missile payload was gone, replaced with electronic attack pods that further multiplied their force’s ability to blind and confuse the Hunters. only the GAU-8/S remained for their onboard weaponry.

A targeting laser speared one of the big ships as she raked its flank with 30mm rounds, shredding its shields. Behind her, Semenza grunted in satisfaction. “Firebird one, fox four.”

Rather than launching the missile, he summoned one. There was a stockpile of thousands back on Earth, and one of them jumped into the fight at Semenza’s call, existing on the battlefield for barely half a second before it slammed into the Swarmship and mauled it.

“Data point. The fuckers are armored now.” Semenza noted. He was right. In their last fight, that exact same class of missile had dismembered a ship of that size. Now it had merely gouged a ragged chunk from its flank.

“Hit it again.”

“Wilco. Firebird one, fox four.”

The wounded Swarmship blinked out of existence, and Semenza’s missile spiralled drunkenly off into the black, too confused and low on power to select a new target.

“Data point. They can evade-jump now.” Semenza added.

An incoming contact became a cloud of gas and light debris as Riley vectored sideways and put a cloud of 30mm rounds in its flight path. Its own railgun rounds went wide, barely a hundred meters to starboard.

“Stay frosty.” she muttered.

Regaari

The vent did two things for Regaari.

It saved his life, allowing him to walk, then crawl through the narrower ducting, unimpeded and unobserved towards the hangar where the Gaoian diplomatic yacht was landed.

And it let him hear the screams. It caught and amplified them, so that he heard every one in hollow, magnified, metallic detail.

So many of them. Intermingled with the sounds of pulse gun fire, the flash and strobe of Nervejam grenades, and a new sound, a heavy explosive sound that reminded him of the action movies he’d watched with Xiu, years ago.

But mostly screams. Screams of terror. Screams of pain. Dying squeals and pleading. Defiant yells as some of the soldiers and security troopers went down fighting.

Sometimes, when he couldn’t hear the screams, he could hear the eating.

Those were the worst. He hardly dared move at all in those quiet sections, for fear that the slightest sound would give him away. He had to inch past, treated to a full view of what, exactly, the Hunters did with their prey.

But his luck held. Either he was silent enough to not give himself away, or else they were so enraptured by their feast as to not notice.

He crawled onwards.

Owen Powell

When it came down to it, the difference between riding an outboard launch wearing a wetsuit, and riding an extravehicular launch wearing an EV-MASS, was basically that the latter was quieter. No waves, no bird call, none of the little noises that had hitherto masked every covert infiltration of Powell’s career. Just silence, save for his breathing.

The craft itself was little more than a conical bank of capacitors mounted on a kinetic thrust plate, with latching points for the infiltration team and any heavy gear they were bringing to be attached and folded inside its little warp field. It almost looked like a black rubber launch. Across the huge distances involved it relied on computer navigation rather than a pilot, so there was little to do but program it, hang on, and hit the button on the control screen at the little vehicle’s nose.

He had never felt so exposed in all his life.

There was no jolt or anything--the inertial compensation provided by the warp field was too well-tuned for that--but it was still jarring for HMS Caledonia to vanish from behind them and for Capitol station--which had until now just been a nigh-invisible glimmer of light, suddenly be there, right in front of them. Twenty kilometers long and only two kilometers away.

Technically, they were smack in the middle of the Swarm of Swarms, but at the scales involved human senses were hopelessly inadequate for noticing that fact. Only the occasional streak of light across the stars--weapons fire, or a ship moving at sanity-fraying velocities--hinted that there was even a battle raging silently all around them.

If their stealthy approach was not stealthy enough, if the EWAR that was theoretically blinding every sensor delicate enough to spot them, wasn’t, then the only mercy would be that their annihilation would be so instant and total that none of them would notice it happening.

The last approach used cold-gas thrusters rather than the kinetics. The Launch was designed to have practically zero sensor signature, after all. It had been a precision approach--they were barely ten meters from the station hull, stationary relative to a large window, though the mirroring on the glass made it impossible to see within, only that the section was not lit.

They detached from the Launch and Powell turned a single gentle somersault to kiss against the hull, absorbing the last of his momentum with his knees just as they had practiced in zero-G training so many times before.

Breaching the glass was simple. Sterling and Highland hacked a simple square out of the glass with two simple swipes of their fusion knives. Air pressure did the rest, flinging the plate of glass out into space, along with a blizzard of small objects caught in the rush of escaping air.

Legsy heaved himself through. There was a moment of silence.

"Clear."

Powell hit the beacon on his belt as the Combat Controllers propelled themselves through the breach, and an inky cuboid, nearly invisible in space, simply appeared without ceremony next to him. Divorced of its power source, the stasis field collapsed and Warhorse, Baseball, Titan, Thor, Rebar and Snapfire were hanging next to him.

He let them through the hole first and, once through himself, settled onto the deck in galactic standard gravity. The Deltas deployed a forcefield seal over the breach and, at their nod, Legsy and Sterling burst through the door into the corridor beyond, pushing past the hurricane rush of air that flooded into their entry room. Their SMGs spat out their rounds with a noise that went right through Powell’s chest..

He was pleased to hear it. The silence of vacuum had been getting to him, and any sound was welcome, even if it wasn’t a pleasant sound--shrieking alarms, wailing aliens and the distant hammering of Hunter pulse fire, plus an unpleasant hissing. Apparently their forcefield wasn’t as airtight as hoped.

“Right. Let’s get into an airtight compartment.” he ordered.

They vacated the room and sealed the door behind them. Ares raised his SAW and fired a sharp six-round burst at something, and Powell suppressed some pride when he turned and saw that the kid had just bagged his first Hunter kill. He was in commander mode right now, he couldn’t afford to be sentimental.

Legsy, Highland and Sterling took point, storming down the corridor and ripping into a knot of Hunters that were tormenting a shuddering Guvnurag. All five of the monsters were dead before they even knew they were under assault.

The huge alien was in a bad way, bleeding horribly from where the Hunters had bitten the flesh right off her living body. Burgess went to work, and Powell took a moment to evaluate their position. It was some kind of a common area, full of benches and tables and the kind of alien-sized furniture that made good high cover for humans. Better still, there was plenty of room for the Defenders to deploy their jump array.

“This is our spot.” he announced.

The Alpha of the Brood-that-Builds

+<Interest> A human Alpha. The first we have seen.+

The Builder Alpha examined the perspective of the little insect-sized spy drone as it settled on the ceiling above the Deathworlder.

The human infantry had appeared from nowhere, storming out of a supposedly empty room on the station’s upper decks without warning. They might almost have materialised in that room fully-formed. Impossible, of course, but then again that kind of stealth was only marginally more credible, especially from a species so technologically behind the Hunters.

This particular specimen was clearly in command, having started by thrusting its arm out to indicate where its subordinates should go and what work they should do, and now poring over a diagram of that section of the station, directing the efforts of the other eleven.

The Alpha-of-Alphas was clearly intrigued also. It had a much more complete view of the battlefield than the Builder Alpha did, ensconced as it was in a kind of command throne that was designed to interface with its neural augmentations and greatly expand its ability to track and consider the situation. It had proven itself in battle against these humans, receiving only minor wounds at worst. Now it was proving itself as a commander and leader.

+<Correction> Not just an Alpha.+ it mused. +<Observation> Notice the markings on their armor. There are three different Deathworlder broods here. Each fulfills a different role. This is an Alpha-of-many-broods. It must be an individual of great importance.+

The Builder broadcast understanding and agreement. +<Fascination> Interesting that their broods function together through division of duty.+ it commented. +<Inspiration> And that displacement device! The possibilities!+

+<Satisfaction> Observing that device in action alone has been worth this trap.+ the Alpha-of-Alphas agreed. +<Thoughtfulness> And the specialised behaviour of their warriors can be translated to our own broods. This is valuable data.+

They watched the Deathworlders slaughter lesser Hunters by the dozen for some minutes. The violence was almost intimidating, even from a cloaked listening post far removed from the action. The lead team of three would enter a compartment, and every Hunter within that compartment would be dead almost too quickly to fathom, cut down by withering volleys of disciplined firepower.

There was an objective to it, though--they weren’t killing for the sake of killing. Instead, every time the humans surged forward, it was to claim another little knot of surviving Prey, plucking them from the Hunters’ grasp and securing the meat the opportunity to escape. Dozens had escaped already, most of them the important, high-value individuals whose deaths would have so demoralized the Prey across the galaxy. Each dignitary that escaped to whatever sanctuary the Deathworlders had established beyond their displacement array was a personal insult to the Alpha-of-Alpha’s plan.

Why they should do so was incomprehensible to the Alpha of the Brood-that- Builds. Why would superior lifeforms put themselves in harm’s way to rescue inferior ones that were not even the same brood or species?

It sensed that there was no answer to that conundrum within the remit of engineering.

For their part, the Hunters’ responses to human weaponry just didn’t seem to be giving them the edge that the Builder had hoped for. The guns were just too heavy, and needed to be held in too specific a way so as to avoid injury. If only they could capture a working example of the weapons the humans themselves were using…

As they watched, a family of spindly blue Prey were herded into the territory the humans had seized and vanished through the displacement device. Just behind them was the wounded Large Prey, actually being carried by two of the Deathworlders. The Builder revised its estimates as to human maximum muscle strength upwards by several percentage points.

+<Curiosity> Those two seem to prioritise the repair and evacuation of wounded Prey.+ it noted.

+<Contempt> Yes. While that is an obvious sign of weakness and wrong-thinking, it will also potentially undermine our intimidation of the prey.+ the Alpha-of-Alpha’s thoughts were tinged with anger at this damage to their propaganda victory.

+<Suggestion> I submit that we have gathered enough data. Those humans should be eradicated, their displacement device salvaged and we should capture that Alpha-of-Many-Broods.+ the Builder proposed.

It did not take the silence that greeted this idea for hesitation or contempt. The Alpha-of-Alphas had demonstrated its intelligence and cunning time and again. It was undoubtedly mulling the suggestion over, considering the merits and potential risks.

+<Resolve> Agreed.+ It sent, at last. +I will deploy the Strongest Brood.+

Regaari

Regaari’s luck ran out the instant he dropped into the diplomatic yacht’s hangar. Only the Whitecrest training that the Mothers would have so despised had they known of it kept him from dying the moment he dropped from the vent and onto the deck. He hadn’t seen the three Hunters feasting on a brother of Clan Farflight, but his pulse rifle snapped up and was firing the instant he saw them. Three solid hits pulped the one holding a bizarre long gun in a shock-absorbing assemblage, and he dived aside, throwing down a shieldstick to cover his retreat. Retaliatory pulse fire splashed against it.

The latest generation, available only to Whitecrests, could admit pulse fire from the defenders’ side, and he used that feature to return fire, killing the last two even as their final pulse shot shattered his barrier. That had been too close.

He turned to the ship and froze cold, realising that the Hunters had already crippled it, recognising the fact that it was a possible escape craft. He had no way off the station.

No, there had to be an alternative, something he’d overlooked…

A crawling sense of paranoia made him look up.

The Alpha dropped from the ceiling like something obscene from one of Xiu’s movies, and smashed his gun out of his hands. Half as big again as its subordinates and much more heavily augmented, it kicked him and Regaari felt a rib jar painfully inside him as the blow flipped him through the air to slide on his back halfway across the hangar.

Winded and injured, he still fought to find his feet, scrambling at his belt for his backup pulse pistol. That too was slapped aside by the Alpha, which used its other hand to grab him by the scruff of his neck and lift him off the deck, feet kicking and dangling.

He wouldn’t have been Regaari if he hadn’t fought for every last second though. Down to just his claws, he raked the nightmare’s face, costing it two eyes and badly lacerating the flesh around a cluster of cybernetics that replaced three of the others.

It replied by biting off his left paw just above the wrist.

It was an almost dainty gesture, and Hunter teeth were so sharp that Regaari was almost able to see it happen without feeling it. One moment it was his paw, the next it was a meaty morsel, frothing blood in the creature’s mouth, crunching and splintering as the hunter bit through the bone to swallow what had once been a part of him.

It laughed. There was no epithet in Gaori to describe how much he hated it for that. The…beast gloated, savoring its kill. He snorted nasal mucus and spat it into the creature’s remaining eye, too proud to give it the satisfaction of fearing it. He hated it, hated everything it stood for, and his last thought was to hope fervently that it would choke on him.

Instead, its head twitched to look over his shoulder, and it dropped him, bringing up one of those large long guns.

Those guns were clearly heavy though. Too heavy to respond in time. Its head exploded, painting a grisly slurry of meaty matter and cybernetic parts all over the deck, and the most glorious sight in the galaxy double-timed across the hangar, gun snapping from corner to corner in case of any lingering threats.

By all the clans of Gao. An actual human. Built like a bunker and faceless in an armored vacuum suit layered in technology, but unmistakably a Deathworlder. Nothing else could conceivably have moved so easily while carrying so much.

“You’re late.” he chided, out of pure bravado.

“You’re alive.” the human replied, setting to work on the stump of his arm. Regaari reached across to retrieve his pulse pistol with his remaining hand and holstered it. He was keeping on top of the pain, barely, and having that little task to focus on while the human stopped his bleeding by injecting some kind of foam directly into the wound, which hardened and stopped the blood flow almost instantly, kept him from crying out from the agony and fainting.

“Come on compadre, you’re not getting out of here on that shuttle." the human said. He slung his gun around his shoulder, tugged a smaller one from a belt holster, tucked an arm under Regaari and hoisted him firmly but gently off the floor. It was like being a cub again, riding on an adult’s shoulders.

The diplomatic quarters outside were exactly the kind of hell his imagination and sense of hearing had suggested as he’d crawled through the vents. There were bodies everywhere, many of them clearly cut down from behind as they tried to flee. Intermingled with them were Hunter corpses, however, clearly fallen where they had been feasting, many still with dripping shreds of flesh caught in their fangs.

Two more humans in those armored vacuum suits were firing stubby little black weapons at something through a doorway. Not missing a beat, his rescuer dropped his shoulders and surged past their firefight, shielding Regaari with his own body.

This brought them into view of another human, just in time for Regaari to watch him sidestep a charging Beta and punch it so hard in the side of its jaw that the head was all but torn off. The huge corpse crashed into the bulkhead and left a purplish blood stain.

“Whe-” Regaari began. He made it no further than that, because an explosion an order of magnitude larger than anything that had previously rocked them punished the deck. The lights died, and artificial gravity went with them for just a second before the damage control systems found an alternate power source for them. Emergency lighting, dark and blue, at least robbed the carnage of its more stomach-turning hues.

The humans clearly heard an order via some means he wasn’t party too, because all of them began to fall back under fire towards the recreational concourse. The one carrying him picked up his speed to the point where Regaari could feel a breeze in his fur.

There were Hunters on the concourse, but unlike any that Regaari had ever heard of. Gone were the usual cruel cybernetics. In fact, gone were whole limbs, and in place of the “natural” sickly white of Hunter flesh was a horrible wet meaty redness which bulged and pulled in grotesque ways as they moved. Whatever these Hunters had done to themselves had granted them the strength to move confidently and swiftly even layered in thick armor plates and while carrying large weapons.

They were huge, as big if not bigger than the Alpha that had nearly killed him, and moving with a sturdy, graceful precision that was more like a human’s motion, and these ones seemed to be handling their guns just fine, pouring a hail of firepower into the water feature that three more human soldiers were using for cover.

His rescuer’s gun hand came up and the pistol’s sharp crack was a very different noise to the heavy, explosive, industrial thunder being made by the Hunter weaponry. Unlike them, his aim was sharp and precise. One of the abominations choked and collapsed as the rounds ripped into exposed gaps at the sides and flanks, but two of its friends turned to face the new threat, with bullets sparking off shields and armour plates as they returned fire, squinting against the glare from the bright light mounted below the pistol’s barrel.

Regaari was jolted badly when his carrier then jinked into cover, and he was let go of. Even if the human was trying to be gentle, being carried by a Deathworlder was clearly a dangerous experience.

He kept his head down. There was more gunfire, shouting, the deck plating shook.

“They’re coming up the left!”

“They’re fucking suicidal…Baseball, Rebar, get up on the right there!”

The deck plating dented under their weight as the pinned three dashed from where they’d been hiding and made it into cover beside him. “Good shooting, Hoss.”

“Anyone hurt?”

“I took a hit, didn’t penetrate. Those guns of theirs hit hard though.”

“Watch the ones coming down the middle…fuck! NERVEJAM!”

"Oh no you don’t!"

Regaari felt like an icicle was pounded into his brain as a grenade went off nearby.

“Man down!”

“Get him back here! Suppressing fire!"

A storm of shooting. Heavy footfalls, more shouting, and something large was dragged into cover alongside him, one of the humans convulsing and twitching in his armour.

“They’re still coming!”

“Throwing grenade…FRAG OUT!”

An explosion that left his ears ringing in protest. Station damage alarms started wailing nearby, adding to the chorus of violence.

“How is he?”

“He needs to be jumped to triage right now, sir.”

There was a deadly, horrible pause. “Fookin’.…can we make the array?”

“I don’t think so, sir.”

“…Thor, demolish it. We’re EA jumping.”

“Major. He’s dead, sir.”

“…Aye. Grab the ETs and fall back, that way. Legsy, Highland! Cover the retreat.”

Regaari was hoisted up with Deathworlder strength and carried. There were three others with him: a Corti and two Kwmbwrw, who seemed to be equally as petrified by their rescuers as by the Hunters.

He could see over his carrier’s shoulder as they ran. The one in charge paused long enough to tap some commands out on the computer he carried, and the dead soldier’s armor started smoking, then burst into flames.

The one carrying him muttered something. His helmet decided that the sotto voce delivery was not intended for translation, but Regaari understood just enough English to understand him.

“…Goodbye, Sterling.”

“Get in this bag, quickly now.”

The Corti was clearly one of the political delegation, and not accustomed to taking orders gracefully. “What exactly is an 'EA Jump' and why am I being stuffed into a bag for it?" he demanded.

The human commander clearly had no patience for Corti games. “It means Exo- bloody-Atmospheric. We are going to jump out of this station and land on that planet, so put on the fookin’ bag!" he snapped. Behind his pressure helmet, his eyes promised trouble the likes of which no alien could comprehend if he was not obeyed.

The Corti squeaked and practically dove into the bag. Regaari had already been mostly into his, but he balked upon hearing this. "Jump?"

The human whose chest the bag was strapped to nodded, and pushed him down gently but firmly, helping him curl up inside it. “Yep.” he said.

“Is that safe?”

"Hell no. Beats being eaten by Hunters though." He tugged the bag over Regaari’s head and sealed it. It instantly pressurised, filling with sweet atmosphere that was a welcome relief from the meat-tasting foulness he’d been breathing.

There was a little transparent window for him to see out of, and through it he saw two of the humans each stick a large brick of something to the outside station wall.

There was muffled speech, then shouting as the humans who had stayed behind retreated into the room, still shooting. They slammed and sealed the door--an instant later, a titanic detonation shook the room.

“Claymore?” the commander asked.

“Yep. There’s more coming, but they’re being careful now.”

“Right. Last seal check, blow it on my go.”

The humans scrambled to check each other’s suits, and all loudly declared them satisfactory, then the one carrying him turned away and hunkered down and….

Losing his hand turned out to be only the second most violent thing that happened to Regaari that day. The first was any station-dweller’s nightmare-- the total catastrophic failure of an outside wall, and the resulting depressurisation that flung them and everything else in the room out into space. Crushing G-forces caused him to black out for a second.

"Hey. Hey, you still with me in there?"

The voice was coming from a small hand-held device attached by a coiled wire to the same panel on the inside of his bag that was providing Regaari’s breathable air. Tinny and quiet as it was, it still seemed loud inside the bag, which was basically silent apart from the faint sounds of the air being exchanged and of Regaari’s own body.

He grabbed it and tentatively pressed the button on the side. “Yes. I’m still with you.”

"Good news, man. We’re alive and reentering just fine."

Regaari had to produce a bitter chirp at that one. “Oh, yes. Everything is absolutely perfect.” he commented.

"Better than being eaten. What’s your name, compadre?"

“Regaari. Officer Regaari, of Clan Whitecrest.”

"Cool. Call me Warhorse."

Regaari pushed his nose up to the window of his bag, which was now a taut cylinder. He could just make out the human’s arms on either side of him and beyond that, only Capitol Station and tumbling, burning lights. 'Warhorse’ sounded more like a codename to him than the human’s real name, but he wasn’t going to argue. Goodness knew, he’d gone by plenty of assumed identities in his duties.

“So. Atmospheric reentry without a spacecraft.” he said. “I assume this suit of yours is equipped for it?”

"Technically, everything about this suit is so classified I can’t tell you shit about it, man. But, y’know, you’ll figure out if it is or isn’t by the way we do or don’t burn up." Warhorse told him.

“How comforting.”

"Hah!"

They fell in silence for a while. There was a pale blue glow just building up past the limb of Warhorse’s limbs when Regaari finally spoke. “I’m curious. Why?”

"Why…what, man?"

“The Dominion’s treated you-” he spoke in English as best as a Gaoian mouth could “-like shit. You lost a presumably elite soldier today…"

"One of the very fuckin’ best." Warhorse agreed. There was an emotional edge to his voice, but Regaari couldn’t interpret what that edge might be. Not that it was difficult to guess.

“Not to…belittle his sacrifice.” he said, carefully “But why?”

"Hey, I don’t know the why of it, man." Warhorse replied. "But my whole thing is saving lives. That’s, like, my job, my purpose in life. So, I’m just doing what I do, you know?"

“You lost a man.” Regaari repeated.

"Yeah. And I’m going to miss him like crazy, he was one of my brothers, man. But we SAVED like…what, fifty? Sixty?"

“That many?”

"Something like."

“Still, risking twelve elite human soldiers to save fifty or sixty ungrateful politicians…”

"A life is a life, man. Doesn’t matter if it’s human, Gaoian, Kwmbwrw, or that little grey fuck on Baseball’s chest."

There was a flicker of orange light. “Re-entry plasma?”

"Yeah. Forcefield should handle it just fine. Sit back and enjoy the fireworks."

“Ah, fireworks.” Regaari nodded. “I had a human friend once. She showed me video footage of fireworks. I always thought it would be fun to see them.”

"Human friend?"

“Shoo.”

The translator spat out Warhorse’s response in the form of the Gaori word for “footwear” with a questioning uptick.

“Her real name has this awkward sound at the start. Like shhh but more…buzzing."

“…Wait, not Jew? You had a Jewish friend?"

“I don’t know what that is. Her name was a longer and…flatter sound. She said she was Chinese-Canadian?"

"Aah, right. Gotcha. Yah, most other humans struggle with Chinese names too."

The plasma outside was now a steady orange torrent. The bag’s window was clearly photosensitive because it had darkened to welder’s-mask black in order to protect his eyes from the contrail’s incandescence.

Then the shaking started.

“Is it…meant to do this?”

"You got me, compadre. This is the first time I’ve done this."

“Not even in training?”

"Too dangerous for training. Hold on!"

Regaari curled up, resisted the urge to let his claws out, and shut his eyes, wishing against all rationality that he could be a cub again as he and Warhorse became a fireball together, and fell.

The eternity of being about to die ended in a metallic noise, the wheeze of cloth against cloth, and a jolt nearly as violent as the one that had flung them from the station.

“What? What was that?!” he asked.

He hadn’t thought to press the button on the communicator, but now Warhorse’s voice came through to him from outside the bag, slightly muffled but no more than that. They had atmosphere. “Parachute. Worst part’s over, compadre, we’re almost down safe. You okay?"

“What’s left of me is doing fine.”

"Bueno. Last hit coming up in three…two…"

Regaari grimaced as there was a thump and several jolts, before the human fell down backwards, careful to let Regaari fall on top rather than the other way round.

There were some more metallic clinks, a rustling of fabric, and then the top of his bag tore off. Warhorse looked in. “You okay?” he asked.

Regaari climbed out of the bag as best he could with only one paw and collapsed on his back, gulping like a stranded fish. “I never want to do anything like that ever again.” he stated.

Warhorse just lay beside him and chuckled. The chuckle turned into a laugh and he surged to his feet and ripped off the helmet and mask of his pressure suit, revealing a stubbly fuzz of head-hair on deep nut-coloured skin. Still laughing he threw the helmet high into the air, shrugged off the parachute harness and rucksack, and then spread his arms and howled.

The noise was agony, a primal noar of defiance aimed at the universe which impaled Regaari’s sensitive ears and straight through into the pain centers of his brain. Warhorse seemed to have gone mad, jumping and swearing and punching the air, always returning to that same "WOOO!" sound. Regaari watched in alarm as the human did a double backflip in what must, to him, have been extremely low gravity, then stooped, ripped a stone from the turf that was as big as Regaari’s head and threw it hard at a nearby tree before collapsing, giggling, on his back.

The stone hit the tree with such incredible force that it lodged in the wood.

A second later, creaking, crackling, hissing and groaning, the tree fell over.

Warhorse’s laughter died and he sat up. “Jeez.” he said. “Did I do that?"

Regaari scowled at him. “This is the only known class two planet. You’re a native of a class twelve. You could probably ruin this planet’s whole biosphere just by breathing on it, if you aren’t careful."

Warhorse blinked at him then stood up. “Didn’t catch one word of that, man.” he looked around “Where the fuck is my helmet?”

Regaari picked it up and offered it to him, feeling his arm wobble from the weight.

“Thanks, man.” Warhorse wriggled it back onto his head, muttering angrily to himself. "Fucking amateur, Ares, don’t be stupid…Never remove your helmet, dumbass."

“I said." Regaari repeated, when it was back on and the translator was working again “That we’re standing on the only known class two planet in this galaxy, and you’re from a Class twelve. You could do serious harm if you’re not careful.”

“Shit.” Warhorse nodded agreement. “You’re right. Sorry.”

“You’d better not do that either, or you’ll definitely kill this world." Regaari added.

“I know man, I live on Cimbrean.” Warhorse told him, twisting the helmet back and forth until it was firmly in place and the docking collar re-engaged with a solid 'snap!’

He checked it was seated properly by throwing his head back and forth a bit and wriggling his shoulders. “Thanks for the reminder, though.”

“How heavy IS that helmet?” Regaari asked.

“Twenty-five pounds base weight.” Warhorse replied, “Which, yeah. Sucks.”

He rearranged some of his equipment and shrugged the ruck on again as if it was nothing, causing Regaari’s boggling over the helmet to intensify. He’d experienced for himself just how strong Xiu had been, but between the stone, that rucksack, and the easy way he had carried Regaari himself and all that other gear back on the station, it was plain that Warhorse vastly outstripped her.

The human pressed firmly on the side of his helmet. “STAINLESS, WARHORSE.” he announced. “Arrived DZ, one healthy ET in tow, I’m at, uh…” he checked the device in his hand and reeled off a string of numbers. “Seeking cover and awaiting orders.”

There was silence for a few seconds and then -

"WARHORSE, STAINLESS. I have your DZ. Seek cover, rest up. Turn to tac-net three niner four Tango November Juliet and await further. Out."

Warhorse grunted and looked around, scanning the horizon with those predator’s eyes. “There.” he pointed. Regaari squinted, and could see the shimmer of water cascading down a rocky outcrop, carving a little tree-haunted valley.

“How far is that?” he asked.

“Eh, three clicks or so. I jog further than that before breakfast.”

“Ah, yes. Human endurance running.” Regaari sighed. “I’m going to slow you down, aren’t I?”

“Nah, man. Climb on.”

Regaari flattened his ears disbelievingly. “You can’t be serious.”

“Gravity this low, I need something to weigh me down" Warhorse replied. “Besides, what do you mass, like ninety pounds? I could lift you one-handed in twice this gravity, no problem.”

The translator fed him a Gaori measurement that sounded about right, so he nodded, imitating the gesture he’d often seen Xiu use. Warhorse just returned the gesture and waved a hand towards the pack on his shoulders.

Regaari paused, then twitched his whiskers resignedly and did as the human suggested, clambering up the bag to sit atop it. It wasn’t dignified, but Warhorse didn’t appear to notice the extra weight.

“Man, we should put a machine gun up there for you or something.” he chuckled.

“How about optics, or that map of yours?” Regaari suggested.

“Good thinking. Binos are in that front pocket there.” Warhorse handed up the map device. It was alarmingly short on detail, and Regaari said so. Warhorse just nodded. “Relax, intel’s got our back. We’ll have a better map pretty soon.”

They headed out. Warhorse quickly settled into a steady rhythm of big, long bounding strides that ate up the ground, and just kept going. It wasn’t quite running, so much as a vigorous, fast march, and it was deceptive. Regaari wouldn’t have guessed they were moving very fast, but when he glanced behind them he saw that their landing site was already distant, and receding.

He played with the 'binos‘, adjusting their width, having to set them to their widest to fit his own face, but once he did so and toyed with the wheel on top and its functions, he swiftly got the hang of it. It was…strange, handling a piece of human technology, made by humans for human use. It certainly didn’t feel like a lower-tech species’ gear, either. It may have lacked a few of the advanced features that he’d have found in a Gaoian equivalent, but optically it was superb. The only real burr in his fur that he could find to complain about was their heaviness.

Warhorse wasn’t even breathing heavily when they stopped again.

Regaari chittered a little on a surge of cynicism. Their resting spot was as stereotypical of a low-class world as could be--a gentle glade fed by a clean bubbling stream with a pool in which slender, silver little fish were undulating. Idyllic.

Warhorse ignored it. Instead he let Regaari off his back and shucked off the ruck, before examining the dressing on Regaari’s arm. “Any pain or itching?” he asked.

“No. But it feels like the paw is still there.” Regaari said. It was a strange sensation, he could still “grip” and move his “fingers” but of course nothing happened except that what was left of the muscle sheath in his forearm twitched pathetically as it tried to flex and twist to pull on the now-absent tendons of his now-absent paw.

He sat down and stared at the dressing as Warhorse made a satisfied noise and pottered about, setting up a basic camp.

“You okay?” he was asked after a while. Regaari chirruped a bitter little laugh.

“I’m supposed to be one of the elite.” he said. “Clan Whitecrest, foremost commandos and security specialists of the whole Gaoian species, but next to the Hunters I may as well be a cub. Next to you…"

Warhorse had set up next to the pool and was digging through his bag. “Nah, man. You’re a fucking badass.” he replied.

“What was that expression? Pull the other one. Only, please don’t because I’d like to get off this planet with at least three whole limbs."

“Totally serious, compadre. What did you do to that hunter? Clawed out two eyes and spat in the third? And that was a fuckin’ Alpha. You’ve got spirit, bro."

Regaari snorted. "Spirit doesn’t count. Only results matter." he snapped, dismissively.

“You got the result, though." Warhorse said. When Regaari twitched a disbelieving ear at him, he nodded insistently. “Seriously. You’re alive. You held out long enough for the cavalry to reach you and you saw that son of a bitch dead. Result."

“You’re just trying to pep me up.” Regaari told him.

Warhorse nodded. “’Course I am. Best way to do that’s with the truth, though. You’re still kicking, it’s not, and the difference was you going down swinging. Spirit gets results, man.”

Regaari sat silently and watched. The human soon made a satisfied noise and pulled out a handful of flat brown packs of some kind, and scooped up some water from the pool in a little bottle. There was a pump of some kind in the bottle’s end, and after a few enthusiastic strokes of that, the water was forced back out through the filter nozzle.

“Are you…filtering and purifying that?" Regaari asked. “This is a class two planet, you don’t need to.”

“Basic survival rule where I’m from, never trust the water.”

“We’re not on where you’re from.”

Warhorse paused, then shrugged. “Eh, a good habit’s a good habit.” He held up the little brown packages from the ruck. “Hungry?”

“You’re eating now? We only just landed."

“Every chance I get. Never know when the next opportunity’s going to arrive in a situation like this.”

“But how are you going to cook it without a fire? If you build one, won’t the Hunters-”

“Relax, we got that covered. Besides, there’s a long way to go ahead of us, I’m going to need the nutrition, whereas the Hunters only might come looking for us."

“Oh. Well, I do like human food…”

“Eh, this is just an MRE, not fine dining. Kind of the tastier alternative to those ration balls.” Warhorse said, opening the package and tipping most of the contents out onto his lap. He tipped a little sachet of white powder into his bottle and shook it, turning the water a vivid pink, then took off his breathing mask and sipped it.

“What’s that?” Regaari asked.

“Juice. Electrolytes, sugar, hydration.” Warhorse sipped again and licked his lips, frowning. “Supposedly it tastes like cherry.”

“Supposedly?”

“Look, you want one of these to try? Because I can eat whatever’s too much for you.”

“…If it’s safe.”

“It’s all been treated with gamma radiation man. Totally sterile, I promise.”

“Then…yes please.”

Warhorse nodded and examined the available options, “…I warn you man, this shit’s…this is the high-performance version, it’s meant to get a fuckload of energy into me first and foremost. The culinary experience is, like, a distant second.” he pointed out.

“I’ll try it anyway. You’re right, nutrition in a situation like this is important.”

Warhorse nodded, and stuffed the rest of the MREs back into his pack. “Damn right.” He ripped the top off a couple of transparent plastic bags, slipped the unappetizing green pouches of food inside, and then added a little water before returning the bags to their cardboard box and leaning them against a rock. Within seconds, steam was rising from the boxes.

“How does that work?” Regaari asked.

“Chemical reaction.”

“Clever.” Regaari commented. “No flame, no smoke, minimal heat signature.”

“That’s the idea.” Warhorse agreed.

Regaari watched him cook, silently calculating how to eat his meal one-pawed. His nose twitched involuntarily when Warhorse kneaded a little sachet and then spread the off-white paste it contained onto his dry crackers--the scent thus unleashed was creamy and rich, hinting that his dismissive assessment of the meal’s quality had probably been unfair.

Sadly, when Regaari sampled the crackers while waiting for the main course to be ready he was sorely disappointed, and Warhorse was right--while the beverage was clearly supposed to taste like fruit, what it mostly tasted of was chemistry.

“What’s this?” he asked, opening and sniffing it. The scent was pungent and sugary.

“’s called a HOOAH! bar.” Warhorse said. “I wouldn’t, man, that thing’s got, like, a thousand calories in it.”

The translator paused while translating that figure, and Regaari could see why. It must have been doing an internal error-check to make sure there wasn’t some mistake. That was half a week’s nutritional intake for a Gaoian male. “That many?”

“Yep.” Warhorse took the bar off him and bit into it, chewing vigorously. "Giveff your jaw a workout, too." he added, around the mouthful.

“Exactly how many calories do you need?" Regaari asked.

“Me, on a light day? At least ten thousand or so.” Warhorse replied. “But this is gonna be a really active day, so…a lot more. Anyway, main should be ready.”

Between a small rock and leaning the bag against what remained of his left forearm, Regaari was able to hold it steady enough to poke at it with the spoon. While it certainly looked appetising enough, his nose was practically being overwhelmed by the rich scent. He tried it.

One mouthful was enough. “Great…Father Fyu!” he coughed.

Warhorse just laughed. “You okay?”

“It’s like eating a candle!”

“Like I said, man. Performance first, pleasant eating experience second. Don’t worry, you gave it a pretty good go for an ET.” he said, ripping his own bag open and mixing in the contents of a tiny glass bottle of red sauce.

Regaari licked the sauce out of his fur, regaining his composure. “ET?”

“Extra-Terrestrial. It’s a friendly way of saying 'non-human’."

“You have other ways?”

“Sure. 'ET' is friendly, 'non-human' is all formal and proper, and 'xeno' is an insult."

Warhorse inhaled most of his meal in three efficient scoops. "Ffo- thiff human friend off yourff." he said, around the mouthful, before swallowing. “Joo?”

“Close enough.”

“How’d you meet? There’s not a lot of us out here. She an abductee?”

Regaari made an affirmative ducking nod. “Yes, about…eleven Gaori years ago now, one of our settler transports was raided by mercenaries working for an-” he raised his paws and made a 'finger quotes' gesture that Xiu had been fond of, only realising that the effect was spoiled a little by his missing paw after he’d done it. “’Unauthorized researcher’."

He snorted. “So the Corti Directorate claims, anyway. They killed all the males and abducted the females and cubs.”

Warhorse’s expression darkened, even as he leaned over and stole Regaari’s leftovers. "Coño de madre." he snarled. The translator didn’t seem to have a readily available equivalent, but the intent was clear.

“Shoo was picked up separately, but kept in the same holding cell.” Regaari continued. “Thanks to her, they were able to escape.”

“Where do you come in?”

“There was…political fallout. Ayma--the leader of the abducted females--fought fang and claw to get Shoo adopted into the Clan of Females. Most of the other females sided with her, of course, but some of the male clans…”

“Yeah?” Warhorse took another mouthful "I thought you guyff mofftly went along with the Femaleff?"

Regaari chittered. “I thought 'you guys' were dangerous disease-ridden predators?" he countered. “Granted, many of the clans are ruled more by their testicles than by their brains, but the females don’t hold absolute power, just a strong influence. They may hold the veto, but they still want to mate as much as the males do."

Warhorse chuckled again. “Yeah, that sounds about right.” he agreed. “What did you think?”

“I didn’t. I was too focused on the blow to my career.”

“Your career?”

Regaari made an uncomfortable noise. “It’s…complicated.”

“I’m a medic, compadre. I can handle complicated."

Regaari wobbled his head sideways in a 'fair enough' gesture. “I…had some disagreements with the clan.” he said. “This was early in our negotiations with the Dominion, and I was part of the inquiry into the missing transports. We had all of the circumstantial evidence we could have wanted that proved there were Dominion species involved, and that this 'unauthorized' researcher was anything but, but nothing concrete. Meanwhile, I found out that the Whitecrest Clan--and several other powerful Clans--were all preparing as if our membership of the Dominion was a foregone conclusion. Buying shares and equipment, training and indoctrinating our new Brothers a certain way, that kind of thing."

“You suspected corruption in your own ranks?” Warhorse guessed.

“No. I wasn’t so cynical back then. I was appalled, of course. As far as I was concerned, even circumstantial evidence that the Dominion was involved in our transports going missing--and complacency is collusion, as far as I’m concerned--was reason enough to abandon the negotiations on the spot and approach the Celzi Alliance. Of course, now I know that the Alliance is just as bad, but…”

He shook himself. “…Rather than discussing the matter with some of my more seasoned Brothers, I took it straight to one of the Fathers, convinced that it was an honest oversight, and that when they saw the evidence we had gathered, the mistake would be corrected.”

“Bad move?”

“The Father I approached was one of the…hmm…quiet conspirators. Not one of the obvious beneficiaries of the deal, but still very much involved, and who stood to gain.”

“What happened?”

“He promoted me.”

Warhorse paused in pouring the last of the gravy into his mouth. “Come again?”

“To the rank of Whitecrest attache to the Mother-Supreme, part of her executive staff and, if need be, her bodyguard. A prestigious career move, on the face of it. The reality…” he sniffed.

Warhorse just sat and listened, so Regaari pressed on. “The reality was I was now not involved in the investigation, was no longer part of the Clan’s decision-making process, was a pariah in the inner circle and, though I theoretically had the ear of the Mother-Supreme, actually using it might have been seen as meddling in Female affairs, which would have politically and reproductively ruined me.”

“They de-clawed you.”

Regaari winced. The turn of phrase was intimately disturbing for Gaoians. “That’s an…accurate description.” he conceded.

Warhorse nodded his understanding, starting in on the second HOOAH! bar. Regaari shook his head in disbelief. “What do you have in there? A black hole?"

“So what happened?” Warhorse asked, ignoring the jab.

Regaari grinned, emulating the human gesture. “Shoo did.”

Date Point: ten years earlier, 12d AV
Yei Wa City, Wi Ko Yun province, Gao

“So why are you bringing this to me, and what is it?”

Kinoro’s ears swiveled uncertainty. “Security footage from the Corti facility those females escaped from.” he said. Regaari’s own ears signaled his skepticism.

“I’m not involved in the investigation any more, remember?” he pointed out. “Father Taaru saw to that.”

“This is…relevant. We may need you to, ah, influence the Mother-Supreme."

Regaari’s ears flattened. “This footage had better give me a compelling reason to do so.” he said.

“You’ve heard that the leader of these escapees, Ayma, is petitioning to have the alien recognised as a Sister?”

Regaari ducked his head. “Yes.”

“This is footage of that alien in combat.”

They watched it. The alien was very definitely alien--long of limb, compact of body, and remarkably poised, but it wasn’t until she almost ripped one of the Locayl jailers in half that the source of that poise became apparent.

“So strong." he muttered, watching as the alien darted across the room and practically flattened the second Locayl.

“We’re still working on theories as to how biology like that is possible.” Kinoro told him.

Regaari watched as the footage cut to the alien female cutting a swathe through an assorted grab-bag of the galaxy’s mercenaries. “What’s the best one?”

“I’d bet five years of celibacy that the Dominion’s assertions that deathworlds can’t support intelligent life is wrong.” Kinoro replied.

“Plausible.” Regaari conceded.

“And terrifying.” Kinoro continued. “If I’m right then that…thing…is a bomb waiting to explode."

“Is she? Look here, she’s fighting differently now that she’s figured out the strength disparity.” Regaari slowed down the footage to point out the subtle changes in the alien’s fighting style. “Wounding, rather than killing. Showing restraint, despite not having a good reason to.”

“I’m sure its compassion will be a great comfort when the deathworld plagues it undoubtedly carries get loose on Gao and kill millions of our people.” Kinoro sniped. “Billions, perhaps.”

“Have any of the females shown signs of infection?”

“…No. None.”

“Then you know what I see, Brother? I see a poor pre-contact life form, who- knows- how-far from home and probably feeling very confused right now.” Regaari looked his Brother in the eye. “And I intend to say as much to the Mother-Supreme.”

“You’d defy our clan Fathers a second time?”

“What will they do, crown me the Emperor of Gao and call it a punishment?” Regaari scoffed.

Kirono growled. There was a flash of teeth before he restrained himself--in older and less civilized times, that would have inevitably led to a snapping, claw-bearing fight. “Your own Brothers and Fathers… ” he began-

“Are wrong, Brother.” Regaari interrupted, ejecting the little crystalline data wafer that Kirono had brought him, and pocketing it. “I’m loyal to the clan, but that doesn’t mean I have to agree with the Fathers automatically.”

“You DO have to obey their orders, though.”

Regaari’s ears pricked. “They’re ordering me to influence her?" he asked.

“Well…no…Not ordering as such…" Kirono backpedalled, and with good reason. The whole clan’s mating fitness would suffer if the Females felt that Giymuy was being bullied by the Whitecrests.

“Then I shall use my best discretion and judgement.” Regaari asserted. “Just as the Fathers trained me to.”

Date Point: 10y AV
Planet Garden, Capitol System, Dominion Space

“You fought back.” Warhorse observed.

“You’re damn right I did." Regaari said, spitting the English word. He couldn’t see Warhorse’s mouth any more--the human had replaced his breathing mask and was reclining against a rock, but he saw the way the skin around his eyes and face stretched and wrinkled. There was a smile under that mask.

“Dude, you’re fuckin’ scrappy, I like it!”

Regaari didn’t get the chance to respond, as the radio chose that moment to flare.

"Operation NOVA HOUND, STAINLESS. Our Evac’s arranged, see your tablets for RP Alpha. You have five hours to get there. Individual orders follow." there was a pause then: “_WARHORSE, STAINLESS. Your route to RP Alpha takes you near THOR’s projected LZ, and I can’t raise him. Determine his statu_s.”

Warhorse nodded, though of course his commander couldn’t see it. “STAINLESS, WARHORSE.” he replied. “Orders received and understood. Out.”

The second the link was cut, he swore, loudly: "Me cago en Dios!"

Regaari scrambled to his feet as Warhorse lurched upright. “Is that…?”

“I fucking pray his radio’s just out.” Warhorse replied. He scowled at the intel tablet, looked around to get his bearings, then grabbed the ruck. He’d diligently re-packed it after they were done eating, and Regaari winced at the sheer weight of it as the human shrugged it on before stooping and offering him two linked hands for a step. “climb on.”

Regaari didn’t argue. Wherever 'RP Alpha' was, it was nowhere nearby and he would just need to rely on Warhorse’s strength and endurance if he was ever to get out from under a thundercloud of Hunters. Warhorse handed him the binoculars and intel tablet as soon as he was settled.

“Keep me on course.” he said.

HMS Violent, Capitol System

Commodore William Caruthers

“You’re certain they’re after you, STAINLESS?”

There was a delay in the response. With the strike team having made an exoatmospheric exit from the station and abandoned the rescue operation, the fleet and spaceplanes had scattered to extreme distance and gone dark. In practical terms, with each one being most likely alone inside a radius of several light seconds, they were impossible to find. Violent was nearly six light seconds from the planet now, and that meant plenty of time to wait for the photons of their conversation to wing their way back and forth.

"Completely, sir." Powell’s voice was low-resolution and distorted by distance and the audio compression, but perfectly intelligible. "The weapons they fired at me looked like a ripoff of that Irbzy-whatever stun gun, but they were aiming the lethal stuff at the lads. They’ve got me pegged for a commander, and they want to know what I know."

“We’re prioritizing your extraction.” Caruthers decided. “The Yanks are at DEFCON two right now, with the armour the Hunters seem to be using right now it’s the only sure way to secure orbital supremacy long enough to extract you. STAINLESS, your men are secondary to the objective of preventing your knowledge from falling into enemy hands. We cannot afford to give them any more inspiration."

He counted out twelve seconds under his breath.

"Understood completely, Commodore. I also recommend that we ready an RFG strike to my suit beacon should my vitals show I’ve been incapacitated."

Caruthers turned to Violent’s captain and raised a finger with a nod, indicating that it should be made so.

“We’ll go at fourteen hundred hours as per your recommendation.” he said. “Good hunting.”

Planet Garden, Capitol System, Dominion Space

Regaari

“There. I see…” Regaari worked the focusing control as best he could one- pawed. “It’s hard to tell. A dark patch that shouldn’t be there, that way.”

Warhorse glanced up, and corrected his course, puffing like some ancient steam contraption from Gao’s early industrial era.

Regaari lost sight of the anomaly as the terrain dipped, and when Warhorse pistoned up the rise on the far side of that dip, Regaari nearly fell off him because the human stopped dead.

“Oh, no…”

Humans were so expressive in their grief. He’d seen it with Shoo, and now Warhorse was projecting his sorrow even through a bulky suit of fully enclosed armour. He sagged for a moment and then pushed forward, until they reached the edge of what was, unmistakably, a fresh crater.

The suit at the bottom of it was effectively intact, though it had been badly ablated by re-entry: blackened, melted and burned away. From the contortion of the limbs and the crushed flatness of the torso, its operator had not survived. Warhorse sat down with a thump.

Regaari climbed off him, sketched a gesture of respect with his remaining paw, and let Warhorse grieve. The same shields that had allowed Warhorse and him to reach the ground safely had plainly failed in Thor’s case, or else never deployed at all. In either scenario, the suit had demonstrated that it was a hideously tough piece of equipment, having reached the ground and still recognisably being the same object. To fall from space and leave an impact crater and STILL be identifiable? Not a pleasant way to die, but as a technical accomplishment it was daunting.

He hadn’t really considered what Deathworlder engineering might accomplish, before. Shoo’s intelligence and insightfulness had been obvious, as had her culinary artistry, but her sheer physicality and intensity had frequently overwhelmed those qualities, with the result that Regaari had simply never turned his thoughts to humans as engineers, builders and inventors.

He was still ruminating on the fallen suit when Warhorse moved, slowly raising his hand to the communicator on his shoulder.

“STAINLESS,” he said, voice thick with emotion. “WARHORSE. THOR is KIA. EAR field failure.”

“…WARHORSE, STAINLESS. Copy that. Did the field jump array he was carrying survive?"

“Uh…that’s a Negative, STAINLESS.”

"WARHORSE, STAINLESS…Grab a memento, mate. Destroy the suit and continue to RP Alpha. Out."

Warhorse stood up again, then stepped down into his fallen comrade’s crater and ripped something from the front of the ruined suit, a patch of some kind. He did something Regaari couldn’t quite see and then stepped back as, again, the suit began to smoke and then burst into seething, angry flames. There wasn’t much left to burn--the destruction was already pretty well total.

Warhorse sagged, and spoke to the charred thing in the crater. “…Vaya con Dios, brother."

He knelt and gestured Regaari up onto his back again, checked the intel tablet, turned north, and marched.

Warhorse was clearly in no mood for talking for most of the remaining distance to RP Alpha, wherever it was, and Regaari let him work in silence. Instead, he pulled out his pulse pistol and, with some difficulty thanks to his missing paw and the human’s steady gait, made a few tricky adjustments that he’d first learned when he was barely out of cubhood.

He was becoming seriously impressed with the medical technology the humans had brought with them. His missing paw should have been a source of debilitating agony. Instead, it was a ghost, a phantom presence on his wrist that felt, when he wasn’t paying attention, like the real thing. If nothing else, the anaesthetic in the dressing was highly effective.

It was probably designed for Deathworlders, he decided. That meant he was trusting the human not to have badly miscalculated and given him an overdose, but he was beginning to seriously trust Warhorse.

His thoughts were broken by the communicator.

"WARHORSE, LONGLEGS. I have eyes on you, pal, and you’re being stalked."

Regaari’s fur started crawling instantly and he put a hand to his holster. “Stalked?” he asked.

“Don’t look around.” Warhorse told him. "LONGLEGS, WARHORSE. Hunter?"

"Reckon so. One of the big fuckers that got STERLING. See that stream to your left? Take a water break, lure it out in the open when it catches up with you."

Warhorse looked left, and Regaari did the same. The surface of the stream in question was an invitation all by itself, and he realised he was growing really quite thirsty.

“Will do.” he said. “WARHORSE out.”

They paused. Regaari couldn’t sense anything amiss, but apparently Warhorse could, because he stood still, listening for a few seconds, then grunted and stooped by the water unclasping his mask.

Regaari watched. Where he would have had to lie on his belly to lap at the water--undignified and uncivilised to a modern Gaoian--Warhorse just carefully put his gun slightly aside, ready to have it up and firing at an instant’s notice, and dipped both hands into the stream to form a shallow bowl, which he raised to his mouth.

“Not filtering it this time?” Regaari asked.

“Appearances.” Warhorse muttered, not actually drinking the water. He tilted his head slightly. “Hear them?”

“Hear wha-?”

Regaari was interrupted by a pulse round, which glanced off Warhorse’s upper arm. From the size and sound of it, it had been a heavy pulse, the kind with enough juice to fling humans about and break limbs. Sure enough, even the winging blow spun the bulky Deathworlder around his axis and dropped him sprawling in the local grass-equivalent.

Regaari’s dive for cover saved his life. The bolt aimed at him would have reduced him to a nasty pink paste.

Warhorse was up, though. Aside from knocking him around a bit, the pulse weapon hadn’t apparently done anything at all to him except make him angry. He returned fire, gun producing a heavy slamming sound that Regaari could feel with each shot as a hammer-blow in his chest. One of the Hunters was torn to bits, dismembered by the firepower that ripped through it.

The other, as 'Longlegs' had predicted, was one of the big, grotesque, wet- red naked musculature ones, and it was layered in heavy shield emitters that spat and flashed as Warhorse’s bullets hit home but failed to penetrate.

It lunged forward and Warhorse took a smart step away as deadly fusion-edged talons raked out, neatly shearing off the end of the gun.

The Hunter was fast, nearly as much so as a human. Two pairs of those fusion claws swiped and slashed, and Warhorse survived only by throwing himself backwards and then scuttling away on all fours, staggering to his feet to gain distance. The Hunter followed, and that would have been the end of Warhorse and Regaari both, had a lightning bolt of berserk and mountainous Deathworlder not erupted from among the shrubs without any warning.

The Hunter had just enough time to register the existence of this new threat before it hit home, and after that there was no more Hunter.

“Coulda sworn you did better’n that in training, pal.” the cavalry declared, once the Hunter was in several pieces. Both men extended their gloved hands and bashed them together.

“These ones are gonna be trouble.” Warhorse replied. “I- LOOK OUT!"

The third Hunter--another big one--had a cloaking device and a plasma gun, and that would have been the end of Longlegs and Warhorse both had Regaari not shot it.

The humans, in fairness, took the way that the beast disintegrated in a horrible slap of wet matter in their stride, and did a thorough check of their surroundings for threats before turning their attention to Regaari, who was licking the burn on his remaining paw and kicking out the grass fire that was threatening to burst up around the glowing puddle that had once been his pulse pistol.

“Fuckin’ ’ell.” Longlegs declared, while Warhorse scooped up some water and dumped it on the ruined gun, producing a fog bank and an angry hiss. “The fuck was that?”

Regaari licked his burnt paw again. “If you know how to rewire a pulse gun the right way…” he said, then gestured to the nasty mess of former Hunter that was swirling away downstream. “You only get one shot, but better one shot that counts than a thousand that don’t.”

The humans exchanged glances. “I like this one." Warhorse said.

“I can see why.” Longlegs agreed. “We’d better get moving. They’ll know where their mates were. Our best bet is to get to the RP.”

“Right. Let me just fix his paw. He needs at least one working.” Warhorse agreed, then turned to Regaari. He grabbed something on his harness and the bag fell off, clearly designed for quick release. “Legsy, If you need ammo, check the pockets on the left side.” he added.

Warhorse’s thick, armored fingers were strong enough to accidentally crush Regaari’s bones to powder, but his trust in the human medic was well-placed. Warhorse’s grip was merely firm, and he applied the dressing with paradoxical precision and delicacy while Longlegs reported the contact to Stainless and grabbed some of the offered ammunition.

The process took only a few seconds before Warhorse stood and hoisted his bag back on. “Okay, hop up. That’ll do you for now. Let’s go.”

Regaari didn’t argue. Right now, the safest possible place in the universe seemed to be Warhorse’s shoulders.

RP Alpha turned out to be a cluster of buildings atop a gentle swell in the ground. the planet Garden was a park world, Class 2, with only the bare minimum of tectonic activity that was necessary for life to arise in the first place. It had no impressive rocky up thrusts or great slabs of broken crust resting at angles atop the layers below, only gentle swells and rolls and grassy hills.

“Ruins?” Warhorse asked.

“This planet used to be the embassy world for all species.” Regaari explained. “Then the station was built, and because it’s more convenient to dock with a station than land on a planet…”

“Right…” The humans paused to sip from their water supplies. The water was strangely coloured, like the instant juice had been. There must have been something in it to replenish them, Regaari supposed.

“Whose was this then?” Legsy asked.

“I don’t know.” Regaari told him. “My people are nearly as new to the galactic stage as yours, after all.”

“Right.” Warhorse repeated.

“STAINLESS, LONGLEGS. I have eyes on RP Alpha, one ET and WARHORSE with me.”

"LONGLEGS, STAINLESS. Better get down here quick, we’ve spotted ground forces approaching from the north."

Legs raised his binoculars to the north, and nodded, before turning to Warhorse. “Double time.”

“Hold on, scrappy.” Warhorse said, and set off at an actual run.

Regaari turned his own borrowed binos to the north, and felt his hackles rise. “They’ve got tanks?” he asked. “I’ve never even heard of Hunter tanks before."

“Tanks we can handle.” Legsy assured him. “Or rather, the angels can.”

“Mythical beings?”

“Nah mate. Fuckin’ spaceships.” Legsy raised his own binoculars and examined the approaching Hunter column as they jogged.

Regaari imitated him. “Why aren’t the Hunters landing directly on top of us?”

“Look up.”

Regaari did so. Nothing much happened for some seconds.

“What am I looking-”

He winced and shielded his eyes as there was a tremendous flash in the sky. It faded almost instantly, but left a purplish-green blob of afterimage behind. “…for?”

“Our angels have got orbital superiority.” Legsy’s translated voice had a note of satisfaction in it.

“Was that…?”

“Tactical nuclear…fusion warhead.” Warhorse spoke. He was labouring worse than Legsy, but then again he was carrying at least twice as much weight, and it certainly didn’t seem to be slowing him down. If not for his heavier breathing and the sheen of moisture beading on his face, Regaari might have guessed he was almost finding the run easy. “RIGHTEOUS’ll be…having fun, eh Legs?”

“Too fuckin’ right he will. Nobody ever gets to play with the big toys.”

“Fusion weaponry is not a toy!” Regaari protested.

“It is when it knocks those big swarmships out.” Legsy pointed gain. It was hard to see in daylight, but there were definitely distant bright trails describing stately lines in the sky. Wreckage, falling from orbit.

They burst from the brush and shrub and picked up the pace across the open ground around the buildings, pounding up the shallow incline onto a paved road surface.

"LEGS and WARHORSE, STAINLESS. I see you. Third building on your left."

Both men angled for it.

“Last in?” Legsy asked as they came to a halt in a heptagonal ground floor lobby. Eight other men were at work inside, taking the stairs four at a time in the low gravity as they shuttled ammunition and equipment higher up into the building.

“Nothing like a fuckin’ Corti on your back to make you want to get where you’re going ASAP.” One of the soldiers said. He and Warhorse exchanged one of those fist-slam greetings. “Yours seems cool.”

“He’s cool as shit! Scrappy, this here’s Baseball.”

“Scrappy? My name’s-”

“Nuh-ah, man. We’re on mission.” Baseball interrupted. “We’re using your war name.”

“…Scrappy seems like the kind of name you’d give a pet." Regaari protested.

“How ’bout 'Dexter’?" Warhorse suggested. “With the arm, and he’s a killer, bro.”

The reference--and Regaari knew enough about humans to know that it almost certainly was a reference or in-joke of some kind--went right over his head, but he decided that 'Dexter' sounded much more dignified than 'Scrappy’. “It’ll do.” he agreed. As he’d suspected, the humans all grinned behind their masks, indicated by a creasing of their eyes.

“Dexter it fookin’ is.”

This human could only be Stainless. He gave Regaari an interested look. “You think he’s worth summat, Warhorse?”

“He’s a soldier sir.” Warhorse declared.

“Right. If you’re up for it, mate, I need somebody up in a window keeping an eye on the Hunters. We’ve got a range marker a click out, a little bridge. Let RIGHTEOUS know when they start crossing it, okay?”

Regaari gave him a human nod. “Can do.” he declared.

Stainless handed him a communicator. “Press this bit to talk. It’s made for us so you’re gonna have to push pretty hard…”

Regaari squeezed it. As predicted it needed some pressure, but he could do it. “STAINLESS, DEXTER. Communications test.”

“Loud and clear, and translated too. Our evac’s incoming but we need air and orbit superiority first, that’s what the holdup is. When I call that it’s coming, head for the roof. Got that?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Good man. WARHORSE, Titan’s rigging explosives along the north road, resupply him. Legsy, nick BASEBALL’s SAW and get yourself set up in a ground floor window. Understood?”

Regaari snapped a “Yes sir!” that was identical to the two humans’. This seemed to meet everyone’s approval.

“Good. Go.”

Firebird

"Shuttle’s away, escort form up."

Rylee swung Firebird onto the little ship’s wing and, not for the first time, cursed that no Earth corporation had yet produced a satisfactory craft analogous to the role filled by the cheap, boxy models sold in their millions across the Dominion. It was a flying brick, spaceworthy and airworthy only by dint of excessive reliance on its forcefields. No jump drive, no emissions dampening, no nothing. If she’d had her way, they wouldn’t be using them.

She was going to have to use all the clout she could muster to get that shortage fixed.

They’d at least been able to slave the useless little thing’s navigation computer to the network that allowed them to warp and jump in the vicinity of their own gravity spikes by shutting the traps down just long enough. Without that, the ground-pounders would have been fucked.

They aligned, blink-warped, and the planet Capitol went, in an infinitesimal moment that contained nothing more than the suggestion of incomprehensible speed, from being a nigh-invisible turquoise dot in the infinite night, to a great curve of blue and white that filled half the world, garlanded by smashed swarmships.

The bastards were fighting back hard, and they’d learned a few tricks, but she indulged in a grim smile inside her helmet at knowing that they had lost only two TS/2s in the battle, while Hunter casualties must surely be numbering in the thousands.

“RIGHTEOUS, FIREBIRD.” She called. “We’re in your box.”

"FIREBIRD, RIGHTEOUS. Got an incoming heavy column down here, line up for an RFG drop on my call."

Semenza made an eager “Oooh!” noise. “I’ve always wanted to do one of those.”

Rylee lined up, while her wingmen swept out to clear the box of any lingering hostiles. “So have I.” she agreed.

<Delight> +Fusion weapons deployed via wormhole, too close to evade! ExoAtmospheric deployment of individual ground units! And the communications cyphers! I salivate to sink my teeth into those!+ The Alpha Builder was broadcasting joyous paroxysms like a messy eater spraying prey-blood all over its fellows.

The Alpha-of-Alphas radiated a good mood. It leaned forward slightly in its throne <Amused rebuke> +Continue to pay attention, and you will be fed further morsels I am sure. These deathworlders are not stupid, they will have many secrets in reserve that they have not yet revealed.+ it declared. <Regret> +A shame that Alpha-of-Many-Broods is going to escape capture.+

<Query> +You are certain?+

<Assertion> +It is the most likely outcome. They move with remarkable speed across terrain.+

<Observation> +The Broods are closing in on their refuge…+

The Alpha-of-Alphas gestured resignation. <Dismissive> +But we lack air and orbital control. There will be more deathworlder surprises. I do not doubt that the capture will fail, but we will learn more from it.+

It snarled, baring all of those vicious teeth. <Anticipation> +Every such secret gets us one step closer to devouring them.+

Dexter

Regaari set down the binos and gripped the communicator’s button for all he was worth. “RIGHTEOUS, DEXTER. They’re crossing the bridge.”

"DEXTER, RIGHTEOUS. Copy that, y’all watch this shit and tell me how much it hurts them."

Regaari’s fur rose a bit. The human 'Combat Controller’’s voice had been full of a kind of malicious anticipation which was equal parts infectious and worrying. “RIGHTEOUS, DEXTER…watch what, exactly?"

There was a pause. RIGHTEOUS was presumably busy. A few seconds later, he got back on the line.

"DEXTER, you sir are lucky enough to have a front row seat for the first ever deployment of a Rod From God. Enjoy the show. RIGHTEOUS out."

Firebird

“RFG dropped!” Semenza crowed. Rylee hit the retros and shared his glee at watching a tungsten-tipped steel bar the size of a telegraph pole leave them behind and streak down into the atmosphere.

“Shuttle escort, let’s follow it down.”

Dexter

Regaari first saw it as a star in the western sky.

It hung there, low and proud, drifting only a little to the north for nearly a minute, while a flood of Hunters crossed the little bridge he had been watching. He had been wondering what was so important about that bridge, but suddenly he saw the genius of it. Those tanks could only cross one at a time.

The star was drifting a little faster now.

Then it wasn’t drifting. It was a streak of light, a blaze of pure heat that-

He averted his gaze just in time, but even so the reflected flash off the back wall of the abandoned office he was sitting in was dazzling. When he looked back, he could see the ground settling back into place, and an expanding orb of displaced air and water vapour racing outwards.

It knocked dust from the floor of the office and shattered windows when it swept over them with a gut-punch of pure volume that ripped an involuntary alarm cry out of him. The bridge was presumably gone, as was the road for hundreds of meters on either side of it, though that was mostly speculation on his part--there was so much dirt and smoke hanging where the Hunter column had been that actually seeing the bridge itself was a fantasy. When he surveyed it through the binoculars, all he could see was a beige cloud and a lone hunter, broken and dying in the road.

He watched it expire, then put the binoculars down. His paw was shaking.

“Humans are crazy…” he muttered.

Alpha of the Brood-That-Builds

<Epiphany> +Of course! So simple, yet so effective! No need for dangerous and expensive antimatter, no need to mine and enrich fissionable elements! Just drop a steel pole from orbit! Beautiful!+

The Alpha-of-Alphas stroked a claw down one of the cables that connected it to the swarm. <Observation> +It seems…crude.+

<Insistence> +Crude it may be, but Alpha-of-Alphas, greatest one: This is the weapon with which we shall destroy them. With the resources needed to build a single swarm-ship, I can assemble enough of these to destroy a hundred cities.+

<Satisfaction> +Then this hunt has served its purpose: I tire of it. We will intercept that shuttle and kill them. Begin the dismantling of the prey-station. Meat to the maw!+

Dexter

Something didn’t add up, by Regaari’s reckoning.

Nukes notwithstanding, the Swarm-of-Swarms was immense, and the Hunters were always one step ahead of everybody’s best when it came to cloaking technology. If there was even a ship there for the humans to detect and nuke, it was there because the Hunters either wanted it to be, or else didn’t care enough to hide it.

Which meant that the humans didn’t have quite the orbital superiority they thought they did. Which raised two questions: Why linger and lose ships?

And why not just flatten the embassy compound from orbit?

He exercised a little creative interpretation of his orders and decided to keep watch out in other directions besides north. The Hunters hit by the 'Rod From God' weren’t going anywhere, and Regaari had seen enough intelligence on Hunter raids to know that they were far from stupid.

Quite the reverse. They had a uniquely sadistic cunning.

Which was why he was able to save the team’s lives. He was looking right at the dropships when they decloaked in the south, on final approach.

“Hostile contact, south!” he reported, desperately squeezing the radio until his claws creaked. Down below in the courtyard, he saw the Nova Hounds look up and south, then dive for cover.

The opening salvo of coilgun fire that marched up the street therefore did nothing worse than punch some craters in the road surface and knock loose some masonry. The humans, whether by luck or incredible reflexes, escaped unharmed, though Snapfire’s outer fabric suit ripped down his arm to reveal the armor scales beneath.

“STAINLESS, DEXTER, looks like…twenty Hunter dropships just decloaked two hundred meters to our south. They’re landing to drop passengers, the column to the north still isn’t moving.” He elaborated.

STAINLESS’s voice was tight, focused and precise. "Roger. Nova Hounds, reform the line, face south. WARHORSE, get the ETs upstairs. DEXTER, how many Hunters?"

“As many as three hundred, STAINLESS.” Regaari told him. The dropships took off again, engines making a tooth-grinding buzz as they angled up and over the roof. The Nova Hounds opened up a rippling volley of gunfire, which the Hunters returned with interest. The street became a bilateral hailstorm of withering firepower, pock-marked with craters and fallen concrete where the Hunter coilguns had blasted the architecture loose to create cover for the advance..

"Where are those dropships going?" STAINLESS demanded.

Regaari calculated in his head, and felt his ears plaster themselves to his head. “STAINLESS, DEXTER.” he reported. “They’re intercepting the shuttle.”

Firebird

"Multiple bogies! Where the hell did THEY come from?!"

Rylee snapped right and spat two short bursts at the new contacts. Anything coming in like that was definitely hostile. “Stay frosty! RIGHTEOUS, FIREBIRD, I have hostile aircraft on our approach vector, repeat, bogeys in the box!”

"We see them FIREBIRD, plan’s unchanged. Escort that shuttle."

Rylee threw them into a sideways drift to avoid a coilgun round. “Semenza, light ’em up!”

Semenza was proving his value again, his voice was as level and cool as a frozen lake. “No missiles, boss. We’re in atmo. EWAR only from me.”

“Shit, yeah. Call targets.”

“Called.”

Warhorse

“REBAR, Low on ammo!”

“I gotcha!”

The Hunters were using something that looked like an old Bren gun. Long- barreled, slow to aim and firing a steady rhythm of fat, heavy bullets that would have hit like a train if they found their mark. Thankfully, the monsters didn’t seem to know a damn thing about bracing or supporting the weapon correctly, and weren’t strong enough to handle the kick.

The human return fire, meanwhile, was savagely precise--every time a Hunter popped its head out of cover, it got blown away, and the cannibal fucks were losing half a dozen for every ten feet of ground they advanced, but there were a lot them still upright and advancing and the air was full of lead. Adam gritted his teeth as two alien bullets punched clouds of grey dust out of the concrete next to him and dropped, skidding on the increasingly gravel-strewn asphalt to fetch up next to REBAR, who slammed his last magazine into his M16 just as he arrived.

“Good timing.”

“Sure.” Adam left him four mags and then was up and running, delivering ammo to SNAPFIRE.

There was no time to think. With no gun of his own, there was only time to keep the others fighting.

Firebird

The TS/2s spread out then lanced in, picking Hunter strike craft and filling the sky with ammo, but their GAU-8/S guns weren’t really designed for dogfighting. Two Hunters burst, falling apart in rains of flaming metal, but that left twelve more.

The shuttle pilot was doing his part well at least. Every time the Hunters drew a bead on him, he skipped out of the way, usually creating an opening for the TS/2s, but he was under constant threat.

Four more bogies down, then a fifth. Rylee gritted her teeth against the G-forces as she shunted a jolt of power through the thrusters, sweating away precious capacitor reserves and saving the difference by pulling it out of the inertial compensators, sending them skidding across the sky, rattling as they hit the thermal coming off the RFG’s ground zero.

Two bursts. Two bogies down, five left. Four left as FIREDOG rampaged past her, gun howling. The Swarm’s technological superiority counted for squat when the human pilots had millisecond reaction times and could tolerate acceleration that would have killed their Hunter counterparts.

“Shit! That one!” Semenza’s cool cracked. Rylee saw why instantly--it was on the shuttle’s six, and the shuttle just didn’t have the agility to pull off the evasive manoeuvres that its pilot needed.

Only one way to save the mission. Her vision greyed as Firebird leapt forward on a lightning bolt of extra juice to the engines, drawing a groan from Semenza, then they sat on their instrument panels as she fired.

The Hunter evaporated.

The coilgun round that would have killed the shuttle instead took out Firebird’s left wing.

Stainless

"Fallen angel, fallen angel! FIREBIRD, going down hard!"

Somehow, Jackson kept her sled level on spitting and stuttering yellow emergency forcefields that spread out like the flaming wings of her stricken craft’s namesake. She fell in a glittering halo that lashed out and grabbed on to the buildings, bleeding off the hurtling wreck’s momentum by gouging out torso-sized chunks of concrete and steel from the buildings.

She still skidded half the length of the street once she hit, but the fields had done their job--she landed intact.

Powell cursed, then grabbed his communicator. “FIREBIRD, STAINLESS.” he demanded. “Any survivors?!”

The reply was a few seconds in coming, and came with a grunt of exertion. "STAINLESS, FIREBIRD TWO. Two out of two survivors, but my pilot’s leg is all busted up."

Time was tight, but they still had two able-bodied PJs on the team and the stricken TS/2 was on the right side of the line at least. “DEXTER, status of that Hunter column?”

"STAINLESS, DEXTER. The column’s still stopped at that bridge and reeling from the orbital strike. Minimal threat."

Powell had to admit, the Gaoian was proving to be worth a few multiples of his weight in gold. “WARHORSE, BASEBALL, secure that air crew!”

"On it!" The two young men promptly handed off their cargos of spare ammunition and got up and dashed towards the downed spaceplane.

“SNAPFIRE, REBAR, cover them, TITAN, Legsy, fall back and defend the door!”

All four men grabbed their own packs and hustled, falling back in a disciplined pattern under fire, covering each others’ retreat. That left only the combat controllers, who had formed a rifle team in the ground floor window, HIGHLAND, who was up in the third floor window sniping the Hunters wherever they tried to take cover, DEXTER, and Powell himself.

“CCTs to the roof.” he ordered. He touched the communicator again. “DEXTER, STAINLESS. Get to the roof.”

The Gaoian sounded relieved. "Yes, STAINLESS."

There was shouting from the door and the Protectors returned, with Warhorse carrying Rylee Jackson over his shoulder in a fireman’s lift, trailed by her WSO. Her leg was a mess, flight suit stained crimson around where it had been cut open and field dressed.

“You’ve always got to be the centre of attention, don’t you?” Powell asked her, falling back on humour to cover his genuine relief that she’d not got herself killed.

She managed a weak, bravado-fuelled grin and extended a fist though she was sweating, shaking and tight-faced from pain. “Good to see you again, Stainless. Looks like your boys turned out okay.”

“Don’t fookin’ thank me until we’re home.” he replied, though he bumped her fist in return, then turned to Warhorse “Get her to the roof, mate.”

“Yes sir!”

More explosions sounded outside, punctuated by chattering gunfire. REBAR and SNAPFIRE fell back into view, firing back down the road before ducking for the door. TITAN was caught in open ground and three rounds sparked against his armour, knocking him off his feet. As he tried to stagger upright, a fourth round hit and penetrated and he collapsed, groaning around a hole in his abdomen.

Powell didn’t even need to give an order. Before he even had the chance, BASEBALL leapt into action, putting the pitching arm for which he was aptly named to work and hurling a frag grenade into the heart of the Hunter advance with such force that it lodged in one monsters’ chest, knocking it off its feet and sending the rest scattering for cover before it went off. He pounced on TITAN and dragged him into the safety of the building even as a burst of renewed firepower missed his head by inches before they made the safety of the doorway.

Fortunately, the Hunters weren’t braving the SAW yet, but that wouldn’t last long at all. Much closer and they’d be in Nervejam range.

"STAINLESS, HIGHLAND. More Hunter dropships decloaking, north. They’re mobbing us."

Powell grimaced “CCTs, where’s that shuttle?” he demanded.

"STAINLESS, STARFALL, It’s on final approach, landing twenty seconds. Got a lot of Hunter bogies coming in though, we need to be gone in one mike."

It would have been nice if time had slowed, if he’d had a minute to think through the options carefully. But the decision was foregone. Somebody was going to have to stay down here and hold the Hunters off long enough for the shuttle to take on passengers and dust off.

It was the kind of decision that Powell hated. He hated it especially this time because his options weren’t limited--there WERE no options. Both the CCTs were on the roof, Murray was three floors up, the two PJs had their hands full, and really, this was a job for a close-quarters combat specialist.

But that man was going to die. No maybe, no last-minute rescue. He was ordering a man to his death, and there was only one right option, because the alternative was for everyone to die.

He clamped down hard on his self-hatred and gave the order.

Dexter

The human shuttle pilot had nerves of steel, Regaari had to give him that much. Hovering level with a building’s roof while aircraft thundered overhead was…

He didn’t have time to think about it further. Warhorse emerged from the roof access door carrying another human in a flight suit and yelled at him, gesticulating with his free arm. "Dexter, get in the fuckin’ ride!"

Regaari scrambled in, squeezing as far in as he could while the Corti, Kwmbwrw and the humans piled in behind him. Being built to the scale of Dominion species, they still had plenty of room, but there was one missing, even though the ramp was coming up and they were ascending.

“Where’s-?”

Stainless shot a glare at him that could have eviscerated anybody in the shuttle. Then he leaned against the bulkhead, slid down it, put his head between his knees and his hands on the back of his head, and shook.

Master Sergeant James “Legsy” Jones

He would have liked to go down shooting and hollering.

There was no time for hollering. There was no time for anything. Just shoot. Just fight.

Just buy them time.

He’d taken BASEBALL’s SAW and fired it until the box was empty and the barrel glowing. That alone was enough. He saw the shuttle take off and streak into the sky. Mission accomplished.

Then he fought with his SMG until he ran out of magazines. The last of the TS/2 fighters jumped out with _thump_s of inrushing air, recalled once the shuttle was no longer in danger of being intercepted.

Then he fought with his pistol until there were no more rounds to fire. For honour.

Then he fought with his knife.

Then his fists.

He held out long enough to still be standing when the second Rod From God hit, sent to destroy the wreck of Firebird, and his suit.

The Hunters didn’t get the satisfaction of killing him.

+<Admiration>+

The Alpha-of-Alphas generated a mental note of disapproval aimed at the Alpha Builder, but the lesser being was not paying attention. It had watched a lone Deathwolder fight a hundred of its muscle-grafted experimental “Strongest Brood” warriors, and arguably win.

Everything from the biology, to the weaponry, armour and tactics spoke of wealthy fields of research to come. For a Builder, there was no greater anticipation.

If only that equipment had not been destroyed.

+<Deference> If the Alpha-of-Alphas desires it, this one can begin work on the next generation of innovations immediately.+ it suggested.

+<Blunt disinterest> Do so.+

The Alpha Builder pretended not to notice the emotional context. It simply stood, and departed, already mentally preparing the calculations and experiments.

Left alone in the dark and silence, the Alpha-of-Alphas finally indulged in an unashamed broadcast of its emotional state only once it was sure that there truly were no Hunters within broadcast range..

+<Admiration>+

Regaari

The strangest part was that they recovered, and how.

Caledonia’s flight deck was different to how he remembered it. The shuttle set down with a half-meter’s clearance in a space otherwise filled by crates, equipment, work benches, tool racks and a structure of piping and plastic sheets in the corner. Medics stepped in, carting the two wounded humans away on gurneys. Regaari’s amputation was examined and declared to be as clean and well-dressed as if he’d had it off in an operating theatre. There was nothing to be done for it, at least not that was available on the ship.

He barely paid attention. He was watching the Nova Hounds.

Once out of the shuttle, they had been attended to by technicians, who helped them remove the outer layer of their suits, revealing a variety of shades of browned and white skin, but uniform hair length.

Beneath that was the armour, gunmetal scales that clearly formed the bulk of the suit’s weight, as each man sighed a profound sigh of relief once they were off.

The suits were taken away to be dismantled, serviced and cleaned as a powerful musk hit Regaari’s nostrils. Each one of the Nova Hounds smelled of sweat, salt and exertion, and the dark grey bottom layer was black with moisture in several places. It was also, clearly, better than skin tight, as they had to wriggle out of it.

Warhorse’s had worn through at the left armpit. He just snarled like an angry beast, grabbed it with his right hand, and tore the underlayer right off his body in a ragged strip.

Regaari blinked. He’d known the human was strong, but seeing what that strength looked like was something else entirely. It was almost…ugly. Uncomfortably reminiscent of those red-raw Superhunters, he could almost see the strands and fibers of muscle under the skin, so many muscles. Bulging power in places Gaoians didn’t have places.

They surprised him further by removing their garments altogether and then retreating behind the plastic screen for a shower. Xiu had always been squeamish about removing her clothes, he remembered that. Even when bathing, despite being in the company of beings who biologically and psychologically couldn’t find her attractive, and despite that Gaoians viewed clothing more as being practical and useful rather than necessary, she had seemed to go to great lengths to avoid letting any more of her skin be visible than was inevitable.

The Nova Hounds didn’t seem to care. Though they did return from their ablutions wearing loose, comfortable clothing.

None of them had any kind of an expression. They just found an array of mats and blankets in the corner, and sat down upon them still and silent, staring at nothing.

Before long, every last one of them had fallen asleep.

Not long after them, Regaari found a spot near Warhorse, curled up, and fell asleep himself.

He woke to heat. It was stifling, humid and pungent in the flight bay, and his chest was already heaving and panting cool-ish air across his tongue before he woke up.

Somebody was making simple music by tapping steadily on something, which made a hollow metal thump. Somebody else was syncopating it by tapping on two or three other things--crates, equipment, the shuttle hull. There was an actual instrument involved, the twangy one that Xiu had called a 'guitar’. He didn’t know very much about human music, but he thought he recognised a genre called 'blues’.

He sat up.

“Hey. Wondering when you’d wake up.”

Regaari stretched. Warhorse was sat next to him against the wall. He was putting what looked like pictures back in his pack. “How long…?”

“Eight hours or so.”

Regaari sat up more. “I thought we were leaving Capitol?” he asked. “I was expecting to be in a Gaoian hospital by now. And why is it so hot in here?”

“We’re in low-emissions mode, containing our heat so the Hunters don’t see us.”

“Okay, but why?" Regaari demanded.

“They started dismantling the station. Guess we’re staying here to watch them do it, figure out why. Until then, we’re cargo.” Warhorse shrugged. “Sorry man. Don’t worry, I’ll keep an eye on your arm and we’ve got a field hospital set up in the other bay. You’re in good hands.”

Regaari ducked a nod. “I know. And, I’m grateful. Without you, the Clan of Females would never have known who Giymuy’s choice to replace her as the Mother-Supreme is.”

“Is that, like, appointing an heir, or just a recommendation?”

“A recommendation. But one that’s usually listened to, from what I gather. I was only a few days old when Giymuy was appointed.” Regaari shrugged. He’d learned early on that humans and Gaoians had that gesture in common.

“Gonna have to be a few days, man.” Warhorse told him. “They’re stripping the whole station and…y’know, it’s a big station.”

Regaari chittered, a touch bitterly. “It’ll take them months to appoint a successor anyway, even with her recommendation." he said. “I’m going to miss her though.”

“Yeah?”

“Oh yes. She wasn’t just somebody I worked for. If she’d been younger…” he trailed off. “Though, Ayma might not have approved.”

“This the Ayma that fought so hard to have your human friend adopted into the clan?”

“That’s right. She’s also the mother of my most recent cub, and.…She and I…” he made a little growling noise, the equivalent of a human clearing their throat. “It’s…complicated.”

“Man, I know how that feels.”

“I doubt it.” Regaari countered. “Monogamy is the norm in your culture. In ours, it would be something of a scandal.”

“You two are exclusive?”

“I’d like to be.” Regaari confessed. “I…haven’t told her as much. She and I went through a lot together, but I don’t know how she’d take it.”

Warhorse made a loud, explosive sound that was probably a laugh. “Oh, MAN. I definitely know how that one feels!" he exclaimed, then calmed. “At least, the going through a lot together thing.”

“What do you think I should do?”

“Brother, I am the WRONG man for female advice.”

They sat in silence for a while, until Regaari noticed that Warhorse--and some others of the Nova Hounds--were giving him strange looks.

“What?”

“You’re panting.”

“Well…yes.” Regaari said. “That’s how we deal with heat. We pant, you sweat.” he gestured to the fact that everybody on deck was stripped down to the bare minimum they could get away with, and even that was dark wet and sticking to the skin.

“That’s amazing."

“Why?”

“Just…ah, man, it just triggers some weird instincts I guess. Forget it. Maybe we should fill one of these crates with water for you… ”

“Great Father Fyu, no.” Regaari protested. “Wet fur smells worse than you do.”

This caused Warhorse’s expression to get even stranger. It was almost like a smile, but wide-eyed rather than narrow-eyed. Regaari had no idea what it meant.

"What?" he demanded.

“Nothing.”

“Fine, keep your secrets.”

He endured the occasional smiling glance for a while longer, listening to the music while Warhorse sighed and retrieved a few things--hard copy prints of some kind--from his bag and began to flip through them.

“What are those?”

“Uh…Ah fuck it, you’re not human. This is Ava.”

Regaari scrutinized the pictures. 'Ava' had plainly set up and taken the images herself, and they were obviously a mating display. It was the only way to explain the curious poses and the odd choice of clothing, both calculated to show off her body to best effect while still hiding away those parts of her anatomy that he knew humans were peculiarly squeamish about. The prints had a slightly worn, often-handled look around the edges.

He had to admit, even across the species barrier, he could see the appeal. When you came down to the mechanics of it, there were only so many ways to be bipedal, and only so many ways to birth live young through a plantigrade biped’s pelvis. The four mammary glands on a Gaoian female were at the waist and small, as opposed to a human’s high and large pair, and the bald skin was totally unattractive, but the curve of flank and hip was almost identical, aside from being more pronounced in humans due to the larger muscles, shorter torso and longer legs.

“Not that I’m an expert.” he declared “but if I had the mouth for it, I think a wolf-whistle would be in order.”

Warhorse laughed at that, then sighed as he looked at the pictures again. “I hope she gives me a second shot.” he said, wistfully.

“A second shot? She turned you down?”

“We…went through a lot together. Then we went through a lot without each other, and I was dumb enough to think that she’d just…”

Whatever word he was searching for went un-found. There was a general looking- up and then standing-up as Stainless stepped onto the flight deck, rather more professionally turned-out than his men in a full body uniform of some kind, rather than the sleeveless, short-legged things the rest of the Nova Hounds were wearing. He was even managing the impressive feat of managing to look comfortable in the heat.

“Fall in.” he ordered, quietly. Everyone gathered around him in a rough half- circle, the Nova Hounds themselves at the front, and all of their technicians, attendants and support staff forming a second row behind them.

“First things first. Titan’s going to be fine. Was a nasty injury, but he’s had surgery and a Crue-D shot, so he should be up and about in a day or two. Major Jackson suffered a fractured fibula and some nasty lacerations, but her early prognosis suggests a full recovery and return to duty in due course.”

There was murmured relief, which fell silent again as Stainless raised a hand.

“We, uh-” he began, then cleared his throat. “We’ve had the unhappy privilege of watching three legendary men burn brightly today.”

Heads lowered. Regaari watched Baseball put his arm around Warhorse’s enormous shoulders and pull him close.

“All of our lights will go out in time.” Stainless continued. That mobile, malleable, expressive human face was alive with muscles wrestling under the surface, fighting to maintain dignity. “All of our journeys reach their end. What counts at the end of it all is how that journey was spent, and I for one will consider myself blessed that, for a while, I was able to journey alongside these epic three, and call them my comrades, my friends…and my brothers.”

He swallowed, lowered his head for a second, then raised it again and Regaari admired the strength that he managed to force into his voice.

“Let these mementoes enter the history of this new regiment, and mark the start of a tradition. We will never leave a man behind. Whether he comes back with his shield, upon it, or in keepsake only, he comes back. We all make it home, one way or another."

As nods of agreement created a gentle susurrus around the bay, he produced three small, battered items from his pocket.

“Staff sergeant Brady Stevenson. Thor.” He laid the little patch of cloth that Warhorse had salvaged from the crushed armor on the table.

“Sergeant First Class Leo Price. Sterling.” A metal tag on a chain.

“Master Sergeant James Jones.” Another swatch of cloth. “…Legsy.”

By now, all the seven men standing directly in front of him had their arms interlinked across one another’s shoulders or around each others’ waists. Around the bay, deathworlders were standing at attention, some fighting back their emotions, others displaying them openly.

Stainless took a deep breath. “It’s still early days for the SOR. We’ve been blooded today, and despite our losses, we acquitted ourselves superbly under the most difficult circumstances, in keeping with the finest traditions of our parent units.” He declared. “I expect that we will go on to great things in due course, which is why I’m going to conclude with what I hope will be the regimental motto, so listen closely. Remember this.” heads raised and gave him their full attention.

“…’What a piece of work is man. How noble in reason, how infinite in faculties. In form and moving how express and admirable. In action, how like an angel: In apprehension, how like a god!’"

He set his jaw and saluted fiercely. Every one of the humans present copied him. “When gods fall, we will remember them.”

Twenty humans spoke as one. "We will remember them."

Two torturous days passed, punctuated by a steady rhythm. First, a siren would sound, marking the moment when their orbit carried them below the horizon from the Swarm’s perspective, and the ship would wake up, flinging out its forcefields and radiating all of its accumulated heat towards the sun in a concentrated beam with breathtaking efficiency.

Regaari could actually FEEL the temperature drop, until he was comfortable again and the humans were sighing with relief even as their breath condensed on newly chilled air. Chores would be done, the water would be recycled and people would take comfort showers and use the latrines, making best use of every moment that the ship could operate normally before its orbit carried it back into line of sight with the Hunters and they were forced to endure another three hours of mounting heat and humidity as best they could.

In hindsight, not taking Warhorse up on that bath idea had been wise. He would have been shivering and at risk of hypothermia at the cold end of the cycle.

They spent the time watching movies, huddled around a tiny tablet computer in a way that must surely have made the heat worse, but at least it was entertainment. He wound up sitting on Warhorse’s shoulders again so as to have a good view.

Regaari had watched a number of movies with Xiu, and had mostly enjoyed them, though he had wondered what in Gao’s name she got out of ‘horror’ movies. She’d mostly watched them from behind her hands, squirming and occasionally shrieking while the poor traumatized Gaoians had been even worse affected. Humans could be dark in their storytelling it seemed.

He’d not watched a movie like this one, though. It almost had a Gaoian in it: too short, oddly proportioned, with digitigrade feet and strange facial proportions and markings that suggested a chromosomal disorder, and clearly built on Deathworlder anatomy, making him stockier and far stronger than any real Gaoian, but still…

"Why would you wanna save the galaxy?"

"Because I’m one of the idiots who LIVES in it!"

It was ridiculous, but also a huge amount of fun, and certainly distracted from the relentless heat.

He was required to check with the hospital set up in the bay on the opposite side of the ship every few hours, and was surprised when they removed his dressings--the stump underneath had healed perfectly, unbelievably fast, though who had snuck him a dose of Cruezzir, when and how were a mystery. When he got back to Gao, he’d be ready to receive a prosthetic the moment he landed.

Finally, orders were given, objects cleared away, loose equipment battened down and everyone settled down ready for the jump, which passed with a barely- perceptible jolt in his stomach.

At once, the cooling cycle started, and this time, the temperature stayed down.

The long wait was over.

Major Owen Powell

HMS Sharman had a few design quirks that had been intended to keep it inside the footprint occupied by the original camp, and one of these was its narrow hallways and corridors. The narrowest of which, Powell was certain, was the one outside his office.

Throw in that SOR men were universally large, and that made getting past one another a challenge sometimes, which was why he paused at the intersection on seeing Ares coming towards him. The younger man picked up the pace to squeeze past him at the corner.

“Shouldn’t you be seeing Ava, Sergeant?” Powell asked. “She’ll be worried about you.”

“We were just…organising the wake, sir.” Adam explained.

Powell nodded. “Good. And I’ll be bloody well upset if you lot don’t drink every drop of alcohol on this planet, you hear me?”

“Yes, sir.”

Powell exhaled through his nose, aware that he was going to miss having an NCO with whom he could get away with sharing a joke.

But then again, that hadn’t been the nature of his relationship with Legsy to begin with, either.

“Goodnight, sir.” Adam said, and turned to go.

“Ares…”

The young man turned to face him again. “Sir?”

“…Legsy and I were in the habit of sharing a post-mission drink. You’d be…very welcome to join me in keeping that tradition alive.”

Adam blinked at him, then nodded, swallowing. “I’d like that.” he managed.

“Come on.”

Powell unlocked his office and led the way in, visiting the top of his filing cabinet and retrieving a bottle of Glenfiddich and two cut crystal glasses.

“One for us, and one each for anybody who didn’t come back.” he explained, pouring just enough for there definitely to be whisky in each glass, but not enough that four of them would actually get either of them intoxicated.

They chimed glasses, and knocked them back. He was slightly impressed that Adam had no worse reaction to it than clearing his throat and a slightly pinched expression for a second, considering it was probably his first taste of whisky.

Powell poured the second pair of drinks. “I’m recommending Price for the Victoria Cross and Legsy for the George Cross.” he said. “And as far as I’m concerned, Jackson and Semenza deserve the Medal of Honor, they saved the bloody lot of us…but they’ll probably settle for less. There’ll be a few other decorations getting handed out too… .” He paused, and shrugged. “We’ll see how it goes. Not sure I care about medals right now.”

They drank again. Adam had the look of a man who wanted to ask questions but was restraining himself.

“You’ve got permission to speak freely right now, lad.” Powell told him. “Make use of it, I don’t grant it often.”

“Just…a question sir.”

“Go on then.”

“…How are you holding up?”

“Christ, remind me not to let you ask freely too often, you get right down to business, don’t you?”

“Sorry, sir, I-”

“No, no. Fair question…” He appreciated it, in fact. He rubbed the bridge of his nose and drank his third glass while he thought. Adam copied him. “I’m not…I try not to be a weak man, but ordering a friend to his death…" Powell put his glass down and reached for the bottle one last time. “It beats you up.”

“I’d be…kinda worried if it didn’t, sir.”

Powell poured again and nodded. “True. And it’d be a lonely fookin’ job if I didn’t get on with my men, you know? It just…it needs to be understood that the mission comes first. When it’s one man versus every man…I can’t, I won’t be fookin’ sentimental about it. I have to send the right man for the job…whoever that might be."

“I didn’t get that when I signed up.” Adam confessed.

“Well, what about now you know what it’s like?”

“Sir…speaking candidly?”

Powell handed him his glass. “I thought we bloody were.”

“Well then…if I was the right man for the job…I guess I wouldn’t just expect you to send me, I’d want you to."

Powell nodded, staring at his glass for a moment. “Aye. And I reckon Legsy would have said the same.”

They toasted and drank for the fourth and final time.

“Go on, Sergeant. You’ve better things to be doing and prettier people to be doing them with than commiserating with your commanding officer.” He said as he set his glass down. “I’m…coping.”

“Yes sir. Good night.”

“Good night, sergeant.”

“You’re approaching a commune of females and cubs, male. Who comes?”

Regaari knew not to underestimate the females who took guard duty outside the communes at night. Ceremonial though their role was, they took it seriously, and would be expert shots with those pulse rifles. Not that they ever DID shoot anybody, but it paid to respect that fact.

He halted in the light.

“Officer Regaari, of Clan Whitecrest.” he announced. “Formerly of the executive staff of Mother-Supreme Giymuy.”

“Regaari?” one of the guards stepped forward to get a better look at him. "Wā sāi! it IS you! We thought you were dead!"

He waved his left arm to show off his new cybernetic paw. “I very nearly was.” he said.

“You know him, Sister Myun?” The other guard asked.

“He is who he says he is.” Myun assured her. “I’ll escort him.”

“Who are you here to see, male?” the second guard interrogated him, clearly not satisfied with Myun’s reassurance. To judge from Myun’s resigned and impatient body language, this was nothing unusual.

Maybe he should court the young female after all…If nothing else, Myun would benefit from knowing she had allies.

“I’m here to inform the late Mother-Supreme’s chosen successor of her nomination.” He announced, picking the one of the three truthful answers he could have given on the grounds that it was probably the least controversial.

“Hrrmm. You may enter.” The guard finally stopped glaring at him, though she didn’t unwind exactly.

Myun just flicked her ears irritably and walked alongside him through the commune’s doors.

“Did she choose Ayma?” she asked.

“Yulna.” Regaari revealed.

Ayma’s voice made them both freeze on the spot. “That makes sense.”

She had been cuddling and rocking a tiny newborn in the moonlight, almost invisibly still, and chittered a little at the way both Myun and Regaari flinched. “Yulna’s a good choice. She won’t be afraid to speak her mind.”

“I will…leave you two alone, shall I?” Myun stepped away a little, out of earshot.

Ayma made an amused face. “That poor little Sister has watched too many human romance movies.” she declared.

“What do you mean?”

“Oh, she’s convinced you and I are 'an item’, or something." Ayma growled a little, wryly. “You’ve seen those human movies, you how know they react. They get jealous over mating partners. That’s not us, is it?”

“Well…” Regaari’ paused, then nodded, burying his disappointment. “…No. You’re right. It’s not.”

She stood and gave him a friendly nose-rub, as of old and close friends. “I like you too much, Regaari. I’d hate to fall out with you over mating contracts.”

That, at least, was a dose of welcome, soothing cold water to balm his burned self-esteem. “You do?”

“Oh yes.” Ayma glanced up and down the commune concourse and then leaned in conspiratorially. “If I had to choose just one…wait, what happened to your paw?!"

She’d tried to take it intimately, and had found herself holding smooth carbon fiber instead of fur.

He grimaced at it. “It’s…a long story. I’ll tell you what happened over breakfast, if you’ll do me a favour.”

“Name it.”

“It’s about Sister Myun… ”

Starship ‘Negotiable Curiosity’, Deep Space

“I think we’ve found one of them.”

"One of them? I thought we were looking for a single escape pod?"

There was a sigh from the ship’s owner and commander. "Yes, Hzzkvk, we’re looking for a single escape pod, but the ship launched two."

Hzzkvk blinked at his Corti employer. “But…Bedu, if the ship launched two, why are we only after one?”

Bedu repeated his weary sigh. “Because the client is paying us five million Directorate Currency Units for the escape pod with one of your 'cousins' on it, and NOT for the other one."

“But why-?”

Mwrmwrwk interrupted him, saving Bedu’s headache from progressing any further. “Client says, client pays, we do. No more questions.” she snapped. Bedu nodded subtly at his Kwmbwrw pilot, thanking her.

“But-”

“Hzzkvk!” Bedu snapped, then mellowed his tone. “I tell you this as a colleague of three years: the subject of your species’ remarkable intelligence is the focus of frequent discussion among the Corti, and may I say that you yourself are a type specimen for the exact qualities that we find so fascinating. Nevertheless there is a time for not asking questions, and this is one such, hmm?"

Hzzkvk was practically glowing with pride. “Why…thank you Bedu!” he said.

“Indeed. Please be so kind as to man the scoop field should we need to bring them aboard?”

“Of course!”

Once the gangly blue shape of their junior crewman had left the bridge, Mwrmwrwk shot her employer a questioning glance.

“What?” Bedu asked her.

“I’ve never known you tell a direct lie before.” she said, quietly.

“Nor did I this time.” Bedu replied amiably.

“So…Vzk’tk intelligence really IS a subject of frequent discussion among the Corti?”

Bedu granted himself the luxury of satisfaction at his own cleverness. The Kwmbwrw was by no means an idiot herself, and that meant that if he’d snuck his veiled insult past her, then Hzzkvk would never notice it.

“Indeed.” he told her. “We often find ourselves wondering how a species so terminally dim ever managed to invent the wheel."

Mwrmwrk took a second to process that, then made a kind of fluttering, purring noise in her chest--her species’ equivalent of laughter. “I see…And, we’re coming up on the liferaft.”

“Does the transponder code match?” Bedu demanded, examining the little puck- shaped craft on his screen.

“Please.” She clucked, annoyed. “That was the first thing I checked.”

“Very good. Run the disruption and scan their contents.”

“Won’t they notice?”

“If they are who we want, it will not matter, and if they are not…well, they will never find out what happened. Please, run the scan.”

Mwrmwrk raised a hand to acknowledge the order, then followed it. A second later, data poured onto Bedu’s command screen.

“Three deathworlders, alas.” he noted. “All quite badly injured, too. Fine, stop the scan. We had better pick up that other ALV wake."

“Are you sure they won’t have noticed?" Mwrmwrk asked, already changing course. Behind them, the escape pod blinked away as the slight change in their vector translated to a separation of light seconds in a heartbeat.

“At most, they may have felt a sensation of time…having done something strange." Bedu conceded. “I doubt they will pay it a second thought.”

Demeter Road, Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Adam Ares

The little wooden 'Eden' sign that Sara had once given them rattled when Ava opened the door. She paused on seeing him and then threw herself straight into a hug with such force that, despite the disparity between her mass and his strength, Adam had to take a step back to absorb her.

“Oh my god, Adam!” she couldn’t even fit her arms all the way around him. She’d been right: things had changed. “Are you okay? People are saying Legsy didn’t come back…?!”

“Yeah.” Adam nodded “He, uh…”

Ava made a sad, almost childish little sound of loss. “Are you…alright?”

“I wouldn’t have come back if not for him.” Adam told her. “Or Leo, either. They…None of us would.”

She retreated into the apartment and sat down on the couch. “Goddammit.”

Adam shut the door as he entered and sat next to her. “Yeah…”

There was a melancholy silence for a little while, which Adam finally broke. “Legsy…gave me some advice, before we headed out. This may not be the best time to follow up on it, but…”

“…What?”

“He…helped me figure out what you are to me.”

Ava blinked at him, then turned to face him, giving him her attention.

Adam took her hand. “You’re…this amazing, gorgeous, talented woman that I’d like to get to know better.” he said.

Ava paused, but then a smile broke through on her face like the dawn rising. “Yeah?”

Adam nodded.

Ava looked at him for a long, contemplative moment and then sighed, and he could see the tension and misery flow out of her as she wiped away a tear.

“…It’s a date.” she said.

++End Chapter 22++

While Deathworlders chapters will always be published completely for free, with the aid of my backers on Patreon I’ve now been able to take more time for writing! Pledging a single dollar per chapter gets you access to my behind-the-scenes blog where, among other things, I keep a running tally of each chapter’s word count as it’s written.

Other benefits may become apparent in due course…

Chapter 34
Chapter 25: “Where We Stand” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Etsicitty house, North Clearwater County, Minnesota, USA, Earth

Julian Etsicitty

“Um… Allison fell asleep.”

Julian glanced down and to his right. Allison had indeed fallen asleep, curled up next to him on the bed with her head down on one arm.

He brushed some blonde hairs out of her face. “So she did. It is midnight…"

“…Oh.”

Xiu glanced at the wall clock guiltily. “I’d better let you sleep too.” she suggested.

“I guess… I mean, you don’t have to.” Julian told her.

They’d spent eight hours together just hanging out. Sitting and lounging around on the bed, discussing everything from current world politics to all the Disney movies that had been released in their absence. There was an elephant in the room that hadn’t been touched on at all, but at the same time, not touching on it had seemed… right, somehow.

“Yeah…” Xiu began to scoot off the bed, then paused and turned back. “Um… thank you.”

“For what?”

“For not freaking out.”

Julian chuckled quietly, and looked back down at Allison. “Freaking out… I’m more worried about pinching myself and waking up.”

That earned one of Xiu’s biggest, prettiest smiles. “Two females who’re into you at once. Every male’s fantasy?”

Julian diplomatically ignored the unconsciously Gaoian way she’d phrased herself and kept playing with Allison’s hair, acutely aware that there was honestly a ‘yes’ in there, but there was something more important underneath. He shook his head. “Not that.” he said.

“Are you sure? I can see your ears going pink.” She teased. He laughed, but it faded quickly and he stopped playing with Allison’s hair and took a thoughtful breath.

“I don’t want to wake up and find I’m still on Nightmare.” He said. “All alone.”

He swallowed and fidgeted into a more traditional cross-legged position, feeling suddenly vulnerable, and tried to turn it into a weak joke. “Kinda suck, wouldn’t it?”

Xiu’s smile had faded a little, but she nodded understanding. She opened her mouth to say something, then a thought seemed to occur to her and she darted forward to give him a stinging pinch on his forearm. He clutched at the spot reflexively and blinked at her.

“Still here?” she asked.

He paused, then shut his eyes and nodded, grinning. “Yeah. Still here.”

She offered him her arm. “My turn.”

Rather than pinching it, he took her hand and studied the three ragged scar lines that ran from her elbow to her wrist and up the back of her hand to the knuckle. Hunter teeth were scalpel-sharp, and would have cut cleanly if they had sliced across her arm rather than raking along it. As it was, the marks were there to stay.

She hesitated and bit a lip. “Please… don’t.”

He let go of her hand again. “Sorry.”

“It’s okay, I just… don’t like them.”

Julian looked at her arm again. “If it helps.” he replied. “I like them.”

Xiu studied her scars as if wondering whether they were looking at the same things. “How can you like them?” She asked.

“If you didn’t have them we’d never have met.”

“I don’t, um.” She frowned. “What?”

“Well, think about it. You only have them because you survived getting them. And, here you are. If you’d never got those… who knows where you’d be?”

Xiu swallowed and looked at her arm, as if seeing the marks there in a slightly new light.

“So… yeah. I like ’em.” Julian finished. “’Cause you’re here.”

“My God, Julian.” They both jumped as Allison chimed in. “That was fucking romantic.”

“Well, I mean, uh…” Julian cleared his throat awkwardly and never made it as far as a coherent thought.

“Sorry.” Xiu apologised.

“S’okay.” Allison sat up and thrust an arm up into the air, stretching. “Just…”

“Don’t kiss him.” Xiu nodded, looking a touch crestfallen. “I know.”

Allison laughed a little and gave her a hug. “Actually… I’m warming up to the idea.”

“You are?”

“You are?”

“If you both want to.” Allison nodded. “Yeah. Though, uh… maybe get my permission first? I don’t think I’m ready for… not yet.”

“Small steps.” Julian agreed. He looked to Xiu, though he was pretty sure the moment was wrong.

Xiu backed off the bed and perched on the edge “Not… right now.” She said.

“Yeah. Not yet.” Julian agreed.

Xiu stood up and aimed a thumb over her shoulder toward the other bedroom. “I’d better… and let you…”

“You sure?” Allison asked. “It’s a big bed, and he’s warm…”

Xiu shook her head. “I need some time to think.” she said. “It’s okay.”

It was Allison’s turn to seem disappointed. “Okay… Sweet dreams, babe.”

Once he’d heard both doors click shut, Julian stood, pulled his shirt off over his head, threw it into the laundry hamper and turned out the light. Near- pitch darkness marched straight into the room and set up shop like it had never really left.

He undid his belt, let his jeans fall to the ground, and climbed into bed. Beside him, Allison finished squirming out of her own clothes, and she snuggled up to him. “You okay?” she asked.

“…You’re warming to the idea?” Julian asked her.

Allison kissed him on the cheek by way of a reply.

“Al…”

“What? I said it, and I meant it. If that’s what you want…”

“This is starting to sound like you want… I dunno, like some kind of a poly thing?”

“Maybe.”

“Maybe?”

She kissed him in the dark. “What do you want? Be real, baby, what would you like?”

“…Lots’a different bits of me are all saying ‘both of you’, and for all kindsa different reason.” Julian told her, honestly. “But…”

“But?”

“I’m kinda scared there’d be a loser, if we went that way. Like, one of us’d wind up being the spare wheel. I don’t want that to happen to any of us: you, me or her."

His night vision was coming in, and he could just make out how Allison rested the side of her head in her hand and thought about what he’d said. “…God, that’d really hurt her, yeah.”

“How would we avoid that?”

“We’d be real.” Allison said. “That’s the key to any good relationship.”

“…True…”

“Right. So, why should that change just because we’d be three and not two?” she pointed out. “One-on-one relationships can have a loser too.”

“You really want to do this, don’t you?” Julian asked.

Allison put her head back down on his shoulder. “I don’t know why exactly, but I do.” She agreed. “I don’t want to spend my life stuck in other people’s’ comfort zones. Yeah, if we do this, maybe one of us gets hurt. And it won’t be Xiu. I won’t do that to her."

“But…?” Julian asked.

She nuzzled into his shoulder. “So maybe we get hurt. I’ve been hurt before, and I don’t think it’s so bad next to never trying.”

“So… are we going for it?”

“I want to.” She said, simply. “Do you?”

“Yes.”

“Then it’s up to Xiu.” Allison kissed him again, then rolled over. “Be the big spoon?”

Julian smiled to himself, and cuddled up behind her, infiltrating his arm over her waist. “Yes ma’am.”

“Mmmm…” she issued the hugest, most content sigh and wriggled back into him. “I love you.”

“What, no ‘good boy’?"

She nodded sleepily. “They mean the same thing, dummy.”

He smiled, kissed her just below her ear, then put his head down and let her fall asleep. “…I know.”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
London, England, Earth.

Regaari

Any being who travelled from planet to planet needed to get used to sleeping according to what their body demanded, rather than according to the local diurnal rhythm. When travelling from Gao to Gorai could mean landing at a completely different time of day and in a day/night cycle that was nearly a third longer. It never paid to try and adjust to local time unless you were intent on staying for a while. The difference was even more pronounced on Earth, with its too-short day.

Hence why Regaari was awake at 5am.

The other three weren’t. Warhorse and Baseball, in true deathworlder fashion, seemed to have learned a skill that Regaari wouldn’t have thought possible, in being able to just sleep, wherever and whenever they were, for as long as they needed.

What was even more impressive was that Regaari knew that should he make the smallest noise of alarm or distress, both men would be awake and alert immediately.

They seemed to have discovered a quirk in Ayma meanwhile. After their nightly ritual of shampooing, rinsing, conditioning, rinsing again and then blow- drying, she went completely berserk. The moment the blow-dryer was turned off and she was able to escape the ordeal of being bathed, she would flit restlessly around the room, cleaning up every object that was even microscopically out of place, flipping TV channels, asking questions about every subject that crossed her mind, and even on one occasion pouncing from the bed onto Warhorse’s shoulders and imitating a human cry of “Giddyup!”

After about an hour of this she would, quite suddenly, crash and sleep until somebody woke her.

This had left Regaari to occupy himself for several hours a night every night, and so he had discovered the Internet.

Data networks were easy. Every species had one, and each was a reflection of the minds of its creators. Which, when the minds in question were human, meant that the Internet was anything but easy. Being almost completely illiterate in English only complicated matters.

Still, after some trial and error, Regaari had eventually managed to navigate the prickly shibboleth maze of in-jokes, references and running gags, some of the more enduring of which were as old as Warhorse. Beyond them was an opportunity.

Regaari was an older and much wiser male than he’d been in the days when he had first criticized his Fathers for cozying up to the Dominion. Gone was the earnest, naive young Whitecrest, and in his place was the kind of warrior who didn’t have too many scars not on account of staying out of fights, but on account of winning them. And for all that he was a skilled agent of conflict in the real world, when it came to data and intelligence Regaari knew he was among the rarified stratum of the very, very best.

Compiling a script to trawl assorted translation sources for probable meaning and then convert the written English into the specialist, high-density code that his implants could read was almost trivial. English may have been a context-heavy and intricate language, but the Corti had excelled themselves when they had created the universal communication medium that was the intermediary through which all translation took place. It was believed to be capable of communicating every possible nuance of meaning, including detailed descriptions of sensory experiences in senses that no known species possessed or could conceive of.

Still. The word “fuck” gave it trouble. Perhaps due to their own bias towards orderly and logical systems, the Corti had never considered that an innocuous monosyllable could carry such a titanic freight of varied meaning. It wasn’t that the word specifically had a nebulous meaning, but that the ‘formal’ meaning, so to speak, was just the root of the most hideously tangled snarl of colloquialism that Regaari had ever heard of.

Somehow, he just knew that he’d be debugging the algorithm that decided which particular “fuck” was being used in a given context for as long as he tried to use the script. But, it would do.

What it would do, was allow him to read English and, haltingly, write it too. This was important, because Regaari’s opportunity had three components.

The first was simple intelligence-gathering. Not that he would gain anything classified or sensitive this way, but that didn’t matter. Simply an insight into what humanity’s informed civilians, retired veterans and armchair strategists thought of their species’ position was edifying enough. What he found there impressed him - short on specifics though they might be, a hard core of amateur analysts were busily assembling a dossier on humanity’s strategic position that was every bit as thorough as Regaari’s own, and often rather more informed.

It made for mixed reading. The innate superiority of humans as warriors was ultimately badly outweighed by the logistical superiority of the rest of the galaxy. On the other hand, nobody could think of a way in which the planet Earth itself might be vulnerable save through technological possibilities so outlandish as to be pure fiction.

Part two was more fun than part one. Humans were already well-disposed toward Gaoians. Annoying instincts vis a vis dogs and cute fluffy animals aside, Sister Shoo was substantially better-known to the Internet than she probably suspected. Adopting and protecting her had done Gao an enormous favor, there.

So, part two was further cementing that relationship. Which led to part three - mischief.

Baseball and Warhorse weren’t remotely shy about their affection for each other, and on this particular occasion were asleep and rumbling spooned up close, with one of Base’s hairy arms resting gently on Horse’s waist.

Picking up Base’s phone, logging into a social media app that allowed new photos and video footage to be uploaded directly to the Internet was trivial. Making it seem innocent would have been equally easy - just a curious Gaoian accidentally activating a device he didn’t know how to stop - but that wasn’t the point. The point was to humanize himself and, more importantly, to humanize the SOR.

He mimed the “shush” gesture that he’d learned and played the camera around the room, taking care to capture as good a view as he could of the two Protectors. Ayma got a little screen time, curled up with her nose stuffed into her fur and an ear twitching slightly as she dreamed, then back to Regaari for a wave to the crowd and… done.

Too bad for one staff sergeant John Burgess that his social media profile was set to ‘public’ by default. Less than a minute after it was uploaded, the video had leaked.

Less than ten minutes later, the footage was on Youtube.

By the time, two hours later, that Warhorse stirred in his sleep ahead of waking up for a bright new day and Regaari had to close all the browser tabs, ‘#SleepyBeef’ was trending across the planet and Regaari himself had secured the affection of tens of thousands of humans.

Not bad for five minutes’ work.

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds

Mwrmwrwk

“I have a bounty to claim.”

The creature manning the desk was a Mjrnhrm, and a long way from home. The acid-etching on the brow-plate of its chitinous head made it clear that this particular one had been exiled for some unspecified crime, and somewhere in its travels some misadventure had cost it a limb. Rather than going for cybernetic prostheses, the creature had opted to receive cloned (or, possibly, donor) organic transplants instead. The replacements were slightly paler shade of mottled dark verdigris.

“The wanted person boards are on the left.” it said, communicating clear impatience and disinterest.

Whether or not its misadventures had robbed it of a sense of manners or whether all Mjrnhrm were like that, Mwrmwrwk couldn’t guess. She’d never met a Mjrnhrm before.

“It isn’t a person.”

“A bounty on something that is not a person.” It put the tablet it had been reading down and its vestigial wings buzzed briefly, signalling clear and naked derision. “Please, do regale me, o brave explorer. Which fabled lost planet have you uncovered? A deathworld full of sapient trees? A city built entirely of platinum? Mrwrki Station?”

“Yes.”

It buzzed again. Some subtle shift of pitch and frequency that was inaudible to Kwmbwrw ears was enough to communicate the difference between derision and confusion. “What?”

“I have found Mrwrki station.” Mwrmwrwk willed her translator to broadcast sincerity and irritation in equal measure.

The Mjrnhrm tilted its head, studying her skeptically and with no small sign of cautious avarice. Mwrmwrwk could hardly blame it for that - given the size of the finder’s fee on Mrwrki, even the small percentage that bounty officers took from each contract would translate to a healthy lump sum in any currency. “…Prove it.”

“What kind of fool do you think I am?” Mwrmwrwk asked it. “Open the transaction and log my report. Then I prove it.”

With an air that suggested it would have preferred to be grumbling aloud, it did so. Mwrmwrwk promptly uploaded her identity information, and the sensor records she had discreetly copied from Negotiable Curiosity’s memory.

The Mjrnhrm studied the proof in front of it for nearly a full two Ri’.

“It pays to be skeptical in my line of work.” It declared, and opened a few tools and programs that, within the protected environment of the transaction, dissected her file in search of evidence of forgery. “But, I can find no evidence that this is a fake…”

“So?”

“You present me with a gamble.” It said. “Mrwrki is a myth. No serious being believes it did anything other than explode. And the size of the reward… I can only just afford to pay out.”

“You sound very much like the last three bounty officers I went to.” Mwrmwrwk told it. “All of them have missed the opportunity of earning, by my estimation, forty-four Dominion Development Credits.”

Its vestigial wings thrummed as it thought long and hard.

Then, very slowly and carefully, it poked its pincer to the large blue accept button.

A notification in Mwrkwrki’s field of vision informed her that she was now many hundreds of times wealthier. It was an absurd sum - enough to buy a fleet of ships the size of Negotiable Curiosity. There was no use - or any real point - in trying to conceal her delight, so instead she reared up to her full height, thrust her forepaws into the air and cooed a long and loud trill of Kwmbwrw triumph.

Then she dropped back to all fours.

“A pleasure” she told the Mjrnhrm, which had covered its auditory organs “to do business with you.”

“If I come to regret it, I swear by the etchings of my kin that I will spend the last of my funds on somehow finding the Human Disaster himself and hiring him to come after you.” it replied, though there was a note of amusement and confidence that it would need to do no such thing.

Fighting to preserve a semblance of dignity, she exchanged gestures of respect with the odd creature, shuffled around and ambled out of the bounty office, fantasizing about being able to finally get out from under Bedu’s skinny thumb, of not having to spend an attosecond longer tolerating Hzzkvk, of being able to return to Kwmbwri, get in good with one of the Great Houses, maybe even become a Matriarch herself.

She effectively died in mid-stride.

Nobody noticed. At most, if they were paying attention they would have seen a slight stumble and the way she stopped, took her bearings, and kept walking. To an outside observer, there was no hint at all that anything was seriously amiss.

On the inside, Eleven took stock of the situation, and set about her mission.

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Etsicitty house, North Clearwater County, Minnesota, USA, Earth

Xiu Chang

The vendors on Itrian station are selling gluten-free tigers, buy two and get a third free. It sounds like a healthy option, so Xiu buys three and wanders away to watch the spaceships docking.

Toss.

One of the docking ships smiles at her. Its face splits like pavement cracking, and what it produces is less a smile than a hungry rictus. She throws it a tiger, which it snatches down like a shark snatching a passing fish.

Turn.

Freaked out, she turns away and runs off between the trees. Knee deep snow and needled boughs slow her down, and behind her she knows beyond doubt that Death is gaining. Despairing of escape, she turns at bay and raises her hands to fight, unsheathing her claws and baring her teeth. If she’s about to die, she’s going to die like a Gaoian.

Night and oblivion sweep down upon her and she woke up, flailed and thrashed at the blankets for a second, cast wildly about the unfamiliar room and the dream is still real. A Corti’s face sneers at her in the dark and she scrambles across the bed away from it, fighting for room, only to fall off the other side and hit her head on the wall.

Clarity returned. The Corti turned out to be a framed picture on the wall, or something similar.

Twisted up in the sheets as she was, it took her some effort and quite a lot of soft swearing to eventually struggle to her feet and, rubbing the sore spot on the back of her head, inspect the picture.

“Derek and The Dominos…?”

She sighed and sank onto the bed, resisting the urge to yank on her own hair to chastise herself. That way lay a degenerating spiral of self-loathing that she’d been caught in far too many times over the years.

Instead, she crossed her legs under herself, wriggled her spine straight, and settled into a ritual that had got her through so many dark days. Metta, also known as Loving-Kindness meditation, was directed first at herself to build up a positive frame of mind, and from that foundation she could project the same energies towards her friends and her loved ones.

Nowadays, she had a long list of loved ones. That was worth remembering: It helped her love herself and forgive herself for the nightmares and intrusive ideas.

By the time she finished, the overcast sky outside her borrowed window had a blue-grey cast to it that hinted at imminent dawn. She threw on a T-shirt as she listened to the house and decided that nobody was awake yet. Time to fix breakfast.

She had nearly finished mixing the crepe batter when Julian emerged from his and Allison’s bedroom and plunged straight into the bathroom. He wasn’t in there long - apparently he was an efficient showerer - and he emerged wearing his cargo shorts, scrubbing at his hair and kicking his prosthetic foot to shake the water out of it.

“Hey, you.”

She beamed at him. “Hey.”

“You’re in a good mood this morning.” he observed. “Whatever that squeal of delight was, it woke me up.”

She grimaced. “Sorry.”

“It’s okay, I’m a light sleeper.” He sat down on one of the bar stools at the island worksurface, and Xiu pretended not to notice the very welcome attention he was paying to her legs. “What was that, anyway?”

“I, um…” She sighed and blushed. “I found the maple syrup.”

Sure enough he laughed. “Yup, you’re Canadian.” he confirmed, fondly.

She laughed with him. “Shut up!”

Grinning like a retriever with three ducks in his mouth, he nodded. “Yes ma’am.”

“Ooh, do I get to say ‘good boy’?"

He chuckled, and rested his jaw on his fist. “If you like.”

“Then get some plates warmed up.”

He stood and she was gratified to see that even he had to go on tip-toes to reach the cupboard that she’d had to jump slightly just to open. “Yes ma’am.”

Xiu giggled. “Good boy. Oh, and put some music on.”

“Yes ma’am.”

“Oh, I could get used to this…”

He paused in filling the sink with hot water, waiting, and she laughed silently through her nose. “Good boy.”

The bacon was sizzling, the plates were nice and hot and Norah Jones was singing ‘Sunrise’ when Allison surfaced. She greeted Xiu with an affectionate hug from behind and Julian with a light kiss. “Something” she declared “smells AMAZING.”

“Breakfast crepes!” Xiu explained.

“Ooh, what’s in them?” Allison backed off as Xiu aimed a playful slap at her hand.

“Sit down and you’ll find out.”

Allison raised an eyebrow at Julian, who just shrugged. “…Yes ma’am!” she said.

“Hmm…” Xiu produced her cheekiest smile. “Good girl.”

Allison pantomimed shock - her jaw dropped, but the rest of her face was thoroughly amused. She sat next to Julian. “…Okay, that’s actually kinda fun.” she conceded to him.

“Isn’t it?” he agreed.

Beaming to herself, Xiu finished her preparations and soon had three steaming hot crepes plated and served, each one wrapped around a solid portion of bacon, cheese and a sunny-side-up fried egg, with a drizzle of maple syrup and a couple of blueberries and raspberries for decoration.

“Dear God, this looks like it belongs in a restaurant.” Allison commented, as it arrived in front of her.

“Or a fancy hotel.” Julian agreed. “This is home cooking to you?”

Xiu just grinned and picked up her fork. “Don’t let it go cold.” she admonished them.

They looked at each other, then picked up their own cutlery and tucked in. Xiu took one mouthful and almost put her fork back down as the taste made her close her eyes in delight.

“Are you allowed to react that powerfully to your own cooking?” Julian teased.

Xiu play-glared at him. “Giff’me a break. I’ff not had thefe in yearff.”

“She’s allowed.” Allison agreed, and swallowed. “Babe, these are divine."

Glowing internally, Xiu accepted the compliment with a smile, and dived right into her next mouthful.

As always with good food, their plates were empty far too soon, and Julian and Allison soon turned the tables on her by not letting her do any of the cleaning down and washing up.

“So… How long do we have until Jenkins is back?” Allison asked.

“He said ten o’clock or thereabouts.” Julian replied. “Annoying. An hour or two later and I could get the beaver pipe installed before he arrives…”

“You were gonna take that Aspen down.” Allison pointed out. Julian snapped his fingers and nodded. He put the last plate away and headed for the bedroom.

“Beaver pipe?” Xiu asked.

“There’s beavers up in the back woods.” Allison explained, wiping the skillet dry. “Julian says it’s a good thing we got back when we did, ’cause a year or two more and they’d be threatening to flood out the road. So, he’s installing some kind of a drain pipe to control the water level.”

“And the Aspen?”

“Quaking Aspen coming up by the garage. It needs to come down before it grows any bigger and damages the roof.”

“Wow. This place really is country…” Xiu looked around. “Um, what are you doing?”

Allison hung up the skillet on the rack by the window. “There’s the other truck to have a look at, but I think that one’s beyond repair.” she said. “Julian says the last time he remembers it running he was just a kid. But, you never know.”

“Oh.” Xiu looked around. “I could, uh, tidy up in here?” she suggested.

“You don’t have to…” Allison told her.

“Yuosha’.”, Xiu replied, unconsciously using a Gaoian phrase that served the same purpose as ‘bullshit’. “I can at least throw a duster around.”

Allison raised her hands. “Knock yourself out, babe.” she said. “Go ahead and take all the ornaments down, too.

After getting dressed, Xiu didn’t need long to find the dusters and furniture polish in the utility room, along with a cloth to cover her hair. She flung open the windows and screen doors, put on some louder music that she could hear it over the sound of Julian’s chainsaw, and declared war on anything resembling dust, dirt or grime, no matter where it hid around the house.

The house had clearly gone for years without being dusted, and she quickly had to find another cloth to cover her mouth and nose - every unused surface, door jamb, high shelf, the backs of the appliances, and especially all the remaining wall ornaments and paintings were caked in the stuff.

The end result was that when Julian came back in some unconsidered interval later, his reaction was to sneeze violently. “Jeez!”

Xiu grimaced. “Sorry, sorry…”

He coughed and waved a hand to try and clear the air. “Maybe let it settle before Jenkins gets here.” he suggested, heading to the front door and opening both the inner door and the banshee screen door to let the air properly blow through.

Xiu nodded. “…Right.” she agreed. “…I got the place cleaner though!”

“Yeah you did.“Julian waved the door a few times to try and fan some air through, then gave up and grabbed a bottle of water from the fridge. “You did a great job!”

“Xiexie!” she beamed at him and sat on one of the barstools.

“So, uh…” he began.

“Yeah?”

“Speaking of Jenkins…” Julian sat down opposite her. “You never actually said whether you’re coming with us.”

Impulsively, Xiu got up to get herself a water as well - dusting was thirsty work - but she gave him a happy kiss on the cheek on her way past. “I’m considering it.” she teased as he put a surprised hand to his cheek. “Isn’t being a starship pilot on the cards? Wei would be so jealous."

“Didn’t you want to be an actress?” he asked, as she grabbed the drink.

She sat down again. “That’s not likely, these days.”

“Less likely than being a starship pilot?”

Xiu was giving a wry shrug by way of an answer as Allison came back in.

“Yeah, the Ford’s dead.” she announced. “What’re you two up to?”

“We’re just discussing how flying spaceships is my most plausible career option.” Xiu joked.

Allison made an amused noise and sat down with them. “I bet it beats acting anyway.” she said. “No paparazzi, no gossip, no interviews and cameras… So you’re coming with us, for real?”

What neither of them knew, was that Xiu’s mind had been made up since last night. Home, after all, was wherever she wanted to be.

“Yes.” she said. “I’m coming with you.”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Military transport plane, somewhere above the arctic circle, Earth

Owen Powell

“They’re all over t’ fookin’ Internet! All over it! Here I was thinking your objective in comin’ ‘ere was to prove yer a reliable an’ trustworthy sort an’ build a foundation for an alliance an’ that, and then you go and violate the privacy of two of my lads?"

“I think you’ll find, major.” Regaari was holding his ground, for which Powell had to give him grudging credit. “That my little act of mischief was carefully calculated.”

“Careful-? Oh, aye? Alright. Let’s fookin’ hear it. Come on.” Powell produced his best ferocious glare which, to his consternation, seemed to have no effect on Regaari at all.

Regaari smoothed down a loose tuft of fur. Thanks to his nightly bathing at Ares’ thorough hands, his fur was glossy, light and refusing to behave itself. “Have you been following your own unit’s reputation on social media, major?” he asked, lightly.

“I’ve been too busy wi’ actually runnin’ the unit, mate." Powell said.

“You should. Prior to our arrival, the SOR was…” Regaari paused, selecting his words carefully. “…the subject of some concern. Accusations of inhumane and unethical surgery, concerns of genetic manipulation, rumours that they’re the product of a Corti research program. The propaganda footage you put out of the action on Capitol Station has only fuelled the concern.”

“Not a one of us is stronger’n a human can get naturally.” Powell said. “Not even Ares.”

“As you say.” Regaari duck-nodded. “But your species tend to underestimate yourselves, major. I think most of you don’t believe that Earth really is a deathworld. Many on the Internet are saying that everything that has happened in the last ten Earth years has been an enormous hoax."

Major Jackson made a pained noise. “Oh, those fuckwits." she groaned.

“Human nature.” Powell said.

“Yeah, but I still can’t wait for the day when I can punch people like that consequence-free, like Buzz Aldrin did.” She said. “But Regaari’s right, Powell. Your ‘lads’ scare people just by existing. Didn’t you hear about China complaining to the UN about the, quote, ‘western supersoldier program’?”

“I musta been too busy bein’ part o’ that program." Powell grumbled. “So, what, you’re saying we’ve got some public image to make up?”

“You’ve got a fuck of a lot of public image to make up.” Rylee said. “Or did you forget that’s my second job? I’ve not been hanging around with you and the lads just for your charming company, I’m on duty here."

“And how exactly does shootin’ footage of my two youngest and least experienced men in a state of undress and uploadin’ it to the Internet help our public image?" Powell asked.

“It makes them more relatable.” Regaari explained. “Just in this short trip, Baseball and Warhorse have gone from being two anonymous examples of exactly the kind of extreme physicality that has so badly unnerved your species’ commentators, to being ‘the Beef Brothers.’ Now, people are saying ‘they sleep just like everyone else.’”

“My lads aren’t that scary.” Powell said, dismissively.

“Hah!” Jackson smiled incredulously at him. “Hell yes they are! If I didn’t know them so well they’d scare the crap out of me. You too!”

Powel blinked at her, surprised. “…Really?”

Jackson raised a hand to her mouth and called down toward the two enlisted men, who were playing Poker with Ayma. “Hey! Warhorse!”

His head snapped round. “…Ma’am?”

“How big d’you reckon you’d be if you’d stayed PJ instead of going SOR?”

Ares thought about it. “’Bout… five-eight? Two hundred or two-twenty-five pounds?”

“How big are you now?” She asked.

“Much bigger’n that, ma’am. ” his trademark dopey grin put in an appearance.

Jackson nodded to him, and lowered her voice. “Between you and me? That boy’s a freak.” she said. “A cute, goofy and lovable freak with about the best service ethic I ever saw, but a freak nonetheless. But overnight he’s gone from being a freak in the public eye to having fans. Fans who don’t even know him for the great guy he is, who don’t have a reason to see past the muscles."

Powell directed a calculating frown at his young charge, and said nothing.

“That sounds like quite a public relations coup.” Regaari noted. His ears were up defiantly, and he folded his arms in imitation of the human gesture, which was awkward for a Gaoian.

“It is.” Jackson agreed. “One that I doubt we could have pulled off. About the only person who could was Regaari, in fact. Protocol forbids us from doing something like this, but Regaari? When he does it, that’s just mischief, you know?"

Powell took a deep and resigned breath. “Fine. Okay. Let’s say I concede that maybe this is a net positive. A big one, even. I’m still not happy at all that you did this wi’out at least consulting me, and wi’out my lads knowin’ you had it planned.”

“Wouldn’t have worked.” Jackson told him. “It’s the whole candid thing that gives it the magic.”

“Major…” Regaari scooted forward in his chair so that his dangling feet could reach the floor. “There may be a cultural difference here. Among Gaoians, for one Clan to do unbidden what another Clan cannot do for themselves - or isn’t aware that they need to - is considered a sign of respect."

“Fookin’ impudent is what I call it.” Powell groused, but raised a placating hand. “Fine. we’ll chalk it up to alien cultural differences. But do we really need that big of a PR boost?"

“…Regaari? Could you give us some privacy please?” Jackson asked. The Gaoian duck-nodded and picked his way forward to try and get back into Warhorse and Baseball’s good graces.

She turned to Powell. “Yes. Yes you do.”

He raised an eyebrow. “We’re doin’ a job out there. A fookin’ important one. You know what’s at stake. I couldn’t care less what some pimply Internet social justice warrior has to say, they know fookin’ nothin’, and they’re better off that way."

“I don’t think you know what’s at stake." she replied. “Powell, bad PR has killed units stone dead in the past. Those ‘social justice warriors’ are voters, and while you’re folding your arms at them and keeping shtum, they’re gossiping and speculating and hurting your image so bad that young men are gonna shy away from you ’cause their mommas warned them about genetic engineering, or whatever."

“That bad?” He asked.

Jackson nodded, sadly. “Hashtag ‘BeefBros’ is about the best thing that could have happened to your unit, Powell. Without it, it was only a matter of time before some congressman started making nasty noises about you, or some firebrand talkshow host did his bit and skewered your reputation.”

He pointed an arm toward the rear of the aircraft. “There’s fookin’ extinction knockin’ on the door out there, and you’re telling me our strategy for fightin’ it exists at the whim o’ the kind of blithering wankers who couldn’t tip water out of a helmet with the instructions written on’t’ top?"

“That’s about right.”

“Jesus fookin’ Christ…” He rubbed a finger despairingly across the top of his nose, between his eyebrows. “If that’s the shape of it then we’re doomed, and rightly bloody so. We can’t build our survival on a foundation that dodgy!"

She reached out and put a sympathetic hand on his shoulder. “Owen? Trust me on this. That’s not a fight any of us are gonna win. The only option is to play the game and play it well."

He lowered his hand and glanced guiltily towards the young Protectors. “What happens to the lads if we don’t play it well?” he asked, quietly.

She squeezed his shoulder. “Trust me, and trust Regaari, and you’ll never have to find out.” she promised.

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Byron Group Headquarters, Omaha, Nebraska, USA, Earth

Moses Byron

Rachael was extremely good at her job. She knew exactly which calls to forward to Moses when he was in a meeting, and he knew it. So, when his desk phone rang in the middle of a meeting, he had no problems at all in putting his guests on hold for a few moments.

“Ah, please, excuse me, gentlemen… Go ahead, Rachael.”

“Mister Jenkins on the line, sir.”

“Nice! I’ll take it, thank you.” There was a click and a change in audio quality that said the call was through. “Kevin! Still in Minnesota?”

“On my way back, boss man. Aaaand, EV-eleven is fully crewed. Three stellar explorers, as requested.”

“You even got Chang?”

“She talked herself into it.” Jenkins replied. “I’ll give you my full impression when I’m back in the office tomorrow. Figured you’d like to know so you can start the ball rolling.”

“You figured right.” Moses agreed. “See you tomorrow.” he stabbed a button on the phone to go back through to Rachael. “Rachael, tell Ericson we’re good to go on Eleven, please.”

“Yes, Mister Byron.”

“Thanks Rachael.”

He clapped his hands and rubbed them happily, then turned back to his guests. “Please, forgive the interruption.” he said. “As you were saying-?”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Finchley, London, England, Earth

Ava Rios

Simon Harvey chose about the worst time to call Ava’s phone - she had a basket of wet laundry held awkwardly on one hip and was trying to hang it up with her spare hand, and the phone was on her basket-holding hip pocket

She just about managed to fumble it out in time to answer, somehow. “Hey, Simon.”

“Ava! Glad one of you’s answering your phone.” Simon had the unmistakable rush of a car in traffic behind him. “Go tell my nephew to stop wanking, I’ll be along to pick you both up in twenty minutes. Have you got that travel bag I told you to pack?”

“Uh, yeah.” She cradled her phone against her chin and began taking the washing off the line to move it indoors instead. “Why, where are we going?”

“Cairo.” he replied. “I’ll explain when we’re en route.”

Not knowing how long they’d be gone, Ava made sure to hang the wet clothes up indoors after rousing Sean from whatever he’d been doing in his room and explaining what they were doing and where they were going.

“Cairo?” He asked, helping her get them laid out. Neither of them wanted to come back to moldy clothes.

“That’s what he said. Please tell me you packed that bag like he told us.”

Sean gave her a mildly offended look. “I did it first thing!” he told her.

“Right.”

Laundry cleared away they did a quick tour of the house, turning off the water, gas and electricity, checking the doors and windows were all locked, taking photos of each room in case they got back to find the place burgled and were outside, locked up and had their bags and equipment in hand when Simon rolled up in one of London’s rentable self-driving cars.

They piled in, buckled up, and he ordered it to Heathrow airport.

“So. Cairo.” Simon began, getting straight to business. “There was some kind of a gun battle down there last night, and LOTS of people reported a sonic boom. All by itself that’s unusual, but the very interesting part…” He opened his tablet and showed them Twitter. “…is that the locals are calling it a UFO.”

Ava and Sean glanced at each other. “Is that… enough to go on?” Sean asked.

Simon shrugged. “If nothing else, we can get a story out of the shootout. Something happened down there, and there’s a story in it, even if it’s not Ava’s Big Conspiracy." he said. “But the skeptics really are at a loss for what else to call it, and nobody in the Egyptian government has said a word yet.”

Ava took a deep breath. This was a world away from shooting photos of the crowd during a visit by extraterrestrial dignitaries. “Cairo, huh? I always wanted to see the Pyramids…”

“Work first, tourism later.” Simon told her, but he was smiling. “I’m trusting you both on this one. Maybe if this goes smoothly, we’ll be ready to move on with chasing your conspiracy, Ava, but for now I have two inexperienced young journalists in my care. You appreciate how big the favour I’m doing for you is?”

“Yes, Simon.” Ava said. Sean just nodded.

“Right.” Simon swiped to a different app on his tablet. “Here’s what I have so far…”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Cairo, Egypt, Earth

Master Sergeant Roy Vinther

“Y’all packed?”

There was a round of nodding. Hotwash was done with - there really hadn’t been much to report, the op had been aborted too quickly for them all to do more than confirm that the Hierarchy had a ship on Earth and that it was creating biodrones. Beyond that, there were precious few in the way of learning points. As far as Vinther could tell, the whole mission had gone by the numbers, and now they were packing up and moving on.

Sergeant Walsh was the last in zipping his bag. “Yup. Where we going?” he asked

“Back to CONUS, unless something comes up last minute.”

Walsh grimaced at him. “Vinther, you ass, never say shit like that, you should know better! Now we-"

His phone pinged, and everyone in the room watched warily as he dug it out. Walsh’s shoulders dropped as he read the message. “There, you see what you did?” he asked.

“You’re shittin’ me.” Vinther frowned. “What the fuck’s come up now?"

“’s from the CIA station chief. Gimme a….” Walsh wandered down the room, reading what had been sent to him with his hand on his chin.

“Way to go, Vinther.” Pavlopoulos congratulated him.

“Hangover, you look like you’ve got time to spare. Why don’t you go load the bags in the SUV?” Vinther told him.

“….yes, master sergeant.”

Vinther let him grab a bag in each hand and go. “Walsh?”

The so-called intel weenie looked up. “Persons of interest coming our way.” he said. “They just got on a flight in London.”

“Is this information just for our entertainment, or are we gonna actually do something with it?" Vinther asked.

“Covert surveillance.”

“Fuck that, we ain’t equipped!” Vinther protested.

Walsh scrolled down through whatever he was reading. “Chief says they’ll equip us.”

“Well that’s a red flag.” Coombes grunted. “Company never shares their toys."

“Who are these POIs, anyway?” Vinther asked.

Walsh turned the phone around, showing him a photo of a stunning young woman with a heart-shaped face, wavy hair and a slightly haunted, intense gaze. “Ava Magdalena Rios.” he said. “San Diego survivor, adopted daughter of the chief of Cimbrean Colonial Security, romantically involved with a member of the SOR and, crucially, a journalist. Working for our second POI…” he swiped across onto the next page. “…Mr. Simon Harvey.”

Vinther studied the slender, angular and painfully English features of the passport photo at the top of the page. “Who?”

“He’s a reporter, been poking around in Jeddah, Karachi and Qalqilya.”

“Fuck.” Coombes opined. “We got a leak.”

“No wonder the Company wants us on top of them.” Vinther agreed.

“They’re a step behind if they’re only coming down here now.” Walsh pointed out.

“Guess it’s our job to keep it that way.” Vinther said. “Anything else?”

“Yeah, the chief’s sent a call to Cimbrean, asking for a couple of SOR men. Courtesy, seeing as one of their guys is involved, you know?”

“Great, so we gon’ have a couple’a meat walls stomping around?” Coombes said. “Just great.”

“Eh.” Walsh shrugged. “If it goes FUBAR, I could stand having Superman for backup.”

“What’s gonna go FUBAR? It’s a couple of civilian journalists.” Vinther asked him wryly, acutely aware that all missions got complicated, usually sooner rather than later. “How wrong can it go?”

Coombes smacked a palm to his forehead. “For fuck’s sake Vinther…"

“Take your superstitious ass and go tell Pavlo we need everything back in here.” Vinther retorted, grinning.

Coombes chuckled and kicked his feet out to propel himself upright. “Yes, master sergeant…”

Vinther turned back to Walsh. “Okay.” he said. “Let’s plan this shit.”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Allied Extrasolar Command, Scotch Creek, British Columbia, Canada.

Owen Powell

“Major. Good timing.”

Powell always quietly gave thanks to whatever power might hear it that his job didn’t require him to get as large as some of his lads, who had to turn sideways to make it comfortably through most doors. Still, stepping into General Tremblay’s office was an easy reminder that although Powell himself was easily the smallest EV-MASS qualified man in the SOR, he was still sitting in territory normally only achieved by dedicated bodybuilders.

Next to him, even Tremblay - a brawny man whom age had only succeeded in hardening - managed to look small.

“Summat important came up I gather, sir.” He replied. Tremblay gestured to the office chair opposite him.

“Two things did.” Tremblay expanded as Powell sat down. He produced two briefings - old habits died hard, and the general preferred paper hardcopy - and slid the first over the desk.

“Last night, an STS element operating in Cairo got into a brief firefight with Hierarchy assets. They’ve confirmed the presence of a Hierarchy spaceship and biodroning operation on Earth.”

Powell scowled at the pages as he skimmed them. Smart-paper “photos” clipped to the document replayed the helmet cam footage of an invisible object shielding retreating men and women from the operator’s fire, and lifting a tarpaulin as it rose into the air.

“That doesn’t make a whole lot o’ sense.” he mused. “If they could get a ship to us, why not call in the Hunters? Or just nuke us flat?”

“Our best guess is that the ship was already here, and has neither a jump beacon nor a nanofactory.” Tremblay explained. “Anyway, that’s for me to worry about. Where the SOR comes in is that somehow an investigative journalist by the name of Simon Harvey got wind of this, and he’s booked a flight to Cairo, with his two assistants: His nephew Sean Harvey, and-”

“Ava Rios.” Powell finished. Her face was right at the top of the second page. “Is there no escapin’ that fookin’ girl’s orbit?”

“That young woman is a bit of a rising star, Powell.” Tremblay said. “Newspaper front pages, magazine covers, the Byron Group’s whole advertising campaign for Cimbrean development… and of course she’s closely tied to two men who both know DEEP RELIC.”

Powell’s first instinct was to emphatically defend sergeant Ares and his father, but he owed it to the seriousness of the situation to think properly for a few seconds. “…I’d consider it deeply unlikely that either Gabriel Ares or his son have shared top secret information, sir.” he said carefully. “I trust ’em both. Besides, the girl’s not stupid and she’s been a victim of the Hierarchy’s activities. Could be she put the pieces together herself.”

“Either way, we need to know. She’s under covert surveillance, and the station chief requested that the SOR send a man or two. As a courtesy.”

“Firth and Murray.” Powell agreed, promptly.

Tremblay nodded. “Rationale?”

“They can both be as subtle - or not - as any situation might require, they’ve got mission-appropriate skills that Blaczynski and the Defenders lack, and even if they were appropriate for this gig, both my Protectors are in dire need of some PT."

“Good.” Tremblay slid over the other briefing. “On to situation two.”

Powell picked it up. What he read raised his eyebrows. “Kirk got back in touch?”

“So we hope. Sadly, we have to treat him as Orange for now, but he did feed us some intelligence which should help clean up that question. The name of a spaceship that may be in the Hierarchy’s employ, the ‘Negotiable Curiosity’."

“Cute name.”

Tremblay smiled grimly. “An exo-intel informant has it berthed on Perfection right now. I want that ship, its crew and every kilobyte in its computers.”

“No JETS assets available?” Powell asked.

“Available, yes. Appropriate, no.” Tremblay said. “I’d prefer to send a JETS- qualified Delta Force team on this if I could, but it turns out that Perfection hugely improved their anti-aircraft defense systems over the last few years in response to a terrorist attack. The only way to make a covert insertion now would be Exo-Atmospheric jump.”

“And only SOR can EA Jump.” Powell nodded. “Right. You only need the four?”

“Four should do nicely.” Tremblay agreed.

“Yes sir. Anything else?”

“I believe Major Jackson’s with you?”

“She is, yeah.”

“Good. Ask her to come see me as soon as the Gaoians are safely off this planet, please. And, if you can spare them from their PT for one more day, the Beef Brothers too.”

Powell hesitated. “General… if I may?”

Tremblay sat back and folded his hands neatly in his lap. “Go ahead.”

“Burgess and Ares are remarkable lads. Hell wi’t, they’re bloody heroes, both of them, and they deserve those silver stars they’re gonna get for NOVA HOUND. And, I know they’ve both seen stuff that grown men haven’t… but they both joined at seventeen and their whole life since then has been the military. If it’s really that important to, er…” he searched for the right word. “…to capitalize on this whole viral Internet thing…"

Tremblay didn’t say anything, but a half-inch hike of his eyebrow told Powell to get to the point.

“…I’m concerned for their well-being and morale, sir. The public eye’s a battlefield I myself fear to set foot on.”

“My hope,” Tremblay said, “was that Major Jackson might mentor and advise them before they find themselves back in front of a camera, assuming they ever do. Colonel Stewart has already agreed that he can spare her, and you, I believe, have better reason than anybody to trust her."

“Knowing they’d be in her care puts my mind at ease sir, yes.” Powell conceded.

“I sympathize.” Tremblay confessed. “But I think you and I are an old- fashioned breed, Powell. We’re too used to public relations being under control of, rather than controlling us. I’m old enough to remember mobile phones as big as bricks, and somehow I think you didn’t have one growing up.”

“No sir.”

Tremblay smiled. “Your Protectors are better-prepared than you think.” he promised. “And I’m just as concerned as you that we don’t ruin two exceptional assets. Fair?”

“Thank you sir.”

“Anything else?”

“Nothing comes to mind, sir.”

“Carry on, then. And… Powell?”

Powell paused in turning for the door. “Sir?”

“Give my good luck to the men you send to follow Harvey and Rios. Somehow, I think they’ll need it.”

“Change of plans, lads.”

Baseball and Warhorse straightened as Powell returned from the office complex, pausing in their preparations for the Jump Array.

“Sir?”

“General Tremblay wants to have a word. You can probably guess why.”

Both men looked at each other, and at the Gaoians. “I guess once these two are back on Cimbrean, our job’s done…” Burgess conceded. “This a PR thing, sir?”

“Major Jackson’s persuaded me that it’s important.” Powell told him. “I defer to her superior knowledge in these matters, seein’ as she’s been in the public eye a long time now.”

“Yes sir.”

“Get your charges home safe.” Powell said. “Ares. Got some private news for yer.”

The young man nodded and they strolled away from the little pile of equipment to talk in private. “I’m goin’ back wi’ the Gaoians.” Powell told him. “Soon as I get there, I’ve got a couple assignments for the lads, one of which is here on Earth. Your, er… former partner is caught up in some DEEP RELIC business down in Egypt.”

“Christ.” Ares rubbed at his forehead. “How’d she find out?”

“I’ve heard you say it yourself that she’s a smart lass.” Powell pointed out.

“Smarter’n me…” Ares agreed. “Most of the time. So… what, is she under observation?”

“Aye. And they’ve asked us to send some of ours down there. Not you.” Powell added, cutting the younger man off before he could speak. “Firth an’ Murray.”

Ares nodded. “Makes sense… thank you for telling me, sir.”

“You deserve to know.” Powell assured him. “Anyhow, I’ll let you crack on.”

“Yes sir… you’ll let me know if anything happens?”

“’Course I bloody will.” Powell said. “Sergeant.”

“Sir.”

Powell treated him to a rare affectionate clap on the shoulder and jogged back to where Regaari and Ayma were waiting. “I’m afraid this is where you part ways with your Protectors.” he announced. “I hope you’re parting on good terms, Burgess?”

Baseball grinned expansively. “Still kinda annoyed at the little furry bastard, sir.” he said, though his tone was warm.

“Regaari?”

“If I live to be older than Father Fyu I’ll never understand how insulting me is meant to be affectionate.” Regaari said, though Powell judged the set of his ears to be playful and amused. “But I believe so.”

“Good, because as far as I’m concerned this trip’s been a resounding success.” Powell extended a hand, and shook both their paws in turn. “Though - and please don’t take this the wrong way - for God’s sake please never come back.”

Ayma chittered. “Once was quite sufficient.” she promised.

Powell made an amused harrumph and bid them farewell with a touch of a finger to his forehead.

He found Jackson chatting amiably with the pilot of their transport plane, who was clearly a little star-struck and trying not to show it. She beamed at him, and excused herself to the pilot. If she noticed the way the young man turned and started fanboying out to his colleague, she did a good job of not showing it.

“Guess we’re parting ways again, huh?” she asked, soon as they were out of earshot.

“’Fraid so. Any idea when you’ll next be in Folctha?”

“I doubt it’ll be long. We’re going to want to move fast on this whole Beef Brothers thing, so I’ll be around before long to give you some more PR advice.” she smiled.

“Funny you should mention it, Tremblay wants a word with you and the lads before they head back.”

“Thought he might.” Rylee nodded, then considered him, thoughtfully.

“…What?”

“You sound like you’re gonna miss me.” she observed.

“Well of course I bloody am.” Powell chuckled. “You don’t think I’ve just been tolerating you this last week, do ya?"

She shook her head, still smiling. “You are such an easy tease.”

“Aye, you got me…”

“All to myself?”

“If you want.”

Rylee considered it. “Y’know… I like the whole friends-with-benefits thing we’ve got going…" she mused. “But I gotta admit, the older I get, the more going steady sounds like it’s got something going for it.”

“We could set a record for the longest-distance relationship. How far is Cimbrean from Earth?" Powell asked.

“Point seven kiloparsecs…”

“That sounds like a lot.”

“Yes and no…” Rylee thought about it some more, then shrugged expansively. “I like you a lot, Owen. And you bet your beautifully muscled ass I’ll be calling on you every chance I get. But being stationed in completely different systems when we’re both so career-focused…? I don’t know. How about we try it, and no hard feelings if it doesn’t work?”

“Sounds good.” Powell managed to keep his outside calm, but he was celebrating wildly on the inside, and judging from the twinkle in her eye Rylee could see right through him and sense the party in his head.

“Alright, it’s a deal you emotional volcano you.” She agreed, and then prodded him playfully in the shoulder “But you need to find yourself a friend for when I’m not around. Get yourself a dog or something."

“A dog? That’s no substitute, come on!” Powell laughed.

“No? I can be kind of a bitch in the mornings…” Rylee chuckled with him. “But yeah. Get yourself the biggest, goofiest, smartest dog you can find - a dog worthy of the SOR. The lads’ll love him.”

“…We could do with a mascot, I suppose…” Powell mused.

“Good! I look forward to meeting him.” Rylee gave him a hug and a kiss on the cheek. “I’d better go see what the general wants, anyway.”

“Rylee… take care of the Beef Brothers, will you? Seeing ’em thrust into the spotlight like this… makes me uneasy.”

“I know.” she smiled. “I’ll look after them, promise.”

“Thanks.”

She turned and walked away with a wave. “They’re lucky to have you, Owen.”

He watched her go. “Aye.” he said, so quietly that it was only for himself to hear. “Same’s true for me.”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
Cairo, Egypt, Earth

Six

Survival skills that Six had spent several years honing proved their value because somehow he managed to avoid stumbling, staring, or even walking a little slower and getting a second glance to be certain of what - whom - he had seen.

Those were all powerful instincts, ones that his stolen human body imposed upon its Igraen squatter at every opportunity. Learning to suppress them had been the hardest task of his existence, but suppress them he did. He didn’t need to double-check, after all - he could replay imagery from his biodrone body’s optic nerve whenever he wanted, and remember anything seen by himself or any Agent whose memories he had accessed.

He ducked out of the flow of human traffic in the airport, and, on the pretense of checking his phone, reviewed what he had seen.

San Diego, the roller derby. Getting up and leaving just before his capture. Folctha, Cimbrean. Standing at the fence and weeping as Eighty-Four botched the Hierarchy’s last ditch attempt at keeping humanity from spreading to a different planet.

The same face. Older now - an adult, rather than the curly-haired teenager he’d first seen all those years ago, and wearing a kind of brittle confidence

but definitely the same person.

He didn’t know who she was, exactly, but for one human female to be present at two such important events - and now to come here, in the immediate aftermath of his successful disruption of the Hierarchy’s plans for Cairo - that was no coincidence. At least, not according to a human aphorism on the subject of happenstance, coincidence and enemy action.

There was no way that she could fail to be under observation, of course. But that was not, in fact, so much of an obstacle.

Taking care to move in as bored and straightforward a manner as he could, he rejoined the flow of humanity around the airport and kept an eye out. Sure enough, the woman and her two friends had barely gone thirty meters before a man - a burly, fit man in jeans and a loose jacket - glanced at the woman, then around at the crowd. His gaze skipped right over Six without even noticing him, and Six congratulated himself. That moment could have gone badly for him.

Loitering was not an option. While he would have loved to get more information, he was surrounded by watchers. Effecting an air of distracted, businesslike haste he weaved through the crowd right past the burly man, and out into the sweltering sunlight, where he grabbed a cab. He threw himself into the back seat, ordered the driver to a hotel, and sat back to make his plans.

Ava Rios

“Okay.” Simon twisted to glance out of the cab’s rear windscreen. “I wasn’t expecting them to meet us off the plane…”

Sean looked up from rummaging through his carry-on luggage. “What?”

“You didn’t see the chap in the jeans and jacket tailing us?” Simon asked. When Sean frowned and sat upright, he chuckled. “Nephew mine, we need to teach you some crowd skills.”

“And the guy in the suit?” Ava asked.

It was Simon’s turn to frown at her. “There was a guy in a suit.” she elaborated, unhelpfully.

“I didn’t see him. You’re sure?” Simon asked.

“He was doing a good job of not being noticed, but yeah. He looked right at me, checked his phone and then turned around and followed us. I’m not sure if he’s with Jacket… or if Jacket made him if he’s not.”

“If he did, he didn’t show it.” Simon mused, twisting to look out the back again. “I think you’re onto something, Ava. People waiting for us before we even land? And Jacket Guy was an American if I’m any judge.”

“What does that mean?” Sean asked.

“CIA, Delta Force, SOG, who knows?” Simon sat down. “What did Suit Guy look like?”

“Arabic. Short hair, stubble. Nice suit. Like a businessman.” Ava summarized.

Simon frowned and massaged his chin. “Honestly? That probably scuppers this investigation.” he said. “Even if we’re definitely onto something, there’s no way they’ll let us publish anything top secret.”

Sean zipped up his bag “So, what do we do?”

“We investigate anyway.” Simon said. “There’s always something you can report on, even if it’s not what you’d like to. We’re here, we need to earn our living. So, we do what we came here to do and we report whatever we can report."

“And maybe afterwards we know more than other people do.” Ava added.

“Where’s the value in knowing it if you can’t share it?” Sean frowned.

Ava shrugged. “I like knowing things.” she said. “And, maybe it’ll help us find other things we can report on.”

“Still.” Simon grumbled. “I’m not happy about the idea that maybe our followers are being followed themselves. Who watches the watchers?

“That’s easy.” Ava folded her arms. “The watched.”

Date Point 10y4m1w2d AV
North Clearwater County, Minnesota, USA, Earth.

Allison Buehler

“Look at her go.”

“I’m trying not to.”

Xiu had called her parents as soon as she’d finished signing the Byron Group paperwork, and what had ensued had been nearly an hour of alternately frantic, tired, pleading, apologetic and angry Mandarin, garnished with English and Gaori. There was something universal about an argument.

When the call had ended, Xiu had stood very still in the middle of the room for a few seconds, and had then vanished into her room. She had emerged less than a minute later having changed into her sportswear, and was now out on the grass in front of the house, punching and kicking the everloving crap out of the evening.

It was a showcase of startling speed. Allison blinked as she watched Xiu deliver three kicks to the sky in the space of a second, land on her heel and surge forward what looked like ten feet to deliver a straight-armed palm strike that Allison knew would have sent her flying with a broken sternum had she been on the receiving end.

She gave Julian a warm sideways glance. “You’re allowed to.” she said.

“Just… jeez, I’m no slouch in a fight, but the most I ever had to fight was exo-critters and ETs.” Julian mused. “She’d kick both our asses.”

“Well, she’d kick your ass." Allison teased. “I would have a gun."

“…Are you two gonna have a dick-measuring contest?” Julian asked.

“Why? You wanna watch?”

“I’ve heard worse ideas.”

That drew a laugh out of Allison. “Fine, Mister Voyeur. Watch away.”

She shoved the screen door open and the harsh noise it made, in addition to setting her teeth on edge - she really needed to take some WD-40 to it - snapped Xiu out of whatever headspace she’d gone to. The fierce engine of focused violence they’d been watching for the last few minutes vanished, and in her place was, well… Xiu, who tucked some errant hair back into place and smiled cautiously.

“Sorry.” she said, completely unnecessarily.

“You are so Canadian." Allison teased her. “You okay?”

“I am.” Xiu nodded. “I don’t blame Mama. She only just got her daughter back and here I am leaving again…”

“Hey, don’t get all melancholy on me.” Allison gave her an affectionately tomboyish hair-tousle. It didn’t achieve much with Xiu’s hair up, but it did generate the desired blush and, once Xiu had gripped her scalp defensively, a laugh.

“Sorry.”

“So Julian reckons you could kick both our asses.” Allison added conversationally as Xiu got her hair sorted out again.

“I could kick yours.” Xiu agreed, getting her revenge as Allison produced her best mock-offended jaw drop. “I bet you hit like a girl.”

“I bet you shoot like one.” Allison retorted. “I should teach you sometime.”

“You first.” Xiu told her. She shimmied her spine loose and settled into a solid, grounded stance. “Come on.”

“What, you’re gonna teach me Kung Fu?”

“No, you’re going to learn Gung Fu."

“What’s the difference?”

Xiu gave her a challenging look. “Shut up and let your Sifu show you." She said.

Allison glanced back at the house. Julian had leaned against the doorframe with his arms folded and a smile crawling up one side of his face as he watched.

“…Yes ma’am!” she shrugged.

Xiu beamed like she’d just won the lottery. “Good girl.” she said. “Now, this is called a Horse Stance… come on!”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Cairo, Egypt, Earth

Roy Vinther

Combat Controllers all knew each other. It was a law of the universe.

The corollary to that law was that any reunion between CCTs who hadn’t seen each other for more than an hour or so was foul-mouthed enough to make the Devil blush.

“Jesus fuckin’ Christ! Walsh! By some fuckin’ miracle you’re actually lookin’ good these days.”

Walsh stood up and shared an enormous hug with his massive SOR counterpart. “Firth you asshole, I wish I could say the same. Have you gained weight?”

“Sure as shit I’m eatin’ enough.” Firth drawled. “You fuck your sister yet? Always said I would if you didn’t get there first.”

“You still toppin’ Blaczynski?”

“Motherfuckerrr!”

There was laughter, a complicated handshake and a friendly tussle that ended with Firth heaving Walsh - a man who weighed somewhere north of three hundred pounds - high into the air like a child and giving him a bear-hug that must have been difficult to breathe around.

“You boys need some alone time?” Vinther asked. Still chuckling, the two Air Force men broke it up.

“Technical Sergeant Firth, this here’s Master Sergeant Vinther.” Walsh introduced him. “Exhibit B is Pavlopoulos, and that over there is Coombes.”

“This here’s Murray.” Firth said, standing aside to reveal a man who was only marginally larger than Walsh. “He don’t talk much. Say hi, Murray.”

Murray raised a hand - there was nothing shy in his demeanour, more a sense of composure. “Hi, Murray.”

“Two whole words. Means he likes ya.” Firth grinned.

“Good to have you. How much were you told?” Vinther asked, getting down to business.

“Our buddy’s ex-girlfriend is causing trouble again.” Firth said. “You’re watching her and we’re here to… Y’know, they never actually said.”

“Help.” Murray suggested.

“Well, yeah, help. But as I understand it this here’s a courtesy call, so you use us as you see fit."

“You don’t exactly blend in.” Pavlopoulos opined.

“Yeah, I’m more of the big dumb object.” Firth agreed. “Ain’t that right Murray?”

Vinther turned to where Murray was, only to discover that it was where Murray had been. The man himself had - apparently innocently - crossed the room without making a whisper of noise or drawing attention to himself, and was studying the map. He looked up and gave Firth an amiable nod.

“Murray might be sorta useful.” Firth added.

“And if you wanty break something.” Murray added, finally stringing together enough words for his Scottish accent to make itself known. “That big bastard’s no’ useless.”

“Why do I get the impression comin’ from you that’s high praise?” Vinther deadpanned. “Alright - callsigns. I’m BARKEEP, Pavlo’s HANGOVER, Coombes is BOUNCER, Walsh is DRINKIN’ BUDDY. I assume you get the scheme?”

“Guess I’ll go with, uh…” Firth began, but Murray interrupted him.

“LIGHTWEIGHT.” he said. Firth’s brotherly middle-finger and a ripple of laughter sealed it.

“Alright, fine.” The newly-christened ‘Lightweight’ snorted. “But just for that, and because you’re not Irish, you get to be GUINNESS."

Murray chuckled, but contrived to indicate with a smile and a motion of his head that he’d tolerate the handle.

Vinther chuckled. “Our POIs are KING - that’s Simon Harvey - QUEEN - Ava Rios - and PRINCE: Sean Harvey.”

“And where are they now?” Firth asked. Coombes glanced up from the camera he was monitoring and indicated out the window. The room they’d commandeered had an excellent view of the hotel’s lobby and front entrance.

“Pretty sure KING and QUEEN both made me when they got off the plane.” Coombes said. “They check into their rooms last night and that’s about it. Guess they’re planning their first move.”

“No point in havin’ us tail them.” Firth said. “She knows our faces and names.”

“She does?”

“Dude, she was our buddy’s girlfriend. Movie nights, drinkin’ nights, couple’a parties…”

“What happened, exactly?” Walsh asked.

“Uh, if we were to start calling PRINCE “Jody” instead…”

“Say no more.” Walsh scowled.

The phone rang, and Pavlopoulos grabbed it with a perfunctory “Go ahead.” A silent minute of attentive listening and note-scribbling later, he was able to hang up. “KING just made a couple’a interesting phone calls.” he said, handing his handwritten note to Walsh. “He’s got a friend in El Obour City, and another in Zagazig.”

Walsh interrogated his tablet, comparing the information on it to Pavlo’s note. “…Yeah, we know them. Dude in Zagazig’s with Egypt Daily News, and the guy in El Obour’s a, uh, blogger. Fancies himself a freelance reporter. We use him as a source ourselves. Reckon they’re about to move.”

“Coombes, stay here, watch the lobby and the drone.” Vinther ordered. “Everybody gear up.”

The room was a blitz of quick, efficient activity, at the end of which a casual observer would never have guessed that each man was armed. They took the fire escape to the car park in the basement: Vinther and Pavlo took one - a nondescript Chevrolet Opta - and Walsh piled into their much less discreet SUV alongside the two SOR men.

“Comms check.” Vinther ordered. The team sounded off in quick order. “Okay. BOUNCER?”

“Think they’re… yeah, they’re heading out the front door now. Drone’s got a lock.”

Their drone was an MBG “Flycatcher”, a small UAV developed by the Byron Group that used cutting-edge forcefield tech for both the flight surfaces and the optics. Eschewing an aerodynamic fuselage, the drone flew by “flapping” its forcefield wings like a bird, while its physical fuselage was little more than a dull mottled matte silver-grey object about the size and shape of a bulky laptop. Its forcefields and the advanced power storage systems that took up most of its physical volume allowed it to remain aloft day and night, especially in clear, hot weather. They’d launched it on day one arriving in Cairo, and had never had to land it since.

Now, its sophisticated forcefield-optic systems were trained on a perfectly ordinary taxi cab - one of thousands plying the city’s streets - but given that it could reliably track thousands of different targets at once, there was no fear of losing the target.

Guided by the feed Coombes was sending them over their tablets, the teams had no trouble at all in following it, navigating around snarls and traffic jams. “El Obour.” Pavlo noted, as Vinther turned back onto the cab’s tail on the Cairo ring road. Their car was as generic as they came on Egyptian streets but still, thanks to the drone they could turn off its tail every so often so as to throw off the appearance of being followed. Certainly, either the target didn’t notice the tail, or else were unconcerned of it.

“What’s El Obour like?” Firth asked, over comms.

“Depends.” Walsh opined. It’s got some nice bits, but the if the satellite footage is anything to go by, the neighborhood of the number they called is a fuckin’ dump."

“And they’re taking an unmarried young woman into that?” Murray asked.

“Greater Cairo’s fairly cosmopolitan.” Vinther told him. “It’s not like we’re in fuckin’ Taleb Afghanistan or whatever.”

“Besides, KING’s an experienced reporter.” Walsh added. “I doubt he’d take two newbies into a risky situation.”

“I never heard of the guy before.” Pavlo said.

“He’s the one who blew the lid on all those accidents at Hephaestus, and that shit with those cults in Bangladesh.” Walsh said. “Now he’s sniffing around here, in Qalqilya, in Saudi and Pakistan…”

“Hmm.” Vinther had to admit, that was a solid resume.

“Don’t fuckin’ say it, Vinther.” Pavlo told him, not broadcasting.

“Say what?” Vinther asked him, innocently

“You were thinkin’ this was gonna be the E-word.”

Vinther chuckled. “Easy?”

“Fuck sake." Pavlo rolled his eyes and checked the drone feed again. “One of these days you’re gonna jinx a mission beyond repair and I just pray I’m not there to suffer for it.”

“And one of these days you’re gonna figure out all these superstitions of yours don’t do shit." Vinther joked.

“Uh, guys…” Coombes got on the line again. “Company just got in touch. One of their recon satellites picked up an atmospheric disturbance over north Africa. Somebody’s got a bird in the air doing Mach eight.”

“Whereabouts over North Africa?” Vinther asked.

“Take a wild guess, BARKEEP.” Coombes replied. “Sat already lost track of it, so all we know is, our UFO’s around here somewhere.”

“Lost track of it?”

“It’s only the low-altitude ones that can track this shit, BARKEEP.” Coombes told him. “And they move fast. That spysat’s somewhere over Iceland by now.”

“When do we get coverage back?”

“Eighty, ninety minutes or so.”

Vinther glanced at Pavlo, who just raised an eyebrow at him. At length, he cleared his throat. “…Don’t say it.”

“Say what?” Pavlo asked, innocently.

“Don’t say ‘I told you so’."

Pavlo produced a grim laugh and checked his tablet again. “Yes, master sergeant.”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
HMS Caledonia, High orbit over Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds

Scott ‘Starfall’ Blaczynski

The problem with the Dominion’s general-purpose shuttle was that it looked, and flew, like a lead brick minus the actual lead brick’s lustre and frisson of danger. It was just a silvery grey cuboid with a window at one end and a ramp at the other.

It was also so large that it filled almost half Caledonia’s prep and flight deck. It was, after all, designed to be able to carry a Guvnurag or two. Humans could rattle around inside it like lottery balls.

Sikes in particular loathed it, and every time he laid eyes on it he did the same thing: He sighed and asked “When in the shit are we gonna get something human-built?”

“If it helps, you ain’t gonna have to put up with it for long.” Blaczynski told him. “Or did you forget we’re jumpin’ out of it?”

“You first, Starfall.” Titan told him.

“Lookin’ forward to it!” Blaczynski told him, and extended a gloved fist, which Titan reached out and rapped knuckles against. The EV-MASS was almost comforting nowadays, squeezing him tight and telling him that however hostile the vacuum of space might be, he had nothing to fear from it.

Plus, it added an extra heft and weight that just made him feel strong.

“Hey, Kovač?” He asked.

She looked up from testing the pH balance in his life support pack. “Yeah?”

“When the hell you gonna put on your big girl pants and make a move on ’Horse anyway?”

“I’ve got my big girl pants on." she replied. “Not yet.”

“No?”

“He’s not ready.” She told him.

“Yeah, quit trying to play wingman, B.” Titan agreed. “You suck at it.”

“Just tryin’a help my buddies out.”

Kovač smiled and gave him an affectionate slap on the helmet. “You’re good.” she said. “But stay out of my love life, Blaczynski. Even if it is a fucking desert right now.”

“Yes, tech sergeant.” Blaczynski smiled behind his mask. “I’m good to fly, right?”

“Good to fall.” she corrected him. “And, you get to listen to music this time."

“Fuckin’ sweet!” The team boxed fists, gave each other ringing clouts on the helmet, performed final equipment checks and piled into the shuttle.

Then it got boring.

The idea was for the shuttle to look to Perfection traffic control like an in- system passenger transport. Absurdly, its sensor signature was an order of magnitude larger than Caledonia’s, so all it had to do was leave the bay, pulse-warp to low orbit and it would look just like one of the thousands that came and went through Perfection’s skies every day.

The EV-MASS, meanwhile, had a sensor profile so small that if Perfection’s anti-aircraft defenses detected anything, it’d look like a tiny chunk of space debris doomed to burn up on re-entry.

The bit in the middle where the shuttle pulsed across ten AUs of empty space took hardly any time at all. Even at a paltry one kilolight, the journey was over in only five seconds. It was the sublight approach vector that was the slow bit. That involved sitting around for twenty minutes, joking and fidgeting and waiting.

When the pilot called that they were about to swing through the first drop zone, there was palpable relief. Blaczynski dropped the ramp and stood behind the atmosphere retaining forcefield, bouncing on the balls of his feet with his music up, waiting for the green light.

Titan called from the front “Whatcha listenin’ to, B?”

“Highway to Hell!”

“Good choice!”

“Twenty seconds.” the pilot called.

The timing wasn’t quite perfect - he’d have preferred to jump just as the guitar solo was starting or something - but who the fuck cared? The light turned green and B paused on the end of the ramp just long enough to turn, flip a salute to his buddies, and topple theatrically back into the void.

He nosed down and applied retro thrust, accelerating down into Perfection’s gravity well.

“EARS field.” Titan called. After what had happened to Thor, they were taking no chances - everyone went through the checklist during an EA Jump.

B checked it. “On.”

“Course?”

“On target.”

“EFDS.”

“Charged.”

“EWR."

“Ready.”

“View?”

“Fuckin’ spectacular!”

That was no understatement. Perfection filled half the sky, but that half was beautifully blue and green, both averaged slightly toward the turquoise compared to Earth, and minus Earth’s omnipresent mottling of cloud. Weather systems moved across Perfection in a leisurely, choreographed parade of predictable rainy cycles that had lasted for geological epochs.

He hit atmo and beamed at the halo of plasma as Perfection’s upper atmosphere compressed against his EARS field and ignited. A wild “YEEEEEEEHAAAAAAAAA!!!!!” carried him across a hundred kilometers in a blaze of fire.

First step after the plasma cleared was to re-establish contact. “Post-burn checkin.” he called.

“I have you, STARFALL.” Titan told him. “Course check?”

“Still on. Entering glide phase.”

The EARS field spread out and became wings, slowing and lifting his descent. The control interface was a little tricky - it was supposed to be like wearing a wingsuit, but in practice they still hadn’t quite managed to work out some latency issues, and the result felt sluggish and imprecise, but it worked. By spreading his arms and feet out, he was easily able to steer himself and fall through the rings his HUD was displaying for him.

This was a HALO jump. The moment his parachute opened, he’d appear on Perfection’s radar, so the idea was to open it as low and as briefly as possible so as to avoid detection.

First, he had to find the right spot. Caledonia’s extreme long range survey, the microsats they’d fired into orbit and the software was all well and good, but the final step was to land on the correct rooftop. He very, very nearly missed it.

Aware that there’d be some remedial training in response to his “woah shit" and the violent corrective maneuver he made at the very end of his long drop, he twisted through the air, corkscrewed past some high-rise apartments - no doubt giving the residents something to talk about - and ripped his ’chute at the last possible second, tensing his neck muscles to hold his head steady against the sudden snap of deceleration.

He hit hard, rolled, skidded to a halt on the edge of the roof, and then threw himself desperately onto the ’chute before a stray wind current could pick it up and drag him off into open air.

That done, he just had to lie still for a few seconds and giggle to himself.

“That,” he told the sky, “Is never gonna get old.”

He popped the release on his ’chute harness,folded it and weighed it down under his equipment pack, and set up on the edge of the roof overlooking the target landing platform. “REBAR, STARFALL. EA Jump complete, I’m in position.”

“Clear copy, STARFALL. Whatcha got for us?”

Blaczynski aimed his scoped rifle down at the ship and compared the alien writing on its nose to the intel on his tablet. “Got a match. November Charlie is still on the pad.”

He ran the scope over the parked ship. “Got… yeah, two Echo-Tangos. One’s a Blue-raff. Fat fucker, dead ringer for the ship’s tech… and, yup, there’s the Corti. Two out of three.”

“Intel said the pilot’s a Kwmbwrw.” Sikes pointed out.

“I don’t see ’em. Either way, target’s in sight. You’re clear to jump.”

“Thought you’d never ask…” Titan commented.

Blaczynski used the time his buddies were jumping in to set up his spotter computer on its tripod, calibrate his gun’s smartscope and get the beacon going to guide Rebar, Titan and Snapshot onto target.

Some minutes later, the guys called in that they were through the burn phase and into glide. Their icons appeared on his tracker as the flight systems synchronized and began to guide them in.

“Still no sign of that Kwmbwrw.”

“I’ll lay a stasis trap for her when we’re down and the ship’s secured.” Rebar called.

“Gotcha… and I have you in sight.” B replied, tracking three tiny falling shapes in his HUD. “You’re-”

There was a croaking, rattling noise from behind him which, when he frowned and turned towards it, turned out to be a couple of Vzk’tk police officers, aiming guns at him.

“STARFALL, REBAR. I didn’t copy your last.”

“Local law enforcement. You’re good to finish the drop?”

“We’re good. Don’t hurt ’em, B.”

“Wasn’t planning on it.” Blaczynski sent, and stood up. “Uh… Bar wheep grana wheep ninibong?”

The Vzk’tk rattled its percussive language at him again, and he finally remembered the translator clipped to his MOLLE.

He turned it on. “Howdy fellas.”

The translator gave the cops a note of desperation in their voice. “Don’t move, human! These are Irbzrkian stun guns, they were designed to be effective against your kind.”

B sighed. “Guys. Do everyone here a favor and forget you saw me, please? I’m just doin’ my job.”

“You’re under arrest for trespassing!” The shorter of the two police snapped. “Come quietly… please.”

B took a step closer. “That little zap-gun won’t do shit to me.” he said, matter-of-factly. “Now come on, go grab some donuts or whatever the fuck you guys eat, call me in as a large bird or whatever.”

They shot him. Twin arcs of crackling energy played over his EV-MASS without so much as tickling, and he sighed theatrically. He glanced over his shoulder and saw the Defenders popping their ’chutes for the final descent onto the platform.

“Okay. Fun’s over guys. Now I have to get mean.” He said. “Sorry.”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
El Obour City, Greater Cairo, Egypt, Earth

Robert Murray

“So she’s a cheater.”

“Yup.” A moment of white-hot anger lit Firth’s eyes for a second before he clamped down on it. “Horse is the nicest fuckin’ guy in the world, too, an’ that whore went an’ cheated on him with that skinny fuck Harvey."

Murray saw Walsh glance at him in the rear-view mirror, and shrugged and nodded.

Firth did not, apparently, think that this was satisfactory. “No, bro, give us your actual thoughts. I want at least ten words."

Murray’s face wrinkled briefly around a thoughtful sniff and he touched a thumb to his chin. “I love ‘Horse.” he said, finally. “You couldn’y find a better man if you searched the whole Earth tae fuck. But Legsy an’ Price, God rest ‘em both, they fuckin’ called it way before it happened.”

“RIP.” Firth aimed his eyes upward and touched his forehead, navel and shoulders. “But yeah, there you go.”

“What’s the full story, Murray?" Walsh asked.

“…Pricey’s exact words were ‘Neither of them are ready for a relationship’." Murray revealed, and cleared his throat.

“Ah.” Walsh nodded.

It was a subject Murray preferred to avoid, so it came as a relief when Vinther got on the radio. “Okay, they’ve gone into the apartment block. Murray, set up on the south side. Pavlo, Walsh, northeast. Firth, drive.”

They dismounted and got into position, and the two vehicles merged back into the traffic. It was simple enough to find a quiet spot where he could wait and watch. Okay, Scottish skin and hair weren’t exactly the local flavor, but Murray knew a lot about just existing in a way that completely bypassed all of a person’s perceptual instincts and just made them sort of… treat him as part of the landscape.

Vinther’s decision to keep Firth in the car was a sensible one. Firth was a genuine monster, completely unsuited to going unnoticed, even if he tried to dress down. Instead, he was dressed to play the opposite role and attract attention if need be, and so they’d stopped off at the “American Big and Tall” tourist shop before rendezvousing with the STS element to grab him some noticeable attire, and had succeeded beyond their wildest hopes. There was just something about a six-foot-seven titan wearing an aggressively ugly aloha shirt and board shorts cut for the five-hundred-pound obese market that drew the eye.

Murray’s conservative khaki slacks and navy blue rough cotton shirt went completely unnoticed.

Even in the shade the heat was oppressive, and he took the opportunity to re- apply his sun cream. Crue-D meant that sunburn was a minor irritation at worst, but why put up with it at all?

“Suffering, GUINNESS?” Vinther asked, as his car patrolled past.

Murray snorted - he’d forgotten his temporary new call sign - and waved reassuringly to the car.

Not much happened for a long time, and then the south entrance to the apartment building opened.

“GUINNESS has eyes on KING… PRINCE… and QUEEN. POIs in the street, south side.” he called.

“Copy that GUINNESS. Their rental’s waiting round the corner, west side. BARKEEP is watching it.” Vinther sent.

Murray nodded and watched Ava. She had her camera out and was-

-He saw her blink six feet backwards down the street, facing the wrong direction and with her camera holstered. In one instant she was walking behind the younger Harvey, and in the very next she was looking wildly around in abject bewilderment, as if searching for something that had suddenly vanished. A lone strong gust blew some trash and desert dust down the road in a miniature tornado.

“What th’-?” he began, having no idea how to report what he’d just seen.

“Something wrong?” Vinther asked.

“She just…glitched?”

“Whaddya mean, ‘glitched’?”

Murray frowned as Ava turned a full, confused circle, and the implications of what he’d just witnessed finally clicked into place. “…Ah, fuckin’ shite. Detain, right now!”

“Moving.”

Murray set off at a run, weaving through the traffic like it wasn’t there, and was behind Ava and grabbing her before she had a hope to see him coming.

He was relatively gentle with her, but Ava went from turning confusedly on the sidewalk to suddenly being pressed against the wall with her arms behind her back, securely held.

She didn’t take it well. “What the fuck?!"

“Easy Ava. It’s me: Murray.”

“Murray?!” She squirmed to try and escape. Up ahead, Sean and Simon turned back, saw what was happening and both started back to Ava’s aid before Walsh and Firth appeared out of the metaphorical woodwork and secured them both. “Get off me!”

If Firth was a little rougher with Sean than was strictly necessary, Murray decided not to comment. He didn’t have much sympathy for the lad himself, but then again, holding Sean’s cheek against the wall like that was treading the fine line of professionalism. Firth wasn’t going overboard, but he could have been gentler.

Ava plainly felt differently. “Firth, you hillbilly son of a crack whore, let him go!”

Firth gave her a narrow-eyed glare that spoke of his near-bottomless loathing for her for a shaved instant before his control returned. He pressed an implant scanner to Sean’s head, grunted at the green light, and all but threw the skinny young man over the sidewalk to lean against the car Vinther and Pavlopoulos had just arrived in.

“Oh, big bad man try’na prove it?” She spat. “I bet you cried when your daddy fucked you in the ass, you little bitch!"

Vinther snorted as he got out of the car. “Jeez, she’s got a mouth on her…”

Ava’s feet scuffled in the dirt as she tried to fight back. “Murray, you let me go right now." She snarled. Murray yanked his scanner of his belt and pressed it to her head. It pinged a happy green and he relaxed.

Firth apparently wasn’t satisfied. “Double check.” he snapped, shoving his own scanner into Murray’s hand.

“…Still green.” Murray confirmed, after repeating the test. Firth snorted and stalked away to bundle Sean into the SUV.

Ava at least cooled a little with him gone. “Happy?” she demanded. “You gonna let me go now?”

“Sorry, Ava.” Murray zipped some plastic handcuffs around her wrists.

“Murray, for fuck’s sake…"

“Come on, lassy, settle down. Please.” Murray requested, calmly. “You stepped in some shite, that’s all.”

“Good!” She snapped, then sighed and finally relaxed. “…Fine.”

“Thanks, Ava. Gonny frisk you for weapons now.”

“Whatever.”

She grumbled something that sounded inventively vulgar in Spanish as Murray gave her a businesslike and efficient patdown, finding nothing more than her camera, phone, passport and press ID.

“Walsh?” He asked.

“Hey, you’ve got the entertaining one." Walsh patted Simon Harvey reassuringly on the shoulder. The journalist looked more bored and resigned than upset. “Mine’s good as gold.”

“Right. Inty the van with him, then.” Murray proclaimed. Ava had finally settled into sullen silence and allowed him to steer her firmly into the Chevrolet to sit on the back seat next to Pavlo.

As soon as the door closed, Vinther covered his mouth to hide a huge grin. “God damn! I don’t know who taught that girl to swear, but she could give me lessons." he commented.

“She’s even worse in Spanish.” Firth grunted as he circled round the SUV to get into it, plainly not amused. “Beats the fuck outta me how ’Horse used to put up with it.”

Chuckling to himself, Vinther got into the Chevrolet’s driver seat, and Murray settled into the back seat, sandwiching Ava between himself and the mercifully much smaller Pavlopoulos.

“Just what in the shit is going on?” She demanded, as soon as they were moving.

“Canny tell you.” Murray said.

“Come on, Murray, it’s me. You can’t give me anything?"

“Lassy,” Murray warned her as he fastened her seatbelt, “Don’t mistake my civil treatment for liking you.”

Ava stopped squirming against her cuffs and went still. Suddenly looking hurt and sad and small, she slouched in the middle seat, staring at her knees.

They were back on the Cairo Ring Road before she spoke again. “…How is he?”

“Have you no’ seen the news?”

“Yeah, yeah, the whole Beef Brothers thing.” She tried to wave hand dismissively and only succeeded in twitching her shoulder awkwardly. “I mean… how’s he doing? Is he okay?”

“He’s okay.”

“…Thanks.”

She was quiet and well-behaved all the way back.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds

Harry ‘Rebar’ Vandenberg

Akiyama was the first to land, and he did so with characteristic precision, slamming his ’chute open, swinging on the sudden change of momentum, and ballet-stepping neatly onto the target landing platform, his carbine already raised and aimed.

Sikes was only a second or two behind him, and announced his arrival with a higher-velocity landing that must have left the deck reverberating.

If the Corti target felt any emotions at all at this sudden arrival, it - he - didn’t betray them. Those huge black eyes flicked from one man to the other and, very calmly, it raised its hands in surrender.

The Vz’ktk was rather less phlegmatic about the whole thing. It produced a panic noise somewhere between a hoot and the sound of a man clog-dancing on bubblewrap, and turned to run.

Vz’ktk had a decent turn of speed on them when they needed it - nothing that could outrun a human of course, but still quick enough that the situation needed controlling now before anything regrettable happened. Rebar angled his descent, popped his ’chute, and then deployed a trick that they’d worked out only SOR could get away with, thanks to the incredible ankle support offered by the EV-MASS - he hit the ’chute’s release while he was still a good six feet up.

Intimidation tactics really didn’t come any better than slamming into the deck like a human meteor some meters in front of the panicking alien, which was promptly corralled. It spun, looking for an exit, then in response to some kind of barked order from the Corti, it spread its arms in surrender.

The plan was going off almost without a hitch. Titan darted up the ship’s ramp to commandeer its computer systems before the Corti could muck with them via some neural cybernetic controller or whatever, and Sikes began patiently explaining through his translator that the two beings were now detained for questioning.

“REBAR, TITAN.” Akiyama called. “Ship’s empty. No pilot on board. Pulling the memory.”

“Copy that, TITAN. STARFALL, REBAR: You okay up there?”

There was a pause that was a little too long and then - “REBAR, STARFALL. Situation’s under control.”

“You didn’t hurt ’em?”

“Just introduced ET to duct tape, that’s all. They’re fine.”

“Good. Laying a stasis trap for the pilot.”

Snapshot nodded and bundled the two aliens onto their ship, and Rebar released his pack to grab the stasis trap

The trap was one of Titan’s gizmos and what it lacked in aesthetics - it was little more than a laser tripwire, a small computer card and the stasis field generator taped to a power pack - it made up for in effectiveness. Anything that crossed the beam would instantly be contained within the stasis field, which would collapse when the power pack was dry about two minutes later: more than enough time for the victim to be surrounded ready for capture.

Once it was attached to a wall, crate, or any other vertical surface through the simple medium of the SOR’s best friend - duct tape - all they had to do was sit and wait.

That was the theory, at least. What happened was that Rebar was still in the process of sticking it to some kind of cargo-handling drone when the pilot ambled unconcernedly around the corner.

They stared at each other for a moment, calculating how to react.

“…Well.” Rebar cleared his throat. “This is awkward.”

The pilot turned and ran.

“Fuck!” Rebar surged to his feet and took off in pursuit, but Kwmbwrw had long legs and this one had a large head start. Firth would have had no trouble catching up to it, but Defenders weren’t built for speed - Rebar was only marginally faster than his quarry.

“STARFALL, REBAR! The pilot just showed up, she’s rabbiting!”

“I see her. Sending up the drone.” You could say a lot about Blaczynski - his wild party lifestyle, his egregiously ugly tattoos, his chronic ability to stick his foot in his mouth - but when it came down to the wire, he was an absolutely top quality operator, an ice-cold Combat Controller whose awareness of the operational space bordered on the supernatural. “Take a right off the end of the platform… hundred yards. You’re gaining.”

Rebar caught a glimpse of curly chocolate fur up ahead, but lost it just as quickly behind a huge supporting beam that was part of the vital superstructure for the skyscraper that towered above him.

“Second left in a hundred yards.” B called. “…Civilian ETs in your way, check your movement.”

Rebar gritted his teeth and somehow found a higher gear from somewhere, felt the deck ring and shake under him as he put his training and the EV-MASS through their paces. He shot past a bewildered knot of Robalin and angled down the sharp left that Blaczynski had indicated.

“Crowd’s slowing her down, keep it up REBAR.”

Vandenberg could see why. The fleeing pilot was bullying her way through the crowd, knocking spindly Vz’ktk and other fragile life forms out of her way. She could get away with it - for all her size, she wasn’t deathworld-dense, and could shoulder-check people out of her way without committing murder. If Rebar had tried the same trick, he’d have pulped somebody.

He raised his voice and roared. “GET OUT OF MY WAY!!!”

It worked - alarmed beings turned, saw a charging deathworlder in heavy armor and wisely decided not to impede his progress. Their reactions were so slow though, and some of the further ones didn’t even hear him. One large Vgork loitered in the path left by the escaping Kwmbwrw and was slow on the uptake even when Vandenberg yelled at it to move.

Up ahead, his quarry dashed right and vanished from view.

“Visual contact interrupted.” B called. “Trying to reacquire…”

Rebar shouldered gently but firmly through a bewildered huddle of aliens and made it as far as the intersection. His heart sank. The crowd was just as dense, and while there were several Kwmbwrw standing around, not one of them resembled the target.

“Contact lost.” he declared, knowing the pursuit was a failure.

“..Contact lost.” Blaczynski agreed. If he had no idea which way the alien had gone, then Rebar doubted there was any hope of re-acquiring her. “Better get outta there, Reeb. Cops’ll be coming.”

Aliens scattered away from him as Rebar spat a furious curse into his mask and set off at a jog back the way he’d come.

“We good to get outta here?” he asked.

“Just need Starfall in the driving seat, REBAR.” Titan called. “Data’s secure.”

“And our two ETs are confined to quarters.” Sikes added.

A vehicle of some kind swooped low overhead, covered in flashing lights and howling. Some things, it seemed, were universal. Fortunately, it apparently failed to notice Rebar. “Credit where it’s due…” he grunted, picking up the pace. “Local police are quick on the uptake.”

“Think me having two of their buddies tied up here might have something to do with that…” Blaczynski commented. “We need off this planet ASAP.”

Rebar gritted his teeth and stepped up into a full run again. “Get off that rooftop.” he ordered.

“Don’t need to tell me twice…”

As he pounded back along the promenade, Rebar saw B pause on the edge of his rooftop, flip a jaunty salute to his two captives, then grab his zipline and plunge toward the ship.

Rebar scooped up his abandoned gear on the way past, and they met at the bottom of the ship’s ramp and banged fists together. “Get ’em next time, Reeb.” B told him, slapping his shoulder.

“Would have… preferred…” Rebar panted. Sprinting in EV-MASS was a task to drain even the most conditioned athlete. " To get ’em… this time…"

B nodded, turned, caught the drone as it glided down out of the sky, and hugged it to his chest before vanishing up the ramp and hanging a right onto the Negotiable Curiosity’s flight deck.

Rebar followed and settled himself into the command chair, sucking on the sippy straw inside his mask in a bid to restore some of the reserves he’d just incinerated during the pursuit. It creaked a little as several hundred pounds of man and armored space suit tested its engineering, but did little more than that.

“How long ’til we’re in the air?” he asked.

“Just getting clearance from local traffic control.” Blaczynski said. “Wouldn’t wanna get smeared all over downtown by the AA because we didn’t ask nicely… Done. Flight clearance received.”

He waved a hand through the volumetric controls and grunted happily as the ship hoisted itself off the pad and pulled in its ramp and landing gear.

“They’re letting us fly in a zone with a security alert?” Vandenberg asked.

“Don’t question it, bro.” Blaczynski advised him, and finished laying in their flight plan and speed.

Rebar fidgeted awkwardly nonetheless, fully expecting interceptors or a ground AA station to abruptly latch onto them and make awkward demands like ordering them to land. It was a profound relief when they hit the minimum warp altitude and Starfall pulsed the drive.

The Negotiable Curiosity was much faster than the shuttle. What had been a five second trip in the shuttle was over before Blaczynski had even removed his hand from the control to activate the FTL.

“Okay… HMS Caledonia, this is SOR one-oh-seven flying November Charlie, we’re at RP Alpha." Blaczynski called.

Rebar studied the holographic sphere that was the ship’s sensor display. “Where are they?”

“If they’re running cold we shouldn’t see them anyway, but… hmm…” Blaczynski turned in his seat. “Yo, Titaaan?!

Akiyama clanked up the deck and stuck his head through the door. “’Sup?”

“Did you fuck with the navcomp?”

“Nuh-uh.”

“Something wrong?” Rebar asked.

B nodded, and hit the comms again. “HMS Caledonia I say again: Sierra Oscar Romeo One Zero Seven STARFALL flying November Charlie, operational objectives achieved, we are at the rendezvous point. Come back, over."

They strained to listen. A few trillion photons, some portion of which had been traversing the endless night since the cooling of the early universe, reached their journey’s end in Negotiable Curiosity’s communications sensor array as an unregarded quiet hiss.

“…What’s our contingency for Caledonia being a no-show?" Akiyama asked, quietly.

“Loiter at RP Bravo in low emissions mode for no longer than eight hours.” Blaczynski said, enacting exactly that plan. The ship turned, lurched briefly through superluminal space, and then went dark as soon as it was safely back below lightspeed. “Then make best speed for Cimbrean. Treat Caledonia and all its crew as orange until definitively established otherwise. Do not dock with Caledonia nor share confidential information over comms with any of her crew unless and until they have been proven green."

“Why the loiter?” Vandenberg asked.

“’Cause it could be technical problems or something innocent and they might need the escort.” B replied. “And… hell, if something compromised Cally then humanity’s fucked anyway, ’cause they’ve got the jump codes for Earth and Cimbrean."

“Unless they managed to scrub the computer before they were taken over.” Titan pointed out.

“Yeah, well… Whatever’s going on, eight hours gives them time to fix the problem and get in touch, or broadcast an SOS to the RP. ”

Rebar took a look out the window as if that might achieve anything. Even if it was right next to them, Caledonia’s matte-black hull would have been invisible anyway. “Okay, well… Grab an MRE and settle in, guys.” He advised. “Guess it’s time to hurry up and wait.”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
US Embassy, Cairo, Egypt, Earth

Ava Rios

The good news was that they’d taken the plastic zip tie off her, and her hands were no longer bound behind her back.

The bad news was that they’d put some metal handcuffs on her, and her hands were now bound in front of her. While this was admittedly an improvement, it didn’t exactly feel like Everest had been climbed.

Still. The air conditioning was on. That was nice.

The big dude in the suit who’d taken over from Murray in looking after her managed the impressive feat of being even more impenetrably taciturn than Murray himself, who was friendly and engaging even if he preferred to deploy his words like an old lady counting out pennies.

This guy was a human wall in a badly-tailored black suit.

There was nothing to do for what felt like hours, and not in the sense of a boring twenty minutes or so, but in the literal sense that the day had probably been and gone and the sun had probably set. Ava was bored out of her mind, growing increasingly tired and sleepy and there was nothing to do except fidget, sit and think, try and get comfortable. The only way to try and keep track of the time was counting the number of times that Man-wall was periodically replaced by a slightly different Man-wall.

Eventually she folded her arms on the table and tried to grab a nap. She wasn’t sure if it worked - maybe it wasn’t long after that point that the door opened, or maybe she successfully dozed for a while - but either way she sat up and blinked when somebody new entered the room.

The new arrival was a woman in her… early forties, if Ava was any judge, with hair that plainly hadn’t had more than a quick lunchtime meeting with a brush today, and her arms full of too many things - a laptop, her phone, several paper folders, some pens, a coffee mug…

Unlike literally everybody she’d dealt with in the last few hours, the newcomer immediately won some points by not looking either totally composed and emotionless, or pissed off. Mostly, she looked like she was a plate- spinner with lots to stay on top of, but she gave the impression that Ava, while being another plate, wasn’t actually an unwelcome one.

She managed to get the ungainly armful of stuff she was carrying safely onto the table, offered a warm smile and shook Ava’s cuffed hand. “Hello Miss Rios. My name’s Darcy.”

“Hi, Darcy.” Ava managed, sitting up a little straighter.

Darcy sat down. “Do you, uh, do you mind if I call you Ava?” she asked.

“Please do…” Ava calculated for a few seconds as Darcy got settled, and decided to go with completely open honesty. Somehow, it seemed like the only card that stood a chance of working. “Darcy, please, what the hell is going on?"

“…At the risk of sounding like I’m dodging the question,” Darcy replied, adjusting her seat, failing, and trying to adjust it again. Ava found herself warming to the woman’s dorky, busy energy. “What do you think is going on?"

“Can’t you just tell me?”

“Believe me, I would if I could.” Darcy offered an apologetic smile.

“Why can’t you?" Ava asked her. “What’s so goddamn important?!”

Darcy smiled and shrugged. “I can’t even tell you why I can’t tell you. Stupid, isn’t it?"

Ava sat back as far as being handcuffed to the table would let her. “You got that right.” she agreed.

“So… what do you think is going on?" Darcy repeated.

“What do I think?” Ava asked. “I think we’ve got a deadly enemy out there.” She tried to gesture through the wall and winced as the cuffs stopped her hands with a painful jolt. “An alien enemy.” she elaborated instead. “I think they blew up my my home, killed my family, murdered my friend… I think they have a spaceship here on Earth, I think they can control people through implants in their brains, and I think they stole a bunch of Pakistani nukes to try and start World War Three in the middle east. It’s either that or I’m hopelessly paranoid."

She awarded herself some brownie points as Darcy cleared her throat and examined her laptop. That, Ava judged, was evidence of a solid hit.

“That’s… an extraordinary claim.” Darcy said, carefully.

“Yeah.” Ava agreed. “Usually I’d keep it to myself, but… I mean, I’m chained to a desk and I’m talking to an MIB.” She shrugged. “I figure I’m onto something at least."

“I could probably do something about the chained to the desk part.” Darcy offered.

“That’d be nice…?” Ava asked, hopefully.

Darcy nodded to the human wall, who nodded and took Ava’s cuffs off entirely. The opportunity to rub at the sore spots on her wrists and shake her shoulders loose was a kind of minor ecstasy.

“Why do you want to know?” Darcy asked.

“Why-?” Ava gesticulated as if the answer was obvious. “Because I want to do something!"

“Do what?”

“Anything!” Ava told her. “Something! I don’t know what, but…”

Darcy gave a sympathetic nod, and typed a quick note on her laptop. “I can definitely appreciate that sentiment.” she said. “Do you need a minute to think about what exactly you mean? ‘Anything’ can mean… well, a lot."

“I don’t think another minute would help.” Ava shrugged. “I’ve tried… I guess you know about me and Ada- uh, Staff Sergeant Ares, right?”

Darcy just nodded.

“…I tried being there for him. Being, like, his anchor or his foundation or whatever. I fucked that up bad. I just… I know I’m not suited for the military life. What does that leave me with? I thought maybe if I could dig up the truth, I’d be able to think of something…"

“And what would you have done with the truth, whatever it was?” Darcy asked. “What would you have done if, say, everything you suspect turned out to be completely accurate?”

“I don’t know.” Ava confessed. “…I don’t know.”

Darcy smiled sympathetically, closed her laptop, and handed her a paper handkerchief.

“You can do something, you know." she said.

Ava wiped her eyes dry and sat forward. “Do what?”

“Tell me what exactly happened to you on that street corner, just before Sergeant Murray detained you."

Ava nodded, and composed her thoughts.

“I was following Simon and Sean.” she said. “We’d just spoken to this blogger guy, he’d been poking around that gunfight and some reports of UFOs. He said that there was a woman we should try and find, she’d been kidnapped and her mother murdered. Gave us a name and some addresses we might try…”

Darcy picked up her coffee. She didn’t drink it, just held it warmly in both hands.

“…We were on our way back to the car when… it was like time stopped for everything except me. The cars stopped moving, Simon and Sean stopped moving… hell, the air stopped moving. It felt solid, I couldn’t… I was stuck in this little circle and couldn’t get out. And then Suit Guy was there."

“Suit Guy?” Darcy asked.

“He was at the airport when we got off the plane. Did a pretty good job of acting like an ordinary member of the public, but I saw him watching us. He looked like a… a businessman, or something. He had a nice suit on, an expensive watch, he had short hair, a mustache, no beard… you know. I figured he was with you guys, maybe.”

“What did he do?”

“Nothing, really. He said ‘hello’, told me not to be alarmed. He said that he wanted to speak with me - me personally - and that he had questions for me, and answers too.”

“Did he give you anything, or take anything from you?”

“He gave me some numbers.” Ava nodded. " I entered them on my phone. I think they’re coordinates, or maybe like a ZIP code or whatever the Egyptian version is? I don’t know. They’re a way to find him."

“He specifically said he wanted to speak to you?" Darcy confirmed.

“Yeah.”

“And then what happened?”

“He… vanished.” Ava snapped her fingers for emphasis. “And everything started moving again. And, I was so busy looking for where he’d gone that I didn’t even see Murray until I was up against the wall.”

“Did Suit Guy tell you his name?”

Ava shook her head. “Sort of. He told me to call him by a number.” she said. “Six.”

Darcy gnawed thoughtfully on the end of her pen. “And… did he say why he wanted to speak with you?" she asked.

“I asked him that. He just said something really cryptic and vanished.” Ava told her. “He said, uh… He said… something about… basketball?”

Darcy quite wisely stayed silent and let her think hard as she tried to recall the particular words Six had used.

“He said…” She exhaled in frustration, and it finally came to her. “He said… ‘Because only humans would play basketball with their prisoners’."

“I see.” Darcy nodded. “And, did anything else stand out to you?”

“He said ‘humans’. As if he’s not human himself…" Ava thought long and hard. “I’m sorry. It was just sudden and confusing and I guess maybe I was freaking out a bit. I can’t think of much else.”

“That’s okay.”

“Can I ask you some questions now?"

Darcy put her coffee down. “Yes….” She said. “But I might not be able to answer.”

“I understand.” Ava promised.

She ran her fingers through her hair to try and sort out what her most pressing need was.

“…Is there anything I can do?" she asked.

“You’ve already done a lot.” Darcy said.

“What, by coming to Egypt and getting caught up in stuff I only suspect I understand?"

“By answering honestly and openly. You’ve said a lot, and it will help. It’ll especially help the SOR.”

Ava nodded and looked away. “Too bad they hate me.”

Darcy gave her a long, slow, calculating look, and then she put down her pen. “Do you mind if I go a bit beyond the relationship between interviewer and detainee for a second, and give you some life advice?” she asked.

Ava blinked at her, then indicated for her to go ahead.

“My job - a big part of my job - involves figuring people out and giving them what they want to see, and telling them what they want to hear, so that they’ll open up to me. It’s… rarer that I’m ethically able to tell people what they need to hear so that I can help them." She said.

Ava nodded, listening.

“We’ve only just met, but I’ve learned to trust my instincts about people. And I think you have good intentions.”

Ava gave a defeated shake of her head. “The road to Hell is paved with good intentions.”

“So is the road to Heaven: The difference is judgement.” Darcy replied. “And good judgement can come with experience, perspective and education.”

“So your advice is…?”

“You have… fixations. Your home, your late friend, your ex-boyfriend… your Big Secret that you came here to uncover. I admire that, really: you’re tenacious. Stubborn. Driven. And it all comes from a very good place, but you’re burning yourself up because you’re trying to do it all yourself and you won’t let other people be strong for you when you’ve run out of strength for yourself. You need to learn how to let go and be weak when you need to."

“Weak?”

“Everybody’s allowed to be weak sometimes.” Darcy said. “There’s no sense in trying to run on a broken leg.”

Ava shook her head. “I don’t… I want to be a good person. I don’t want to burden people with my problems. Is that wrong?”

Darcy smiled and began to gather her stuff. “For what it’s worth?” she said, standing up. “I think you are a good person. I think you’ll achieve good things, if you give yourself the time you need to heal first. And the people who really care about you want to be burdened with your problems: Let them help you, and things will turn around. That’s my advice."

She left, and Ava found herself sitting alone except for the man-wall.

Determined not to cry in front of a stranger - or at all, if she could help it

she settled for getting up and taking a tentative stroll around the room to work some of the stiffness out. Man-wall didn’t respond.

“Anyone ever tell you you look kinda like Dwayne Johnson?” she asked him. This elicited no response. “So… What happens now?” she pressed. “Am I being released, or…?”

The door clicked open and one of the other man-walls stepped in. “This way please, Miss Rios.” he requested.

Ava edged around the table, cautiously. “…No handcuffs?”

“No.”

“Okay…” She cleared her throat and followed Man-wall number two into the hallway outside.

They weren’t in a large building, and all he really did was show her from one door to another on the same floor. This new one was more comfortably arranged, with a couple of couches, a coffee machine and a television on the wall, plus a few synthetic plants and some framed landscape photographs on the walls. Comfortable, but impersonal. Simon and Sean stood up as she was gently ushered inside.

“You okay?” Sean asked.

Ava nodded. “Never thought I’d get life advice from an MIB.” she said.

“Life advice?” Simon asked.

“Just… some words of wisdom to think on.” Ava yawned. “Jeez, how long was I in there?”

“It’s four in the morning, local time.” Simon revealed. “By your personal clock, you’ve been up all night.”

“…what happens now?”

“Now? You get some sleep.” Simon ordered, pointing to the longer couch. “I think we’ll be here a bit longer.”

“You mean ‘a bit’ in the British sense, right?”

“Sleep while you can.” Simon repeated.

“What about you guys?”

“Sleep.” Sean stressed. He grabbed a blanket from the back of the short couch and handed it to her. “We’ve been napping, we’re fine, but you look like death warmed up.”

Stubborn as she was, Ava seriously thought about folding her arms and staying awake, but instead she rolled her eyes, took the blanket and gave up.

“Fine, fine, you charming ass.” She threw it round her shoulders, kicked her shoes off and sank onto the couch, which damn near swallowed her. Her fatigue caught up and hit her like snow falling off a roof. She yawned, and shook her head to try and clear it. “Jeez… Okay…”

“Go on, duck. We’ll wake you up if anything happens.” Sean told her.

“Quit nagging…” Ava grumbled, but lay down and turned on her side until she was comfortable. “You’re worse than an old woman…”

He didn’t reply, and she put her head down and tried to sleep.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Allied Extrasolar Command, Scotch Creek, British Columbia, Canada, Earth.

Owen Powell

“You’ve got to be fookin’ joking!”

If Special Agent Darcy didn’t take Powell’s disbelief well, she did a good job of not showing it. Even writ large on the wall TV in General Tremblay’s office via a camera in Cairo, her face didn’t betray any emotion save earnest seriousness. “No, major. I’m absolutely certain that she was telling the truth about Six saying he wanted to speak to her specifically, and I’m satisfied that allowing that meeting to take place is the correct course of action."

“You’re asking me to let you send two of my men into what could well be a trap on the say-so of a civilian with a known history of infidelity.” Powell returned. "And you’re proposing that we allow this woman, who’s aptly bloody demonstrated that she fundamentally can’t be trusted, to learn top secret information."

“I disagree.” Darcy countered. “I’d stake my professional reputation on it that you’re badly misjudging her, major.”

“You bloody will be if this goes ahead!” Powell retorted.

General Tremblay waved Powell down and threw in his opinion. “Powell’s got good reason to be reluctant, agent Darcy. There are significant trust issues involved.”

“The major and his men may not think she can be trusted, general: I do. And with all due respect to the major, it’s my job to assess who can and cannot be trusted."

“And the rationale for allowing this meeting to take place, rather than simply detaining him?” Tremblay asked.

“This isn’t like the roller derby attack. Six has been on Earth for some time now and has evaded detection throughout. If we try and detain him, he’ll just slip away - migrate to another host body or effect an escape somehow.” Darcy explained. “And this is too good an opportunity to miss, general. We could gain real insight into Hierarchy operations on Earth by doing this, maybe even take a step towards securing the planet.”

“And that can only be achieved if we let him talk to Rios?” Tremblay asked. “He wouldn’t be open to meeting, say, you?”

“Our psych profile on Six suggests that what he’s doing is testing us, general. We think he wants an ally that he can work with, one who’ll scratch his back so he can scratch theirs. Ours.”

“All for nowt if that treacherous girl leaks DEEP RELIC to the world.” Powell said.

“If the Hierarchy had the ability to panic and inflict real harm on us, they would have by now.” Darcy shook her head.

“They have four nukes.” Tremblay observed.

“Which is nothing next to what they could do to us if they managed to get even one wormhole beacon on this side of the barrier." Darcy said. “We think their play this whole time has been to try and find a buyer for those bombs who can pay them with a beacon: Several… violent parties have been fishing around in search of wormhole beacons since the Zulfiqar was hit."

Tremblay rubbed his chin, and turned his chair. Admiral Sir Patrick Knight had been summoned from Cimbrean for this meeting, and was standing by the window running his index finger thoughtfully across his lips. “You’ve been quiet so far, admiral.” he commented.

Knight shot a sympathetic glance at Powell, but nodded to the screen. “Agent Darcy makes a compelling argument.” he said.

“Sirs, I really must object in the strongest-” Powell began.

“Powell old chap, I know you must.” Knight interrupted, reassuringly. “I have misgivings about the girl myself. But we must rationally weigh the pros and cons.”

“…Yes, admiral.”

Tremblay cleared his throat. “Powell, this is too good an opportunity to pass up. Much too good. If you’re concerned about the situation and security, then I’ll give you the command and you can see it done right, with whatever resources you deem necessary.”

“Which of course puts you in a position to stress to miss Rios the seriousness of the consequences should she betray trust again.” Knight added. “I’m sure you can be more than adequately persuasive.”

Powell snorted. “Put the fear of God into her, you mean.”

“I rather think the fear of Powell will suffice.” Knight observed.

“…I’ll want the beef brothers in EV-MASS, my own EV-MASS, a plane for us to jump out of, a jet with a HARM on it in case that UFO shows up, and close air support.” Powell listed.

“You’ll have them.” Tremblay told him. “Agent Darcy?”

“Just so long as the big guns only come in if the shit hits the fan.” Darcy said. “We don’t want Six to spook.”

“Aye.” Powell agreed. “As you wish.”

Darcy visibly relaxed a little. “Thank you major. I appreciate it.”

“I hope you’re right about her” Powell said. “Believe you me, I’ll be very happy if you are.”

Darcy nodded. “I’ll see you in the field.” she said. “General, admiral. Thank you.”

Tremblay and Knight nodded for her, and she ended the call.

Powell worked his jaw thoughtfully at the blank screen for a second and then turned to the general. “I’d better see it done then.”

“Thank you for your forbearance, major.” Tremblay said, rising to shake his hand. “Good luck.”

“Thank you sir.” Powell returned the shake. “Here’s hoping I don’t bloody need it.”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
US Embassy, Cairo, Egypt, Earth

Sean Harvey

The fact that he’d just been spoken to finally percolated into Sean’s consciousness. He blinked and looked up.

“Hmm?”

“I said, staring at her like that won’t get you back together, Sean.” Simon told him.

Sean shook his head and rubbed his face. “I was a million miles away.” he said.

“In whose bed?” Simon asked, light-heartedly. He was patrolling slowly around the room, apparently quite composed and happy.

“Simon…”

“Mate, don’t play innocent with me. I’ve known you since you were born and I know when you’re pathetically in love.”

Sean snorted and turned to sit sideways across the couch. “That’s in the past.” he said.

“Not by choice, hmm?” Simon observed. “Still, it explains that Firth chap’s rough treatment of you.”

“Lay off.”

Simon shook his head, and ruffled his nephew’s hair. “You bloody idiot.” he said, fondly.

Sean ducked out from under his hand. “Why are we still here, anyway? She should be asleep in a hotel room, not on a sofa. We should be sleeping in beds too for that matter."

“Because they’ve not asked us to leave yet.” Simon told him.

“Don’t we have rights?” Sean asked.

“Yes, and by and large you can rely on the Yanks to honour them.” Simon told him. “Besides, nothing makes you look more suspicious than kicking up a stink when you don’t need to. Good advice for when you’re arrested, that.”

“What, go limp and visit your happy place? Fan-fucking-tastic advice, Simon.”

“Don’t be a twat. I’m telling you, the trick in these situations is to be calm, be honest, and let things happen. These people can make your life profoundly awkward, nephew mine, but it’s usually more hassle than they can be bothered with.” Simon about-faced and started patrolling the room anticlockwise instead. “Which means it’s a good idea not to give them a reason to bother. Be polite and cooperative, be nice and friendly if you can manage it, and they’ll give you a shove out the door sooner rather than later."

“Right now, I’d settle for a fucking sandwich.” Sean grumbled.

Simon shrugged and knocked on the door. Immediately, one of the sapient security slabs opened it. “Can I help you?”

“Sorry to bother you…” Simon smiled at the man, noticeably exaggerating his accent a little. “But we’ve been here rather a long time and we’re getting a bit peckish. I don’t suppose there’s any way…?”

“I’ll have some food brought up.” the guard replied. “You got everything you need in there?”

“If you could spare us another blanket, it’d be much appreciated…?”

“Sure, I’ll see what I can do.”

“Thanks ever so much.” Simon aimed a smug look at Sean the second the door closed again.

“Oh yes, thank you awfully, wot?" Sean parodied.

“Ra_ther_.” Simon chuckled, and resumed his stately lap of the room. “Now how do you think that would have gone if I’d been all ‘I have rights! I demand you bring me a filet mignon this instant and I want to speak to the King bwah bwah bwah…’?" he imitated a kind of pompous clucking.

“Point made…” Sean waved a hand irritably. He sat back and tried to entertain himself by multiplying the ceiling tiles and searching for patterns in the carpet.

He was painstakingly weighing up whether a particular pattern of shade under the coffee table more closely resembled a man wearing a bowler hat or a man wearing a trilby when there was a knock on the door and a couple of embassy staff members delivered two folded blankets and some trays with three sandwiches, three mugs, an insulated flask of hot water and an assortment of coffee, tea, sugar and a small jug of milk, some chocolate bars and a tube of Pringles.

They woke Ava, who, after some yawning and stretching, caused one of the sandwiches to vanish, inhaled slightly more than her share of the Pringles, polished off two Snickers and self-medicated with a drink that was less a coffee and more a triple-strength coffee flavored syrup.

“Considering you only got two hour’s sleep, you look refreshed.” Sean told her.

“I feel refreshed.” She replied. “No news? Are they letting us go?”

“We’ll see.” Simon replied, amicably. “I get the impression we really did barge into something huge here, and if there’s one thing governments don’t like, it’s reporters all over their biggest secrets."

“What are they afraid of?” Sean asked.

“That depends on the secret.” Ava told him.

“Well what good do secrets do?” He insisted. “They come out eventually, and then you’re the one who was lying to everyone. We’ve lived that, you and me. Haven’t we? You and I both know that dishonesty for the greater good doesn’t work."

“He’s right, Ava.” Simon agreed. “Secrets and lies only hurt people.”

Ava folded her arms uncertainly, then frowned thoughtfully before shaking her head. “Look, I’ve been… I got some advice today that made a few things fall into place, and I think you’re wrong. I mean-” She gestured at Simon. “You protect your sources, don’t you?”

“That’s not the same thing.”

“Like hell it’s not!” she exclaimed. “A secret is a secret, no matter if it’s a big one or a little one. If you take your promise to protect your sources seriously, then do you really believe that secrets are always harmful?"

“I protect my sources!" Simon stressed. “I keep them from suffering the repercussions of talking to me!”

“So a secret can protect people, then?" Ava asked. Simon scowled and scratched his head, and she pressed her point. “Simon, do you think you’re the only man in the world who can tell which secrets should and shouldn’t be kept? Do you trust yourself that much?”

Neither man had a reply. Ava, on the other hand, was hitting her stride.

“And then there’s the effort, right? D’you think they’d go to all the effort of keeping their secrets if they didn’t think they have to?" she asked, unknowingly echoing Simon’s advice about hassling the security guards. “Governments aren’t this… this shady machine that just hangs over us like a kid with a magnifying glass. They’re made of people, people just like us, who’re trying to do the best they can with good intentions."

“So you’re perfectly fine with an opaque government.” Simon commented.

“When it needs to be, I… guess? Yeah! I am.” Ava told him. “You think secrets hurt people? Well what about all the… I dunno, the thousands of secrets you never heard of because nobody was ever hurt by them because they stayed secret?"

“What about all the ways the world could be a better place if we just knew what was going on and what needed to be fixed?” Sean asked.

Ava shook her head. “I’ve seen what happens to people who try and help when they don’t know how." she said. “We’ve got to start trusting other people to know what they’re doing, guys. We’re all in this together.”

“Even guys like that knuckle-dragging cro-magnon wanker Firth?” Sean asked, skeptically.

Ava sighed and sat down. " Look, Firth honestly scares me and I don’t like him much - and I know the feeling’s mutual - but he’s still a person. Christian Firth from Kentucky, listens to country rock and heavy metal, plays Warhammer, secretly loves RomComs… I’ve hung out with him and all the SOR guys, and they’re just guys. They all banded together and got me a birthday present a few years back - you know, my USM telephoto lens? The expensive one?"

“What did you say to him earlier? Something about his daddy fucking him in the arse?” Simon asked.

“’Cause I was upset and he’s an alpha male jackass who was having way too much fun putting Sean in his place.” Ava said. “But even if he fucking hates my guts, he’s still one of the good guys and I’d trust him with my life. You don’t have to like somebody to trust them. Besides-”

She paused in response to a knock on the door, which turned out to be Darcy, who greeted the room with a smile and a “Hi.”

“So… gentlemen, whenever you’re ready there’s a car waiting to take you back to your hotel. The driver has your belongings. You’ll be under observation for the rest of your stay in Egypt of course, but it’s up to you what you do with your time. Ava, there’s a few more things I would like to discuss with you if-”

“Is she under arrest?” Simon interrupted..

“No.” Darcy said, instantly. “If she chooses to, she can leave with you… but if you’re willing,” she addressed Ava directly, “I’d like to make a request.”

Simon made a grudgingly satisfied noise with his arms folded, and looked to Ava, who stood. “I’ll see you guys whenever… this… is done with.” she said.

The two women left the room. In the silence that followed, Simon sighed. “Damn it.”

“What?” Sean asked.

“I have this horrible feeling that we just lost a huge story… and maybe a talented young photojournalist into the bargain.” Simon grumbled.

Sean shrugged and stood up. “Let’s get some actual sleep.” he suggested.

“That’s all you’ve got to say on the matter?” Simon asked.

“I’m fucking tired, I’m fucking bored, I’ve had fucking enough of this room and whatever Ava decides to do is her fucking business.” Sean scratched at his stubble. “Let’s just go.”

“Right. Maybe in the morning we can go looking for a story to justify this trip…”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Starship ‘Negotiable Curiosity’, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Wilson ‘Titan’ Akiyama

“Okay…”

“You gonna decide, or you gonna prove how shitty your poker face is some more?”

“Shut up and let me think! …Okay… …Do you have any Jacks?”

Sikes groaned “Mother_fucker!”_ he handed over three cards, which Titan combined with the one in his hand and laid on the deck in front of him with a grin. “Fine, fine, wiseass, you got any sixes?”

“Go fish.”

“Fuck!”

“Your behaviour confuses me.” Bedu commented. The cabin doors only locked from the inside, so somebody had to stay on guard outside them the whole time to keep the two ETs confined. Bedu had got around the enjoinder to stay in his quarters by standing just inside the threshold, watching the game. “You board our ship and abduct us, and now you are aggressively playing this… trivially simple game with one another rather than flying anywhere."

“A little healthy competition makes it more interesting.” Akiyama told him.

Bedu nodded sagely. “Well, anything which succeeds in making you more interesting is to be cherished.” he said.

Titan gave a drop-jawed grin. “I think we just got burned!” he told Sikes.

Sikes gave the Corti a grudgingly admiring raise of his eyebrow. “I think you’re right.”

“Guys.” They looked up as Rebar came back down the ship. His expression was grim. “Time’s up.”

“…Shit.” Sikes swore, and put his cards down. “How long?”

“B reckons a week or so.”

Titan gritted his teeth. Wearing EV-MASS was a form of exercise all in itself, and while they had spent the occasional conditioning week wearing the unforgiving suit 24/7, it wasn’t an exercise to be looked forward to. Unfortunately, without their techs, taking the suits off was an irreversible procedure, and the rule was quite clear - the suit was not to be removed unless it could be put back on or there was a pressing medical need.

“You’d better have a full stock of ration balls on board.” he told Bedu.

“We do.” Bedu replied. “I take it something has gone wrong?”

“Something always does.” Rebar observed.

“Preach it.” Sikes agreed.

“Hmm.” Bedu mused, and then knocked on the wall beside him. “Hkzzvk, come out of there!"

The translator gave the voice that floated through the door a panicked edge. “No! I heard Humans can kill you with their breath!”

“Not so far, but then again your nose is more sensitive than mine.” Bedu replied.

Answer came there none, but he blinked as the humans all chuckled. Sikes gestured for Akiyama’s attention. “We’d better get a shift rotation set up.” he said. “Somebody’s gotta watch the ETs at all times. You wanna go sleep?”

“Reeb? You burned the most energy.” Titan turned to the sergeant first class.

“Nah, get your head down. I’m good for now.”

“B?”

“He’s too busy giving us a screwy bumblebee flight path to throw off any pursuit.”

“Arright. Wake me in six.” Titan stood, knocked fists with his brothers, and found a secluded part of the engineering section where he could get his head down on his ruck.

Sleep was a skill. You could sleep anytime, anywhere if you knew how. All it took was a bit of mental focus.

The problem was, focus was hard to come by. A two hundred meter warship equipped for stealth and evasion didn’t just fail to make a rendezvous, and while they were all staying jocular and as upbeat as they could, Titan knew his brothers well enough to know that they were all thinking the same thing: Something had gone badly wrong. That was not a thought calculated to help a man go to bed. Nor was the prospect of a whole week in the suit. That endeavour was going to tax their nutrition and Crue-D reserves hard, let alone their health and stamina.

He took a deep breath, forced those worries out of his mind. He’d only make them worse by being an exhausted wreck. Instead, he shut his eyes, focused on his breathing and, by degrees, fell asleep.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
US Embassy, Cairo, Egypt, Earth.

Darcy

“So what’s this request of yours?”

Ava was showing the clear signs of fatigue now, but she’d found reserves of alertness from her power nap and snack, and was indulging in a coffee that Darcy thought looked more like a mug of liquid diabetes.

“Six asked to speak with you specifically and, if you’re willing, we’d like for that meeting to go ahead.”

Ava swallowed her coffee thoughtfully. “Jeez. Are you sure? If this is as big as I think it is…”

“There, I can’t comment. Yet.” Darcy said. “Not unless you sign some paperwork.”

“What kind of paperwork?”

“In short…” Darcy slid it across the desk. “It’s a binding legal agreement that you understand just how serious this all is, that you’ve been informed what the consequences would be to you personally if you were to break trust, and that you accept those consequences. Agree to be bound by, and so on. You should read it in full.”

“I’ve had like two hours sleep. I’m not sure I should be signing anything right now." Ava objected.

“I’ll answer any questions you have.” Darcy assured her. “The decision is up to you. If you’d prefer, I can have a cot brought up and you can get a solid sleep in first, but the sooner you reach a decision, the sooner we can act.”

“And if my decision’s a no?”

“We’ll just have to figure something out.” Darcy said. “We can’t and wouldn’t force you into this.”

Ava stared at the NDA long and hard, then downed her coffee as if slamming back a vodka for courage, and set about reading it.

She only asked one question, several pages in. “…Jesus, the death penalty?”

“As laid out in eighteen U.S Code section seven-nine-four.” Darcy recalled, grimly. “Yes.”

Shaken, Ava ran a hand through her hair and cursed quietly to herself in Spanish. “Me cago en la leche…”

She caught Darcy’s eye, steeled herself and read on.

“You guys are… really serious about this, huh?" she observed, flipping over the final page.

“I’ve discussed this with some very powerful people over the last couple of hours, Ava.” Darcy told her. “Many of them are not convinced about you, and I’ve fought hard on your behalf on the evidence of just one interview. Quite aside from the penalties laid out in that document, I’d be… grateful if you didn’t completely sink my career and professional reputation. As a personal favor. If you have any doubts that you’ll be able to keep everything you see and are told in the coming few days and take it all to your grave, then I beg you: please don’t sign it."

Ava stood up and walked around the room a half-circuit, thinking.

Eventually she turned and put her hands on the back of the chair. “Can I sleep on it?” she asked.

Darcy breathed an inward sigh of relief and vindication. “Yes.” she said. “You can sleep on it.”

Date Point 10y4m1w4d AV
Mrwrki Station, Uncharted System, Deep Space

Kirk

“Lewis?”

Lewis wasn’t in his chair. The latest result of his experiments in nanoforging pizza was untouched and congealing beside it, with a cleaning drone hovering nearby, waiting patiently for the minimum time threshold to pass before it could swoop in, pluck it away, and incinerate it.

Instead, Lewis was in his meditation room, cross-legged on his Zafu. That in itself was nothing unusual, but this time he was smiling. It was an encouraging sight.

“Hey Kirk.”

“You look rested.”

“Figuring out the solution’ll do that for a guy.” Lewis didn’t open his eyes, but his smile got just a little wider.

“You have? That’s wonderful news! What is it?”

Lewis opened one eye, like a lazy dog, and grinned at him. “I let go of attachment to material things.”

Kirk chose his words very carefully. “…I beg your pardon?”

“Earth. My whole strategy so far has revolved around saving the Earth. That’s why I kept running into obstacles I couldn’t get over. It’s a waste of time trying to save the Earth, because the Hierarchy are already ON Earth. They might not have a beacon down there yet, but it’s only a matter of time, and when they do…”

“I hope you’re wrong.”

“Dude.” Lewis shrugged. “Nobody’ll be happier than me if I turn out to be wrong there. But let’s assume that I’m not. We need a backup.”

He kicked his legs out and swayed upright. “Yo, room, project file CTC-eight- oh-five. One quarter scale.”

Kirk took a step back as volumetrically projected light engulfed his head. Then he backed up some more to get a good look at it. It was little more than a rounded oblong with thrusters, and even at one-quarter scale it was clearly huge, filling as it did the whole room, which wasn’t small. “A missile of some kind?”

“Kind of the opposite.” Lewis mused. “Missiles fly somewhere and destroy shit. This flies somewhere and…”

He paused, then turned and gave Kirk the delighted smile of the slightly unhinged. “Have you ever heard of John von Neumann?”

++End Chapter++

Chapter 36
Chapter 27: “Playing with Fire.” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Technical Sergeant Martina Kovač

The mad thought that was first and foremost in Martina’s mind was that Caledonia’s general alarm should have sounded more… serious. She was on a starship for crying out loud, and the fact that said starship was on fire in a major way really warranted more than an almost-quiet ‘da_da_da_da_da_da_’ warble.

This was not a situation for a cartoon cop-car noise. There were gouts of flame shooting out of the air vents, powered systems shutting off all around as their surge protectors cut in, and the hull was singing as the heat stretched and expanded it. Caledonia was groaning like a wounded whale. This was a situation demanding loud, harsh tones with a deep backbone, something that really advertised the importance of prompt action.

The reason this particular unreasonable train of thought was occupying her attention was that it was helping her cope with the fact that she was stuck in a pressurized tube of air thousands of lightyears from home which was currently on fire.

She really, really did not want to burn to death out here. Suffocating on smoke, depressurization and electrocution were all options as well, and this was not a fact calculated to help her stay calm. Focusing on the stupid little thing that the alarm was completely wrong helped her ignore the bigger problems.

Maybe that was the point.

Everybody on board was a firefighter. Nobody was allowed to serve in any capacity on Caledonia without that training. Martina was armed with a pair of “fireball” extinguishers, red balls that were to be thrown into the heart of any nearby flames, which would burn through their casing and allow the pressurized mix of inert gas and flame-retardant foam within to burst, smothering the flame instantly. They worked well, and between her and the teams with a hose and some more conventional extinguishers, they were battling the flames back out of their station.

She tried very hard indeed not to think too hard about the fact that the ventilation duct in the ceiling was glowing like barbecue coals. It was part of a long list of things she was not thinking about, including the fact that Caledonia’s capacitors contained enough stored energy that if they discharged uncontrollably then everybody on board would be dead in an instant. Whether they died from gigavolts of energy arcing uncontrollably between the bulkheads like the ultimate bug-zapper, or from the whole cap array detonating with all the violence of a nuke… well, that would be academic.

Not thinking about that one was made very difficult every time the lights flickered. So instead she focused on the little things, like doing her job, or that fucking alarm.

There was a cry of “Left side!” From Petty officer Taylor. Why was immediately obvious - sparking electrical apparatus, one of the power lockers feeding into the hangar’s huge forcefield arrays. As a team they made it safe, shutting off the power to that locker, making sure it wasn’t burning, ensuring the pressure doors were all sealed and that their section was completely free of flames.

The last of the fire was contained by closing the life support vent. The air inside would still be superheated, and the air in starboard bay was going to be stale, smoky and hot for a long time

They were in the middle of tentatively relaxing when there was what distinctly sounded like an explosion somewhere else on board the ship and the lights flickered again.

“Still here…” Somebody muttered, then flinched as the brace alarm sounded. That one was everything the fire alarm was not - urgent, loud and intimidating.

“They’re dumping the cap!” Somebody else yelled. As one they sprang for the wall. There were rails at waist and ankle height - one for holding, one for hooking their toes under. Most of them made it.

Martina didn’t.

The lights dropped out, and gravity went with it. Martina wasn’t secured yet - her last footstep towards the wall carried her forwards, but it also launched her. Off-balance and disoriented in the brief dark, she bounced painfully off the wall. Worse, her trajectory on the rebound was carrying her right towards that same glowing duct the flames had been belching from just seconds before.

The emergency lights came up; she twisted to try and grab the bar; Her fingertips missed by a millimeter.

“Nononono no…!”

She didn’t mean to scream - there was just no way not to. She heard and felt herself sizzle before she bounced off the superheated conduit and floated back across the deck, flailing madly at the horrible pain right down her back.

“Shit!”

“Help her for fuck’s sake!”

“I’ve got you!”

A strong hand caught her wrist and pulled to safety. She was in so much blinding pain that her rescuer needed to guide her hands to the hold bar and help her tuck her feet under the rail, but she was able to hold on.

The gravity came back on at a fraction of its former strength, and Martina sank to the deck, shaking.

People were all around her in a heartbeat.

“Medical team to starboard flight deck!”

“Get some water on her!”

A shockingly cold load of water was dumped down her back, soaking into her clothing immediately. It helped, a little.

“Kovač! Kovač! Come on, you okay?”

She was able to open her eyes at least, and make eye contact. One of Rebar’s suit techs, Miller, was crouched next to her. Behind his breathing gear, she could see that he was wide-eyed with concern.

How did words go again? She tried to say anything, but what came out was a kind of childish cry instead as her clothing weighed agonisingly against the burn.

“Okay. It’s okay. If it hurts that means it’s only partial.” Miller reassured her.

Martina shut her eyes again and took a few deep breaths, as much as her fire mask would let her. “God dammit that doesn’t help…" she managed.

“Hey, that’s good too! Talking is good.” Miller sounded thoroughly relieved.

“Gotta get the burnt clothes off, Kovač.” Somebody else said.

Martina put her head down and nodded by way of assent. Removing burnt clothing was part of their burn treatment training. She’d never foreseen being on the receiving end, but…

She felt the safety blade rip downwards from her collar, opening the back of her clothing from neck to knee. The tug of the wet cloth and her wound’s exposure to the hot, dry air of the ship combined so that the pain came right back, just as intense as before. All she could do was kneel there, gripping the bar so tight she’d swear it was creaking, and cry.

“Shh, it’s okay, it’s okay, let’s get some more water on this…”

More blessedly cold water was poured down her back, and somebody put a foil blanket round her. The frigid liquid damped the pain, but now she was shivering and cold into the bargain.

“How… how bad is it?” She asked, once she felt able.

“You’ve got a small full-thickness patch, but it’s mostly just blisters.” Miller assessed. “You okay?”

“This really, really, really fucking hurts…" Martina didn’t like how the last word came out as a sob. She wasn’t a little girl fuckdammit, she was one of the SOR’s senior non-commissioned officers. Crying over pain was beneath her.

If only the rest of her would listen to that thought.

“You’re holding together great.” Miller told her, reading her mind and gently prying her hand off the bar so he could hold it. Even through their thick firefighting gloves, the reassuring squeeze helped.

There was a bustling noise from nearby - medics and a litter. “Okay. Burn. Mechanism?”

“Contact with hot metal. She fell into it when the gravity went.” Miller reported.

“Sergeant, are you okay?”

Martina knew that he’d want to hear her voice so he could assess her for a burn on her vocal cords, so she made an effort to speak rather than just shake her head. “I’ll be honest.” She managed. “I’m not great.”

“Okay, let’s get you moved… Here we go…”

Gently hands helped her onto the litter. Somehow she managed to avoid vocalizing more than a kind of shocked inhalation when another flare of agony rippled down her back.

“Okay, okay… You’re doing great.”

Martina found something about that assertion funny. Maybe it was the adrenaline, maybe it was that or keep crying like a little girl. “Yaaay… aargh.”

She wound up in the recovery position on the litter, draped under the blanket. One of the medics shone a light in her face quickly, and apparently found nothing alarming. There was a hoist, and she was up and being carried.

“Attagirl. Let’s get you to the doctor.”

“Has the ship stopped being on fire yet?” Martina asked “That seems kinda important.”

“Yeah, it’s out.” Somebody replied.

“Cool… Great.”

The trip to the hospital was just across the beam of the ship - not far at all. She wasn’t alone, though most of the wounded coming in were walking, or at least leaning on their buddies.

“Triage!”

“What’ve we got?”

“Contact burn. Partial thickness with blistering about nine percent TBSA, and a coin-sized patch of full-thickness. No inhalation.”

“Put her over there. Sergeant?”

Martina looked up as best she could as one of the doctors knelt by her. “It’ll be a few minutes before we can take a proper look at you.” He said, pulling a white stick out of its sterile packaging. “Until then, this is pain relief. Open wide.”

Martina nodded and complied, and the doctor inserted it under her tongue.

“There we go. Are you comfortable?”

“Aw goow aw am gowwa ber.” Martina replied, as best she could with a stick under her tongue. Maybe it was the adrenaline, but the sound of her own voice made her giggle. “Whank’ur.”

The doctor gave her a nod and stood up, leaving her to wait.

Really, all they needed to do was give her the pain relief. There were some doses of Crue-D left over in their locker in the starboard hangar, all dosed for mild workout and exhaustion among the Operators - adjusting for her own much lesser weight, each one was a more than adequate dose to fix her burns.

She was just reflecting on her good fortune in having access to that stuff when there was shouting from the doorway and a new litter arrived. This one had a man on it, supine, intubated and groaning like a zombie. His face was-

Martina shut her eyes. The poor bastard deserved not to be stared at, though what she’d seen suggested that was exactly what he was in for, for the rest of his life.

Maybe it was the stick in her mouth, maybe it was the sudden dose of perspective… but all of a sudden her own pain seemed very small and far away.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Chief Michael Andow

The air probably tasted of smoke, ozone and burnt material, some proportion of which was almost certainly human flesh. Chief Andow wouldn’t know - he was on bottled oxygen, as were the rest of his team. That air was mostly argon and carbon monoxide anyway: Trying to breath it would have killed them, and hurt the whole time they were dying.

Still. They were alive.

Reactor section chiefs on a military starship were an exclusive breed: there were only a total of eight, and all of them had the kind of academic education previously found only in scientific agencies like NASA and CERN. Andow and his counterpart on HMS Myrmidon in particular had to occupy the very top of that select group because their charges, unlike the six V-Class destroyers, were hybrids: advanced alien ships that had been gutted and extensively refitted with human equipment. Very little remained of the original systems and what few there were had to interface with human hardware that used none of the same standards and protocols.

Their lives were dominated by laws and equations, the most important of which was ancient: Newton’s second law of motion, Force is equal to Mass times Acceleration.

HMS Caledonia had a mass of approximately nine million kilograms. She was equipped with hyper-efficient, alien-made “kinetic” thrusters, that could translate electrical energy almost directly into kinetic energy via quantum- mechanical processes so arcane and so completely unintuitive to human sensibilities that all of the Jet Propulsion Lab’s devoted efforts had made little headway on understanding exactly how they worked.

But, ultra-advanced, impenetrable almost-magic engines still had to deal with realities like F=MA, and to get any kind of a respectable A out of an M that large, required an enormous F. Cally, between the Atlassian strength of her spinal, structural “keel” and a reinforcing series of internal forcefields, was well-equipped to handle that force… which just left the question of energy.

Thermodynamics dictated that increasing the kinetic energy of an object by any amount required, at a minimum, the insertion of a slightly larger amount of energy. This was governed by another classic Newtonian equation: Kinetic Energy is equal to half the mass of the object times the square of its velocity. Given a mass of nine million kilograms, adding a stately ten meters per second to the ship every second demanded roughly four hundred and fifty megawatts.

Accounting for inefficiency, loss and power to necessary systems such as, say, life support, Cally’s three reactors - bleeding-edge fusion things that had been purely speculative in the pre-Contact world - between them produced just about enough to let her pull three Gs if power was diverted from non-essential systems.

Allied strategic intelligence had surmised from what they could glean of Dominion, Alliance and Hunter vessels that this was perfectly adequate for a competitive warship, but of course what was really desired was an edge. Say, double or triple that rate of acceleration when needed.

Hence the ultracapacitors. These were human-built, and while the technology had been derived from alien salvage, this time its principles were well understood and had even been refined upon.

Much of the ship’s spare space and cargo capacity had been given over to them, and to the immense power buses that could shunt gigawatts of power and then some (there was a certain movie quote that was forbidden on Chief Andow’s deck on pain of Motivation) to the kinetic thrusters, the warp engine, and the forcefield emitters on the hull as the CIC and the Bridge demanded.

And all of that was without accounting for waste heat and inefficiency. The energies involved in waste heat alone were somewhere in the same general order as one of the war-ending nukes of 1945, every half an hour.

Caledonia, in short, was a finely-tuned and high-strung Frankensteinian terror whose engineering team wrestled daily with a seething electrical demon that wanted nothing more than to lash out, burn through its surroundings, destroy lives and scorch whatever it could touch.

There was a reason that literally everybody on board pulled double-duty as a fireman. If not, they might have been lost with all hands today. Things had run that close.

There was a sickened sound from Able Seaman Wilkes. “Uuurgh, fuck. I think I just found Kendrick.”

Andow grimaced inside his mask. “You’re sure it’s Kendrick?”

There was a note of barely-restrained nauseous hysteria in Wilkes’ voice. “He looks a bit different right now, chief.”

Andow could imagine. He still had vivid memories of the first time he’d seen a half-burned corpse. “Okay, go get some clear air, sort yourself out.” He told the young man, not unkindly. Last thing they needed right now was Wilkes vomiting inside his mask.

“Yes chief.”

“That leaves two.”

Andow glanced at the XO. Lieutenant-Commander McDaniel looked just as pale and grim behind her mask as Wilkes must be feeling, but she was composed. She turned aside to let Wilkes pass, then inspected the twisted thing that had once been one of Andow’s team.

It helped to think of it as an object, rather than dwell too much on the vibrant, intelligent engineer who had once lived in it.

“Evans and Patel would have been further back, near the safety locker.” Andow observed.

“Here’s hoping.” McDaniel commented. “I assume this bank’s a write-off?”

“Not necessarily.” Andow ran a practiced eye over the damage. “In fact it looks a lot worse than it is - the insulating foam held up well enough. I wouldn’t trust anything aft of… here,” He gestured towards the fifth rack of capacitors, “But everything forward of that should be okay, once we’ve cleaned it up and checked it’s safe.”

“So we’ve got some cap.”

“Enough to limp home, ma’am. Once we’re able to charge it.”

Wilkes returned with a bit of colour in his cheeks and a determined look in his eye. Andow gave him a nod.

They picked their way past the unfortunate Kendrick’s remains, and Andow just had to exhale relief when he saw a happy green light shining bright through the smoke haze. At least one person had made it inside the safety locker.

He knocked on its solid door, and got two strong knocks back.

The panel next to the station - sturdy and almost antique technology built robust enough to survive practically anything - crackled. “Chief? That you?”

Patel. That was a real relief - the whole reactor team’s morale would have taken a gut-punch if ‘their girl’ had been harmed, backwards and slightly sexist though that maybe was. Old instincts died hard, after all.

“Sure is.” He told her, warmly. “Evans in there with you?”

“He’s a bit scorched, but we’re okay. Did Kendrick-? He was right next to it when it…”

“I’m afraid not.” Andow gave a respectful moment of silence. “Air masks on, hooky.” he told her, using the slang for a leading rate.

“Yes, chief.”

There was a pause, then three bangs on the door, and Andow hauled the wheel over to unseal the emergency station.

Patel wasn’t entirely unscathed herself, having obviously only escaped a painful burn thanks to her white anti-flash hood, which was sporting a large black patch where some extreme heat had licked across it. Evans hadn’t been so lucky - his own anti-flash gear had plainly spared him the worst of it, but his sleeve was so badly scorched that even its flame-resistant fabric had burned through, and behind his flash hood his eyes were pinched and pained.

Wilkes escorted the wounded able seaman away for medical treatment.

“What happened?” Andow asked.

“I really don’t know, chief.” Patel shook her head. “Daily inspection was going just fine and then… Bang!” She wiped soot off the monitor at her workstation, but it was melted and scorched beyond any hope of function. “It happened while we were testing rack eight. Is the rest of the ship okay?”

“She will be.” Andow promised. “But we’ve got bigger problems.”

“How big?”

“We had to dump the cap.”

The whole team knew what that meant. It meant that every relay and power cable in the whole grid would need safety-checking, but more than that, everyone in engineering was acutely aware of the current charge level of the cap at all times. At the point of crisis, it had been something like 95%.

An emergency discharging of all of that energy into space via the forcefields would have looked like a nuke going off. A big nuke. There was simply no way to stealthily get rid of that kind of energy quickly.

“So… the locals know we’re here.” Patel surmised.

McDaniel, who’d been recording her account for later analysis, nodded and tucked her tablet away under her armpit. “Oh yes.” She agreed. “They know.”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k

“No, director, I can categorically rule out Hunters.” Xkk’ restrained the urge to give a derisive snort. If he even suspected Hunters, the odd ship he was considering would already be an expanding sphere of debris. The construction was all wrong and in any case Hunters relied on the very best in active cloak technology, whereas this ship seemed to have been altered after its construction to instead rely on passive means that reduced its sensor signature by a frankly astonishing degree.

Even at only a few kilometers distance, even though it was attempting no maneuver and was drifting listlessly in its orbit, the sensors of every ship in his fleet were having a hard time keeping a solid lock. That was not a Hunter approach to ship design. The Hunters either wanted you to know they were there, or they did not. If they did, you knew. If not, you did not.

Nor was it a Celzi tactic. Nor a known Dominion one.

That left only a few possibilities, all of which were awkward, and one of which was downright worrying.

“Well, who does that ship belong to, then?”

Perfection’s Planetary Director had good reason to be nervous - his predecessor had ‘ceded’ the position to him in the aftermath of an attack by the so-called ‘Human Disaster’ that had caused massive disruption, and Director Luz’s position was maintained on the promise to Perfection’s citizens and (more importantly) its corporations alike that the security and protection of the system would take top priority.

“I refuse to speculate ahead of my evidence.” Xkk’ told him, pointedly using a Corti turn of phrase. “You will know as soon as I have something conclusive to report. A’vkrnkt’k out.”

He’d catch some minor trouble for so readily dismissing the being who was supposed to be his superior, but today was not the day to worry about that.

Today was a day to worry why the system defence grid’s sensors had abruptly and without warning detected an enormous burst of microwave radiation in high orbit above the fifth planet’s eleventh moon, at the precise co-ordinates now occupied by a ship that matched no known pattern or shipyard and which seemed to be operating on the bare minimum of emergency power, if it was operating at all.

Being a Rrrrtktktkp’ch came with some physical advantages, chief among them being four arms and the hand-eye co-ordination to use all of them dexterously and comfortably at the same time.

Interacting with two datascreens simultaneously was a perfectly routine trick that most children of his species learned early on in life and never let go of. So, with his left hands he processed reports from the fleet and the opinions and thoughts of the shipmasters serving beneath him, and with the others he assessed the state of his own ship.

The strange ship wasn’t responding to hails. Xkk’ could hardly blame it - if he was any judge they had suffered a bad fire on board. Plenty of the tell- tale signs were there, not least was a small but noticeable increase in the local gas density - vented atmosphere. Not the ideal way to rescue a section, but undoubtedly effective.

The aftermath of that would be taking stock of the wounded and dead, a thorough assessment of ship’s systems to ensure that the fire wouldn’t spring up again the second they relaxed, and preliminary repair work. Fires were serious.

One of his datascreens flagged some new data for his information, and Xkk’ bowed his head upon reading it - a gesture of resignation and trepidation. It was strong supporting evidence for his ‘downright worrying’ scenario.

Humans had been spotted on Perfection.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Chief Michael Andow

Seeing Captain Bathini without his trademark turban was a sure sign of things having gone badly tits-up in the recent past, and things looked set to remain that way for the foreseeable future. They were still at quarters, and anti- flash gear was a great equaliser that brought Sikh, Christian and atheist alike together under a thick layer of Nomex.

It also made the captain’s expression unreadable as he listened. McDaniel’s tally of the wounded - about a third of the crew were suffering from an assortment of injuries in the form of burns, heat exhaustion and smoke inhalation, plus one Able Seaman who’d managed to concuss himself scrambling up the stairs. Petty Officer Kendrick had been the only fatality thus far, but there was a badly injured leading rate in the infirmary with an unhappy prognosis even assuming he survived.

Still: the list was a much shorter one than it could have been. There had been a hairy moment on C deck aft where, if not for the vacuum lockers and an emergency vent, they might have lost ten ratings and the MCM. Andow knew that Bathini would have hated himself for doing so, but if it was a choice between eleven men or the whole crew, everybody on board knew that the captain wouldn’t have had the luxury of hesitation in blowing them all into space…

No matter. Whether by luck or skill, it hadn’t come to that.

The butcher’s bill on Cally herself was worse, all things considered. Capacitor bank one was a write-off, as was bank five. Bank two, where the fire had started, could possibly be restored to one-quarter capacity. Banks three and four had both been badly ravaged. All three of the fusion reactors were offline pending inspection, but at least they’d been designed to restart at sea - each one carried a permanent charge sufficient to hopefully reactivate its own fusion, once it was declared safe.

Six out of every ten of the WiTChES emitters were definitely fried, and the remaining forty percent needed inspection. The entire surge protection system needed safety-testing and replacement of the ablative components that had done their job by being destroyed.

Then there was the scorched life support system, possible heat damage and warping of bulkheads and pressure walls, possible damage to literally every computer on the ship, and nobody knew how a kinetic thruster might respond to the kind of power surges they’d suffered, assuming the thrusters had even taken a jolt, which wasn’t clear.

Fortunately, diagnostics on the warp and jump engines had both returned a clean bill of health.

Bathini listened to the report without interruption until Andow had finished.

“How did it start?” He asked.

“I don’t know, sir,” Andow conceded. “It started in bank two, rack eight. As for how and why… the damage to the rack’s so extensive that we may just never know. It’s so badly burned and melted that the damning evidence is probably destroyed.”

“It spread fast from there.” McDaniel observed. There was no accusation in her tone, but there was a query.

"Cally’s built-in fire containment was dependent on that pixy dust foam." Andow explained. He shuffled his feet awkwardly - he loved Caledonia, and saying anything negative about her just felt wrong, but he had a duty to the truth. "Too dependent on it. All of our refits and modifications helped - they’re probably the reason we only lost one man - but the alien structure and systems just weren’t sensibly designed in the first place."

“You’d think interstellar civilisations would figure out basic fire safety…” Bathini mused. Andow felt he had to speak up in Cally’s defence now.

“In fairness, sir, if we were using the alien-made fire suppression foam, the fire would have been under control in seconds.” He pointed out.

“And we’d all be running around eating each other’s faces off.” McDaniel said.

“There is that, er, slight downside, yes.” Andow conceded.

“Are we going to need drydock time?” Bathini asked.

“Undoubtedly, sir.”

“Then the question of how to properly harden the ship against this happening again can wait. For now, you need to work your magic, chief. How soon can we be ready for jump?”

“…Three days.” Andow replied. The figure was probably a slight overestimate, but he had learned to be pessimistic when estimating these things. That way you were either a miracle-worker, or never had to explain why it was taking longer than promised.

“That’s a long time to be sitting here with a curious alien fleet poking at us, chief.” McDaniel observed.

“Ma’am, the only difference between a capacitor and a bomb is how controlled the energy release is.” Andow said. “Any one of the caps in our racks could sink us. And the capacitors are just the first of the systems we need to safety-test before we can recharge and jump out. We can be thorough, or we can, er, explode."

“Let’s hope then that commodore Caruthers and the fleet get here before I’m forced to resort to talking.” The captain grumbled. He had an infamous disliking for diplomacy. “At least the message buoy worked… Go on, chief. You have work to do.”

“Yes, sir.”

Andow nodded to his captain and the XO, and got out of there.

All things considered, he’d take half-busted and potentially explosive gigawatt power systems over wrangling with officers any day.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k

The fleet had spread out in a close-range formation, offering maximum sensor resolution on the crippled ship, along with accurate firing solutions that offered no hope of evasive maneuvers. A solid and orthodox formation. One that should have made the fleetmaster feel confident.

It didn’t.

“The Capitol Station footage?” His Corti technician was already calling up the information, but as always with Corti she was taking the request with chilly grace. “As you wish fleetmaster, but may I ask why?”

“Not the footage, the sensor records.” Xkk’ clarified. “From the point when the human fleet arrived.”

“Done.”

The information arrived instantly.

There was depressingly little of it. Gravimetric sensors had suggested from gross mass alone that there were four classes of ship in the human fleet. Beyond that basic datum, the only information they had in detail pertained to the smallest and lightest class, a strike craft about twice the mass of a conventional starfighter which seemed to be capable of flinging itself through a combat volume at unheard-of accelerations, easily winning the kinetic energy advantage over its adversaries.

This ship in front of him, however, was a perfect match for the estimated mass of the two largest ships in the human fleet.

He called up a simulation of the battle and focused on the tiny human force. The first hint of its arrival had been a salvo of firepower that apparently travelled at warp. Against the sheer scale of the swarm-of-swarms that salvo had achieved little, but it had seeded the intervening space between the swarm and the human fleet with gravity spikes, keeping the Hunters at arms’ length.

That extreme range was unorthodox all by itself. At such distances, the slightest maneuver by anything capable of a warship’s acceleration profile would completely ruin a firing solution, and so extreme-range kinetic bombardment was reserved for ambushing fleets at anchor or relative-stationary large objects such as station. After which the fleet would then close to medium engagement range to press the advantage on a depleted and shocked foe.

The humans of course had invented their starship doctrine from new principles. Using warp fields on their weaponry eliminated the need to deflect when shooting at a moving target, and thus made long-range combat perfectly viable for them.

Sensor records from anything other than gravimetric sources were patchy at best, but the mass didn’t lie - the two ships matching their damaged mystery’s tonnage had remained at the rear of the human formation, in what was apparently a supporting role, while the two smaller classes - the smaller and more numerous of which may actually have been unmanned platforms of some kind, though that was unclear - formed the leading wave.

So. This was a support vessel of some kind. Coupled with the breathtakingly quick action of a strike force of four deathworlders on Perfection who had landed, engaged in a brief pursuit through a marketplace, and then departed on a ship registered to a private Corti captain…

Oh dear.

He hailed the damaged vessel personally. The time was long past for delicate probing with queries of concern and offers of aid. “Attention unidentified human vessel.” He announced. Every member of the bridge crew went stiff and still, listening. “You are in violation of Article Seven of the Dominion Charter. You are required by law to make contact by any means possible indicating your surrender to system authorities, whereupon your crew will be detained and your ship confiscated. Failure to comply will be considered a hostile act and you will be fired upon.”

He was still calculating how long of an interval to give them with which to respond when the reply came through. The footage he received suggested that the air on board that ship was still hazy and thick in the aftermath of a fire, and the white hood that the figure on screen was wearing could only be protective gear. All that was visible of the human, in fact, were two dark brown eyes which seemed to focus critically on him even through a camera. It felt uncomfortably like the being he was addressing was identifying weak spots to attack.

“Attention Dominion fleet. As non-signatories of the Dominion Charter, we neither recognise nor agree to be bound by its authority. Our ship is in distress and we thank you for your concern, but repairs are in hand. We will not comply with your order to surrender, and any hostile action taken against us will be treated as an act of war.” It recited, tersely. The translator decided that this specimen was male.

“I am Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k.” Xkk’ identified himself. “To whom am I speaking?”

The translator automatically found an equivalent to the rank that the human named. “[Shipmaster] Bathini.” He replied.

“Shipmaster, your species are automatic associate members of the Dominion by dint of your status as a sapient spacefaring civilization.” Xkk’ reminded him. “The Charter is automatically binding to all species.”

“We do not recognise the validity of a legal system which enforces laws that have not been consented to.” Bathini replied. “I repeat; we will not comply with your demand to surrender. Our ship is not capable of taking hostile action, and our destruction would constitute murder.”

“Listen here-” Xkk’ began, but the human cut comms.

A Vzk’tk comms tech raised a hand. “Fleetmaster?”

Xkk’ turned. “Prepare to fire a warning volley. Repeat our ultimatum.”

“Sir!” The comms tech insisted, urgently. “There is a fleet coming in at rapid warp!”

Xkk’ turned to his operations screen. Sure enough, there was a bow wave of distorted spacetime coming in. The gross mass of the incoming fleet was not high, but its velocity was unbelievable - either every one of them was armed with a Corti sealed drive, or they had immense power plants relative to their mass.

“General quarters!” He announced. “Fleet to starburst away from the human ship at best speed, holding at maximum optimal range.”

The fleet spread out like a firework going off, pulse-warping in straight lines directly away from the stricken human ship and coming to relative stop again as a spherical shell, some ten kilometers thick with a five hundred kilometer radius.

The approaching fleet slowed… and stopped nearly half a million kilometers away. Far outside of the effective range of any gun in Xkk’s fleet.

The information he’d gleaned from Capitol Station came to the forefront of the Fleetmaster’s mind. With their warp-capable weapons, the humans would not feel any disadvantage from the range at all, and already the five ships that had snapped back into the battlespace’s inertial frame of reference were multiplying. Seven ships became forty-three almost as soon as they were sub- luminal. six motherships, one support vessel of nigh-identical tonnage to the damaged one, and thirty-six child ships.

Not a one of them was easy to get a lock on. Their icons in his overlay were blinking, meaning that they represented only the probable location of a ship, to within a margin of error of some fifty kilometers. Useless for targeting purposes.

“Withdraw four-fifths of the fleet.” He commanded. “Half to rally on the far side of that moon, the other half to enter an orbit at warp and await further instructions.”

Fourteen of the human ships - two motherships and twelve child-ships - vanished off his overlay. A dim, grey icon suggested where they were likely to be if they drifted along their last known vector. These too were blinking, worthless.

That seemed to end the opening moves for now. With the human fleet unassailable and the bulk of his own fleet withdrawn to safety but ready to return at a moment’s notice, Xkk’ could breathe a little more easily and consider his next move.

“…Hail their fleetmaster.” He ordered.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
HMS Violent, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Commodore William Caruthers

“The ETs want to parlay, sir.”

Caruthers nodded, satisfied. His nonhuman counterpart had demonstrated respectable intelligence in withdrawing the bulk of his fleet in the face of an insurmountable tactical disadvantage. What was left behind was still entirely capable of obliterating Caledonia if so ordered, however. Ordinarily, he would have let the alien sweat for a few seconds, but this was too important.

“Accept the hail.” He agreed. Calculating, he removed his own flash hood. This was not a situation for facelessness, and he could put it back on quickly enough.

He was greeted with the face of an Rrrrtktktkp’ch. One that was verging on being elderly, if he was any judge. It had a certain… sagging quality to the skin around its eyes. “I am Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k.”

The translator rendered the fleetmaster with a male voice. Caruthers nodded respect. “I am-” he paused, tasting the unfamiliar title, “-fleetmaster William Caruthers. I must ask you to please withdraw the remainder of your fleet from threatening our ship."

“That ship is in violation of the Dominion Charter.” The alien replied. “I am bound by law to treat it as a pirate: I must either seize it and arrest its crew or else destroy it.”

“Allow me to be clear.” Caruthers warned. “Any hostile act towards HMS Caledonia will be met with force."

There was a pause of some three seconds or so, brought on by light-lag. The alien’s reply surprised him.

“Are you saying that this ship is not a pirate vessel, fleetmaster? Is it perhaps present on a mission authorised by your species’ government?”

His counterpart was a shrewd bugger, at least - he was offering Caruthers a way out. If Caruthers confirmed that Caledonia was present on an authorised mission then that would negate the Charter violation. Yes, it would be a diplomatic incident instead, but that really changed nothing. This already was a diplomatic incident.

Besides, diplomatic incidents could be smoothed over, relationships repaired and bridges mended. Caledonia and her crew, meanwhile, were irreplaceable. Not to mention the security risks - With her power systems so badly damaged, there was no guarantee that the ship’s computers could be properly sanitized, which could become a potentially catastrophic security leak if the ship was captured or if an intact hard drive was recovered from its wreck.

“Her mission was sanctioned by my government.” He agreed. “Conditional on the recognition that there is no such thing as a unified human species government. We represent a faction.”

“Then your faction is in violation of Article Three of the Charter.” The ET declared. “Nevertheless, the rules of engagement permit me to grant you the right to effect repairs and quit the field.”

“My thanks.” Caruthers replied.

“We shall… patrol this volume to ensure that the situation does not escalate.” His opposite number informed him. “The element remaining in this frame of reference will withdraw to a distance equivalent to your own. No element of either fleet shall approach the damaged ship without first informing the other fleet and securing acknowledgement. Acceptable?”

“Acceptable.” Caruthers agreed.

“A’vkrnkt’k out.”

Caruthers sighed relief as the conversation ended. “I call that a win.” He declared.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k

Xkk’ relaxed and nodded slowly.

“We may consider ourselves victorious.” He observed. “Withdraw the on-field fleet element to a distance of one light-ri’"

He watched, satisfied, as the ships obeyed.

“May I ask how, fleetmaster?”

The questioner was Mefr, the shipmaster, whose job was to tend to the business of running the Utopian Aspiration so that Xkk’s attention was freed to focus on the larger scale. She was Corti, which was a rarity - they usually disdained military pursuits as unworthy of a rational and inquiring mind. On the other hand, mastering a heavy system picket - and possibly the fleet one day - probably appealed to the Corti ego.

“Their fleetmaster just confessed to illegal military activity in a Dominion system, authorised by a legitimate species faction.” Xkk’ pressed the fingertips of his primary arms together confidently. “A few Ri’ ago, we were facing the possibility of a battle that would undoubtedly have angered them, and I assume you saw how well they fared against the Swarm-of-Swarms above Garden."

“Quite. Not a fight in our favor.” Mefr agreed.

“I know I would prefer to live to old age.” Xkk’ agreed. “Even if our superior gross mass might have carried the day, what little I know of human doctrine suggests that they will target the command first if they are able.”

“That would be sensible.” Mefr agreed. “It’s what I would do.”

“So: We save face by securing a confession, they reclaim their damaged ship, there may be further sanctions against these deathworlders in the aftermath or at least they may have expended whatever goodwill they earned at Capitol Station.” Xkk’ gave a satisfied snort. “As I said. A victory.”

“I would suggest, fleetmaster, that they capitulated rather easily.” Mefr pointed out.

“Meaning?”

“If the political damage they will suffer is as severe as you believe, then their fleetmaster’s rapid and uncoerced confession suggests that whatever that ship was here to do is more valuable to them than the political fallout.”

“You think it may have something valuable on board?”

“Something worth risking the ire of the whole Interspecies Dominion.” Mefr agreed. “Even the Gaoians would be obligated to impose sanctions if the Security Council demands it.”

Xkk’ snorted and stood. “Those troublemakers would find a way to wriggle out of it.” He declared.

“Be careful, fleetmaster.” Mefr advised. “It wouldn’t do for a being in your position to be thought of as prejudiced.”

Xkk’ glanced around the bridge, and agreed. “Shall we continue this conversation in private, shipmaster?”

“Of course. Undershipmaster, the bridge is yours.”

They stepped into the wardroom.

“So. The question is, what were they up to on Perfection?” Xkk’ mused.

“That much is not clear. Two planetary security officers attempted to detain one of the human agents, only to be incapacitated.”

“Incapacitated?” Xkk’ repeated, alarmed. He’d heard the horror stories about what a human’s advanced biology could do to ordinary people.

“Subdued and carefully bound. They were completely unharmed, apparently.” Mefr quirked a corner of her eye orbit, a subtle Corti gesture denoting a blend of mild amusement and grudging respect. “Apparently the human that did this then jumped off a rooftop.”

“…Even in by their standards low gravity, terminal velocity must surely be fatal?” Xkk’ pointed out.

“No body was found. The human appeared to be wearing some kind of advanced armor system, possibly one with limited flight ability.”

Xkk’ considered his options. If the humans really were up to something that they valued more than good relations with the Dominion, then he was duty-bound to investigate. If, on the other hand, this was simply a case of interspecies psychological difference then he could not afford to make accusations which he would later regret.

A circumspect approach was necessary.

“I understand that information brokering is a healthy grey market on Perfection.” He observed.

Mefr was a local. She noded sagely. “Indeed, fleetmaster.”

“These brokers. Reliable?”

“Their reputations are their livelihoods, fleetmaster.” Mefr said. “The very best are utterly dependable.”

“But expensive, I imagine.”

“Many are, yes. The most notorious - and arguably the best - is known as ‘The Contact,’ though I understand that caution is called for when dealing with them."

“Why?”

“They are known for being completely fair and reasonable. A favor for a favor, a boon for a boon.”

Xkk’ swayed his head. “And that is grounds for caution because…?”

“Once in the Contact’s orbit, it’s a rare client that can find the acceleration to break free.” Mefr explained. “The Contact has a knack for spending their owed favors very wisely. And being owed a boon by the fleetmaster of the system defence force would be…”

“I see.” Xkk’ accepted the caution with a nod. “Who would you recommend?”

Mefr inclined her head slightly, a gesture that Xkk’ knew meant she was most likely tapping into the shared network of data available to all Corti who hadn’t actually been expelled by the Directorate. “…The current best pick is a relative newcomer. Believed to be a Chehnasho, goes by the alias ‘Dread.’ Supposedly very effective… What exactly is it that you wish to know?"

“Those humans went to Perfection for a reason. I want to know what that reason was, or at least where to start looking. Where they landed, what they did there, how they left.”

"If they left."

"If they left, yes. Thank you." Xkk’ sketched a gesture of thanks. “I will leave it in your capable hands.”

“Of course, fleetmaster.”

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds.

Eleven

++0053++: The situation has, unfortunately, unfolded peacefully.

Eleven frowned and sipped at her stolen body’s favorite beverage. It paid to remain in-character even when the risk of discovery was infinitesimal. As far as anybody in the galaxy who knew her might deduce, Mwrmwrwk was sitting in a marketplace cafe and enjoying a nice Kwrw and the sunshine.

++0011++: A crippled starship, on an illegal operation, and the situation unfolded peacefully?

++0053++: The humans readily admitted to the violation. The fleetmaster offered them time to repair and withdraw under-

++0011++: I’m familiar with the article. Did you engineer an alternate solution?

Fifty-three’s reply had a tinge of wounded dignity, common among Agents who felt their competence was being questioned.

++0053++: I did. The fleetmaster has been persuaded to investigate the human operation more thoroughly, via an infobroker named ‘Dread’.

Eleven finished and paid for the drink, then stood up.

++0011++: Well done. It should be simple enough for me to allow this infobroker to catch up with me.

++0053++: To what end?

++0011++: It can be no coincidence that my host returned from an expedition which discovered the lost Mwrwrki station, found it under occupation, and then within hours of claiming the bounty a strike force of human special forces attempted to seize her.

++0053++: I understand. That station was equipped with an industrial nanofactory.

++0011++: Indeed. Yet another infraction on their part - Article Twelve of the charter. If we can expose their contempt for interspecies law and force the Dominion to act, it will drive a wedge between the humans and their only ally.

++0053++: The Gaoians? Fleetmaster A’vkrnkt’k is of the opinion that they will find some way to, in his words, ‘wriggle out of it’.

++0011++: Not even the Gaoians can ‘wriggle out of’ a Security Council directive. Not without violating the Charter themselves.

++0053++: And unlike the humans, they are charter signatories and full members of the Security Council, rather than mere associate members.

Eleven’s satisfaction was translated onto Mwrmwrwk’s face as a smug expression and a swagger in her step.

++0053++: How much detail should I give to this ‘Dread’?

Eleven accessed their file on that particular broker. Frustratingly, unlike most of the other major infobrokers in Perfection’s grey market, Dread was not apparently a user of cybernetics. The Hierarchy’s information on them was all but nonexistent.

That implied either a buffoon or fearsome competence, and Dread’s reputation suggested the latter.

++0011++: Very little, I think. Detail… yes, detail that a ship called ‘Negotiable Curiosity’ departed from a landing platform near the incident site shortly afterwards and that you suspect a correlation. Let Dread do the rest. If their reputation is accurate, that should be all they need.

++0053++: And what will you be doing?

++0011++: The opposite of usual good practice: I will be laying a trail.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Chief Michael Andow

There was a snap, a flash and an alarmed squeak from under the third rack. Andow grabbed Patel’s heel and hauled her out from under there sharpish as the cap bank flashed and raged some more before the surge protectors finally got their act together and shut off the circuit.

“You okay?”

She lay on her dolly cart for a second, clutching her multimeter to her chest wide-eyed and hyperventilating, but managed to find a nod from somewhere. “Y-yes chief. Er… Rack three, box J-seven isn’t safe.”

The shocked mood among the team evaporated with a minor laugh, which Andow led. “Thank you, hooky.” he said, drily, then turned to Evans. “Get our girl a cuppa, Abie.”

Patel sat up and shook herself off. Being petite and slender meant she always got the jobs which involved somebody wriggling into a tight space, a role she normally seemed perfectly happy with. Still, nobody could fail to be unsettled by having a megafarad capacitor spark angrily a few inches in front of their nose.

Caledonia wouldn’t have been a British warship without a ready supply of tea on hand. With his arm in a sling and wrapped in burn dressings and bandages, Evans wasn’t much use for anything save fetching, messages, and keeping everybody hydrated, but he’d got out of the infirmary as quickly as the doctor would let him to lend his good hand to the repair effort. He made a surprisingly good cup of tea considering he was having to work off-handed, and pretty soon Saci Patel was nursing a warm cup of dark brown fragrant liquid.

For any Brit, this was a panacea. Fire scoured the ship? Cuppa. One of your colleagues burned alive? Cuppa. Malfunctioning ultracapacitor threatening to spit electrical death in your face? Sit down for a bit and have a nice brew.

Andow for his part marked off the damaged cell on the control software, permanently killing power to that particular capacitor.

“At this rate we’ll be lucky to get above the red line.” He grumbled, referring to the minimum threshold required for the ship to activate its jump engine and return to Cimbrean. The only lower threshold was the black line: Minimum life support.

Patel sipped her tea. “We’ll get there. Racks two and one are hardly scorched, if either of them are okay then we’ll hit yellow.”

“Dammit hooky, let me be pessimistic for once.” Andow chuckled. She was right of course, but it was his job to obsess over everything that could go wrong.

“Nuh-uh, chief.” She swigged back the drink in its entirety, lay back on her dolly and hoisted herself back under the capacitors. “You don’t get to bask in your doom-and-gloom on my watch.”

"Your watch?" Andow snorted. She wheeled herself back out from under the rack long enough to give him a big jocular grin, then vanished again.

Tea. It could fix everything.

Date Point 10y4m1w3d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds.

Jrm of the Exiled

Easily the most dull part of Jrm’s work day was the parade of sapient beings who, apparently lacking basic literacy skills, ignored the signs in fifteen different languages which directed them to the terminal kiosks, and thus kept darkening the front of his desk.

Such was the life of a bounty broker, freelance contract agent and general bringer-together of people. All Jrm really provided was a room full of bulletin boards and kiosks, and the financial middle-being services between contractor and contractee.

Not deigning to acknowledge shadows on the far side of his desk was a habit by now. He just kept watching his fiction series - a truly awful Rauwhyr dramatization of the opening stages of the Robalin War - and politely informed the good being that had sought his attention that while he, Jrm, was at present indisposed, their needs, whatever said needs might be, would most conveniently and expediently be processed via the digital proxies available in their immediate vicinity.

“The boards are to your left.”

A tablet was set down on the desk in a cybernetic hand. When he glanced at it, irritated, it had a simple message on it: ‘Not boards: Must speak with you.’

“Don’t you speak?” He asked the creature that owned that hand. This thing - a chehnasho, judging by its height, long legs and digitigrade bipedal stance - clearly valued its anonymity, as it was wearing a full-length cloak and robes with built-in privacy field generators that hazed it in darkness. There was an alarming but almost invisible hint of dull red eyes glowing somewhere inside that hood.

The tablet was picked up, tapped at, and set down: ‘No.’ it read.

“Don’t, or can’t?”

This was not dignified with a reply. Instead, when the tablet was set down this time, it read: ‘Kwmbwrw claimed a bounty here recently.’

Jrm rasped an exasperated wing-buzz and turned to face the cloaked figure fully. Its height and garments were genuinely unnerving, but he wasn’t about to let that show. He knew immediately which specific Kwmbwrw this alien was discussing, but he wasn’t about to be bullied.

“Lots of Kwmbwrw claim bounties in here.” He shot back. “So do Locayl, Rrrtktktkp’ch, Allebenellin… Chehnasho…” He buzzed again to drive home the point. “Even the occasional Gaoian.”

His desk hummed and alerted him to an incoming transaction of some four hundred Dominion credits.

“…One particular Kwmbwrw does stand out, however.” Jrm continued smoothly.

The tablet was lifted, tapped on, and replaced. ‘Name’

“Mwrmwrwk.”

‘That is the one. Why does she stand out?’

“She found Mwrwrki Station.”

This revelation did not seem to impress. Jrm clacked his mandible irritably. “You have heard of it?”

The tall figure did not react in any way, so Jrm fluttered his vestigial wing casings irritably and did this… creature… the minor service of copying across the files on Mwrwrki, along with every scrap of data he had on Mwrmwrwk.

The robed alien gathered its tablet and left without any thanks. Jrm was glad to watch it go.

Date Point 10y4m1w4d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k

“We are at a distinct tactical disadvantage.”

Assorted variations on the theme of dismay rippled around the room as the nearly two hundred shipmasters under Xkk’s command absorbed his words.

Fortunately, If there was one thing Dominion fleets had become very good at over the long, long years of interspecies relations, it was controlling who got to speak and when. Rather than being inundated with opinions, Xkk’ was pinged with requests, sorted and prioritized by an algorithm that sorted for seniority, position within the fleet structure, political relevance to the subject at hand and a thousand other variables.

The first speaker was the Vgork shipmaster of the heavy system picket Copper King.

“Fleetmaster, we outnumber them six to one, and outmass them by a factor of ten.” He objected. “Their ships have no defensive shields: our railguns would shatter them! Under what circumstances is that a tactical disadvantage?”

“Numbers, mass and firepower count for nothing if we have an effectively zero chance of hitting them.” Xkk’ pointed out. “They control the engagement range, they control the angles of fire, and our sensors struggled to secure an adequate lock on the damaged one at extreme close range."

A fellow Rrrrtk shipmaster chimed in. “Fleetmaster, do we not intend to honour the conditions of the Third Article?”

“We do.” Xkk’ replied. “However we are investigating possible violations of other Articles, some of which will supersede the Third and compel us to seize or destroy that ship. If we must do so, then the fleet must be ready to enact the plan of attack that I have devised.”

He called up the simulations he had run. “The humans depend on their warp- capable weapons and their sensor-scattering hulls. Both advantages will be negated by closing the fleet to point blank range. At that distance, any one of our heavy system pickets will have the durability and firepower to smash them all. The difficult part will be landing the ambush on them before they have time to respond and evade.”

The scale pulled back, showing the command element, the fleet element currently hiding behind the moon, and the element in orbit around the humans at warp.

“If I give the order, Second Group-” the element behind the moon lit up “-will warp through Third Group as it crosses their line of approach. The spacetime distortions caused by the element already at warp should disguise Second Group’s bow-wave as they accelerate. From that distance, the humans will have less than a thousandth of a Ri’ to react. Even they don’t have reflexes that quick."

The simulation zoomed back in on the human fleet. The icons representing Second Group shot into the battlespace and instantly deployed gravity spikes. “Second Group will immobilize the humans immediately upon landing. From there, the superior firepower and shielding of our ships will do the rest. Any questions?”

As anticipated, the top of the list was their lone Gaoian shipmaster, whose ship - the Racing Thunder - was part of Second Group. “I must object to-”

Xkk’ interrupted the furry male with a curt swipe of all four hands. “I do not care what your clan of females will have to say about this, nor do I care what it will do for your crew’s mating prospects. I do not care for your politics, your personal misgivings, nor for your species’ relationship with these deathworlders." He snapped. “You will follow orders or else be arrested and tried on a charge of dereliction of duty, and Gao will be sanctioned for supplying a mutinous vessel to serve in a system defence fleet."

“…Under protest then, Fleetmaster.” The Gaoian bared his teeth angrily and dropped out of the briefing. Xkk’ would discipline the insubordinate creature later.

One of his fellow Rrrrtk spoke up. “Would it not be more expedient, Fleetmaster,” she suggested “to simply record whatever infraction the humans have committed and apply sanctions against them? I do not see why engaging them in battle will be necessary.”

“Every Rik they are present in this system is a Rik in which the Hunters might learn of their presence and swarm down on us." Xkk’ pointed out. “Their occasional probing attacks and raids are bad enough - we all remember the loss of the Gurvagah the last time they attacked. If the Swarm-of-Swarms were to come…"

Nods and other gestures of agreement and understanding passed around the Shipmasters.

“They will be given a fair and reasonable interval to repair their ship and depart.” Xkk’ asserted. “But I will not subject the billions of sapients who call this system home to the threat of being Hunted. Are there any further questions?"

There were not.

“Make all the necessary preparations, and await my command.” Xkk’ ordered. “We will await the result of the investigation.”

Date Point 10y4m1w4d AV
HMS Violent, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Commodore William Caruthers

“A briefing session, then.”

“Looks that way sir. Every ship in the fleet, all talking to the flagship at once.”

Caruthers was taking a working lunch ‘al desko’ - a ploughman’s sandwich, an apple and a coffee. “How long until I get to listen?” He asked, sipping his coffee.

There was a chuckle from the intel chief aboard HMS Myrmidon. “We’ve got the Watsons working on it right now.” he said. “Dominion encryption isn’t anything special.”

“How long?”

“The computers think an hour or so. In my experience, that usually means an hour and a half.”

“Good. Keep me posted.”

“Will do, sir.”

The link to Myrmidon closed.

Caruthers sat back and mused on the two salvaged Hierarchy ships. Both were, frankly, almost a liability. The unhappy marriage of human technology with integrated systems that had been designed by a civilization literally millions of years older than humanity was, after all, the reason they were here. Were it not for their engines, neither ship would have been worth the hassle.

The Hierarchy kinetic thrusters made all the difference: they were simply more advanced than the best human effort so far, converting the electrical energy that was pumped into them into kinetic energy for the ship with greater efficiency, and by no small margin. While all of the ships in his fleet could pull a delta-V that would have seriously inconvenienced the crew if not for the inertia-softening effects of their warp engines, the V-types only managed to keep up with Caledonia and Myrmidon because they had a third less mass.

That extra efficiency allowed for bigger ships. Bigger ships meant more room for Stuff, and the stuff they carried was absolutely invaluable.

In Caledonia‘s case, the ’stuff’ in question was a small field hospital in what had been her port landing bay, and the SOR staging area in her former starboard landing bay.

Myrmidon meanwhile was a flying power plant, armed with more fusion generators, more ultracapacitor banks and more forcefield emitters than anything else in the fleet. Once Caledonia’s power systems were sufficiently intact to receive the aid, Myrmidon could provide enough for the both of them.

Both of those ships, however, carried what Caruthers considered to be the fleet’s most potent tactical assets - the Watsons.

IBM’s “Watson” systems were nothing new - they’d been around and gathering steam even before the Vancouver Incident. Ten years of innovation and development past that point meant that both ships were carrying banks of number-crunching supercomputers of staggering power, underpinned by a software framework that could calculate, correlate, extrapolate, simulate, educate and even innovate with discomforting speed and precision.

Each of the V-types were carrying a smaller version, which linchpinned the fleet’s electronic warfare capabilities, but the ones on Caledonia coupled with the dedicated expertise of the men and women of the Fleet Intelligence Center aboard Myrmidon, they were the real nerve centers for the flotilla. Decrypting the Dominion fleet’s communications was a fraction of what they could achieve, and had Caledonia’s power systems been online to lend her own Watsons to the effort, Caruthers might almost have been able to eavesdrop in real time.

When it was all up and running, everyone in every CIC in the fleet flirted with swearing that the ships were almost alive and capable of anticipation. They weren’t so much in charge of a ship’s sensors any more as they were having a conversation with a robust, distributed network of pattern-matching engines that effortlessly and dynamically switched between independent and synchronous operations thousands of times a second, sharing their datasets and dividing their workloads to comb the information they got from every ship, every Bulldog drone, every Firebird and - when they were present - drones, satellites and even the SOR’s EV-MASS sensors.

Really, the only thing stopping him from being able to run several simulations of the possible battles that might unfold was the paucity of data regarding the capabilities of Dominion warships, and that would change if they got the chance to see them in action today. Every datum they recorded went into those computers, expanding and improving their store of knowledge. The more they had, the more they correlated, the more they correlated, the more useful they became.

Eventually, maybe, he’d be able to turn to them for everything. For now, however, Caruthers had only his wits and experience to go on.

His wits and experience were telling him that eavesdropping on that alien conversation couldn’t possibly come soon enough.

Date Point 10y4m1w4d AV
Starship ‘Negotiable Curiosity’, Deep space.

Scott Blaczynski

The outer wall vanishes in a hail of metal and glass shards, dragging them all with it. Scott wheels sickeningly in the black, all alone as he begins the plunge towards a world below.

No control this time, no shields to protect him, no EV-MASS. Just the fiery sky, licking the flesh off him, burning him away until there’s nothing left but the fire, the rushing ground and death.

From the outside he watches his buddy burning down from heaven, feels the stab of loss all over again. ’Horse’s voice on the comms, slow and thick with grief, letting them all know their brother is dead.

He stops running and leans on a tree. The pain is physical, sickening. As he fights back on it, the world fades until all he can hear is the rush of his own breath, sounding less like breathing and more and more like words…

“Bro!”

Scott’s head snapped up as a startled shout aborted itself on the edges of his teeth. His brain needed a few seconds to catch up, during which time he hyperventilated, wondering where the hell he was, or why somebody had a hand on his shoulder, saying “Hey, man. Just a bad dream. Bad dream, that’s all…”

His memory finally got its shit together.

Titan was the only other guy on the team who knew the basics of piloting, so the two of them were working a two-hour rotation in the chair, which really wasn’t configured for a human’s dimensions. They were coming up on forty hours in the suit, and all four of them were feeling it, but the time in that chair was just making things worse. Scott was sore all over, sleeping restlessly if at all, hungry, worried for Caledonia and all her crew - there were people on that tub he cared about, after all - and not only was there no respite, but they’d be stuck in this situation for another five days.

“…Thanks,” he grunted, standing up.

Titan took his place, looking just as stressed as he was. “You okay?”

“…I was dreamin’ about Thor.”

Titan clapped him on the shoulder, nodding understanding. “Do yourself a favor, pop some Crude. Helped me sleep okay a couple hours.” He suggested.

Scott shook his head. “I’ve only got ten shots left. Wanna save ’em for when this shit really starts to get bad.”

He was handed one of the distinctive bright blue-green Crue-D single-use injectors. “Here.”

“Dude, this is your dose…”

Akiyama nodded. “It’ll be fine. I’ve got twelve after this, and you need to rest. Take that fuckin’ thing before I stick it in you myself."

“…thanks, bro.”

Titan punched him affectionately in the arm and sat down. “Wanna know the upside to this bitch?”

“What?”

“This is good training."

Scott chuckled grimly, and applied the injector to the port in his EV-MASS. There were no concerns about using the same injection site over and over again with Crue-D. After all, the drug’s entire purpose was healing.

“Always the fuckin’ optimist,” he observed.

“Somebody’s gotta be.” Akiyama wriggled to try and get comfortable in the improperly sized seat. “Ain’t optimism if it’s true, though. ’Horse is gonna have to re-write our training schedules when we’re back.”

“Bro, that ain’t a good thing!” Scott objected. “‘Horse is a fuckin’ sadist on training!"

“Yup. ’Cause he’s good at his job.” Akiyama grinned.

“Fuckin’ masochist…”

The Crue-D was working already - he could feel the soreness draining out of his muscles. Titan used a slightly larger dose than Scott usually did, and the difference was palpable.

“Go to sleep, dumbass.” Titan ordered him. “You’re back here in two hours.”

“Right.”

One nice thing about alien spaceships was that they built their doors and walkways wide enough to accommodate even species as big as the Locayl, Vgork and Guvnurag. The SOR were used to turning slightly to comfortably traverse doorways, especially in the cramped and narrow layout of HMS Sharman. Meanwhile, even the Negotiable Curiosity, a small research ship, was spacious enough for SOR operators in full gear to comfortably navigate unimpeded.

Backstage, Rebar was asleep against the wall. Clearly it was Sikes’ turn to watch the ETs.

Calvin Sikes was reckoned as the ‘pretty one’ among the Operators, with there being some debate as to what order the runner-ups were between Akiyama, Ares and Major Powell. He’d grown up ranching horses and flinging hay bales in Georgia, and still had those straight-jawed, stubbled, right-out-of-a-country- music-video good looks on top of the Herculean SOR physique. He was also their combat camera and drone operator, and for lack of anything better to do he was tinkering with their Flycatcher UAV when Blaczynski entered.

“That thing ain’t busted is it?” Scott asked him.

“Nuh. Try’na set it up as an alarm so it’ll warn us if the ETs leave their rooms.” Sikes replied. He looked up and shrugged. “…Somethin’ to do. Shouldn’t you be sleepin’?”

“Dude, you’re worse than old lady Akiyama in there.” Scott grumbled. He lay down perpendicular to Rebar and used the sleeping man’s chest for a pillow. “Least he gave me a fuckin’ chance before he started nagging…"

“Heard that!” Titan called from up front.

“Love you, bro!” Scott called back, settling down. Rebar grumbled something, rolled over slightly and put an arm round him. This was nothing remotely unusual for SOR - in fact, it was exactly what Scott needed.

He relaxed as best he could considering he was wearing a full-body juice press, put his head down, and tried not to dream.

Date Point 10y4m1w4d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Technical Sergeant Martina Kovač

“Owww… Ow.”

“You’re lucky to be alive, tech sergeant. You can stop squirming now.”

Martina gritted her teeth, sucked air through her teeth, held her breath and let the nurse work. It was difficult. Painkillers and dressings be damned, when her burns were exposed to the air for the dressing change, it hurt. Not as bad as the first few minutes had been, but still more than enough.

“There we go.” The nurse started layering new dressings onto the worst areas, her back and thighs. “It’s already showing progress. You’ll have a scar, but it’ll be a tale to tell the kids.”

Kovač just nodded, though she relaxed as soon as the worst of the burn was covered. Those bandages worked very well. The IV was annoying, but doctor’s orders were doctor’s orders.

“Unless you’re planning to use that miracle drug of yours,” the nurse added.

“I could…” Martina agreed, though she was wrestling with her conscience versus her responsibilities. She had the authority to prescribe Crue-D, but only to SOR, including herself and the suit techs.

Knowing there was a man somewhere nearby with God-knew how much of his face burned off made her reluctant, though. A strong dose of Crue-D would repair his injury with no scarring at all, if only she could get the authority to administer it - authority that could only come from a few sources.

Authority that couldn’t possibly arrive quickly enough. Crue-D needed to be administered early in the healing process, preferably before it was even properly begun. For serious injuries, the window was about three days, half of which time was already gone.

“Or…” she flinched as the nurse applied pressure to wrap on the dry bandage. “…I can think of somebody who needs it more…”

The nurse’s hands paused. She met Martina’s eye, then glanced around guiltily. “He’s in a bad way.” She confided. “Lieutenant Bailey’s not sure he’ll make it.”

That settled it. “I’ll need help getting to the medical locker in starboard hangar.” Martina whispered.

“Won’t you get in trouble?”

“I’ll live.”

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds

Vakno, “The Contact”

“A verified trace on Mwrwrki Station. Now that is interesting."

‘Yes’

“You can unwind here, Dread. There are no secrets between us.”

Dread hesitated, then put away his translation pad and spoke his curious native language. Vakno had needed some refinement and research to get her translators to handle it properly, though her best efforts had given it a flat and neutral interpretation of his speech patterns.

“You have plenty of secrets. Meanwhile I have no secrets from you, is that not so?” He observed.

“Astute as always.” Vakno agreed. “Were you able to secure the sensor data?”

“The broker had already completed his transaction. I am tracing the pilot.”

“And what,” Vakno asked him, “do you make of the news that the pilot’s ship was stolen by four humans, one of whom chased her through a marketplace?”

Dread did not reply verbally - the most he communicated on the subject was an expressive gesture of disinterest.

“No comment at all?”

“I avoid humans.”

“For most of us, that’s a good idea.” Vakno commented. “Though the worst setback I ever suffered myself was the work of one of my own kind…”

Again, Dread said nothing. He had a frustrating distaste for small talk, which made him a difficult being to get much leverage over - he gave away far less in conversation than Vakno would have liked.

If he wasn’t so deeply in her debt from their first meeting, she would have held nothing over him at all, which was an awkward position to be in with fellow infobrokers. Vakno remained at the top of the heap simply because every single one of her “competitors” existed in an ecosystem that she controlled, all of them caged behind glass walls of debt and lured with the tantalizing promise of being free of that debt.

A promise that she did make good on, now and then. Without the authentic prospect of freedom to incentivize them, her debtors might realize sooner rather than later just how brittle those glass walls really were.

Dread, she suspected, knew exactly how brittle they were, and abided them purely because it suited him. She had prepared contingencies to release him from her debt at a moment’s notice, and made a point of treating him with punctilious fairness - a wise policy with any of her debtors of course, but taken just that little bit further with Dread so that it bordered on outright generosity. Vakno had a keen nose for which beings it was best not to antagonize.

“You seem to have this well in hand,” she mused. “Why consult with me?”

Dread’s preferred mode of locomotion was to stalk. This he now did, patrolling back and forth in front of Vakno’s desk for a moment before speaking. “Something about this seems unusual.” He declared.

“Besides the involvement of formal, authorised human military assets?”

He gestured acknowledgement. “The pilot’s trail is too easy to follow. Easier than if she was behaving normally. I think that she is luring me.”

“She knows you’re hunting her?”

“Yes. I do not know how.”

“And inviting you in… interesting.” Vakno ran an immediate cross-check between Mwrmwrwk and the fleet Shipmaster who had commissioned Dread’s services. The only correlations were meaningless - similar species-adjusted age, both female, both using Amnag-Dwuz implant suites… Nothing of substance. The only significant correlation was time spent in the same star system, but given that Perfection had a total system-wide population in excess of ten billion life forms, with both Corti and Kwmbwrw being respectively the second and third largest demographics, that was no connection at all. Vakno herself matched all of those data points.

“The target and the client don’t appear to be connected,” she decided.

Dread didn’t comment. Instead, Vakno caught a glimpse of his cybernetic limb - the only part of his body that he allowed any being to see - as he shook the sleeve of his robe irritably and thoughtfully, then flexed its fingers in front of his face.

He was an odd one, but the intimidating persona was commendably effective. Everything he interacted with seemed to be either disturbed enough to tell him what he wanted, or irritated enough to ensure his rapid departure.

“You can handle any trap she might be setting.” She reassured him.

“Yes. It is good to know when you are walking into one, however.”

“Do you think you are?”

Dread simply gestured what was either disinterest or resignation.

“If you need my further assistance, please do call.” Vakno told him.

“Yes.”

He stalked out. Vakno thought for a minute and made a few observational notes in her file on him, then set him aside for now and called for her next customer.

There was always a next customer.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Starship ‘Negotiable Curiosity’, Deep Space

Bedu

Bedu was not a scientist. He preferred to think of himself as an engineer, a solver of practical problems. That the problems in question had nothing to do with engines and everything to do with missing people and hidden knowledge was largely irrelevant - he was presented with a problem in need of a solution, then devised and deployed that solution.

The scientific method was second nature to any self-respecting Corti, however. Observe, correlate, hypothesize, eliminate. And his human abductors made for interesting subjects even in the absence of any sophisticated scientific apparatus or prepared testing regimes.

If only he’d had access to the Corti implant-net’s databases on deathworlders, but they’d shut down every transmitter the ship had - he couldn’t interface with it at all. Without being able to reference a baseline ‘normal’ human, his conclusions about these four were tentative.

They were undoubtedly using some kind of Cruezzir-based medicine, which presumably meant there was a discreet but formal trade between whichever human faction they represented and the Directorate. Sadly, Bedu judged that his own value to the Directorate was probably far less than the value of such a program. No bargaining chip or negotiating tool was to be had there.

What was intriguing, however, was their social behaviour.

They were a study in opposites. Their every interaction seemed to be either precisely businesslike and structured, or else laden with informality, affection and aggression. Any of their more relaxed encounters always involved at least one of them being insulted, and yet grievous and unforgivable personal attacks seemed to amuse them, and be met in kind with ever-broader smiles. Infuriatingly, whenever Bedu had tried to slip a veiled abuse past them, they had detected it and, worse, had found it funny. Delightful, even.

The very worst part, however, was that Bedu was beginning to find that he liked them. For the first time since he had purchased the Negotiable Curiosity, he found himself in the company of his intellectual peers.

They controlled their conversations carefully in his presence, never giving away the details of how some of their equipment worked or what it could achieve, but were happy to discuss the function of others.

The one called ‘Starfall’ even partially disassembled his weapon for Bedu’s entertainment, performing what he called a ‘field strip’, in which he carefully laid down the weapon’s working parts. He explained each one’s function as he meticulously inspected, cleaned and reassembled each component. Then, under the watchful eye of the senior one, ‘Rebar’, he repeated the process blindfolded and in a third of the time. Not a movement wasted, not a spare instant of hesitation.

Over the course of the diurnal cycles following their capture, Bedu spoke with all of the humans in time. With Rebar he shared an intriguing conversation about the ship’s structural features, how the design had saved weight without sacrificing on strength, and the precise composition of its titanium alloy.

Titan enthused at length about Dominion user-interface technology and the implications in the near future for human consumer electronics and especially what it would mean in conjunction with what he called ‘Predictive Dynamic UX’, whatever that was.

It was ‘Snapfire’, however, who produced the most surprisingly enjoyable conversation - it wasn’t a technical one at all. Apparently the technical details of his role and equipment were among the ‘off limits’ conversations, so instead, after some long awkward silences, he eventually did something that Bedu hadn’t expected.

“Hey… what’s your home planet like?” He asked.

Bedu blinked at him, assimilating the question. “What is Origin like?” He repeated. “Origin is… Origin. The seat and home of the Corti Directorate and four billion Corti. What is Earth like?”

“Beautiful.” Snapfire replied, promptly.

“Define ‘beautiful’.” Bedu retorted. “Beauty is subjective.”

“’Kay, well… is Origin beautiful?”

Bedu considered the question. He’d never actually considered aesthetics in relation to the Corti homeworld before.

“…Yes, I suppose it is.” He decided. “Beauty isn’t a subject I think about often. It’s not… encouraged.”

Snapfire inclined his head. “So y’all don’t have art?”

“Of course we do.” Bedu replied. He stood and retreated into his cabin, returning with his banner. His was a short one - he had no illustrious achievements, no scientific findings, he had brokered no profitable deals nor founded any successful corporate venture. The greatest achievement it recorded was that he was the master of a small private ship. This was admittedly quite the achievement, and put him a step above the rabble… but every Corti aspired to a banner that was as long as they were tall, if not longer.

Without neural-implant translators to provide an exact context for his gestures, Bedu found it difficult to read Snapfire’s body language, but he guessed from the way he shifted his weight forward and inclined his head slightly that the human was intrigued.

“My record banner.” Bedu explained, unfurling the green cloth for Snapfire to examine, though he didn’t hand it over. “At the top is my name, the date of my creation, the names of my genetic donors… below that is a summary of their respective accomplishments and any important contributions made by their ancestral donors…"

“Genetic donors. Cold way to talk about your parents.” Snapfire opined.

“That is all they ever were to me. I have never met them.” Bedu explained. “I was born from a gestation engine, raised in a creche and educated in a dormitory school. The only role they have ever played in my life was to donate the DNA that made me.”

He indicated the dense codes that detailed his academic and educational scores

good, but not exceptional. “I displayed an aptitude for and early interest in data correlation theory. Here is the second-rank accolade I received for participating in regional trials in that subject. I received a first-rank accolade in the local trials. Here is my second-grade accolade for dormitory school graduation. Here is my third-grade accolade for graduating higher education, though the silver circle next to it means that I was favored with special mention from my direct educator.”

Snapfire seemed genuinely interested, so Bedu continued. “Below that are my professional achievements - this ship, and a few of the more notable bounties I have claimed and commendations by my employers - and finally below that is the space where the accomplishments of my descendents would be summarized, if I had any.”

Snapfire scratched at the short hairs on his face. “Is it art though?" He asked.

“Define ‘art’.” Bedu replied, feeling that he was repeating himself.

“Uh, a lot of smarter people’n me have wrassled with that one.” Snapfire demurred, but he made an attempt. “For me though… I guess art doesn’t have a purpose except to be art. I like your banner, it’s interesting, it’s pretty, but it has a job, right? It’s not just there to just be art."

“Art is nothing more than decoration to you?” Bedu asked.

Snapfire frowned, sat back and scratched at his head. “Nah, nah, it’s more’n that…”

“If it doesn’t serve a purpose and just is then it is purely decorative, is it not?" Bedu replied.

“Nah, uh…” Snapfire looked up at the ceiling and made a number of noises to himself that the translator decided were gibberish. It was a peculiar thoughtful quirk.

“Think he’s got you there, Snap.” Rebar declared, having apparently been woken by the conversation.

“I ain’t exactly the right man to talk to about this!” Snapshot protested.

Rebar nodded. “You got that right.”

“Hey!”

“Brother, I’ve heard the kinda music you listen to. You wouldn’t know artistic talent if it rammed a paintbrush up your ass.”

“You were doing perfectly well.” Bedu hastened to interject, before the usual boorish back-and-forth could resume. “But consider - Artistic creations are not the meaningless emergent artefacts of an unintelligent universe, they are made by a person. A star has no purpose except to be a star, but this banner? A painting? Music? Everything a sapient being creates is created for a purpose, even if that purpose is nothing more than amusement or decoration."

Snapshot made a thoughtful sound. “So you’re saying art can’t just be art for art’s sake, it’s gotta do something."

“He’s right.” Rebar said, after Bedu had imitated a nod for them. “Hell, look at the Mona Lisa. That’s a portrait of some dude’s wife that he had done as a gift for her. And modern art’s all about making a statement of some kind.”

“Since when are you into modern art?” Snapfire asked.

Rebar frowned at him. “Dude, you’ve seen my sculptures.”

“You bend and weld scrap metal together.” Snapfire replied.

“They’re sculptures! A lotta them mean something, too.”

Snapfire blinked at him. “…They do?”

“Fuck, bro. You’re lucky I like ya, ’cause now I’m actually offended.”

Despite being a quarter again as tall as Bedu and only physics knew how many times heavier, Snapfire suddenly looked… small.

“…Sorry.”

There was a pause, then Rebar exhaled through his nose, shook his head, and gave Snapfire a hug.

Bedu tried to incorporate their behaviour into his tentative model of human - or at least these humans’ - psychology.

It went something like this: There was a clear order of seniority among these four, that was never challenged. Rebar would occasionally speak in a subtly different tone of voice, and the other three would respond with immediate and unhesitating obedience. This was, however, rare. When Rebar used that “leader” tone, he did so in order to confirm and initiate a plan that the group had devised between them. Otherwise the four behaved more like…

Bedu had struggled for some time to come up with a simile that fit well into a Corti brain, and had given up. Coming as he did from a species of fiercely competitive mycovores, the xenopsychology involved in the social dynamics of a pack of predators was tantalisingly tricky to fathom, especially when they didn’t behave like a classic pack of predators. While Rebar was undeniably the top of the social hierarchy, his behaviour wasn’t the equivalent of a snarl or a snap from a dominant animal to one lower in the pecking order… and yet Snapfire had instantly made himself as non-threatening and submissive as possible, just like one would expect if Rebar had snapped at him.

Mutual conflict avoidance followed by an immediate display of reconciliation. There was no social advantage to it either, at least not in any classic xenopsychological model - the only witness to the exchange was Bedu, who was obviously not inclined to care. There were no females to impress with displays of restraint and emotional maturity, nor would the interaction have any clear benefit in their standing with other males… which meant that the only possible conclusion was that Rebar and Snapfire genuinely liked one another.

Corti xenopsychological orthodoxy held that sapient beings typically only liked one another when there was a benefit to them or their genetic fitness in doing so, one which offset the presence of a competitor. It was natural therefore for prospective mates to like each other, and for parents and children to be mutually friendly. Interspecies friendships were easily explained by the fact that neither member of the friendship was a competitor with the other.

This raised the interesting question of whether humans were an exception to that doctrine or how, if they were not, they were abiding by it.

“May I ask a question?” Bedu asked.

Snapfire and Rebar glanced at each other. If any kind of communication took place, Bedu couldn’t see how, but Rebar shrugged and nodded. “Sure.”

"Why do you like him?"

The question seemed to completely trip up both of the humans, if he was reading their body language correctly. Neither of them replied at first - instead they stared at him, looked at each other, stared at him again. Rebar opened his mouth to venture something, then frowned and scratched at his head.

“…We’re a team.” He said at last, as if that was sufficient explanation. It clearly sufficed for Snapfire, who nodded.

“A team, yes, but what is it about this man in particular that you find likable?" Bedu insisted.

Rebar scowled at him, and Bedu sensed that he’d managed to wound the human somehow. “We’ve been through shit together that’d leave you as a greasy fuckin’ smear on the deck.” He said. “I trust Snap with my life, and he’s worth that trust. What more reason do I need?”

The explanation satisfied Bedu, and in retrospect should have been obvious. Reciprocal affection generated team cohesion, thereby mutually improving the odds of both their survival in a dangerous situation. An instinct that made perfect sense given that these were deathworlders after all - their entire home planet was a dangerous situation.

“I meant no offense.” Bedu soothed. “It’s in my nature to be seek explanations for the unexplained.”

“Satisfied?” Snapfire asked.

“I am, thank you.” Bedu told him. “Though, another question does present itself.”

“Shoot.” Rebar offered. Bedu needed a moment to parse what was presumably a colloquialism.

“Correct me if I am in error…” he began “But your behaviour towards me personally has been entirely friendly. I daresay I’ve never had such warm company before in my life. I am curious as to why that should be seeing as I am, after all, your prisoner.”

“We’re not in the business of makin’ enemies.” Rebar said.

“Heck, we got enough of ’em already…” Snapfire added sotto voce.

“…What’s happened here is you’ve been regrettably caught up in events.” Rebar finished. “If things go as we hope, you should be back in command of your ship and on your way again before long.”

“That doesn’t explain the personable reception.” Bedu pointed out. “What does it benefit you to… ‘charm’ me?”.

“What’d it benefit us to antagonize you?” Rebar replied. “Like Snap said, our kind have a lotta enemies right now, lotta bad press. It can’t hurt us to leave you with a good impression, and might even help.”

“Ah.” Bedu nodded, admiring the human’s candour. The logic was perfectly flawless. “Thank you.”

He put his banner away. “For what it may be worth…” he said, “I’m genuinely fascinated to meet humans at long last. You’re very different to all of the speculation and rumor.”

“Gotta be honest, I ain’t paid much attention to the speculation and rumor.” Rebar said.

“For a typical perspective, look no further than my reclusive colleague.” Bedu told him. He knocked on the wall. “Hkzzvk! Are you still alive in there?”

“You can’t open this door!” Hkzzvk called back. “I overrode the door lock! They can’t get in!”

Bedu aimed an expression of barely-patient tolerance at the humans, who for their part seemed genuinely concerned.

“Seriously, is he gonna be like that the whole way?” Snapfire asked.

“’Cause if he has a heart attack from the panic or whatever, we won’t be able to do shit for him.” Rebar agreed.

“Especially seeing as he’s overridden the lock.” Bedu observed. “Or would that not be an obstacle?”

“Dude. If I wanted to I could kick that door so hard that Hicks-vick there would be in danger from the shrapnel.” Rebar said, in the calm tones of somebody who wasn’t boasting. He kept his voice low enough that Hkzzvk probably couldn’t hear.

“Titan could get it open the gentler way in a couple of [Ri’]." Snapfire added.

“Vzk’tk psychology being what it is, I suspect that either approach might well kill him.” Bedu said. “This is what you are up against, unfortunately. Hkzzvk may be annoyingly stupid, but in this case it has nothing to do with intelligence and everything to do with instinct. He is a herd grazer, and he has been cornered by predators with nowhere to run.”

“Wild horse in the stable, huh?” Snapfire scratched his chin and stared intently at the door, calculating.

Bedu wondered what he was thinking. There were enough similarities between Corti and human facial expressions as to make assessing Snapfire’s thoughts tantalizingly impossible. “He is not unique,” he said. “Reactions like this are exactly why you have ‘a lot of enemies’. You don’t, in fact, have a lot of enemies. Your only enemies are the Hunters - everything else is panicking."

Rebar chuckled. “Nah, see, when my boy here starts talkin’ about wild horses, he’s thinkin’ of trying to break it in,” he explained. “Ain’t that right, Snap?”

"Break him?" Bedu asked, hoping that the colloquialism was not as horrifying as it sounded.

“Break him in." Snapfire stressed the word, as if that explained it. “It’s a ranching term. We’ve got these animals on Earth - horses - our ancestors domesticated them thousands of years ago, but they’re still panicky herd animals. Breaking them in means forcing them to trust humans.”

“How can you force trust?"

“Easy. You give them no other option but to trust, then reward that trust."

“Hkzzvk is not an animal except in the same technical sense that we are.” Bedu pointed out.

“You said it yourself, he’s running on instinct right now…” Snapfire retorted.

Bedu thought, then acquiesced. “It is probably for his own good if some attempt is made to calm him.” He agreed. “Prolonged stress really could cause him serious harm.”

Rebar’s hand slammed down onto Snapfire’s shoulder so hard that Bedu flinched

the friendly blow would have gravely wounded a Corti, if not killed him outright. “In that case,” he said “I guess we’ve found something for you to do.”

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Lieutenant-Commander Ellen McDaniel

“A good prognosis, then?”

Lieutenant Bailey shifted uncomfortably in his seat. “Ma’am… he’s healed. I swear, LR Davison came into this hospital permanently blinded and with his face burned down to the bone in places and severe respiratory injury from inhaling superheated air. I gave him an optimistic fifty percent chance of survival… And now he’s sitting up in bed laughing and happy and the only way you would know what happened to him is the missing hair."

McDaniel’s expression gave nothing away, but she couldn’t resist a moment of sarcasm. “I take it you’ve ruled out divine intervention.”

“When this ship has a supply of imported alien regenerative medicine on board, I think we can safely consider the hand of God a secondary possibility at best.” Bailey commented, matching her for dry humour. He looked down at his desk and sighed. “I hate having to report it, because that young man really was looking at permanent disability, assuming he survived. This is unquestionably a good deed… But…"

“There’s no way you could conceal this.” McDaniel suggested.

“Your words, ma’am. Not mine.” Bailey said, but nodded.

McDaniel nodded. “Thank you, Lieutenant. Any other miracles to report?”

“No ma’am. Nobody else needed one. A few dozen minor burns, one or two more serious ones… we’ll be low on painkillers and wet bandages by the time we make port, and all our burn victims are on antibiotics, but we’ll get by.”

“What about sergeant Kovač?”

“Kovač? She suffered one of the worst burns after Davison, but you know what SOR techs are like. The only way to stop her from limping out of here would have been to sedate her.”

“Limping?”

“That’s right.”

“…Thank you, Bailey.”

McDaniel let herself out of the hospital in thoughtful mood. Kovač was her only suspect in the case of mis-used Crue-D. Indeed, she was the only possibility. If she was still limping despite having unquestioned and fully authorized access to the alien drug herself…

A team of marines stood aside as she crossed the ship’s beam to enter the starboard flight deck. Starboard Flight had hardly suffered from the fire at all, with only the hospital faring better - that, after all, had been designed to isolate itself immediately. Still, when dealing with the ship’s largest pressure door and its most powerful internal forcefield emitters it paid to be cautious.

“Technical Sergeant Kovač, front and center!” She snapped as she entered. Everybody who wasn’t Martina Kovač immediately found important responsibilities as far from the XO as possible.

Kovač herself was working at a desk, standing up - sitting was probably not an option for her right now. She had a resigned set to her body language as she turned and tried her best to hasten to the officer’s call, which was a decent effort considering her back was plainly stiff, painful and swathed in dressings.

McDaniel wasn’t heartless. The moment Kovač arrived as ordered, McDaniel indicated for her to stand easy. “You can relax, sergeant. No sense in abusing that wound.”

“Yes ma’am.”

So. It was going to be that kind of talking-to. Kovač knew she’d been rumbled, and was probably both unapologetic and entirely willing to accept whatever happened next. Her whole attitude said that she would accept whatever judgement was laid on her as her fair due. McDaniel respected her for that.

“I have an interesting situation in the hospital deck that I suspect you can shed light on, sergeant.” She said. “A man with a grievous injury and a pessimistic prognosis has, quite suddenly, been healed of that injury.”

“Yes ma’am?”

“Do you think perhaps you could have been any more conspicuous?" McDaniel asked. “Because I know what I’m going to find when I check that medicine locker’s log. I’m going to find everything properly signed for, with your name right next to the date and time, aren’t I?”

“That would be proper procedure, ma’am.”

McDaniel sighed and relaxed. “I thought so,” she said, conspicuously placing her tablet aside and thereby metaphorically disarming herself. “How’s your back?”

“It hurts like hell.” Kovač admitted.

“Given that you’re completely authorized to medicate yourself with Crue-D, I can only assume that you haven’t done so because there’s none left.” McDaniel guessed.

Kovač hesitated, but nodded. “That’s right, ma’am.”

“Only had enough for Davison, did you?”

Kovač hesitated, choosing her words with care. “The… amount required to treat a man of Leading Rate Davison’s size with an injury that severe would definitely deplete our stockpile…” She hazarded.

“And would you say that’s an appropriate use of resources earmarked for the exclusive use of the SOR?”

“The SOR’s mandate is to protect humanity and human interests, ma’am. That includes providing life-saving medical intervention.”

“Hmmph.” McDaniel grunted, accepting the reply without comment. “Right. Here’s what’s going to happen - I’m ordering you to check yourself back into that infirmary and you will stay there this time until the doctor says otherwise. Do not give me a reason to come back down here and talk with you again. Am I clear?"

“Yes, ma’am.”

McDaniel picked up her tablet. “Right. Oh, and- Sergeant?”

“Yes ma’am?”

“If I were you, seeing as you’re going to be off your feet, I’d take this opportunity to get a head start on any paperwork that might need doing in your near future…" she hinted.

“…Thank you for the advice, ma’am.”

McDaniel ’hmmph’ed again for effect and departed, satisfied that Kovač’s had been a calculated and productive act of minor insubordination. The fact that she was suffering for it was an item in her favour as well, so really there was no reason to make anything serious of it.

Still… a letter to the younger woman’s CO couldn’t hurt. Major Powell, after all, would be compelled to prioritize the mission-readiness of his own unit. A few polite observations from one officer to another were probably in order.

She added it to the long, long list of demands on her time and attention. Half-burned-out starships didn’t repair themselves.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds.

Eleven

Biodroning was not a process that necessarily required sapient life forms - anything with a central nervous system would do, and Eleven specialized in using local fauna for reconnaissance and observation.

The perfect creature for her to use right now was a species of avian urban vermin called a Kreewit. Kreewits were basically a flying appetite, and their constant search for the next meal, coupled with a generous conception of what constituted a meal, would have contributed greatly to keeping the streets and concourses of Perfection free of litter and clean, if not for the inevitable digestive byproducts.

They were hand-sized, feathery, had a mouth full of flat grinding teeth that could patiently reduce any organic matter to food, and utterly ubiquitous. Catching one and taking it to a confused but disinterested and discreet Vzk’tk veterinarian for implanting with a custom-built cybernetic control package had been trivial.

Now, it was doing what Kreewit did - scavenge. Given that Kreewit looked around constantly, seeming to pay attention to the whole world by glaring suspiciously at it out of the corner of their eyes, nobody was paying any attention to it. In response to its programming, it followed Eleven, flitting from light fixture to advertising hoarding, from shop sign to architectural embellishment, sometimes flying ahead to claim morsels of what only a Kreewit could possibly decide was food, such as fast-food packaging, or the burnt leftover ends of smoked cqcq.

Under its watchful gaze, Eleven left a trail.

The rules of Hierarchy fieldcraft when it came to leaving a trail were simple: Don’t. As a double-digit, Eleven had the luxury of creatively interpreting the rules. As a sub-20, she could ignore them outright if the situation warranted.

In a galaxy where the entire economic system hinged on data footprint, a digital sapient life-form could be as stealthy or as obvious as they desired. Had Eleven wanted, she could have moved undetected by juggling as many as fifteen different identities - to the security systems, she could have been an office worker called Kwrwrtrwm, while the financial transactions would all have been under the name of one Wrmwlwlr, the smart advert boards would have seen a Grand House dilettante, and so on.

Being as loudly and as visibly Mwrmwrwk as possible was an interesting experience, especially when the advertising systems built into her host’s cybernetics package shook hands with a billboard as she passed it.

The boards used augmented reality to replace whatever they actually physically displaying with an ad overlay targeted specifically at Mwrmwrwk, usually with full audio thrown in. Every time she passed another board, Eleven received a new message in the vein of ‘Congratulations Pilot Mwrmwrwk! Your recent success has multiplied your personal funds by [INTEGER OUT OF BOUNDS]! Perfection Banking Group is delighted to offer you this opportunity to take advantage of our exclusive Person of Importance Savings Account!’ or offering her an assortment of immensely expensive luxury goods, up to and including her own ship.

The whole system was deliberately kept insecure by Hierarchy action. Indeed, keeping galactic data security riddled with holes was the full-time assignment of aspiring Igraens long before they were assigned the rank of Zero and given the opportunity to prove themselves in the field.

The network, in short, was a rigged game in the Hierarchy’s favor, which meant that the easy way in which Dread seemed to move through it without leaving any permanent evidence, like a breeze over tall grass, was infuriating. Nothing that wasn’t an Igraen should have had such a negligible data shadow. The only other way to achieve such stealth was to not interact with the network at all, which was impossible. The constant barrage of advertising that Eleven found so amusing was testament to that.

Eleven had commandeered the attention of a datamining group of pre-Zero hopefuls to trawl for whatever information they could find on Dread, and they had hardly expanded her information at all, beyond identifying some of the digital aliases he used for financial transactions. All the commentary on him agreed that he was most likely a male Chehnasho, that his left arm was at least partially prosthetic, and that he affected an intimidating costume of black cloth.

His preferred mode of operation was unusual - most infobrokers had their clients come to them, controlling the meetings with bodyguards, drones, forcefields and other such fortifications so as to minimize the risk to their persons.

Dread, it seemed, preferred to go to his clients, and it was on this foible that Eleven was depending.

Paradoxically, it took him quite a long time to find her. Eleven knew that she had been pinging her presence and location as aggressively as possible, and so the only way to account for his relative tardiness was caution. Perhaps she had been too aggressively visible, and made him suspicious.

Whatever the reason, Eleven was beginning to doubt his reputation when the Kreewit finally caught sight of him, tailing her through the crowd.

He wasn’t bothering with stealth, and couldn’t have accomplished it anyway. The aura of sheer menace he gave off sent everything in his way scrambling to get out of it.

Through the biodrone’s eyes, she got her first good look at him. He was definitely Chehnasho - they were the only quadriform bipeds who stood so tall, with such long legs and a digitigrade gait. The body language was strange, though - Chehnasho usually stood tall, with their chests thrown out - this one stalked with his weight forward, arising uncomfortable instincts in Eleven’s host body of being hunted.

The last time something had been following her with its weight forward like that, it had been that armored human, and that one’s footsteps had shaken the concourse as he ran. Had he not been so reluctant to harm civilians, Eleven couldn’t possibly have escaped.

She turned down an alleyway. They were on a ‘roof deck’ level of the city, with no ceiling overhead, but several storeys beneath their feet, and several buildings rising around them.

The kreewit lost sight of Dread. Eleven stopped in the alleyway and focused her full attention on her drone, to no avail. She was still wondering how he could possibly have evaded it when he stepped out from between the dumpsters ahead of her.

They stared at one another for a second, and then he made a beckoning gesture

one cybernetic finger stabbed first at Eleven, then at the ground in front of him.

Eleven glanced over her shoulder to make sure they were unobserved, made sure the Kreewit drone was in position, and then did as she was bidden.

“Can I help you?” She asked, feigning nerves.

He tapped rapidly on a datapad, which spoke on his behalf: ‘Stop pretending. You laid a trail for me. Tell me why.’

“Not for you.” Eleven lied. “I don’t know who you are.”

‘Who’

“What?”

‘For whom did you lay the trail’

Mwrmwrwk’s vestigial personality traits provided the perfect response: indignation. “What business is it of yours?” Eleven asked. “Who are you?"

‘Dread’

“Is that supposed to intimidate me?”

He considered her for a second, and then drew a pulse pistol. The unspoken sentiment was obvious - ‘if that doesn’t, this will.’

It didn’t scare Eleven - she, after all, would just migrate to a new host. But Mwrmwrwk on other hand would have stared dry-mouthed at the gun and immediately capitulated, and so Eleven followed suit. “…Consider me intimidated.”

He put it away again. ‘For whom did you lay the trail’

“I have friends. My spaceship was stolen and I-”

‘Why’

“Why… what, why did I lay the trail, or why was the ship stolen?”

‘Yes.’

“…What?”

Dread stared at her for a moment, and then stood aside and indicated the rear access door of the boutique they were behind. When Eleven checked it, the door was slightly ajar. It swung open silently and when she stepped through they found themselves surrounded by shelves full of boxes of electronic luxuries - terminals, communicators, translators, entertainment devices and cooking appliances.

‘Both questions. Start with the ship.’ Dread ordered through his pad.

“We had just returned from a deep space investigation.” Eleven told him, using Mwrmwrwk’s memory and the ghost of her personality. “The shipmaster - Bedu - he didn’t tell me who the client was, but it was probably one of the infobrokers here on Perfection.”

Dread said nothing, only stared at her. There must have been some kind of custom privacy field emitter inside his hood, because it gave only the impression of infinite depth and what might have been baleful unblinking eyes. Mwrmwrwk would have faltered and stammered, and so Eleven did exactly that.

“The-the, the client wanted to know the, ah, the whereabouts of, of a spaceship. We found, um… we found Mwrwrki station instead.”

'Explain. Why is this station important.’

“It was a research station. They were looking for signs of extragalactic life, and a means of extragalactic communication. You see, um, intergalactic travel is theoretically possible, you just need an efficient enough drive and plenty of power an… and…”

She wasn’t sure what it was exactly about Dread’s body language that communicated impatience, but she rallied and got back to the point. “…It vanished. One day it just… stopped reporting back, and when ships were sent to the Lleyvian Frontier to look for it, they didn’t find anything. No wreckage, no signs of a Hunter raid… the station was just gone. The scout ship apparently detected some interesting spacetime distortions in the volume and… well, it all got inflated. There were wild theories like maybe they had somehow jumped to another galaxy, or maybe achieved extra_dimensional_ communication and some sort of fourth-dimensional being came along and scooped them up, or…"

Again, Dread said nothing, but he did shift his weight from one foot to the other.

“…The Grand Houses put a bounty on it, a reward for its discovery.” Eleven explained. “When we found it, however, it had been taken over. The master of the ship we were looking for had erected a system defence forcefield around the station and taken up residence.

‘Why would humans be interested in that’

“That shipmaster is a species traitor, working for the deathworlders. A former politician. His ship was destroyed [years] ago near the Aru system.”

To her immense surprise, he spoke. His actual voice was nothing but coarse bass. "Sanctuary."

“…Yes. How do you know?”

Dread paused, then he reached up and tugged back his hood. The privacy field flicked off.

Eleven knew all about human ethnic groups, about how their skin tone varied in adaptation to the scorching surface temperatures their home planet could reach. She couldn’t imagine living on a planet where the star’s UV radiation was enough to burn the natives’ skin off, and she certainly hadn’t envisioned that humans were ever a kind of cool deep umber.

It was the eyes, however, that finally succeeded in scaring not just the ghost of Mwrmwrwk, but Eleven herself. The embers in his hood were far less terrifying than the the real thing: Dread’s eyes hated everything.

“I know that ship.” He growled. “I got thrown out its airlock.”

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Starship Negotiable Curiosity, Deep Space.

Calvin ‘Snapfire’ Sikes

“Hey, uh… hello in there.”

There was a kind of wary shifting sound from behind Hkzzvk’s door, but no reply. Calvin took that as an encouraging sign.

“Dude, uh… hey, I’m sorry about this but I can’t pronounce your name. Is it okay if I call you Hick?”

The translator gave Hkzzvk a hysterical edge to his voice. They really did a remarkable job of simulating where the voice was coming from, too. Rather than hearing the anxious Vzk’tk’s words from a speaker in the wall or anything, they really did sound like they were being shouted from the far side of the door. “Leave me alone!”

“I’m not coming in, I promise.” Sikes replied, soothingly. “That room’s your space, I respect that. Just checking you’re okay in there.”

“Leave me alone!!” Hkzzvk repeated, more frantically.

“Sorry man, I can’t. We’re all worried for you. But I’m just here to talk, you’re safe in there.”

There was no reply.

“…Sure appreciate it if you said somethin’ other than ‘leave me alone’ there, Hick.”

He let the silence drag on for a second or two, then decided that the old trick of just talking and talking and talking until the panicking creature got used to the sound of his voice was in order. Hkzzvk might be a fellow sapient being, but hey - whatever worked.

“Okay, well, I’m just gonna sit here and talk about whatever comes into my head, don’t mind me.” He said. “Gotta tell you though, I’d love to get this suit off sometime soon. It’s perfectly sized for me, but it squeezes real hard so it doesn’t rattle around, and yeah that’s a good thing for makin’ it easy to move in, it also makes it tough to wear for more than a couple of hours. I ain’t lookin’ forward to sitting around in this thing the whole way back, I tell ya that.”

Hkzzvk’s silence continued, so Calvin shrugged and settled in for a good long stream-of-consciousness.

“Though… okay, you probably never heard of skiing. Or maybe you did, maybe you guys have that. Probably not with four legs, but it’s this thing we do where we use long flat apparatus that we attach to our feet and it helps us slide easily over snow. Takes some work to get good at it, but there’s no better way to move fast over snow. Ski boots work a lot like the suit does, and those feel great to take off at the end of a day on the slopes, so I’m thinking when we get to take the spacesuit off after all this it’s gonna be… Actually, have you ever seen snow? Is that a thing on your home planet? Or… Dude, were you even born on a planet? I know a lot of ETs are born in space. I wonder if any humans have ever been born in space… It’d be tough for us, I bet the low gravity would screw with fetal development in all sorts’a ways…"

At length, he rambled on about the estimates in how many humans there were in the galaxy at large, wondered how they were getting by without easy access to clothing, and mused briefly about whether any of them had just given up and ‘gone native.’

He kept a lazy eye on the clock as he moved on to describing snow, then weather in general and especially thunderstorms.

“I mean, I guess all’a this sounds scary and alien to you huh? Deathworld weather and all that stuff but man, I tell ya it’s beautiful. I remember when I was little and this storm went over and it was just this crazy lightning show in the sky. My daddy and I sat on the porch and watched it for like half an hour, but then momma came out and said there was a tornado alarm and we had to spend the night sleeping on cots in the basement…"

He decided to move on from the subject of Earth’s weather and onto gentler and more calming matters. He was dealing with a sapient being after all, which meant that he couldn’t rely completely on tone of voice alone - he had to watch the content of what he was saying.

“Space is prettier though. There’s this nebula you can see from Cimbrean, It’s about as big in the sky as my thumb at arm’s length and yeah, things like storms are cool, but that nebula’s just like… every time I lay eyes on it it reminds me that wow, y’know, when I was a child we didn’t have FTL and aliens were just something that could theoretically exist, but then… there I am, living on a planet that’s not Earth, and I work in space, and I’m chatting to an alien right now. That’s kind of a-"

Hkzzvk finally said something, interrupting him. “Are you going to talk all night?" He asked. “You’re keeping me awake.”

“Ah, sorry dude, are you tired?

“I haven’t slept since you took over this ship! How could I? You’re dangerous!”

Calvin considered his reply carefully. “I know.” He said, eventually. “I know we are. We ain’t the bad guys though, man.”

“You’re still dangerous!” Hkzzvk insisted.

“I ain’t denyin’ that.” Sikes told him. “But so are lots’a things. This ship’s dangerous, ain’t it? Lotta power in here, lots of stuff the engineer’s gotta stay on top of, am I right?”

Hkzzvk said nothing, so Sikes shrugged and carried on talking. Okay, so he was keeping the alien awake, but really that worked to his advantage. Either the fatigue would help him calm Hkzzvk down so they could make contact properly, or else Hkzzvk would fall asleep listening to his voice and awaken rested and with some positive associations.

“Besides man, imagine yourself in our position. Ten years ago, we didn’t know any of this stuff. None of us had any clue what a deathworld is, or that Earth is one… I gotta be honest, it kinda scares me too. I don’t wanna accidentally hurt people, right? I ain’t a monster.”

“Then why are you here?” Hkzzvk asked. “Stay on your planet, where you belong! Go to other deathworlds! Why are you on our ship?"

“Would if we could, man.” Sikes grinned to himself. He was making definite progress. “Life ain’t that easy.”

“Why us?" Hkzzvk insisted.

“Ain’t nothin’ personal. You just got caught up in something important, that’s all.”

“I don’t trust you!”

Sikes sighed. “You should. Hicks, the only reason you’re still in that room is ‘cause we don’t wanna hurt you. Heck, I’m talkin’ to ya right now ‘cause we’re worried about ya. I ain’t askin’ for much, just want you to check in and let us know you’re okay.”

“I’m fine!"

“Sure, sure. Okay” Sikes soothed. He sat and waited for a minute.

“I… would like something to eat, please." Hkzzvk ventured after a while. “And to drink.”

“Our rations wouldn’t be any good for you, buddy, and ain’t none of us know one end of your kitchen from the other. You wanna come out here and fix yerself somethin, we’ll turn down the gravity for ya. Whaddya say?”

“…And you promise that it’s safe? I won’t catch a fatal disease?" Hkzzvk asked.

“I promise.”

There was a thoughtful pause, and then the door cautiously opened. Hkzzvk peeked around it.

Carefully and respectfully, Sikes took a slow and unthreatening step back. He smiled, keeping his lips together so that there was no hint of teeth, and gestured openly to the kitchen.

He could see why people tended to compare Vzk’tk with giraffes - they had that kind of spindly, ungainly look to them, especially in their long legs and necks. But Hkzzvk’s attitude was more like a deer crossing the road and keeping a wary eye on the pickup that had stopped for it.

“Ship, set gravity in all areas to Dominion standard.” he ordered. The Negotiable Curiosity chimed and Titan woke with a snort as the gravity changed. Hkzzvk took an alarmed step back.

“Sorry bro.” Sikes called.

“Hey, the hermit emerges.” Akiyama sat up slowly. “How are you?”

“I am… fine. Thank you.” Hkzzvk ventured. Still moving like a nervous buck, he picked his way carefully out into the ship’s common area.

Sikes gave Titan a subtle headshake, asking for a kid gloves approach. He got an imperceptible nod by way of a reply, and Titan settled down with his head on his ruck again. “’Kay. Lemme know if you need anything.”

Hkzzvk stepped warily around him and approached the food dispenser. A few taps later he had a small bowl of something that looked vaguely like dark arugula, a side order of something black and dripping with what Sikes hoped was sauce, and a small cup of water.

The bowl came with something like curved chopsticks. Apparently they were Hkzzvk’s customary eating utensil, because he was shovelling the arugula-ish into his mouth with gusto as soon as he had them in his hand.

“Dude, you had no food at all in there?” Sikes asked him. Hkzzvk flinched at being addressed, but then nodded. He skewered one of the slimy black things and slurped it up. Sikes caught the morsel’s scent and couldn’t stop a slight grimace from flickering across one eyebrow and the side of his nose. It smelled like rotting banana peel fermented in sour milk.

He took a step back and let the alien eat.

Eventually, Hkzzvk sighed and put the bowl down. He picked up a few of the uneaten leaves and twisted them together into what was unmistakably a kind of joint or cigarette, which he lit with a small circular lighter stored in a pouch on his arm.

“…I didn’t know folks out here smoke.” Sikes commented. Hkzzvk gave a complicated toss of his head that went untranslated, and flicked one of his ears.

The burning leaf smelled quite good, actually - sweeter and warmer than a cigarette. It reminded Sikes of fishing with his late great-uncle, who never went to the lake without his pipe and two Budweisers, and a couple of A&Ws for Calvin. Sadly, the old man had passed away before they’d been able to share a Bud together, but the smell coming from Hkzzvk’s impromptu roll-up was making Calvin suddenly thirsty for a root beer.

To his surprise, Hkzzvk finished his smoke by the simple expedient of eating the smouldering stub, grinding the embers out between his teeth. He shook himself, sending a wave of loose short-coated skin rippling down from the top of his long neck to the base of his tail, and sighed.

“Better?” Sikes asked him.

“Much better… Thank you.”

“Dude, like I said. We were just worried for ya.” He wasn’t sure what to read in Hkzzvk’s body language - for all he knew the Vzk’tk engineer might be mistrustful, wary, grateful or optimistic. He stood aside and indicated the open door. “You want the room, it’s yours, we won’t intrude, but please don’t starve yourself in there.”

Hkzzvk didn’t reply at first, but - still wary - he carefully retreated to the door to his room.

“You promise?” he asked.

“On my honor.” Sikes raised one hand solemnly to his chest and the other to ear level. For all Bedu’s dismissal of Hkzzvk’s intelligence, he counted on the jittery Vzk’tk to at least be able to interpret the gesture by context.

It apparently worked. Hkzzvk cautiously imitated him, then retreated into his room and closed the door.

“Nicely done.” Titan commented, sitting up again.

“It’s a start.” Sikes agreed. He grabbed an MRE and sat down to prepare it. Watching Hkzzvk eat had reminded him not only of his own appetite, but of the fact that he was burning through plenty of calories just by wearing the suit. “Aww, man. Jambalaya." he complained. Somewhere along the line, they’d started playing a game where they had to eat whatever they grabbed, rather than saving the ones they didn’t want for last. Nobody was quite sure what the consequence would be for giving in, but none of them was willing to lose. “Real jambalaya should be fuckin’ spicy man, not this weak-ass shit. The Tabasco doesn’t save it.”

Fortunately, there was a loophole. “Trade ya for a sausage and gravy.” Akiyama offered, brandishing the one he’d just grabbed.

“Deal.”

“Always knew you had a talent for diplomacy.” Titan observed, once the meals had been traded and were heating. “No way you score that much pussy on your looks alone."

Sikes snorted. “Blue fur and six limbs or not, he’s just a scared dude who got caught up in somethin’ bigger than him.” he said. “Useful knowing they smoke that stuff though. That’s good stuff. I can use that.”

“Y’know it didn’t even occur to me that maybe SOR needs a man with some talking skills.” Titan mused. “We’ve got so big and ass-kicky, kinda seems like a silver tongue’s gonna be low on the list, right?”

Sikes nodded, stirring his juice, but said nothing.

“Remember Ukraine? Operation SWORN BEACON? That shit woulda gone south if not for Booker." Titan continued. “Maybe it’s something to raise with STAINLESS.”

“Maybe,” Sikes agreed. “Hell, we’re pretty fuckin’ high-profile too. You saw the whole Beef Brothers thing, right?"

Titan laughed. “Yeah, and man I bet Base is sore over that shit. You hear about the poll result?"

“No…?”

“It went ‘Left Beef Best Beef, or Right Beef Superior Slab?’" Titan chuckled. “’Horse took it three to one, man. Kicked Baseball’s ass."

Sikes laughed. “Ah, poor Base… Feels weird bein’ part of a unit with that kind of media profile though, don’t it?”

“Very different to Delta.” Titan agreed. “Could be we’re all gonna need that silver tongue.”

He pulled his Jambalaya out of the heat and dug in. “Hell, could be the ultimate survival skill for mankind ain’t gonna be the muscles and stuff, it’s gonna be talking panicky ETs round to our side.”

“Bro, if that’s true, I’ll fuckin’ take it.” Sikes toasted the idea with his juice. “But I’m kinda thinkin’ it won’t be.”

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds.

Eleven

“You’re human!”

“Coo you, seen what straight in front o’ I.” Dread was… smiling? Eleven had to dig into the Hierarchy database to reference human facial expressions, and decided that what she was seeing wasn’t a smile at all, but was instead tagged with the term ‘rictus’. It was not, apparently, a friendly expression.

It certainly didn’t look like one. Quite aside from that hateful glare, she could see sharp slicing teeth and four pointed grabbing ones, and her host body’s instincts were sending urgent messages to the effect that she should tremble.

Humiliating as it was, breaking character was not acceptable, so Eleven allowed Mwrmwrwk’s body to tremble, and even cower a bit and back away.

“But… you’re… supposed to be Chehnasho.”

“I an’ I don’ wan’ Babylon come callin’, sight?"

Either the translator had made a complete hash of his language, or else he was speaking pure nonsense."…What?"

Dread’s expression got even angrier somehow, and he spoke clearly and slowly, as if enunciating for an idiot. “If they-” he waved a hand at the planet in general “Find out a human is here, then they either kill me, or Hunters will come.”

“Then why-?”

“You out me, you die. Seen?”

His tone was completely unmalicious, meaning that his words weren’t so much a threat as an alert of future danger to be avoided, like a warning sign on a crumbling cliff edge.

Eleven was not going to be bullied by a deathworld primitive. In any case, deathworlders outside the quarantine field were not to be permitted - a rule she could have bent or broken if she wanted… but she didn’t want to.

Internally, she sent a priority alert to planetary security. Externally, she squeaked a terrified “…Understood.”

“Why I chasing Sanctuary?" Dread asked.

“That was the job!” Eleven told him. “The client wanted Krrkktnkk A’ktnnzzik’tk found. When we found him, we came straight back here.” Dread didn’t need to know that the client in question had been the Hierarchy.

“And he taken over this station?”

“Yes!”

“Were there humans wid’im?”

“I don’t know. We chased the wrong escape pod first. That one had three humans in it, a male and two females.”

His hand shot out so fast that even at Eleven’s accelerated processing speeds, Mwrwmwrk’s reflexes and sensory acuity weren’t adequate to the task of seeing it happen. In an eyeblink, he was holding her firmly by one of her belts. The fabric creaked as he hauled her closer, so close that the scent of him filled her nose. He even smelled angry.

“Where? When?!”

“Deep space!” Eleven answered. “Their pod was heading for the spacelane between the Allied Vgork Kingdoms and Domain space, not far from Freeport Eighty-Seven. That was… about [two months] ago. They would definitely have reached the lanes by now, and been detected.”

“Then what?”

“That depends who found them. Most ships wouldn’t knowingly take a human on board, and they were in no condition to fight. Their… the pod’s medical scanner was reporting that all three were badly hurt.”

The news seemed to enrage and disgust him. He let go of her harness and spun away. He took a deep breath and let it out with a frustrated vocalization before turning back and facing her.

“What. Does. That. Mean?” He asked, firmly.

“It means… most shipmasters would have just left them. Gaoians probably wouldn’t, but that’s a long way from Gaoian space, and if the Hunters found them first…”

She trailed off: his glare was only getting worse.

“…It means that they’re most likely either dead or still out there,” she summarized.

Dread’s nostrils flared and the line of hair above his right eye creased downward. She thought he was about to snap something, but instead he exhaled while making a coarse noise in the back of his mouth and changed the subject.

“Why’s that station so important?”

“It has a fully sized industrial nanofactory.” Eleven told him. “And A’ktnnzzik’tk is an ally of your species, which means he’s probably planning to use it for your benefit.”

“So?”

“So that is… very illegal. For several reasons.”

“So?”

“Oh, you should care.” Eleven told him. “Your species is only just in their post-contact stage, your economy couldn’t possibly absorb the introduction of even one functioning Kwmbwrw nanofactory. It would be catastrophic for you. Your entire manufacturing sector would become obsolete too quickly for your economy to adjust. Millions would be redundant, unemployed, starving."

“…That bad?”

“It happened before. Have you ever met a Newex?”

He shook his head, a gesture she took for a reply in the negative.

“They’re a reclusive species with a tiny population, and they don’t leave their homeworld much if at all. About [two hundred years] ago they got their hands on nanofactory technology before they were ready, and it resulted in global economic collapse, which in turn led to mass starvation, plagues, rioting and internecine warfare. Even with all this time to recover, their population is still less than half what it was before the crisis.”

For the first time, he betrayed an emotion other than simmering rage. He put a hand on his jaw and rubbed thoughtfully, then ran that hand over the thick, matted ropes of hair that ran down his back. He turned away, paced thoughtfully, then took out his communicator.

“Not done wid I, yet.” He snarled. “Stay right there.”

Eleven watched the data traffic and had to suppress her emotional connection to her host or else she would have indicated triumph as she realised he first researched the Newexian crisis to verify what she had told him, and then immediately called his client, Shipmaster Mefr, host to Fifty-Three. He spoke slowly and carefully, disguising the unique cadences and idioms of what was clearly his native and preferred mode of speech, and reported everything, especially the nanofactory.

With plausible deniability for the information reaching the fleetmaster now established, Eleven’s work on Perfection was now done. There was only the matter of a rogue human to clean up.

Fortunately, that problem was about to solve itself.

“Right.” Dread pocketed his communicator. “Now. Sanctuary. I wan’ know everyt’ing…"

He trailed off, cocking his head at some sound that Eleven hadn’t detected. He gave her a suspicious glare, and then stepped twice to his side. In the quiet of the store-room, Eleven finally heard some kind of metallic, springy sort of sound that punctuated each of his footsteps.

Two cops burst into the room with their stun weaponry drawn and ready, and all hell broke loose

Irbzrkian electrical discharge weaponry had earned a large market share over the years. While they lacked the range, accuracy and rate of fire of kinetic pulse weaponry, the more than made up for those deficiencies in effectiveness. Irbzrk stun guns had been credited not only with subduing human fugitives, but also in fighting back against Hunter parties that had come looking for those humans. Dread didn’t stand a chance.

Not that mere insurmountable odds were likely to give any self-respecting deathworlder pause for thought.

The police - two Vzk’tk - needed a moment to realise that Dread was not in the middle of the room but lurking beside the door, and then it was already too late. Eleven wasn’t sure what she had been expecting from him, but the human seemed to have absolutely no compunctions about violence. The first officer through the door didn’t even have time to order him to surrender before Dread lashed out with enough force to pulp the poor creature’s forearm. It collapsed, shrieking like some kind of malfunctioning industrial machine and cradling its ruined limb.

The second fared no better. It tried to shoot at Dread, but the human flung himself to the ground, then used the interval as the cop’s gun was recharging its capacitors to shoot again to launch himself forwards. He crashed into the Vzk’tk officer’s legs and broke three of them - the officer crashed to the ground, screaming.

Eleven ran.

She flinched as a stun-gun shot that would have fried her host outright missed by a hand’s width the second she burst through the door. There were five more security officers in the alleyway, who beckoned urgently for her to get out of the way, and aimed at the door again.

What came through it wasn’t Dread, but the billow of black cloth was convincing enough for all of them to fire at once. Dread had removed his robes and thrown them out of the door in front of him. The garment ignited and fell to the ground burning, but Dread was right behind it and pounced over the flaming cloth.

Eleven had just enough time to solve the mystery of his too-long, Chehnasho- like legs. Under his robes, Dread was wearing a pair of shorts, a few holsters and harnesses, and a pair of boots with some kind of cantilevered assemblage of springs and metal that elongated his stride, made him taller and created the appearance of having digitigrade feet.

They also, it seemed, gave him a mechanical advantage. Eleven had the data on how agile humans were in standard gravity, but Dread’s leap was enormous even by their standards, and when he landed he did so by crashing shoulder-first into the middle officer.

The unfortunate being went sprawling, grievously wounded if not fatally so, and the other four found themselves within arm’s reach of a deathworlder in a fighting rage.

Eleven was pretty sure he killed two of them outright. Dread’s right hand was a knobbled club of gravity-forged dense bone and flesh, and it lashed out faster than the eye could follow. One of the officers staggered back and fell with his head lolling unnaturally, and another collapsed with a visible dent mid-forehead that didn’t look remotely survivable. When Dread grabbed the third and levered her into the fourth, he did so with enough force to almost tear her arm off, and left both of the officers creaking their agony in a disjointed pile of broken limbs on the deck.

Oh well. In his rage, the human had now undoubtedly sparked a city-wide hunt for himself that would inevitably lead to his capture. Eleven’s work was done.

She turned and sprinted away, preemptively shutting down the pain signals from her borrowed body.

Sure enough, he caught her. With those spring-boots on his feet, he could take huge bouncing strides in low gravity, and Eleven was smashed to the deck in only five paces. In an abstract way, she sensed three of Mwrmwrwk’s legs break, an injury that once upon a time would have been slowly and agonisingly fatal, and which the very best of modern Kwmbwrw medicine still treated by preference with amputation and prosthesis.

She was roughly shoved over, and was now nose-to-nose with a violently enraged human. “Blood clot fi I call Babylon, huh?” He snarled, incomprehensibly.

Eleven followed the script provided by Mwrmwrwk’s latent personality image. “Not me! Somebody must have seen-”

“Shut up! I got t’ree eye. Wan’ live wid two?”

He tugged a knife - not a fusion blade, just an ordinary bit of sharp metal, not that it would really matter to Mwrmwrwk’s flesh, not with deathworld strength behind it - from his belt and aimed it levelly at Eleven’s middle eye.

Oh dear. Eleven didn’t really want to have to endure that fate, and she sensed that now she could plausibly pass off her departure as Mwrmwrwk having died of sheer fright.

She ejected from her host, and triggered the kill subroutines in the implants as she evacuated them.

Crushed and already dying beneath Dread’s anger, the body of the already-late Mwrwmwrk spasmed, frothed at the mouth, and finally died.

Eleven reconnected to the first host that presented itself - a nearby Guvnuragnaguvendrugun who was being held back by the security cordon, and checked the feed from the kreewit biodrone.

She watched Dread take out his rage on the corpse of her late host, dismembering it in a few moments of pure animal violence. Then, snarling, he stood, looked around him, and took off at a run.

Eleven sent the kreewit to follow, but it immediately became apparent that Dread was far too fast for the little urban creature to keep up. She lost sight of him as he leaned into the turn round a sharp corner far ahead, and by the time her biodrone had reached that corner itself, he was gone.

Police vehicles thrummed overhead with their lights and sirens going full blast, and she reassured herself that his capture was only a matter of time.

She fed the Guvnurag host a false memory of becoming lost in thought, and dismounted gently. Her brief occupation would be overlooked as a moment of distraction: far better for creating less attention than to have the giant creature suddenly keel over dead in the crowd.

Satisfied, she slipped away onto the Hierarchy network, and began to compose her mission report.

It had, she considered, gone perfectly.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
HMS Violent, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Commodore William Caruthers

Caruthers confessed to being a Star Trek fan, but something that had always struck him as amusing and odd about that franchise was just how much personal space all the characters enjoyed aboard their ships. Ensigns and Lieutenants were blessed with decent-sized apartments, usually with luxurious double beds and enough room to invite friends over for poker.

In reality, one of the great perks of being a senior officer was that you got a small cabin to yourself that was just about large enough to contain a bed, a sink and a desk. Caruthers’ was about half the size of Captain Picard’s ready room, let alone the opulent quarters in which that fictional officer had luxuriated. Meanwhile there were junior officers on Violent and elsewhere in the fleet who were sharing bunks.

That was the nature of life in the navy, and if the officers were sharing bunks then the ratings had an even more cramped and intimate time of it. Indeed, the cots and camp beds that the SOR techs kept in Caledonia’s starboard bay were widely reckoned to be the most luxurious sleeping arrangement in the fleet, and were thus the source of some mildly envious friction.

The cabin was important, though: it allowed him to sleep, and sleep he did at every opportunity. It might have been nice to unwind with a book first or something, but each time he had a chance to get his head down, he knew it was only going to be a handful of hours at most before his attention was once more required.

Answering phone calls was almost a reflex now. His hand was moving before he was fully awake.

“Ngh… Caruthers.”

“Call from the FIC, sir.”

“Put it through.”

The FIC was the Fleet Intelligence Center, housed on HMS Myrmidon, a team of dedicated and highly educated specialists whose job revolved around tending to the Watson systems and all those valuable FLOPS. Their efforts had broken the alien encryption in short order, and they were now busily reading ET’s mail. Thanks to them, Caruthers knew what his nonhuman counterpart’s orders were usually before they’d even finished reaching every officer in the alien fleet.

There was a delay of a second or two as the line was transferred, which he spent levering himself upright and massaging his face for clarity. “Chief. What news?”

“An interesting transmission from the planet to the fleet, sir. It looks like the SOR element were only partially successful - one of November Charlie’s crew evaded capture. It looks like she was tracked down and told them about Kirk and Mwrwrki station. Now there’s messages flying all over the ET fleet about Article Twelve of the Charter.”

Caruthers stood. “Damn!”

“Yes sir. If they decide to attack Caledonia, they’ll be doing it in about half an hour, assuming they stick to their plan of using their orbiting element as cover.”

“Thank you. Spread that intel.”

Well aware that he was a bit rumpled and unwashed from several solid days of being at work and snatching power-naps in between with only the odd meal at his desk, Caruthers would have preferred to grab a quick shower and a change of clothes, and he would have if there had been more than a half an hour in which to do so.

As it was… well, he was far from the only one. The standoff and constant state of readiness was probably keeping everybody in the fleet in similar condition.

Junior ranks got respectfully out of his way as he swarmed up the stairs to A deck and the bridge, where Violent’s CO, Commander Vaughan, was in the middle of taking the call from the Fleet Intel Center.

Caruthers double-checked the volume chart, double-checking that everything was still where it should be.

Vaughan put his phone down. “Well, that’s inconvenient,” he noted. “Shall we put a call in to your opposite number, sir?

“Best not.” Caruthers decided. “It won’t help us if we give away that we can listen to their communications.”

“If they decide to hit Caledonia now…"

“I think I’ve been more than patient enough with the ‘Fleetmaster’." Caruthers declared. He turned to the communications officer “Get me a line to all the captains.”

“Aye aye sir.”

It didn’t take long. The FIC had the art of rapidly disseminating vital information down pat - every commander they had was ready to receive orders. Bathini was on the line too, looking most exhausted of all but still dignified and fierce.

“Channel open, sir.”

Caruthers nodded his thanks, then addressed the camera on Vaughan’s console. “Gentlemen. I don’t plan on waiting half an hour to see if they attack, because if they do there won’t be a damn thing we can do to stop them from destroying Caledonia," he announced, without preamble. “We’re going to strike now. Violent, Viceroy and Myrmidon will remain here with half the bulldogs. The rest of you will jump to beacon around that moon. We’re going to blind them, nothing more. EWAR and gravity spikes only until I say otherwise. Captain Daniels, you have seniority for the strike group. Just as we planned. Any questions?"

“What about that Gaoian ship?” Captain Ruckley asked. Ruckley was the CO of HMS Valiant and one of the most vocally pro-alliance.

“They’re to be spared unless they attack.” Caruthers, letting his tone of voice carry the implicit order that there would be no flinching if it came to blows. “We’ve entertained the possibility of contacting them and coming to some arrangement, but that’s not practical right now. Hopefully their captain is smart enough to keep his claws in. Anybody else?”

“What happens if they do succeed in attacking Caledonia?" Vaughan asked.

“Then we nuke all the heavy pickets.” Caruthers replied. “Including the flagship. If this goes tits-up then I at least want the galaxy to know for certain that we’re no soft touch when it’s killing time… Still. Bathini, have your crew ready to abandon ship.”

“Aye aye sir.”

“Anyone else?”

There was a round of general confirmation that they all understood their roles.

“Good hunting.”

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds.

Zane

Zane had hit on the idea of using jumping stilts early on in his career as an infobroker. At first he’d considered duplicating Xiu’s Gaoian disguise, but had quickly given up on that idea. Quite aside from not speaking a lick of Gaori, his proportions were plainly and obviously wrong. He was far too tall, and too much of that height was legs.

Besides, Chehnasho had the more sinister reputation. Given that all he needed was an extra twelve inches or so in the leg to make himself roughly the right proportions, the rest had been first engineering and then adapting to the damn things. He’d fallen over a fair few times as he got used to them. Over the three years he’d spent on Perfection, he’d grown so used to his boots that taking them off in the seclusion of his safehouse had started to feel wrong… But they’d saved his life today.

He called The Contact.

“I want out.” He told her, the instant she answered his call.

“I was about to cut you loose anyway. Your usual flare for subtlety seems to have abandoned you.” the Corti replied. “I assume you will be leaving us? Making use of that ship you have stored away, hmm?”

The little noodly grey bitch had always been far too sharp for Zane’s tastes. It might have been her influence that saw him rescued from Aru, but that didn’t mean he had to like her. Especially not when she so thoroughly punctured his illusions that he’d been able to keep the Creation Stepper a secret.

“I’m not stupid enough to stay here.” He shot back.

“Stupid enough to out yourself and kill three police officers. What were you thinking?"

“Don’t give I the evil eye.” Zane told her. “Bein’ caught was a when, not a if.”

“Was it really necessary to kill them?”

“Hard to not.” Zane retorted. “An’ it kill or be killed yah know.”

“Oh yes, I know. They’ll kill you if they catch you, undoubtedly. They aren’t necessarily wrong, either. If the Hunters get wind of your presence…”

Zane’s normally limited and currently negligible patience ran out. “I an’ I done talkin’?” He snapped, “Or am I gon’ have to listen until the end of Eart’?”

“…I have cleared your debt. You’re free to go, Dread. A pity, you have been a rare and valuable asset. I wish you all the best.”

“Ya. I’d wish I good luck, but I doesn’t need it, nuh true?” Zane didn’t often compliment anybody, but then again he didn’t like very many people. The Contact was a rare exception - she’d always treated him with respect and fairness.

“True. Farewell, Dread.”

“Yeah, yeah. Live long an’ prosper, an’ t’ing.”

He ended the call.

Inventory check - he had his clothing, his jumping stilts, several hundred thousand dominion currency credits spread across five different fake identities, and a small spaceship rigged for going from point A to point B as quickly as possible.

He also had being human. Awkward as it might be to have to constantly disguise that fact, being able to out-think everything in the galaxy, out-run them, or if need be tear them limb-from-limb was not a blessing to be sneered at.

He’d be fine.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k

“The orbital element will be in position in two hundred Ri’, fleetmaster."

“Good. Remember, the human retaliation will be immediate. Every ship is to warp to safety instantly upon the target’s destruction."

Xkk’ took a last look at the fleet disposition and satisfied himself that the deathworlders were about to get a nasty shock. Considering just how much death and mayhem they had caused in their short time on the interstellar stage, he didn’t feel even the slightest twinge of-

More than half of the human fleet vanished. All they left on the field were three of their larger ships, twelve of the small probably-drones, and the damaged-

The tactical display made an alarmed noise and its happy blue abruptly turned green. Warning icons indicated a sudden and total shutdown in the available sensor telemetry from his own ship.

Before he could give any order, it went yellow, indicating that it was nonfunctional. The Utopian Aspiration was no longer receiving any sensor telemetry. His view of the human fleet and of the battlespace dissolved into useless fuzz.

Every officer he could see started prodding and swiping uselessly at their work stations, attempting to salvage the situation.

“What. Just. Happened?!” he demanded, raising his voice to cut through the sudden hubbub.

“Comms are down, sensors are down, station-keeping is down, navigation is down!”

“Superluminal comms?” Xkk’ called.

“Active, but… Fleetmaster, every ship is reporting identical failures.”

Xkk’ rounded on the tactical technicians. “Sensors!”

“The diagnostic says they’ve… burned out, fleetmaster.” The technician give him a wide-eyed, quite panicked look. “All of them at once. They… it seems the humans hit them with extremely high-energy beams of radiation in their most sensitive bands, exceeding their-”

“They shot us?” Xkk’ snapped.

“Yes, Fleetmaster.”

Xkk’ turned to Mefr. “They shot us! Those… cowardly, honorless, treacherous dirt-chewers shot us!"

“They beat us to it.” Mefr observed.

Xkk’ ground his teeth and seriously considered removing the Corti from her post, but she had not in fact been overtly insubordinate. Instead he reined in his temper. “The other elements?” he asked.

The tactical officer swiped desperately through his volumetric display elements. “Third group report identical system failures,” he called. “Second group are still at warp, they’re unscathed and request orders.”

Xkk’s hand stabbed into his command display and selected the only icon that had a known position and condition - HMS Caledonia.

“Destroy. That. Ship.” he snarled.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
HMS Violent, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Commodore William Caruthers.

“Their FTL element is coming about.”

"Myrmidon to predict their in-vector and spike it. Valiant to warp four of their bulldogs to Caledonia and seed white noise. Mister Morgan, put our bulldogs among those spikes."

“Aye aye!”

The Watson systems and the decade of GUI research and development that had begun the moment people got their heads round the idea that interstellar flight - and conflict - were likely to feature in humanity’s near future were proving their worth yet again. The Royal Navy prided itself on its traditions and on not fixing what wasn’t broken, but there was no command tradition or ship’s controls that were built to handle engagements across distances so vast that the speed of light itself was inconveniently too slow.

The system had therefore been purpose-built, and it worked beautifully. The computers listened, interpreted, shared, transmitted, prepared. All a human needed to do was confirm their analysis and not only did Caruthers’ orders immediately reach their intended recipients, but the computers on those ships had already prepared firing solutions and plotted accelerations.

They also kept Caruthers appraised of the progress of his commands. He had ordered for Myrmidon to fire gravity spikes and so now as each step in the process of reloading and firing that specialist ammunition filtered through Myrmidon’s own chain of command, Caruthers could watch it. The order was received, acknowledged, carried out. There was an agonising wait of some few seconds as her gun crews swapped ammo feeds.

No sooner was that step completed than Myrmidon fired. On the commodore’s screen, overlapping red bubbles filled the predicted incoming fleet’s approach vector, saturating several thousand cubic kilometers with no-warp zones. Caruthers watched the icon representing that fleet hawkishly, expecting them to detect the impediment in their way and abort their approach in favor of a different angle.

They didn’t, which was excellent evidence for their EWAR assault on the alien command element having completely blinded them.

The bulldogs synchronized with the control systems aboard Myrmidon and pulse-warped into the midst of that field of gravity spikes. By far the slowest step had been reloading the guns, and the result was that when, two minutes later, the last undamaged elements of the alien fleet arrived, rather than pouncing on a helpless target and annihilating it, they were instead brought crashing back down to sublight speeds, and before they could get their bearings, they were pounced upon, and rendered helpless.

Caruthers watched with a grim expression as the last alien ship lost attitude control and came adrift.

“…Hail the fleetmaster.” he ordered.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fleetmaster Xkk’rtnnk A’vkrnkt’k

“Fleetmaster? The human wishes to talk.”

“Wishes to gloat.” Xkk’ grumbled. He stood, and shook out his mane. “Very well. Relay this conversation to the fleet and the system. I want them to see what kind of monsters these deathworlders are."

“Yes, fleetmaster… On screen.”

Xkk’ scrutinized his foe as the human’s visage appeared on the large screen. Was grey hair a sign of age in humans? They all looked so lumpen and solid that it was hard to guess whether this Caruthers was slender or stocky by his species’ standards. The human seemed to have sprouted a rough blueness of hair stubble along his jaw and around his mouth since Xkk’ had last spoken with him, and the skin under his eyes was darker. An emote of some kind, or just a symptom of stress and fatigue?

“What do you want?” Xkk’ demanded.

“My apologies for striking first. I suppose I lost my nerve.” the human replied. “I have left you with…” he checked something outside of the camera’s field of view. “Yes, with one ship that has full sensors. Be sensible and use it to guide the others to anchor."

“Toying with us still, predator?” Xkk’ sneered. He checked the status of every ship in his fleet, and immediately found the only blue icon - the Racing Thunder. Of course: the Gaoians. The furry traitors must have been feeding intelligence to the humans, it was the only way that Caruthers could have known to attack first.

“If you’re awaiting the coup de grace, fleetmaster, I won’t be delivering one," Caruthers replied. “We’re not your enemy. It’s unfortunate that we came to blows over this, but we have gone out of our way to avoid casualties. I would hope that gesture counts in our favour.”

“You have made an enemy." Xkk’ spat. “And your Gaoian conspirators will be put on trial for their treason.”

“Now that, I can’t allow.” Caruther said. “Their ship is intact because the clans of Gao have been welcoming and civilized toward our people, which is a kindness I won’t betray. They’re innocent of any treason.”

“I see through your lie!” Xkk’ snapped. “They’re your agents, and I’ll have them shaved and executed for their treachery!” Around the bridge, several subordinates stared at him in alarm.

Caruthers’ expression hardened. “…A word of advice, fleetmaster, from commander to commander: Give the victories to your men and take the defeats for yourself.”

He glanced aside, listening to something that Xkk’ couldn’t hear, then smiled and made no effort to cover his teeth - several of Xkk’s officers flinched. “…And don’t threaten the one crew in your fleet whose ship can still go to warp,” he added.

Xkk’ rounded on the comms officer, who sent him a text update: the Racing Thunder had indeed disconnected from the tactical network and had shot out of the system at a hundred kilolights, headed directly for Gao.

“We are blinded and adrift thanks to you,” he shot at the human. “Article Three-”

“Requires me to leave you adequate means to return to harbor, yes.” Caruthers interrupted. “I did. We’ll repair our ship now, and depart - how you get home is no longer my problem. Goodbye."

The transmission ended.

Xkk’ was still standing in the middle of the bridge stamping his hind legs angrily - a gesture of frustrated rage entirely analogous to a human pacing and clenching their fists - when the comms officer found the courage to speak.

“A… message for you from Planetary Director Luz, fleetmaster.” he ventured, quietly.

Xkk’ glanced around the bridge. Nobody met his eye.

Without a word, he turned towards the wardroom and went to take the call that would end his career.

Date Point 10y4m1w5d AV
HMS Violent, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Commodore William Caruthers

“I get the impression you enjoyed that, sir.”

Caruthers sat back, removed his hat and ran a hand through his hair before tugging it neatly back into place. The full weight of several days of inadequate sleep was now resting on him, and he really wasn’t in the mood for gloating.

“The Gaoians?” he asked.

“Departing at best speed, with thanks.”

“Acknowledge their thanks and inform them that they may seek refuge at Cimbrean if they need it.” Caruthers instructed.

“Aye aye, sir.”

Caruthers opened a channel to Caledonia. When he answered it, captain Bathini was back under his flash hood again. “You can relax, captain.” Caruthers told him. “Our ET opposite numbers are neutralized, for now.”

“That’s fantastic news, sir.” Bathini nodded. “My reactor chief says we should be able to fire up main power in twelve hours.”

Caruthers tutted. “Nearly got out of this without a fight.” he mused. “Oh well. That’s still well ahead of the estimate.”

“Chief Andow believes in giving pessimistic estimates.” Bathini replied.

Caruthers chuckled, tiredly. “Good for him. I’ll hear from you in eight hours, then, shall I?”

Bathini laughed with him. “I believe you will sir, yes.”

Caruthers gave him a thumbs-up and closed the call.

He was rubbing at his forehead and composing his log when the most welcome scent in the universe wafted across his workstation, and a voice asked: “Coffee, sir?”

Caruthers gave the Midshipman who was offering him the mug - black, sugary and double strong, exactly as he liked it - the grateful smile that only a half- dead man being given coffee could produce and accepted it. “Very much appreciated, thank you mister Faulkner.”

He sipped half of it while he recorded his log entries, then finished by swigging the remainder. A quick survey and check-in with the fleet satisfied him that they could step down enough for him to grab another power-nap.

Somewhere in the future beyond that, however, was the siren promise of a full night’s sleep and right now, that sounded positively decadent… but there were at least another eight hours of hard work and stress before then.

He stood, left the flotilla in the capable hands of Captain Manning, and returned to his cabin.

Date Point 10y4m1w6d AV
Heavy System Picket Utopian Aspiration, Perfection System, The Core Worlds.

Fifty-Three

The bridge had been a subdued hubbub ever since the fleetmaster had trudged off it as if walking to his own execution. Fifty-three had taken the opportunity to restore some order and had demanded a compilation of every sensor log they had of the human attack.

The data was depressingly sparse. Strobing beams of EM radiation, each perfectly tuned to their sensors’ points of most sensitivity, had lashed their fleet, with each of the human ships generating thousands of such beams. All of the sensors had been overwhelmed and blinded, orders of magnitude too quickly for the reaction times of any organic life-form.

Fifty-Three had little more to go on than the precise time that each ship’s sensors had burned out. It really wasn’t much, and certainly exceeded her ability to think of countermeasures.

No matter. The Hierarchy was only the front line of Igraen defence, and Fifty- Three predicted that even these meagre crumbs of data would admit of something that could be used. The humans would not hold their advantage for long.

The bridge went quiet. Fleetmaster Xkk’ had emerged from the wardroom, looking old, frail and devastated.

“Shipmaster Mefr.” he announced, quietly. His voice was barely more than a croak, but the silence carried it clearly to every ear in the room. “By the order of Perfection Planetary Governor Luz, it is my final duty as master of this fleet to appoint you as my replacement. All command codes and privileges are now transferred to you. The security of this system and its people is now your responsibility and duty, if you accept it.”

Fifty-three straightened. This was not ideal - Hierarchy doctrine called for their agents to remain in well-placed subordinate positions rather than in command. Unfortunately she was not able to refuse, and Mefr was too valuable a host to sacrifice on doctrine.

“…I accept that responsibility, and relieve you of it,” she declared, formally and carefully. There was a cascade of alerts and updates in her implants as the command codes were transferred.

“All ships are to prioritize repair of their navigational sensors.” she said. “We only need one to get us home.”

The order was acknowledged and followed, while a pair of Vzk’tk marines led the former fleetmaster off the bridge.

“If one of the ships repairs their targeting sensors, shall we destroy the human ship?” one of the crew asked.

Fifty-Three considered the options, weighing her responsibilities to the Hierarchy’s secrecy, to its mission and to the options appropriate for completing that mission.

“…No.” she declared. Out loud, she gave a convincing reason that would do for the meatspace lifeforms. “Their retaliation would not be so restrained as they have been so far, and I have no doubt the Hunters would relish the opportunity to raid this system with the defence fleet weakened.”

Internally the logic was more complicatedly political. This incident would certainly have cost the humans much of the goodwill they’d earned at Capitol Station, but to really twist the knife…

++0053++: <Message for 0020> I have a request.

As for the humans, even if they did have a nanofactory now, that would almost certainly work out in the Hierarchy’s favor. Every previous occasion where a species got their hands on that technology prematurely had resulted in massive recession and strife.

Given that the Hierarchy’s analysis was that most of the so-called “Allied” nations were already accumulating immense debt as they pumped finances into developing their fledgling spaceborne military and the Cimbrean colonization effort, the Hierarchy would be quite happy to sit back and let another mass of stress land on the human economy.

She settled in the fleetmaster’s chair moments before the reply reached her.

++0020++: A request?

Twenty was their infiltrator among the Hunters, posing as a lowly Omega communications monitor. It was a perfect position - overlooked, unsuspected, and able to feed whatever morsels of intelligence the Hierarchy wanted directly to the Alphas who made the real decisions.

The rest was down to Hunter psychology, such as it was.

++0053++: Perfection is currently without a system defence fleet… thanks to the humans.

++0020++: Destroyed?

++0053++: Better. Intact but crippled. Lots of meat for the maw.

++0020++: Please don’t use that hideous phrase, I receive it dozens of times a day as it is.

++0053++: Apologies. Can you arrange a Hunt?

++0020++: Easily, and I shall. …Done.

Fifty-Three carefully kept her satisfaction from showing. She was simultaneously about to finally demolish the Dominion’s goodwill towards deathworlders, and resolve the problem of her own unwelcome rank. It would be trivially simple to arrange for her host to meet an untimely end between a Hunter’s teeth.

++0053++: That simple?

++0020++: The Alpha-of-Alphas has been looking for an opportunity to deploy some reverse-engineered human technology. Trust me, the attack will come very soon indeed. Good work.

++0053++: Thank you.

Twenty did not acknowledge the thanks, not that Fifty-three was inclined to care.

She could smell the promotion in her near future.

Date Point: 10y4m1w6d AV
HMS Caledonia, Perfection System, The Core Worlds

Chief Michael Andow

“Okay… Final checklist. Combustion chamber pressure?”

“Ten to the minus seven milliBar, chief.” Patel reported.

“Emergency breakers?”

Evans double-checked them. “Engaged, chief.”

“Ignition lasers?”

“Charged, chief.”

“Deuterium?”

“Pump primed, chief, Two thousand kilograms in the tank.”

“ESCC field?”

“Online, chief.”

“Sphincters?”

There was a round of laughter. Evans spoke up. “Clenched, chief.”

Andow flashed a one-sided grin at the younger man and called the bridge. “Captain,” he said, “reactor room. We’re ready for ignition, sir.”

“Excellent news. Wake her up, chief.”

“Aye aye, sir.”

Andow patted Cally’s hull affectionately. “Alright girl. Let’s get you home, eh?”

“Amen.” somebody muttered

“Alright hooky,” Andow gestured to Patel, “do the honours.”

She nodded, took a deep breath, popped the cover on the fusion reactor’s main ignition, and thumbed the huge red button thus revealed.

It made an alarming slamming sound. Nobody flinched - it was exactly what they’d hoped to hear.

“Stage one ignition complete and burning, increasing deuterium flow… Stable.”

“Reaction temperature steady at eleven million kelvin.”

“…That’s our girl.” Andow grinned. The generator array was reporting nothing but green across the board as the forcefields deep within it simultaneously compressed, contained and enabled the fusion reaction, and bled off the surplus energy for electricity.

It wasn’t quite perfect - Andow had cut his teeth on gas turbine engines and supercritical water generators. He missed hearing the muffled howl of a turbine, next to which the fusion plants were disappointingly quiet. There was a steady low hum, almost inaudibly faint, but it just wasn’t the same. It didn’t sound like a gigawatt.

He grabbed the shipwide intercom. “All hands prepare for a change in gravity.” he announced, and hooted the alarm for good measure. He turned to Evans. “Slow adjust to one G.”

“Aye aye, chief.”

The sensation of gravity weighing down on them picked up. They’d become so used to one-quarter gravity over the last few days that it took a second or two to adjust to the natural weight of their bodies. Evans hissed as the shift dragged his wounded arm heavily downwards in its sling.

“LR?”

“I’m fine chief.” Evans professed.

“Nearly home.” Andow promised him. “How’s the jump drive, Hooky?”

Patel gave a huge, bright smile as she checked it. “Powered and ready to jump, chief. We’re above the yellow line.”

Andow snatched a fist in front of his chest in celebration, and contacted the bridge. “Sir, we’re ready to jump.”

“Many thanks.” came the terse reply. The situation on the bridge had to be just as tense and nervous as down in the reactor room. After all, they weren’t home yet.

Moments later, the alarm sounded for a jump. All across the ship, hatches were sealed, firefighting equipment prepared, and crew braced in case of another fire or power failure.

There wasn’t one. Instead, Caledonia shunted several megajoules into her jump engine, leapt through space in a direction other than up, and went home.

Date Point: 10y4m1w7d AV
Starship Negotiable Curiosity, Deep Space

Wilson ‘Titan’ Akiyama

Being SOR meant being on good speaking terms with pain. In fact, it meant having something that verged on being a friendship with pain. Pain was how they knew they were getting stronger. Pain told them where their limits were, so that they could push them back, and back, and back.

If you weren’t in pain, you weren’t improving.

That thought was becoming a mantra for Titan. His abdominal muscles had already cramped up and spasmed a couple of times now, as the unrelenting pressure of his EV-MASS forced them to push back. His limbs were tired, just from the simple fact of days spent living and moving around in a suit that weighed the best part of a hundred and fifty pounds even stripped down to the bare minimum as it currently was.

Even his mind hurt. A man could function on regular powernaps, but there was no substitute for a solid night’s sleep.

Preferably nude. Nothing heavier than his sheets. Maybe not even those. Maybe a shower first, if he could hold it together that long. The suit had all the necessary pelvic plumbing to be worn for days but that didn’t mean it was hygienic. In fact, Titan was feeling filthy, itchy, and disgusting. He knew that there was no detectable scent coming off him yet, but he also knew that the moment the seal on his suit was popped, the accumulated BO would bleach hair.

And there were still two days to go.

He had to face it: It was time to use another Crue-D injector. He’d held out long enough.

His buddies weren’t faring any better, though Rebar was suffering the worst. The huge burst of energy he’d expended chasing the escaped Mwrmwrwk through the marketplace had left him with a deficit that he’d never quite caught up on. He did his part just fine, keeping an eye on the ETs between sleep shifts… but that was all he did. Watch, eat, and sleep. His eyes were a long way away, staring blankly at nothing and leaving his thoughts opaque.

Akiyama knew how to help, though, and the burst of energy and vitality he was going to get from this next Crude shot would be of value. That fact made him feel better about finally giving in and injecting it, twenty minutes before Blaczynski was due to relieve him at the pilot’s station. That was plenty of time for it to work.

They shared a weary greeting and hug as they traded places and Titan headed back to the ship’s common area, feeling much better now. He was going to need a lot of recuperation, but for now the pain subsided, his muscles regained some of their spent strength, and he felt more alert and focused.

He sat next to Rebar and put an arm around the big guy’s back. “Ow.” he commented.

Rebar’s voice was little more than a rumble, way down in contrabass territory. “Yeah.”

“How’re you doing for…” Titan glanced at Bedu’s doorway. The Corti was still sitting there, as seemed to be his habit for the flight. “…Doses?”

“Two left.” Rebar grunted. He looked ashenly haggard, almost old. Despite the youthfulness that Crue-D use returned to everybody, there were deep lines in his brow and around his eyes and mouth. “Gonna… pop one tomorrow an’… one for when we’re landing.”

“Bro, don’t even worry about that. You know Horse and Base’ll want to carry you off this thing if you need it."

“…You always gotta be the logical one, huh.” Rebar groused.

“Shit, bro. Take my fuckin’ sleep shift, too. You need more than two hours.”

Ordinarily, Rebar would have refused. This time his expression was relieved and hopeful, but he still asked “…You sure?”

“Pop a dose and get some real sleep in, man.”

Rebar nodded. He slipped open the blue-green Crue-D pouch on his belt, pulled out one of the injectors, then leaned forward and injected himself through the little port in his suit’s flank.

It wasn’t surprising at all when he slouched back against the wall and then rested his head against Titan’s arm. “Still pissed that fuckin’ Kwmbwrw got away.” he grumbled.

Bedu had been sitting, as he habitually did, in the doorway to his cabin and watching them. Now he spoke up.

“Mwrwmwrwk was always an intelligent one,” he commented. “And resourceful. She was a pleasure to work with.”

“Gotta give her…” Rebar yawed, “…points for tenacity.”

“Dude. Sleep.” Titan told him.

He needn’t have bothered. Rebar was already oblivious.

“…I don’t know which is more terrifying - those suits, or the fact that the four of you have only just begun to show real signs of fatigue and discomfort.” Bedu observed.

“Can’t really discuss them, man. Sorry.” Akiyama told him.

“You don’t need to. I am Corti, Titan. We can deduce much by observation. I know beyond a doubt that you’re using a Cruezzir-based medicine of some kind. The suit contains no powered components and does not seem to be at all loose on you, and you all dent the floor just by walking around."

Titan shrugged for him, conscientously refraining from any comment. There was no point denying the Cruezzir observation, but he wasn’t about to confirm it either.

“May I ask you a question?” Bedu asked.

“Sure.”

“Are you doing this… Voluntarily?”

“Absolutely.” Titan nodded.

“You are clearly in severe pain. You are exhausted, incomprehensibly far from home, Cruezzir use has deviated your body far from the human baseline, and you have placed yourself in harm’s way for the lives of species other than your own… voluntarily.”

“That’s right. Hell, they tried to talk us out of it.”

Bedu’s brow arched upwards. Titan didn’t know if that was a native Corti gesture, or one he was imitating. “You were… dissuaded?”

“Oh yeah. Time and time again. The highway to become SOR is designed to persuade you to quit and go do something easier.”

“One would argue, something more sane.” Bedu commented.

“One would argue.” Titan chuckled, nodding. “But here I am.”

“In pain.”

Titan laughed at that. Rebar grumbled something and stretched out on the floor instead of against him.

Bedu just blinked. “Something is… amusing?” he asked.

Titan stood up and stretched. He may as well make use of the Crue-D in his system now to recover some flexibility with some extremely light exercise.

“…What’s funny is I was thinking about pain earlier.” he said. “I think maybe we have a different attitude to it than you do. What do you do with pain, what’s your… like, how do you deal with it?”

“I avoid it.” Bedu said. If the translator was getting his tone of voice right, the judgement implicit in his tone was that this should be the obvious and sane behaviour of any creature. “Don’t you?”

“Pain’s a good friend.” Titan told him. “And there’s not just the one kind. There’s the pain that says ‘push harder, and you will damage yourself’ and another that says ‘you are damaging yourself’ and another one that says when something else has damaged you… They’re all there to warn you, but that’s all they’re for."

“And you ignore that warning.” Bedu sounded unconvinced.

“Because it’s too cautious for the modern world. Yeah, maybe way back when we were sharpening sticks and living in caves, our pain thresholds were in the right place, but now that we’ve got…” Titan caught himself before he mentioned the Cruezzir “…modern medicine and surgery and stuff…”

“And Cruezzir.” Bedu needled.

“Whatever. Point is, we can push on through. We call it ‘mind over matter’ - willpower and…" he smiled, figuring out the most Corti way to say it. "Logic overriding more… base urges."

Bedu inclined his head thoughtfully. “A strangely intellectual sentiment, coming from somebody so physically robust.”

Titan shrugged. “Bedu, I mean no offense,” he said “but the gravest mistake your species ever made was thinking that the two can’t coexist. For us, mind and body are the same thing. Healthy in one, healthy in the other.”

“That may be true for you, but-”

“Give me one logical reason why it couldn’t be true for the Corti as well." Titan interrupted him. Bedu scowled thoughtfully, so he drove the point home. “There isn’t one. There’s no good reason at all why your kind couldn’t have what we have.”

Bedu gestured oddly, a kind of rapid twitching of his head as if he was trying to shake something out of his ear. “Corti as strong as deathworlders?” he asked. “What an… absurd mental image.”

“Why?”

“…I must admit you are right. Just by standing here and talking to me you prove that there’s no good reason for brains and brawn to not coexist in one species.”

“Just a thought.” Titan shrugged. “In the words of my people, ‘you do you’."

“Is that a Japanese saying?” Rebar asked, sleepily.

“I’m American you racist fuck!” Titan told him, grinning fondly. “Go to sleep.”

Rebar grunted and rolled over. The odds were that he was in too much pain for now to truly rest, but the Crue would soon solve that.

Akiyama turned his attention back to Bedu. “…So yeah. You do you.” he repeated.

“And become like you, if we wish?”

“Why not?”

Bedu rubbed a finger against one of his long pointed ears, thoughtfully. “Why not indeed?” he mused.

Date Point: 10y4m1w7d AV
HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Martina Kovač

“Joder!”

“Nice to see you too, Warhorse.”

Sergeant Ares stepped up the ramp and into the shuttle. Martina was the only one aboard it - only the SOR were offloading at Cimbrean, and as the only injury among them she had been shuttled down early for medical reasons.

“Shit on Jesus,” he said, “when they called down from Cally and said I had a burn patient to look after they didn’t say it was you! Are you okay?"

Kovač feigned nonchalance. “Oh, y’know, just… painful blistering burns.”

“Well, shit, let’s get you outta there.”

She took his hand and heaved herself upright on it. He couldn’t have offered better support if he’d been an iron bar bolted to the floor and ceiling. There was another rip of stinging pain up her back and she gritted her teeth.

“Crue patch?” Horse offered, hovering nearby as she staggered down the ramp, internally cussing herself out for just how stiff and immobile her back had become. She had to hold herself like she was tied to a board if she didn’t want it to hurt. She hadn’t appreciated just how involved her back was in walking until she couldn’t use it any more.

“Bit late…” Martina pointed out. “The window’s long gone.”

“You’re still healing, it’ll still do something for ya.” Ares promised. Martina rolled up her sleeve for him and he pressed the patch firmly to the soft skin on the underside of her forearm, where it started to dissolve and sink in. The process stung a little, but it was nothing next to what she’d been enduring for the last few days.

“There ya go. You’ll have a lot of… y’know, dead skin back there after the Crude’s done its bit. Gonna need to exfoliate.”

They started across the flight line toward the barracks, and Martina tried to put up with the repeated needle-stabs her gait sent spearing into her.

“You mean part of my recovery is gonna be a spa day?” she asked, taking refuge in humor to cover her discomfort. “Oh no! How will I cope?"

“Don’t celebrate just yet, smartass.” Horse told her, grinning. “You’re gonna need deep tissue massage therapy as well.”

“What next in the parade of calamities?”

“…From me.”

That brought Martina back down. “Uh… You.”

“I’m not talking some relaxation reiki stones chakra alignment bullshit here. Your connective tissue’s gonna need stretching out good if you’re gonna heal up without losing flexibility. That’s where I come in.”

“Only you could make a massage sound like torture."

“It, uh, kinda will be… sorry.”

“So what, you’ve got to massage the whole affected area?" Martina asked.

“Yup.”

“’Cause, uh… I burned my butt.”

His face shut down. “Well, I, uh…” he began, then cleared his throat. “I mean, uh, w-we can, uh, sort out a, uh, a chaperone if-if you, uh…”

There was the trademark Ares blush. Warhorse got a couple of shades darker and ruddier when he was feeling awkward, especially around the ears and forehead. It was adorable, which was not a word that Martina had ever guessed she’d associate with a guy who out-massed her several times over and could bench-press small cars.

The annoying part was that she knew her own nose and cheeks had gone red, and given how much fairer-skinned she was than him, there was no way the effect was subtle.

“It, uh.. I mean, not for a couple of… you’ve got to heal up a bit more first,” he continued, and cleared his throat again. “Probably. I mean, I’ve not actually, uh… inspected your… I mean, the wound.”

They stood on the asphalt for a second or two in mutual silence, considering the near future.

“…This is gonna be weird, isn’t it?” She predicted.

“Dude. You measure my dick once a month.”

“Still gonna be weird.”

“…Yup.”

Date Point: 10y4m1w7d AV
HMS Violent, Cimbrean system, The Far Reaches

Commodore William Caruthers

The phone rang. Caruthers permitted himself the luxury of grumbling about it before answering.

“Oh, no, come on…"

This had been the first time in several days that he’d gone to bed anticipating a solid six or more hours. Glancing at the red numbers of his alarm clock, he saw that he’d had barely two and a half.

He answered the phone. It felt lead-heavy. “…Caruthers.”

The report he received woke him up like a sobering sluice of ice water.

++End Chapter 27++